<?xml version="1.0"?>

<?dlps id="FroChro"?>
<?dlps page-images="none" figure-images="no"?>
<?dlps transcription="other"?>

<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/tei-p4/tei2.dtd" [
<!ENTITY % POSTKB "INCLUDE">
<!ENTITY % TEI.extensions.ent SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.ent">
<!ENTITY % TEI.extensions.dtd SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.dtd">
<!ENTITY % ISOnum SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/charent/iso-num.ent"> %ISOnum;
<!ENTITY % ISOpub SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/charent/iso-pub.ent"> %ISOpub;

]>

<TEI.2 id="FroChro">
<teiHeader type="migrated" creator="Etext">
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title type="main">The Chronicles of Froissart</title>
<title type="sort">chronicles of froissart</title>
<author>Froissart, Jean; translated by John Bourchier, Lord Berners</author>
<respStmt>
<resp>Creation of machine-readable version</resp>
<name>Judy Boss</name>
</respStmt>
<respStmt>
<resp>Conversion to TEI-conformant markup</resp>
<name>University of Virginia Library Electronic Text Center</name>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt>
<extent>ca. <num type="kilobytes">231</num> kilobytes</extent>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>University of Virginia Library</publisher>
<pubPlace>Charlottesville, Virginia</pubPlace>
<idno type="ETC">FroChro</idno>
<date value="1994">1994</date>
<availability status="public">
<p n="copyright">Copyright &copy; 1994 by the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia</p>
<p n="access">Publicly accessible</p>
</availability>
<idno type="uva-pid">uva-lib:475969</idno>
</publicationStmt>
<seriesStmt>
<title>University of Virginia Library, Text collection</title>
<idno type="uva-set">UVA-LIB-Text</idno>
</seriesStmt>
<sourceDesc>
<biblFull>
<titleStmt>
<title type="main">The Chronicles of Froissart</title>
<title type="sort">chronicles of froissart</title>
<author>Froissart, Jean; translated by John Bourchier, Lord Berners</author>
<respStmt>
<resp>Edited by</resp>
<name>G.C. Macaulay</name>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt>
<editionStmt>
<p>Harvard Classics</p>
</editionStmt>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>P. F. Collier &amp; Son Company</publisher>
<pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
<date value="1910">1910</date>
</publicationStmt>
<seriesStmt>
<p>The Harvard Classics</p>
</seriesStmt>
<notesStmt>
<note>
<p>Chronicle and Romance, vol. 35: this electronic text contains
Froissart's Chronicles only and not the other works in this print
volume</p>
</note>
</notesStmt>
</biblFull>
</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc>
<encodingDesc>
<projectDesc>
<p>Prepared for the University of Virginia Library Electronic Text Center</p>
</projectDesc>
<editorialDecl>
<p>All quotation marks retained as data</p>
<p>Verification made against printed text</p>
<p>All unambiguous end-of-line hyphens have been removed, and the
trailing part of a word has been joined to the preceding line.</p>
<p id="ETC">Keywords in the header are a local Electronic Text Center scheme
to aid in establishing analytical groupings</p>
</editorialDecl>
<refsDecl>
<p>ID elements are given for each page element and are composed of the text's
unique cryptogram and the given page number, as in SpeFQue1 for page one of
Spenser's Faerie Queene.</p>
</refsDecl>
</encodingDesc>
<profileDesc>
<creation>
<date value="1524" certainty="ca">1523-1525</date>
</creation>
<langUsage>
<language id="eng" usage="main">English</language>
</langUsage>
<textClass>
<keywords>
<term>Nonfiction; prose</term>
<term>Literature in Translation</term>
</keywords>
</textClass>
</profileDesc>
<revisionDesc>
<change>
<date value="1994-08">August 1994</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>corrector</resp>
<name>David Seaman, Electronic Text Center, University of
Virginia</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Parsed against uva.dtd, a minor variant of the Oxford Text
Archive dtd.</item>
</change>
<change>
<date value="1993">1993</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>corrector</resp>
<name>Kelly Tetterton, Electronic Text Center, University of
Virginia</name>
</respStmt>
<item>minimal TEI tagging; unambiguous line-end hyphenation
removed; entity references and footnotes included</item>
</change>
<change>
<date value="2005-07">July 2005</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>Corrector</resp>
<name>John Ivor Carlson</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Converted SGML to XML. Fixed tagging.</item>
</change>
<change>
<date value="2007-09">September 2007</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>Migration</resp>
<name>Ethan Gruber, University of Virginia Library</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Converted XML markup from TEI Lite to uva-dl-tei (TEI P4 with local customizations).</item>
</change>
<change>
<date value="2008-01">January 2008</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>Migration</resp>
<name>Greg Murray, University of Virginia Library</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Programmatically updated TEI header markup (but not header content) for minimal compliance with current QA requirements.</item>
</change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>
<text id="d1">
<front id="d2">


<titlePage id="d3">
	<pb/>
<docTitle>
<titlePart type="main">THE HARVARD CLASSICS</titlePart></docTitle>
<byline>
	<docAuthor>EDITED BY CHARLES W ELIOT LLD</docAuthor>
</byline>

<titlePart type="sub">CHRONICLE AND ROMANCE
FROISSART -MALORY -HOLINSHED
WITH INTRODUCTIONS AND NOTES
VOLUME 35</titlePart>

<docImprint>
<publisher>P F COLLIER &amp; SON COMPANY</publisher>
<pubPlace>NEW YORK</pubPlace>
<pb/>
<docDate>Copyright  1910</docDate>

BY P. F. COLLIER &amp; SON<lb/>
	<lb/>
Designed, Printed. and Bound at The Collier Press, New York</docImprint>
</titlePage>



<div1 type="contents" id="d4">

<list>
<head>THE CHRONICLES OF FROISSART, TRANSLATED BY LORD BERNERS
<lb/>
EDITED BY G. C. MACAULAY </head>

<item>The  Campaign  of  Crecy . . . . . . . . . . . .    5</item>
<item>The Battle of Poitiers . . . . . . . . . . . . .   34</item>
<item>Wat Tyler's Rebellion  . . . . . . . . . . . . .   61</item>
<item>The Battle of  Otterburn . . . . . . . . . . . .   83</item>
</list>
</div1>

<div1 type="introduction" id="d5">
<head>Introduction</head>

<pb n="3"/>

<p>JEAN FROISSART, the most representative of the chroniclers
of the later Middle Ages, was born at Valenciennes in 1337.
The Chronicle which, more than his poetry, has kept his fame
alive, was undertaken when he was only twenty; the first book
was written in its earliest form by 1369; and he kept revising
and enlarging the work to the end of his life.  In 1361 he went
to England, entered the Church, and attached himself to Queen
Philippa of Hainault, the wife of Edward III, who made him
her secretary and clerk of her chapel.  Much of his life was
spent in travel.  He went to France with the Black Prince, and
to Italy with the Duke of Clarence.  He saw fighting on the
Scottish border, visited Holland, Savoy, and Provence, returning
at intervals to Paris and London.  He was Vicar of Estinnes-au-Mont, Canon of Chimay, and chaplain to the Comte de Blois;
but the Church to him was rather a source of revenue than a
religious calling.  He finally settled down in his native town,
where he died about 1410.
</p>
<p>Froissart's wandering life points to one of the most prominent of
his characteristics as a historian.  Uncritical and often inconsistent
as he is, his mistakes are not due to Partisanship, for he
is extraordinarily cosmopolitan.  The Germans he dislikes
as unchivalrous; but though his life lay in the period of the
Hundred Years' War between England and France, and though
he describes many of the events of that war, he is as friendly to
England as to France.
</p>
<p>By birth Froissart belonged to the bourgeoisie, but his tastes
and associations made him an aristocrat.  Glimpses of the sufferings
which the lower classes underwent in the wars of his time
appear in his pages, but they are given incidentally and without
sympathy.  His interests are all in the somewhat degenerate
chivalry of his age, in the splendor of courts, the pomp and
circumstance of war, in tourneys, and in pageantry.  Full of the
love of adventure, he would travel across half of Europe to
see a gallant feat of arms, a coronation, a royal marriage.
Strength and courage and loyalty were the virtues he loved;
cowardice and petty greed he hated.  Cruelty and injustice

<pb n="4"/>

could not dim for him the brilliance of the careers of those
brigand lords who were his friends and patrons.
</p>
<p>The material for the earlier part of his Chronicles he took
largely from his predecessor and model, Jean Lebel; the later
books are filled with narratives of what he saw with his own eyes,
or gathered from the lips of men who had themselves been part
of what they told.  This fact, along with his mastery of a style
which is always vivacious if sometimes diffuse, accounts for the
vividness and picturesqueness of his work.  The Pageant of
medieval life in court and camp dazzled and delighted him, and
it is as a Pageant that we see the Middle Ages in his book.
</p>
<p>Froissart holds a distinguished place among the poets as well
as the historians of his century.  He wrote chiefly in the allegorical
style then in vogue; and his poems, though cast in
a mold no longer in fashion, are fresh and full of color, and
were found worthy of imitation by Geoffrey Chaucer.
</p>
<p>But it is as the supreme chronicler of the later age of chivalry
that he lives.  "God has been gracious enough," he writes,
"to permit me to visit the courts and palaces of kings, . . .
and all the nobles, kings, dukes, counts, barons, and knights,
belonging to all nations, have been kind to me, have listened
to me, willingly received me, and proved very useful to me.
. . . Wherever I went I enquired of old knights and squires
who had shared in deeds of arms, and could speak with authority
concerning them, and also spoke with heralds in order to verify
and corroborate all that was told me.  In this way I gathered
noble facts for my history, and as long as I live, I shall, by the
grace of God, continue to do this, for the more I labour at this
the more pleasure I have, and I trust that the gentle knight who
loves arms will be nourished on such noble fare, and accomplish
still more."
</p>

</div1>
</front>

<body id="d6">
<div1 type="chapter" n="1" id="d7">
<head>The Campaign of Crecy</head>

<pb n="5"/>
<div2 type="section" id="d8">
<head>
HOW THE KING OF ENGLAND CAME OVER THE SEA AGAIN, TO<lb/>
RESCUE THEM IN AIGUILLON</head>

<p>THE king of England, who had heard how his men
were sore constrained in the castle of Aiguillon, then
he thought to go over the sea into Gascoyne with a
great army.  There he made his provision and sent for men
all about his realm and in other places, where he thought to
speed for his money.  In the same season the lord Godfrey of
Harcourt came into England, who was banished out of
France: he was well received with the king and retained to
be about him, and had fair lands assigned him in England to
maintain his degree.  Then the king caused a great navy of
ships to be ready in the haven of Hampton, and caused all
manner of men of war to draw thither.  About the feast of
Saint John Baptist the year of our Lord God MCCCXLVI., the
king departed from the queen and left her in the guiding
of the earl of Kent his cousin; and he stablished the lord
Percy and the lord Nevill to be wardens of his realm with
[the archbishop of Canterbury,] the archbishop of York, the
bishop of Lincoln and the bishop of Durham; for he never
voided his realm but that he left ever enough at home to
keep and defend the realm, if need were.  Then the king
rode to Hampton and there tarried for wind: then he entered
into his ship and the prince of Wales with him, and the lord
Godfrey of Harcourt, and all other lords, earls, barons and
knights, with all their companies.  They were in number a
four thousand men of arms and ten thousand archers, beside
Irishmen and Welshmen that followed the host afoot.
</p><p>Now I shall name you certain of the lords that went over
with king Edward in that journey.  First, Edward his eldest
son, prince of Wales, who as then was of the age of thirteen

<pb n="6"/>

years or thereabout,<note place="foot" n="1"><p>He was in fact sixteen;
born 15th June 1330.</p></note> the earls of Hereford, Northampton,
Arundel, Cornwall, Warwick, Huntingdon, Suffolk, and
Oxford; and of barons the lord Mortimer, who was after
earl of March, the lords John, Louis and Roger of Beauchamp,
and the lord Raynold Cobham; of lords the lord of
Mowbray, Ros, Lucy, Felton, Bradestan, Multon, Delaware,
Manne,<note place="foot" n="2"><p>Probably 'Mohun.'</p></note>
Basset, Berkeley, and Willoughby, with divers other
lords; and of bachelors there was John Chandos, Fitz-Warin,
Peter and James Audley, Roger of Wetenhale, Bartholomew
of Burghersh, and Richard of Pembridge, with divers other
that I cannot name.  Few there were of strangers: there
was the earl Hainault,<note place="foot" n="3"><p>The usual
confusion between 'comte' and 'comte.' It means, 'of the
county of Hainault there was sir Wulfart of Ghistelles,' etc.</p></note>
sir Wulfart of Ghistelles, and five or six other knights
of Almaine, and many other that I cannot name.
</p><p>Thus they sailed forth that day in the name of God.  They
were well onward on their way toward Gascoyne, but on the
third day there rose a contrary wind and drave them on the
marches of Cornwall, and there they lay at anchor six days.
In that space the king had other counsel by the means of sir
Godfrey Harcourt: he counselled the king not to go into
Gascoyne, but rather to set aland in Normandy, and said to
the king: 'Sir, the country of Normandy is one of the
plenteous countries of the world: sir, on jeopardy of my
head, if ye will land there, there is none that shall resist you;
the people of Normandy have not been used to the War, and
all the knights and squires of the country are now at the
siege before Aiguillon with the duke.  And, sir, there ye
shall find great towns that be not walled, whereby your
men shall have such winning, that they shall be the better
thereby twenty year after; and, sir, ye may follow with your
army till ye come to Caen in Normandy: sir, I require you
to believe me in this voyage.'
</p><p>The king, who was as then but in the flower of his youth,
desiring nothing so much as to have deeds of arms, inclined
greatly to the saying of the lord Harcourt, whom he called
cousin.  Then he commanded the mariners to set their
course to Normandy, and he took into his ship the token of

<pb n="7"/>

the admiral the earl of Warwick, and said how he would be
admiral for that viage, and so sailed on before as governour
of that navy, and they had wind at will.  Then the king
arrived in the isle of Cotentin, at a port called Hogue Saint-Vaast.<note place="foot" n="4"><p>Saint-Vaast-de la Hogue.</p></note>
</p>
<p>Tidings anon spread abroad how the Englishmen were
aland: the towns of Cotentin sent word thereof to Paris to
king Philip.  He had well heard before how the king of
England was on the sea with a great army, but he wist not
what way he would draw, other into Normandy, Bretayne or
Gascoyne.  As soon as he knew that the king of England was
aland in Normandy, he sent his constable the earl of Guines,
and the earl of Tancarville, who were but newly come to
him from his son from the siege at Aiguillon, to the town of
Caen, commanding them to keep that town against the
Englishmen.  They said they would do their best: they
departed from Paris with a good number of men of war, and
daily there came more to them by the way, and so came to
the town of Caen, where they were received with great joy
of men of the town and of the country thereabout, that were
drawn thither for surety.  These lords took heed for the provision
of the town, the which as then was not walled.  The
king thus was arrived at the port Hogue Saint-Vaast near to
Saint-Saviour the Viscount<note place="foot" n="5"><p>Saint-Sauveur-le-Vicomte.</p></note> the right heritage to the lord
Godfrey of Harcourt, who as then was there with the king
of England.
</p>
</div2>
<div2 type="section" id="d9">
<head>HOW THE KING OF ENGLAND RODE IN THREE BATTLES<lb/>
THROUGH NORMANDY</head>

<p>WHEN the king of England arrived in the Hogue Saint-Vaast, the king issued out of his ship, and the first foot that
he set on the ground, he fell so rudely, that the blood brast
out of his nose.  The knights that were about him took him
up and said: 'Sir, for God's sake enter again into your
ship, and come not aland this day, for this is but an evil sign
for us.'  Then the king answered quickly and said: 'Wherefore?
This is a good token for me, for the land desireth to
have me.'  Of the which answer all his men were right joyful.

<pb n="8"/>

So that day and night the king lodged on the sands, and
in the meantime discharged the ships of their horses and
other baggages: there the king made two marshals of his
host, the one the lord Godfrey of Harcourt and the other the
earl of Warwick, and the earl of Arundel constable.  And he
ordained that the earl of Huntingdon should keep the fleet
of ships with a hundred men of arms and four hundred
archers: and also he ordained three battles, one to go on his
right hand, closing to the sea-side, and the other on his left
hand, and the king himself in the midst, and every night to
lodge all in one field.
</p>
<p>Thus they set forth as they were ordained, and they that
went by the sea took all the ships that they found in their
ways: and so long they went forth, what by sea and what
by land, that they came to a good port and to a good town
called Barfleur, the which incontinent was won, for they
within gave up for fear of death.  Howbeit, for all that,
the town was robbed, and much gold and silver there found,
and rich jewels: there was found so much riches, that the
boys and villains of the host set nothing by good furred
gowns: they made all the men of the town to issue out and to
go into the ships, because they would not suffer them to be
behind them for fear of rebelling again.  After the town of
Barfleur was thus taken and robbed without brenning, then
they spread abroad in the country and did what they list, for
there was not to resist them.  At last they came to a great
and a rich town called Cherbourg: the town they won and
robbed it, and brent part thereof, but into the castle they
could not come, it was so strong and well furnished with men
of war.  Then they passed forth and came to Montebourg,
and took it and robbed and brent it clean.  In this manner
they brent many other towns in that country and won so
much riches, that it was marvel to reckon it.  Then they came
to a great town well closed called Carentan, where there was
also a strong castle and many soldiers within to keep it.
Then the lords came out of their ships and fiercely made
assault: the burgesses of the town were in great fear of their
lives, wives and children: they suffered the Englishmen to
enter into the town against the will of all the soldiers that
were there; they put all their goods to the Englishmen's

<pb n="9"/>

pleasures, they thought that most advantage.  When the
soldiers within saw that, they went into the castle: the
Englishmen went into the town, and two days together they
made sore assaults, so that when they within saw no succour,
they yielded up, their lives and goods saved, and so departed.
The Englishmen had their pleasure of that good town and
castle, and when they saw they might not maintain to keep
it, they set fire therein and brent it, and made the burgesses
of the town to enter into their ships, as they had done with
them of Barfleur, Cherbourg and Montebourg, and of other
towns that they had won on the sea-side.  All this was done
by the battle that went by the sea-side, and by them on the
sea together.<note place="foot" n="1"><p>Froissart is mistaken in
supposing that a division of the land army went to these towns:
Barfleur and Cherbourg were visited only by the fleet.  According
to Michael of Northburgh, who accompanied the expedition, Edward
disembarked 12th July and remained at Saint-Vaast till the 18th,
and meanwhile the fleet went to Barfleur and Cherbourg.  The army
arrived at Caen on the 26th.</p></note>
</p>
<p>Now let us speak of the king's battle.  When he had sent
his first battle along by the sea-side, as ye have heard,
whereof one of his marshals, the earl of Warwick, was
captain, and the lord Cobham with him, then he made his
other marshal to lead his host on his left hand, for he knew
the issues and entries of Normandy better than any other
did there.  The lord Godfrey as marshal rode forth with
five hundred men of arms, and rode off from the king's
battle as six or seven leagues, in brenning and exiling
the country, the which was plentiful of everything &mdash; the
granges full of corn, the houses full of all riches, rich
burgesses, carts and chariots, horse, swine, muttons and
other beasts: they took what them list and brought into the
king's host; but the soldiers made no count to the king nor
to none of his officers of the gold and silver that they did
get; they kept that to themselves.  Thus sir Godfrey of
Harcourt rode every day off from the king's host, and for
most part every night resorted to the king's field.  The king
took his way to Saint-Lo in Cotentin, but or he came there
he lodged by a river, abiding for his men that rode along by
the sea-side; and when they were come, they set forth their
carriage, and the earl of Warwick, the earl of Suffolk,
sir Thomas Holland and sir Raynold Cobham, and their

<pb n="10"/>

company rode out on the one side and wasted and exiled
the country, as the lord Harcourt had done; and the king
ever rode between these battles, and every night they
lodged together.
</p>
</div2>
<div2 type="section" id="d10">
<head>OF THE GREAT ASSEMBLY THAT THE FRENCH KING MADE TO<lb/>
RESIST THE KING OF ENGLAND</head>

<p>THUS by the Englishmen was brent, exiled, robbed, wasted
and pilled the good, plentiful country of Normandy.  Then
the French king sent for the lord John of Hainault, who
came to him with a great number: also the king sent for other
men of arms, dukes, earls, barons, knights and squires, and
assembled together the greatest number of people that had
been seen in France a hundred year before.  He sent for men
into so far countries, that it was long or they came together,
wherefore the king of England did what him list in the mean
season.  The French king heard well what he did, and sware
and said how they should never return again unfought
withal, and that such hurts and damages as they had done
should be dearly revenged; wherefore he had sent letters to
his friends in the Empire, to such as were farthest off, and
also to the gentle king of Bohemia and to the lord Charles
his son, who from thenceforth was called king of Almaine;
he was made king by the aid of his father and the French
king, and had taken on him the arms of the Empire: the
French king desired them to come to him with all their
powers, to the intent to fight with the king of England, who
brent and wasted his country.  These princes and lords made
them ready with great number of men of arms, of Almains,
Bohemians and Luxemburgers, and so came to the French
king.  Also king Philip sent to the duke of Lorraine, who
came to serve him with three hundred spears: also there
came the earl [of] Salm in Saumois, the earl of Sarrebruck,
the earl of Flanders, the earl William of Namur, every
man with a fair company.
</p>
<p>Ye have heard herebefore of the order of the Englishmen,
how they went in three battles, the marshals on the right
hand and on the left, the king and the prince of Wales his
son in the midst.  They rode but small journeys and every

<pb n="11"/>

day took their lodgings between noon and three of the clock,
and found the country so fruitful, that they needed not to
make no provision for their host, but all only for wine; and
yet they found reasonably sufficient thereof.<note place="foot" n="1"><p>
Or rather, 'thus they found reasonably sufficient provisions.'</p></note>
It was no marvel though they of the country were afraid, for
before that time they had never seen men of war, nor they wist not
what war or battle meant.  They fled away as far as they
might hear speaking of the Englishmen,<note place="foot" n="2"><p>That
is, they fled as soon as they heard their coming spoken of.</p></note>
and left their houses well stuffed, and granges full of corn,
they wist not how to save and keep it.  The king of England and
the prince had in their battle a three thousand men of arms and six
thousand archers and a ten thousand men afoot, beside them
that rode with the marshals.
</p>
<p>Thus as ye have heard, the king rode forth, wasting and
brenning the country without breaking of his order.  He left
the city of Coutances<note place="foot" n="3"><p>That is, he did not
turn aside to go to it.  Froissart says, 'He did not turn aside
to the city of Coutances, but went on toward the great town of
Saint-Lo in Cotentin, which at that time was very rich and of
great merchandise and three times as great as the city of Coutances.'
Michael of Northburgh says that Barfleur was about equal in importance
to Sandwich and Carentan to Leicester, Saint-Lo greater than Lincoln,
and Caen greater than any city in England except London.</p></note>
and went to a great town called Saint-Lo, a rich town of drapery and many rich burgesses.  In that
town there were dwelling an eight or nine score burgesses,
crafty men.  When the king came there, he took his lodging
without, for he would never lodge in the town for fear of
fire: but he sent his men before and anon the town was
taken and clean robbed.  It was hard to think the great
riches that there was won, in clothes specially; cloth would
there have been sold good cheap, if there had been any
buyers.
</p>
<p>Then the king went toward Caen, the which was a greater
town and full of drapery and other merchandise, and rich
burgesses, noble ladies and damosels, and fair churches,
and specially two great and rich abbeys, one of the Trinity,
another of Saint Stephen; and on the one side of the town
one of the fairest castles of all Normandy, and captain
therein was Robert of Wargny, with three hundred Genoways,
and in the town was the earl of Eu and of Guines,
constable of France, and the earl of Tancarville, with a

<pb n="12"/>

good number of men of war.  The king of England rode that
day in good order and lodged all his battles together that
night, a two leagues from Caen, in a town with a little
haven called Austrehem, and thither came also all his navy
of ships with the earl of Huntingdon, who was governour of
them.
</p>
<p>The constable and other lords of France that night
watched well the town of Caen, and in the morning armed
them with all them of the town: then the constable ordained
that none should issue out, but keep their defences on the
walls, gate, bridge and river, and left the suburbs void
because they were not closed; for they thought they should
have enough to do to defend the town, because it was not
closed but with the river.  They of the town said how they
would issue out, for they were strong enough to fight with
the king of England.  When the constable saw their good
wills, he said: 'In the name of God be it, ye shall not fight
without me.'  Then they issued out in good order and made
good face to fight and to defend them and to put their lives
in adventure.
</p>
</div2>
<div2 type="section" id="d11">
<head>OF THE BATTLE OF CAEN, AND HOW THE ENGLISHMEN<lb/>
TOOK THE TOWN</head>

<p>THE same day the Englishmen rose early and apparelled
them ready to go to Caen.<note place="foot" n="1"><p>This was 26th
July.  Edward arrived at Poissy On 12th August: Philip of Valois
left Paris on the 14th: the English crossed the Seine at Poissy
on the 16th and the Somme at Blanche-taque on the 24th.</p></note>
The king heard mass before the
sun-rising and then took his horse, and the prince his son,
with sir Godfrey of Harcourt marshal and leader of the
host, whose counsel the king much followed.  Then they
drew toward Caen with their battles in good array, and so
approached the good town of Caen.  When they of the town,
who were ready in the field, saw these three battles coming
in good order, with their banners and standards waving in
the wind, and the archers, the which they had not been
accustomed to see, they were sore afraid and fled away
toward the town without any order or good array, for all
that the constable could do: then the Englishmen pursued
them eagerly.  When the constable and the earl Tancarville


<pb n="13"/>

saw that, they took a gate at the entry and saved themselves
<note place="foot" n="2"><p>'Set themselves for safety in a gate at
the entry of the bridge.'</p></note>
and certain with them, for the Englishmen were entered into
the town.  Some of the knights and squires of France, such
as knew the way to the castle, went thither, and the captain
there received them all, for the castle was large.  The
Englishmen in the chase slew many, for they took none to
mercy.
</p>
<p>Then the constable and the earl of Tancarville, being in
the little tower at the bridge foot, looked along the street and
saw their men slain without mercy: they doubted to fall in
their hands.  At last they saw an English knight with one
eye called sir Thomas Holland, and a five or six other knights
with him: they knew them, for they had seen them before in
Pruce, in Granade, and in other viages.  Then they called to
sir Thomas and said how they would yield themselves
prisoners.  Then sir Thomas came thither with his company
and mounted up into the gate, and there found the said lords
with twenty-five knights with them, who yielded them to sir
Thomas, and he took them for his prisoners and left company
to keep them, and then mounted again on his horse and
rode into the streets, and saved many lives of ladies,
damosels, and cloisterers from defoiling, for the soldiers
were without mercy.  It fell so well the same season for the
Englishmen, that the river, which was able to bear ships,
at that time was so low, that men went in and out beside
the bridge.  They of the town were entered into their houses,
and cast down into the street stones, timber and iron, and
slew and hurt more than five hundred Englishmen, wherewith
the king was sore displeased.  At night when he heard
thereof, he commanded that the next day all should be put
to the sword and the town brent; but then sir Godfrey of
Harcourt said: 'Dear sir, for God's sake assuage somewhat
your courage, and let it suffice you that ye have done.  Ye
have yet a great voyage to do or ye come before Calais,
whither ye purpose to go; and, sir, in this town there is
much people who will defend their houses, and it will cost
many of your men their lives, or ye have all at your will;
whereby peradventure ye shall not keep your purpose to
Calais, the which should redound to your rack.  Sir, save


<pb n="14"/>

your people, for ye shall have need of them or this month
pass; for I think verily your adversary king Philip will meet
with you to fight, and ye shall find many straight passages and
rencounters; wherefore your men, an ye had more, shall
stand you in good stead: and, sir, without any further slaying
ye shall be lord of this town; men and women will put all
that they have to your pleasure.'  Then the king said: 'Sir
Godfrey, you are our marshal, ordain everything as ye will.'
Then sir Godfrey with his banner rode from street to street,
and commanded in the king's name none to be so hardy to
put fire in any house, to slay any person, nor to violate any
woman.  When they of the town heard that cry, they received
the Englishmen into their houses and made them
good cheer, and some opened their coffers and bade
them take what them list, so they might be assured of their
lives; howbeit there were done in the town many evil deeds,
murders and robberies.  Thus the Englishmen were lords
of the town three days and won great riches, the which
they sent by barks and barges to Saint-Saviour by the river
of Austrehem,<note place="foot" n="3"><p>Froissart says that they
sent their booty in barges and boats 'on the river as far as
Austrehem, a two leagues from thence, where their great
navy lay.'  He makes no mention of Saint-Sauveur here.  The river in
question is the Orne, at the mouth of which Austrehem is situated.</p></note>
a two leagues thence, whereas all their
navy lay.  Then the king sent the earl of Huntingdon with
two hundred men of arms and four hundred archers, with his
navy and prisoners and riches that they had got, back again
into England.  And the king bought of sir Thomas Holland
the constable of France and the earl of Tancarville, and paid
for them twenty thousand nobles.
</p>
</div2>
<div2 type="section" id="d12">
<head>HOW SIR GODFREY OF HARCOURT FOUGHT WITH THEM OF<lb/>
AMIENS BEFORE PARIS.</head>

<p>THUS the king of England ordered his business, being in
the town of Caen, and sent into England his navy of ships
charged with clothes, jewels, vessels of gold and silver,
and of other riches, and of prisoners more than sixty knights
and three hundred burgesses.  Then he departed from the
town of Caen and rode in the same order as he did before,
brenning and exiling the country, and took the way to

<pb n="15"/>

Evreux and so passed by it; and from thence they rode to a
great town called Louviers: it was the chief town of all
Normandy of drapery, riches, and full of merchandise.  The
Englishmen soon entered therein, for as then it was not
closed; it was overrun, spoiled and robbed without mercy:
there was won great riches.  Then they entered into the
country of Evreux and brent and pilled all the country
except the good towns closed and castles, to the which the
king made none assault, because of the sparing of his people
and his artillery.
</p>
<p>On the river of Seine near to Rouen there was the earl of
Harcourt, brother to sir Godfrey of Harcourt, but he was
on the French party, and the earl of Dreux with him, with
a good number of men of war: but the Englishmen left
Rouen and went to Gisors, where was a strong castle: they
brent the town and then they brent Vernon and all the
country about Rouen and Pont-de-l'Arche and came to
Mantes and to Meulan, and wasted all the country about,
and passed by the strong castle of Rolleboise; and in every
place along the river of Seine they found the bridges broken.
At last they came to Poissy, and found the bridge broken, but
the arches and joists lay in the river: the king lay there a
five days: in the mean season the bridge was made, to pass
the host without peril.  The English marshals ran abroad
just to Paris, and brent Saint-Germain in Laye and Montjoie,
and Saint-Cloud, and petty Boulogne by Paris, and the
Queen's Bourg:<note place="foot" n="1"><p>Bourg-la-Reine.</p></note>
they of Paris were not well assured of
themselves, for it was not as then closed.
</p>
<p>Then king Philip removed to Saint-Denis, and or he went
caused all the pentices in Paris to be pulled down; and at
Saint-Denis were ready come the king of Bohemia, the lord
John of Hainault, the duke of Lorraine, the earl of Flanders,
the earl of Blois, and many other great lords and knights,
ready to serve the French king.  When the people of Paris
saw their king depart, they came to him and kneeled down
and said: 'Ah, sir and noble king, what will ye do? leave
thus this noble city of Paris?'  The king said: 'My good
people, doubt ye not: the Englishmen will approach you
no nearer than they be.'  'Why so, sir?' quoth they; 'they

<pb n="16"/>

be within these two leagues, and as soon as they know of
your departing, they will come and assail us; and we not
able to defend them: sir, tarry here still and help to defend
your good city of Paris.'  'Speak no more,' quoth the king,
'for I will go to Saint-Denis to my men of war: for I will
encounter the Englishmen and fight against them, whatsoever
fall thereof.'
</p>
<p>The king of England was at Poissy, and lay in the nunnery
there, and kept there the feast of our Lady in August and sat
in his robes of scarlet furred with ermines; and after that
feast he went forth in order as they were before.  The lord
Godfrey of Harcourt rode out on the one side with five
hundred men of arms and thirteen<note place="foot" n="2"><p>A better
reading is 'twelve.'</p></note> hundred archers; and by
adventure he encountered a great number of burgesses of
Amiens a-horseback, who were riding by the king's commandment
to Paris.  They were quickly assailed and they
defended themselves valiantly, for they were a great number
and well armed: there were four knights of Amiens their
captains.  This skirmish dured long: at the first meeting
many were overthrown on both parts; but finally the burgesses
were taken and nigh all slain, and the Englishmen
took all their carriages and harness.  They were well stuffed,
for they were going to the French king well appointed, because
they had not seen him a great season before.  There
were slain in the field a twelve hundred.
</p>
<p>Then the king of England entered into the country of
Beauvoisis, brenning and exiling the plain country, and
lodged at a fair abbey and a rich called Saint-Messie
<note place="foot" n="3"><p>Commonly called Saint-Lucien, but
Saint-Maximianus (Messien) is also associated with the place.</p></note> near
to Beauvais: there the king tarried a night and in the morning
departed.  And when he was on his way he looked behind
him and saw the abbey a-fire: he caused incontinent
twenty of them to be hanged that set the fire there, for he
had commanded before on pain of death none to violate any
church nor to bren any abbey.  Then the king passed by the
city of Beauvais without any assault giving, for because he
would not trouble his people nor waste his artillery.  And so
that day he took his lodging betime in a little town called
Milly.  The two marshals came so near to Beauvais, that

<pb n="17"/>

they made assault and skirmish at the barriers in three
places, the which assault endured a long space; but the town
within was so well defended by the means of the bishop,
who was there within, that finally the Englishmen departed,
and brent clean hard to the gates all the suburbs, and then at
night they came into the king's field.
</p>
<p>The next day the king departed, brenning and wasting all
before him, and at night lodged in a good village called
Grandvilliers.  The next day the king passed by Dargies:
there was none to defend the castle, wherefore it was soon
taken and brent.  Then they went forth destroying the
country all about, and so came to the castle of Poix, where
there was a good town and two castles.  There was nobody
in them but two fair damosels, daughters to the lord of
Poix; they were soon taken, and had been violated, an two
English knights had not been, sir John Chandos and sir
Basset; they defended them and brought them to the king,
who for his honour made them good cheer and demanded of
them whither they would fainest go.  They said, 'To Corbie,'
and the king caused them to be brought thither without
peril.  That night the king lodged in the town of Poix.  They
of the town and of the castles spake that night with the marshals
of the host, to save them and their town from brenning,
and they to pay a certain sum of florins the next day
as soon as the host was departed.  This was granted them,
and in the morning the king departed with all his host except
a certain that were left there to receive the money that they
of the town had promised to pay.  When they of the town
saw the host depart and but a few left behind, then they said
they would pay never a penny, and so ran out and set on the
Englishmen, who defended themselves as well as they might
and sent after the host for succour.  When sir Raynold Cobham
and sir Thomas Holland, who had the rule of the rearguard,
heard thereof, they returned and cried, 'Treason,
treason!' and so came again to Poix-ward and found their
companions still fighting with them of the town.  Then anon
they of the town were nigh all slain, and the town brent, and
the two castles beaten down.  Then they returned to the
king's host, who was as then at Airaines and there lodged,
and had commanded all manner of men on pain of death

<pb n="18"/>

to do no hurt to no town of Arsyn,<note place="foot" n="4"><p>A mistranslation.
The original is '(il avoit) defendu sus le hart que nuis ne fourfesist
rien a le ville d'arin ne d'autre cose,' 'he had commanded all on pain
of hanging to do no hurt to the town by burning or otherwise.'  The
translator has taken 'arsin' for a proper name.</p></note> for there the king was
minded to lie a day or two to take advice how he might pass
the river of Somme; for it was necessary for him to pass the
river, as ye shall hear after.
</p>
</div2>
<div2 type="section" id="d13">
<head>HOW THE FRENCH KING FOLLOWED THE KING OF ENGLAND<lb/>
IN BEAUVOISINOIS</head>

<p>Now let us speak of King Philip, who was at Sant-Denis
and his people about him, and daily increased.  Then on
a day he departed and rode so long that he came to Coppegueule,
a three leagues from Amiens, and there he tarried.
The king of England being at Airaines wist not where for
to pass the river of Somme, the which was large and deep,
and all bridges were broken and the passages well kept.
Then at the king's commandment his two marshals with a
thousand men of arms and two thousand archers went along
the river to find some passage, and passed by Longpre,
and came to the bridge of Remy,<note place="foot" n="1"><p>Pont-a-Remy,
corrupted here into 'bridge of Athyne.'</p></note> the which was well kept
with a great number of knights and squires and men of the
country.  The Englishmen alighted afoot and assailed the
Frenchmen from the morning till it was noon; but the bridge
was so well fortified and defended, that the Englishmen departed
without winning of anything.  Then they went to a
great town called Fountains on the river of Somme, the which
was clean robbed and brent, for it was not closed.  Then
they went to another town called Long-en-Ponthieu; they
could not win the bridge, it was so well kept and defended.
Then they departed and went to Picquigny, and found the
town, the bridge, and the castle so well fortified, that
it was not likely to pass there: the French king had so
well defended the passages, to the intent that the king of
England should not pass the river of Somme, to fight with
him at his advantage or else to famish him there.
</p>
<p>When these two marshals had assayed in all places to
find passage and could find none, they returned again to

<pb n="19"/>

the king, and shewed how they could find no passage in no
place.  The same night the French king came to Amiens
with more than a hundred thousand men.  The king of
England was right pensive, and the next morning heard
mass before the sun-rising and then dislodged; and every
man followed the marshals' banners and so rode in the country
of Vimeu approaching to the good town of Abbeville, and
found a town thereby, whereunto was come much people of
the country in trust of a little defence that was there; but
the Englishmen anon won it, and all they that were within
slain, and many taken of the town and of the country.  The
king took his lodging in a great hospital<note place="foot" n="2"><p>
That is, a house of the knights of Saint John.</p></note> that was there.
The same day the French king departed from Amiens and
came to Airaines about noon; and the Englishmen were
departed thence in the morning.  The Frenchmen found
there great provision that the Englishmen had left behind
them, because they departed in haste.  There they found
flesh ready on the broaches, bread and pasties in the ovens,
wine in tuns and barrels, and the tables ready laid.  There
the French king lodged and tarried for his lords.
</p>
<p>That night the king of England was lodged at Oisemont.
At night when the two marshals were returned, who had
that day overrun the country to the gates of Abbeville and
to Saint-Valery and made a great skirmish there, then the
king assembled together his council and made to be brought
before him certain prisoners of the country of Ponthieu
and of Vimeu.  The king right courteously demanded of
them, if there were any among them that knew any passage
beneath Abbeville, that he and his host might pass over
the river of Somme: if he would shew him thereof, he
should be quit of his ransom, and twenty of his company
for his love.  There was a varlet called Gobin Agace who
stepped forth and said to the king: 'Sir, I promise you on
the jeopardy of my head I shall bring you to such a place,
whereas ye and all your host shall pass the river of Somme
without peril.  There be certain places in the passage that
ye shall pass twelve men afront two times between day and
night: ye shall not go in the water to the knees.  But when
the flood cometh, the river then waxeth so great, that no

<pb n="20"/>

man can pass; but when the flood is gone, the which is two
times between day and night, then the river is so low, that
it may be passed without danger both a-horseback and afoot.
The passage is hard in the bottom with white stones, so
that all your carriage may go surely; therefore the passage
is called Blanche-taque.  An ye make ready to depart betimes,
ye may be there by the sun-rising.'  The king said: 'If
this be true that ye say, I quit thee thy ransom and all thy
company, and moreover shall give thee a hundred nobles.'
Then the king commanded every man to be ready at the
sound of the trumpet to depart.
</p>
</div2>
<div2 type="section" id="d14">
<head>OF THE BATTLE OF BLANCHE-TAQUE BETWEEN THE KING OF<lb/>
ENGLAND AND SIR GODEMAR DU FAY</head>

<p>THE king of England slept not much that night, for at midnight
he arose and sowned his trumpet: then incontinent they
made ready carriages and all things, and at the breaking
of the day they departed from the town of Oisemont and
rode after the guiding of Gobin Agace, so that they came
by the sun-rising to Blanche-taque; but as then the flood was
up, so that they might not pass: so the king tarried there
till it was prime; then the ebb came.
</p>
<p>The French king had his currours in the country, who
brought him word of the demeanour of the Englishmen.
Then he thought to close the king of England between
Abbeville and the river of Somme, and so to fight with him
at his pleasure.  And when he was at Amiens he had
ordained a great baron of Normandy, called sir Godemar
du Fay, to go and keep the passage of Blanche-taque, where
the Englishmen must pass or else in none other place.  He
had with him a thousand men of arms and six thousand
afoot, with the Genoways: so they went by Saint-Riquier
in Ponthieu and from thence to Crotoy, whereas the passage
lay; and also he had with him a great number of men of the
country, and also a great number of them of Montreuil, so
that they were a twelve thousand men one and other.
</p>
<p>When the English host was come thither, sir Godemar du
Fay arranged all his company to defend the passage.  The
king of England let not for all that; but when the flood

<pb n="21"/>

was gone, he commanded his marshals to enter into the water
in the name of God and Saint George.  Then they that
were hardy and courageous entered on both parties, and
many a man reversed.  There were some of the Frenchmen
of Artois and Picardy that were as glad to joust in the
water as on the dry land.
</p>
<p>The Frenchmen defended so well the passage at the issuing
out of the water, that they had much to do.  The Genoways
did them great trouble with their cross-bows: on the
other side the archers of England shot so wholly together,
that the Frenchmen were fain to give place to the Englishmen.
There was a sore battle, and many a noble feat of
arms done on both sides.  Finally the Englishmen passed
over and assembled together in the field.  The king and the
prince passed, and all the lords; then the Frenchmen kept
none array, but departed, he that might best.  When sir Godemar
saw that discomfiture, he fled and saved himself: some
fled to Abbeville and some to Saint-Riquiers.  They that were
there afoot could not flee, so that there were slain a great
number of them of Abbeville, Montreuil, Rue and of Saint-Riquiers: the chase endured more than a great league.  And
as yet all the Englishmen were not passed the river, and
certain currours of the king of Bohemia and of sir John
of Hainault came on them that were behind and took certain
horses and carriages and slew divers, or they could
take the passage.
</p>
<p>The French king the same morning was departed from
Airaines, trusting to have found the Englishmen between
him and the river of Somme: but when he heard how that sir
Godemar du Fay and his company were discomfited, he
tarried in the field and demanded of his marshals what
was best to do.  They said, 'Sir, ye cannot pass the
river but at the bridge of Abbeville, for the flood is
come in at Blanche-taque': then he returned and lodged
at Abbeville.
</p>
<p>The king of England when he was past the river, he
thanked God and so rode forth in like manner as he did
before.  Then he called Gobin Agace and did quit him his
ransom and all his company, and gave him a hundred nobles
and a good horse.  And so the king rode forth fair and

<pb n="22"/>

easily, and thought to have lodged in a great town called
Noyelles; but when he knew that the town pertained to
the countess d'Aumale, sister to the lord Robert of Artois,
<note place="foot" n="1"><p>She was in fact his daughter.</p></note>
the king assured the town and country as much as pertained
to her, and so went forth; and his marshals rode to
Crotoy on the sea-side and brent the town, and found in
the haven many ships and barks charged with wines of
Poitou, pertaining to the merchants of Saintonge and of
Rochelle: they brought the best thereof to the king's host.
Then one of the marshals rode to the gates of Abbeville and
from thence to Saint-Riquiers, and after to the town of
Rue-Saint-Esprit.  This was on a Friday, and both battles
of the marshals returned to the king's host about noon and so
lodged all together near to Cressy in Ponthieu.
</p>
<p>The king of England was well informed how the French
king followed after him to fight.  Then he said to his company:
'Let us take here some plot of ground, for we will
go no farther till we have seen our enemies.  I have good
cause here to abide them, for I am on the right heritage of
the queen my mother, the which land was given at her marriage:
I will challenge it of mine adversary Philip of
Valois.'  And because that he had not the eighth part in
number of men as the French king had, therefore he commanded
his marshals to chose a plot of ground somewhat
for his advantage: and so they did, and thither the king
and his host went.  Then he sent his currours to Abbeville,
to see if the French king drew that day into the field or
not.  They went forth and returned again, and said how
they could see none appearance of his coming: then every
man took their lodging for that day, and to be ready in
the morning at the sound of the trumpet in the same place.
This Friday the French king tarried still in Abbeville abiding
for his company, and sent his two marshals to ride out
to see the dealing of the Englishmen, and at night they
returned, and said how the Englishmen were lodged in the
fields.  That night the French king made a supper to all
the chief lords that were there with him, and after supper
the king desired them to be friends each to other.  The
king looked for the earl of Savoy, who should come to

<pb n="23"/>

him with a thousand spears, for he had received wages for
a three months of them at Troyes in Champagne.
</p>
</div2>
<div2 type="section" id="d15">
<head>OF THE ORDER OF THE ENGLISHMEN AT CRESSY, AND<lb/>
HOW THEY MADE THREE BATTLES AFOOT</head>

<p>ON the Friday, as I said before, the king of England lay
in the fields, for the country was plentiful of wines and
other victual, and if need had been, they had provision
following in carts and other carriages.  That night the king
made a supper to all his chief lords of his host and made
them good cheer; and when they were all departed to take
their rest, then the king entered into his oratory and kneeled
down before the altar, praying God devoutly, that if he
fought the next day, that he might achieve the journey
to his honour: then about midnight he laid him down to
rest, and in the morning he rose betimes and heard mass,
and the prince his son with him, and the most part of his
company were confessed and houselled; and after the mass
said, he commanded every man to be armed and to draw
to the field to the same place before appointed.  Then the
king caused a park to be made by the wood side behind his
host, and there was set all carts and carriages, and within the
park were all their horses, for every man was afoot; and
into this park there was but one entry.  Then he ordained
three battles: in the first was the young prince of Wales,
with him the earl of Warwick and Oxford, the lord Godfrey
of Harcourt, sir Raynold Cobham, sir Thomas Holland,
the lord Stafford, the lord of Mohun, the lord Delaware, sir
John Chandos, sir Bartholomew de Burghersh, sir Robert
Nevill, the lord Thomas Clifford, the lord Bourchier, the
lord de Latimer, and divers other knights and squires that
I cannot name: they were an eight hundred men of arms
and two thousand archers, and a thousand of other with
the Welshmen: every lord drew to the field appointed
under his own banner and pennon.  In the second battle
was the earl of Northampton, the earl of Arundel, the lord
Ros, the lord Lucy, the lord Willoughby, the lord Basset,
the lord of Saint-Aubin, sir Louis Tufton, the lord of
Multon, the lord Lascelles and divers other, about an eight

<pb n="24"/>

hundred men of arms and twelve hundred archers.  The
third battle had the king: he had seven hundred men of arms
and two thousand archers.  Then the king leapt on a hobby,
<note place="foot" n="1"><p>'Un petit palefroi.'</p></note>
with a white rod in his hand, one of his marshals on the
one hand and the other on the other hand: he rode from
rank to rank desiring every man to take heed that day to his
right and honour.  He spake it so sweetly and with so good
countenance and merry cheer, that all such as were discomfited
took courage in the seeing and hearing of him.  And
when he had thus visited all his battles, it was then nine
of the day: then he caused every man to eat and drink a
little, and so they did at their leisure.  And afterward they
ordered again their battles: then every man lay down on the
earth and by him his salet and bow, to be the more fresher
when their enemies should come.
</p>
</div2>
<div2 type="section" id="d16">
<head>THE ORDER OF THE FRENCHMEN AT CRESSY, AND HOW
THEY<lb/>
BEHELD THE DEMEANOUR OF THE ENGLISHMEN</head>

<p>THIS Saturday the French king rose betimes and heard
mass in Abbeville in his lodging in the abbey of Saint
Peter, and he departed after the sun-rising.  When he was
out of the town two leagues, approaching toward his enemies,
some of his lords said to him: 'Sir, it were good that ye
ordered your battles, and let all your footmen pass somewhat
on before, that they be not troubled with the horsemen.'
Then the king sent four knights, the Moine [of]
Bazeilles, the lord of Noyers, the lord of Beaujeu and the
lord d'Aubigny to ride to aview the English host; and so
they rode so near that they might well see part of their
dealing.  The Englishmen saw them well and knew well
how they were come thither to aview them: they let them
alone and made no countenance toward them, and let them
return as they came.  And when the French king saw these
four knights return again, he tarried till they came to him
and said: 'Sirs, what tidings?'  These four knights each
of them looked on other, for there was none would speak
before his companion; finally the king said to [the] Moine,
who pertained to the king of Bohemia and had done in his

<pb n="25"/>

days so much, that he was reputed for one of the valiantest
knights of the world: 'Sir, speak you.'  Then he said:
'Sir, I shall speak, sith it pleaseth you, under the correction
of my fellows.  Sir, we have ridden and seen the behaving
of your enemies: know ye for truth they are rested in three
battles abiding for you.  Sir, I will counsel you as for my
part, saving your displeasure, that you and all your company
rest here and lodge for this night: for or they that be behind
of your company be come hither, and or your battles
be set in good order, it will be very late, and your people
be weary and out of array, and ye shall find your enemies
fresh and ready to receive you.  Early in the morning
ye may order your battles at more leisure and advise your
enemies at more deliberation, and to regard well what
way ye will assail them; for, sir, surely they will abide
you.'
</p>
<p>Then the king commanded that it should be so done.  Then
his two marshals one rode before, another behind, saying
to every banner: 'Tarry and abide here in the name of
God and Saint Denis.'  They that were foremost tarried,
but they that were behind would not tarry, but rode forth,
and said how they would in no wise abide till they were as
far forward as the foremost: and when they before saw
them come on behind, then they rode forward again, so
that the king nor his marshals could not rule them.  So they
rode without order or good array, till they came in sight of
their enemies: and as soon as the foremost saw them, they
reculed then aback without good array, whereof they behind
had marvel and were abashed, and thought that the
foremost company had been fighting.  Then they might
have had leisure and room to have gone forward, if they
had list: some went forth and some abode still.  The commons,
of whom all the ways between Abbeville and Cressy
were full, when they saw that they were near to their
enemies, they took their swords and cried: 'Down with
them! let us slay them all.'  There is no man, though he
were present at the journey, that could imagine or shew
the truth of the evil order that was among the French
party, and yet they were a marvellous great number.  That
I write in this book I learned it specially of the Englishmen,

<pb n="26"/>

who well beheld their dealing; and also certain knights of
sir John of Hainault's, who was always about king Philip,
shewed me as they knew.
</p>
</div2>
<div2 type="section" id="d17">
<head>OF THE BATTLE OF CRESSY BETWEEN THE KING OF<lb/>
ENGLAND AND THE FRENCH KING</head>

<p>THE Englishmen, who were in three battles lying on the
ground to rest them, as soon as they saw the Frenchmen
approach, they rose upon their feet fair and easily without
any haste and arranged their battles.   The first, which was
the prince's battle, the archers there stood in manner of
a herse and the men of arms in the bottom of the battle.
The earl of Northampton and the earl of Arundel with the
second battle were on a wing in good order, ready to comfort
the prince's battle, if need were.
</p>
<p>The lords and knights of France came not to the assembly
together in good order, for some came before and some
came after in such haste and evil order, that one of them
did trouble another.  When the French king saw the Englishmen,
his blood changed, and said to his marshals: 'Make
the Genoways go on before and begin the battle in the
name of God and Saint Denis.'  There were of the Genoways
cross-bows about a fifteen thousand,<note place="foot" n="1"><p>
Villani, a very good authority on the subject, says 6000, brought from
the ships at Harfleur.</p></note> but they were
so weary of going afoot that day a six leagues armed with
their cross-bows, that they said to their constables: 'We be
not well ordered to fight this day, for we be not in the case
to do any great deed of arms: we have more need of rest.'
These words came to the earl of Alencon, who said: 'A
man is well at ease to be charged with such a sort of rascals,
to be faint and fail now at most need.'  Also the same
season there fell a great rain and a clipse<note place="foot" n="2"><p>
A mistranslation of 'une esclistre,' 'a flash of lightning.'</p></note>
with a terrible
thunder, and before the rain there came flying over both
battles a great number of crows for fear of the tempest
coming.  Then anon the air began to wax clear, and the
sun to shine fair and bright, the which was right in the
Frenchmen's eyen and on the Englishmen's backs.  When

<pb n="27"/>

the Genoways were assembled together and began to approach,
they made a great leap<note place="foot" n="3"><p>These
'leaps' of the Genoese are invented by the translator, and have
passed from him into several respectable English text-books,
sometimes in company with the eclipse above mentioned.  Froissart
says: 'Il commencierent a juper mouit epouvantablement'; that is,
'to utter cries.'  Another text makes mention of the English
cannons at this point: 'The English remained still and let off
some cannons that they had, to frighten the Genoese.'</p></note>
and cry to abash the Englishmen,
but they stood still and stirred not for all that:
then the Genoways again the second time made another
leap and a fell cry, and stept forward a little, and the Englishmen
removed not one foot: thirdly, again they leapt
and cried, and went forth till they came within shot; then
they shot fiercely with their cross-bows.  Then the English
archers stept forth one pace and let fly their arrows so
wholly [together] and so thick, that it seemed snow.  When
the Genoways felt the arrows piercing through heads, arms
and breasts, many of them cast down their cross-bows and
did cut their strings and returned discomfited.  When the
French king saw them fly away, he said: 'Slay these rascals,
for they shall let and trouble us without reason.'  Then
ye should have seen the men of arms dash in among them
and killed a great number of them: and ever still the Englishmen
shot whereas they saw thickest press; the sharp arrows
ran into the men of arms and into their horses, and many
fell, horse and men, among the Genoways, and when they
were down, they could not relieve<note place="foot" n="4"><p>The
translator's word 'relieve' (relyuue) represents 'relever,'
for 'se relever.'</p></note> again, the press was so
thick that one overthrew another.  And also among the
Englishmen there were certain rascals that went afoot with
great knives, and they went in among the men of arms,
and slew and murdered many as they lay on the ground,
both earls, barons, knights and squires, whereof the king
of England was after displeased, for he had rather they had
been taken prisoners.
</p>
<p>The valiant king of Bohemia called Charles of Luxembourg,
son to the noble emperor Henry of Luxembourg, for
all that he was nigh blind, when he understood the order
of the battle, he said to them about him: 'Where is the
lord Charles my son?'  His men said: 'Sir, we cannot tell;
we think he be fighting.'  Then he said: 'Sirs, ye are my

<pb n="28"/>

men, my companions and friends in this journey: I require
you bring me so far forward, that I may strike one
stroke with my sword.'  They said they would do his commandment,
and to the intent that they should not lose him in
the press, they tied all their reins of their bridles each to
other and set the king before to accomplish his desire, and
so they went on their enemies.  The lord Charles of Bohemia
his son, who wrote himself king of Almaine and bare
the arms, he came in good order to the battle; but when he
saw that the matter went awry on their party, he departed,
I cannot tell you which way.  The king his father was so
far forward that he strake a stroke with his sword, yea
and more than four, and fought valiantly and so did his
company; and they adventured themselves so forward, that
they were there all slain, and the next day they were
found in the place about the king, and all their horses tied
each to other.
</p>
<p>The earl of Alencon came to the battle right ordinately
and fought with the Englishmen, and the earl of Flanders
also on his part.  These two lords with their companies
coasted the English archers and came to the prince's battle,
and there fought valiantly long.  The French king would
fain have come thither, when he saw their banners, but
there was a great hedge of archers before him.  The same
day the French king had given a great black courser to sir
John of Hainault, and he made the lord Tierry of Senzeille
to ride on him and to bear his banner.  The same horse
took the bridle in the teeth and brought him through
all the currours of the Englishmen, and as he would have
returned again, he fell in a great dike and was sore hurt,
and had been there dead, an his page had not been, who
followed him through all the battles and saw where his
master lay in the dike, and had none other let but for
his horse, for the Englishmen would not issue out of
their battle for taking of any prisoner.  Then the page
alighted and relieved his master: then he went not back
again the same way that they came, there was too many
in his way.
</p>
<p>This battle between Broye and Cressy this Saturday was
right cruel and fell, and many a feat of arms done that came

<pb n="29"/>

not to my knowledge.  In the night<note place="foot" n="5"><p>
'Sus le nuit,' 'towards nightfall.'</p></note> divers knights and
squires lost their masters, and sometime came on the
Englishmen, who received them in such wise that they were
ever nigh slain; for there was none taken to mercy nor to
ransom, for so the Englishmen were determined.
</p>
<p>In the morning<note place="foot" n="6"><p>The text has
suffered by omissions.  What Froissart says is that if the
battle had begun in the morning, it might have gone better
for the French, and then he instances the exploits of those
who broke through the archers. The battle did not begin till
four o'clock in the afternoon.</p></note>
the day of the battle certain Frenchmen
and Almains perforce opened the archers of the prince's
battle and came and fought with the men of arms hand to
hand.  Then the second battle of the Englishmen came to
succour the prince's battle, the which was time, for they
had as then much ado; and they with the prince sent a
messenger to the king, who was on a little windmill hill.
Then the knight said to the king: 'Sir, the earl of Warwick
and the earl of Oxford, sir Raynold Cobham and other,
such as be about the prince, your son, are fiercely fought
withal and are sore handled; wherefore they desire you
that you and your battle will come and aid them; for if
the Frenchmen increase, as they doubt they will, your son
and they shall have much ado.'  Then the king said: 'Is
my son dead or hurt or on the earth felled?'  'No, sir,'
quoth the knight, 'but he is hardly matched; wherefore he
hath need of your aid.'  'Well" said the king, 'return to
him and to them that sent you hither, and say to them that
they send no more to me for any adventure that falleth,
as long as my son is alive: and also say to them that they
suffer him this day to win his spurs;
<note place="foot" n="7"><p>'Que il laissent a l'enfant gaegnier
ses esperons.'</p></note> for if God be pleased,
I will this journey be his and the honour thereof, and to
them that be about him.'  Then the knight returned again
to them and shewed the king's words, the which greatly
encouraged them, and repoined<note place="foot" n="8"><p>i.e. 'they
repoined': Fr.  'se reprisent.'</p></note> in that they had sent to
the king as they did.
</p>
<p>Sir Godfrey of Harcourt would gladly that the earl of
Harcourt his brother might have been saved; for he heard
say by them that saw his banner how that he was there in
the field on the French party: but sir Godfrey could not

<pb n="30"/>

come to him betimes, for he was slain or he could come at
him, and so was also the earl of Aumale his nephew.  In
another place the earl of Alencon and the earl of Flanders
fought valiantly, every lord under his own banner; but
finally they could not resist against the puissance of the
Englishmen, and so there they were also slain, and divers
other knights and squires.  Also the earl Louis of Blois,
nephew to the French king, and the duke of Lorraine
fought under their banners, but at last they were closed in
among a company of Englishmen and Welshmen, and there
were slain for all their prowess.  Also there was slain
the earl of Auxerre, the earl of Saint-Pol and many other.
</p>
<p>In the evening the French king, who had left about him
no more than a three-score persons, one and other, whereof
sir John of Hainault was one, who had remounted once
the king, for his horse was slain with an arrow, then he
said to the king: 'Sir, depart hence, for it is time; lose
not yourself wilfully: if ye have loss at this time, ye shall
recover it again another season.'  And so he took the king's
horse by the bridle and led him away in a manner perforce.
Then the king rode till he came to the castle of Broye.  The
gate was closed, because it was by that time dark: then the
king called the captain, who came to the walls and said: 'Who
is that calleth there this time of night?'  Then the king
said: 'Open your gate quickly, for this is the fortune of
France.'<note place="foot" n="9"><p>'C'est la fortune de France':
but the better MSS. have 'c'est li infortunes rois de France.'</p></note>
The captain knew then it was the king, and
opened the gate and let down the bridge.  Then the king
entered, and he had with him but five barons, sir John of
Hainault, sir Charles of Montmorency, the lord of Beaujeu,
the lord d'Aubigny and the lord of Montsault.  The king
would not tarry there, but drank and departed thence about
midnight, and so rode by such guides as knew the country
till he came in the morning to Amiens, and there he rested.
</p>
<p>This Saturday the Englishmen never departed from their
battles for chasing of any man, but kept still their field,
and ever defended themselves against all such as came to
assail them.  This battle ended about evensong time.
</p>

<pb n="31"/>
</div2>
<div2 type="section" id="d18">
<head>HOW THE NEXT DAY AFTER THE BATTLE THE ENGLISHMEN<lb/>
DISCOMFITED DIVERS FRENCHMEN</head>

<p>ON this Saturday, when the night was come and that the
Englishmen heard no more noise of the Frenchmen, then
they reputed themselves to have the victory, and the Frenchmen
to be discomfited, slain and fled away.  Then they made
great fires and lighted up torches and candles, because it
was very dark.  Then the king avaled down from the little
hill whereas he stood; and of all that day till then his helm
came never on his head.  Then he went with all his battle
to his son the prince and embraced him in his arms and
kissed him, and said: 'Fair son, God give you good perseverance;
ye are my good son, thus ye have acquitted you
nobly: ye are worthy to keep a realm.'  The prince inclined
himself to the earth, honouring the king his father.
</p>
<p>This night they thanked God for their good adventure
and made no boast thereof, for the king would that no man
should be proud or make boast, but every man humbly to
thank God.  On the Sunday in the morning there was
such a mist, that a man might not see the breadth of an acre
of land from him.  Then there departed from the host by
the commandment of the king and marshals five hundred
spears and two thousand archers, to see if they might see
any Frenchmen gathered again together in any place.  The
same morning out of Abbeville and Saint-Riquiers in Ponthieu
the commons of Rouen and of Beauvais issued out
of their towns, not knowing of the discomfiture of the day
before.  They met with the Englishmen weening they had
been Frenchmen, and when the Englishmen saw them, they
set on them freshly, and there was a sore battle; but at last
the Frenchmen fled and kept none array.  There were slain
in the ways and in hedges and bushes more than seven
thousand and if the day had been clear there had never
a one escaped.  Anon after, another company of Frenchmen
were met by the Englishmen, the archbishop of Rouen and
the great prior of France, who also knew nothing of the discomfiture
the day before; for they heard that the French
king should have fought the same Sunday, and they were going

<pb n="32"/>

thitherward.  When they met with the Englishmen, there
was a great battle, for they were a great number, but they
could not endure against the Englishmen; for they were
nigh all slain, few escaped; the two lords were slain.
This morning the Englishmen met with divers Frenchmen
that had lost their way on the Saturday and had lain all
night in the fields, and wist not where the king was nor the
captains.  They were all slain, as many as were met with;
and it was shewed me that of the commons and men afoot
of the cities and good towns of France there was slain four
times as many as were slain the Saturday in the great
battle.
</p>
</div2>
<div2 type="section" id="d19">
<head>HOW THE NEXT DAY AFTER THE BATTLE OF CRESSY THEY
THAT<lb/>
WERE DEAD WERE NUMBERED BY THE ENGLISHMEN</head>

<p>THE same Sunday, as the king of England came from mass,
such as had been sent forth returned and shewed the king
what they had seen and done, and said: 'Sir, we think
surely there is now no more appearance of any of our
enemies.'  Then the king sent to search how many were
slain and what they were.  Sir Raynold Cobham and sir
Richard Stafford with three heralds went to search the
field and country: they visited all them that were slain and
rode all day in the fields, and returned again to the host as
the king was going to supper.  They made just report of that
they had seen, and said how there were eleven great princes
dead, fourscore banners, twelve hundred knights, and more
than thirty thousand other.<note place="foot" n="1"><p>Another text
makes the loss of persons below the rank of knight 15,000
or 16,000, including the men of the towns.  Both estimates must
be greatly exaggerated.  Michael of Northburgh says that 1542
were killed in the battle and about 2000 on the next day.  The
great princes killed were the king of Bohemia, the duke of
Lorraine, the earls of Alencon, Flanders, Blois, Auxerre, Harcourt,
Saint-Pol, Aumale, the grand prior of France and the archbishop
of Rouen.</p></note>  The Englishmen kept still
their field all that night: on the Monday in the morning the
king prepared to depart: the king caused the dead bodies
of the great lords to be taken up and conveyed to Montreuil,
and there buried in holy ground, and made a cry in
the country to grant truce for three days, to the intent

<pb n="33"/>

that they of the country might search the field of Cressy to
bury the dead bodies.
</p>
<p>Then the king went forth and came before the town of
Montreuil-by-the-sea, and his marshals ran toward Hesdin
and brent Waben and Serain, but they did nothing to the
castle, it was so strong and so well kept.  They lodged that
night on the river of Hesdin towards Blangy.  The next
day they rode toward Boulogne and came to the town of
Wissant: there the king and the prince lodged, and tarried
there a day to refresh his men, and on the Wednesday the
king came before the strong town of Calais.
</p>

<pb n="34"/>
</div2>
</div1>

<div1 type="chapter" n="2" id="d20">
<head>The Battle of Poitiers</head>
<div2 type="section" id="d21">
<head>OF THE GREAT HOST THAT THE FRENCH KING BROUGHT<lb/>
TO THE BATTLE OF POITIERS</head>

<p>AFTER the taking of the castle of Romorantin and of
them that were therein, the prince then and his company
rode as they did before, destroying the country,
approaching to Anjou and to Touraine.  The French king, who
was at Chartres, departed and came to Blois and there tarried
two days, and then to Amboise and the next day to Loches:
and then he heard how that the prince was at Touraine
<note place="foot" n="1"><p>"En Touraine."</p></note> and
how that he was returning by Poitou: ever the Englishmen
were coasted by certain expert knights of France, who
alway made report to the king what the Englishmen did.
Then the king came to the Haye in Touraine and his men
had passed the river of Loire, some at the bridge of Orleans
and some at Meung, at Saumur, at Blois, and at Tours
and whereas they might: they were in number a twenty
thousand men of arms beside other; there were a twenty-six dukes and earls and more than sixscore banners, and
the four sons of the king, who were but young, the duke
Charles of Normandy, the lord Louis, that was from thenceforth
duke of Anjou, and the lord John duke of Berry, and
the lord Philip, who was after duke of Burgoyne.  The same
season, pope Innocent the sixth sent the lord Bertrand,
cardinal of Perigord, and the lord Nicholas, cardinal of
Urgel, into France, to treat for a peace between the French
king and all his enemies, first between him and the king of
Navarre, who was in prison: and these cardinals oftentimes
spake to the king for his deliverance during the siege at
Bretuel, but they could do nothing in that behalf.  Then the
cardinal of Perigord went to Tours, and there he heard

<pb n="35"/>

how the French king hasted sore to find the Englishmen:
then he rode to Poitiers, for he heard how both the hosts
drew thitherward.
</p>
<p>The French king heard how the prince hasted greatly to
return, and the king feared that he should scape him and
so departed from Haye in Touraine, and all his company,
and rode to Chauvigny, where he tarried that Thursday in
the town and without along by the river of Creuse, and the
next day the king passed the river at the bridge there, weening
that the Englishmen had been before him, but they were
not.  Howbeit they pursued after and passed the bridge that
day more than threescore thousand horses, and divers other
passed at Chatelleraut, and ever as they passed they took
the way to Poitiers.
</p>
<p>On the other side the prince wist not truly where the
Frenchmen were; but they supposed that they were not far
off, for they could not find no more forage, whereby they
had great fault in their host of victual, and some of them
repented that they had destroyed so much as they had done
before when they were in Berry, Anjou and Touraine, and
in that they had made no better provision.  The same Friday
three great lords of France, the lord of Craon, the lord
Raoul of Coucy and the earl of Joigny, tarried all day at
the town of Chauvigny, and part of their companies.  The
Saturday they passed the bridge and followed the king, who
was then a three leagues before, and took the way among
bushes without a wood side to go to Poitiers.
</p>
<p>The same Saturday the prince and his company dislodged
from a little village thereby, and sent before him certain
currours to see if they might find any adventure and to hear
where the Frenchmen were.  They were in number a three-score men of arms well horsed, and with them was the lord
Eustace d'Aubrecicourt and the lord John of Ghistelles, and
by adventure the Englishmen and Frenchmen met together
by the foresaid wood side.  The Frenchmen knew anon how
they were their enemies; then in haste they did on their
helmets and displayed their banners and came a great pace
towards the Englishmen: they were in number a two hundred
men of arms.  When the Englishmen saw them, and
that they were so great a number, then they determined to

<pb n="36"/>

fly and let the Frenchmen chase them, for they knew well
the prince with his host was not far behind.  Then they
turned their horses and took the corner of the wood, and
the Frenchmen after them crying their cries and made great
noise.  And as they chased, they came on the prince's battle
or they were ware thereof themselves; the prince tarried
there to have word again from them that he sent forth.
The lord Raoul de Coucy with his banner went so far forward
that he was under the prince's banner: there was a
sore battle and the knight fought valiantly; howbeit he
was there taken, and the earl of Joigny, the viscount of
Brosse, the lord of Chauvigny and all the other taken or
slain, but a few that scaped.  And by the prisoners the
prince knew how the French king followed him in such wise
that he could not eschew the battle:<note place="foot" n="2"><p>Or rather,
'that the French king had gone in front of them (les avoit
advancez) and that he could in no way depart without being
fought with.'</p></note>then he assembled
together all his men and commanded that no man should go
before the marshals' banners.  Thus the prince rode that
Saturday from the morning till it was against night, so that
he came within two little leagues of Poitiers.  Then the
captal de Buch, sir Aymenion of Pommiers, the lord Bartholomew
of Burghersh and the lord Eustace d'Aubrecicourt,
all these the prince sent forth to see if they might know
what the Frenchmen did.  These knights departed with two
hundred men of arms well horsed: they rode so far that they
saw the great battle of the king's, they saw all the fields
covered with men of arms.  These Englishmen could not
forbear, but set on the tail of the French host and cast down
many to the earth and took divers prisoners, so that the
host began to stir, and tidings thereof came to the French
king as he was entering into the city of Poitiers.  Then he
returned again and made all his host do the same, so that
Saturday it was very late or he was lodged in the field.
The English currours returned again to the prince and
shewed him all that they saw and knew, and said how the
French host was a great number of people.  'Well,' said the
prince, 'in the name of God let us now study how we shall
fight with them at our advantage.'  That night the Englishmen
lodged in a strong place among hedges, vines and

<pb n="37"/>

bushes, and their host well watched, and so was the French
host.
</p></div2>
<div2 type="section" id="d22">
<head>OF THE ORDER OF THE FRENCHMEN BEFORE<lb/>
THE BATTLE OF P0ITIERS</head>

<p>ON the Sunday in the morning the French king, who had
great desire to fight with the Englishmen, heard his mass
in his pavilion and was houselled, and his four sons with
him.  After mass there came to him the duke of Orleans,
the duke of Bourbon, the earl of Ponthieu, the lord Jaques
of Bourbon,<note place="foot" n="1"><p>That is, Jaques de Bourbon,
earl of la Marche and Ponthieu.</p></note> the duke of Athens,
constable of France, the
earl of Tancarville, the earl of Sarrebruck, the earl of
Dammartin, the earl of Ventadour, and divers other great
barons of France and of other neighbours holding of France,
as the lord Clermont, the lord Arnold d'Audrehem, marshal
of France, the lord of Saint-Venant, the lord John of
Landas, the lord Eustace Ribemont, the lord Fiennes, the
lord Geoffrey of Charny, the lord Chatillon, the lord of
Sully, the lord of Nesle, sir Robert Duras and divers other;
all these with the king went to counsel.  Then finally it was
ordained that all manner of men should draw into the field,
and every lord to display his banner and to set forth in the
name of God and Saint Denis: then trumpets blew up
through the host and every man mounted on horseback and
went into the field, where they saw the king's banner wave
with the wind.  There might a been seen great nobless of
fair harness and rich armoury of banners and pennons; for
there was all the flower of France, there was none durst
abide at home without he would be shamed for ever.  Then
it was ordained by the advice of the constable and marshals
to be made three battles, and in each ward sixteen thousand
men of arms all mustered and passed for men of arms.
The first battle the duke of Orleans to govern, with thirty-six banners and twice as many pennons, the second the duke
of Normandy and his two brethren the lord Louis and the
lord John, the third the king himself: and while that these
battles were setting in array, the king called to him the lord
Eustace Ribemont, the lord John of Landas and the lord

<pb n="38"/>

Richard of Beaujeu, and said to them: 'Sirs, ride on before
to see the dealing of the Englishmen and advise well
what number they be and by what means we may fight with
them, other afoot or a-horseback.'  These three knights
rode forth and the king was on a white courser and said
a-high to his men: 'Sirs, among you, when ye be at Paris,
at Chartres, at Rouen or at Orleans, then ye do threat the
Englishmen and desire to be in arms out against them.  Now
ye be come thereto: I shall now shew you them: now shew
forth your evil will that ye bear them and revenge your
displeasures and damages that they have done you, for
without doubt we shall fight with them.'  Such as heard him
said: 'Sir, in God's name so be it; that would we see
<note place="foot" n="2"><p>'Verrons': but a better reading is 'ferons,'
'that will we do gladly.'</p></note> gladly.'
</p>
<p>Therewith the three knights returned again to the king,
who demanded of them tidings.  Then sir Eustace of Ribemont
answered for all and said: 'Sir, we have seen the
Englishmen: by estimation they be two thousand men of
arms and four thousand archers and a fifteen hundred of
other.  Howbeit they be in a strong place, and as far as we
can imagine they are in one battle; howbeit they be wisely
ordered, and along the way they have fortified strongly
the hedges and bushes: one part of their archers are along
by the hedge, so that none can go nor ride that way, but
must pass by them, and that way must ye go an ye purpose
to fight with them.  In this hedge there is but one entry
and one issue by likelihood that four horsemen may ride
afront.  At the end of this hedge, whereas no man can go
nor ride, there be men of arms afoot and archers afore them
in manner of a herse, so that they will not be lightly discomfited.'
<note place="foot" n="3"><p>The translation of this
passage is unsatisfactory.  It should be: 'Howbeit they have
ordered it wisely, and have taken post along the road, which
on one side (or according to another text, on one side and on
the other) with their archers, so that one cannot enter nor
ride along their road except by them, and that way must he go
who purposes to fight with them.  In this hedge there is but
one entry and one issue, where by likelihood four men of arms,
as on the road, might ride a-front.  At the end of this hedge
among vines and thorn-bushes, where no man can go nor ride, are
their men of arms all afoot, and they have set in front of them
their archers in manner of a harrow, whom it would not be easy
to discomfit.</p></note>  'Well,' said the king, 'what will ye then
counsel us to do?'  Sir Eustace said: 'Sir, let us all be afoot,

<pb n="39"/>

except three hundred men of arms, well horsed, of the best
in your host and most hardiest, to the intent they somewhat
to break and to open the archers, and then your battles to
follow on quickly afoot and so to fight with their men of
arms hand to hand.  This is the best advice that I can give
you: if any other think any other way better, let him speak.'
The king said: 'Thus shall it be done': then the two
marshals rode from battle to battle and chose out a three
hundred knights and squires of the most expert men of
arms of all the host, every man well armed and horsed.
Also it was ordained that the battles of Almains should
abide still on horseback to comfort the marshals, if need
were, whereof the earl of Sarrebruck, the earl of Nidau
and the earl of Nassau were captains.  King John of France
was there armed, and twenty other in his apparel; and he
did put the guiding of his eldest son to the lord of Saint-Venant, the lord of Landas and the lord Thibault of Vaudenay;
and the lord Arnold of Cervolles, called the archpriest,
<note place="foot" n="4"><p>Arnaud de Cervolles, one of the most
celebrated adventurers of the 14th  century, called the
archpriest because though a layman he possessed the
ecclesiastical fief of Velines.</p></note>
was armed in the armour of the young earl of Alencon.
</p>
</div2>
<div2 type="section" id="d23">
<head>HOW THE CARDINAL OF PERIGORD TREATED TO MAKE
AGREEMENT<lb/>
BETWEEN THE FRENCH KING AND THE<lb/>
PRINCE BEFORE THE BATTLE OF POITIERS</head>

<p>WHEN the French king's battles was ordered and every
lord under his banner among their own men, then it was commanded
that every man should cut their spears to a five
foot long and every man to put off their spurs.  Thus as they
were ready to approach, the cardinal of Perigord
<note place="foot" n="1"><p>Talleyrand de Perigord.</p></note> came in
great haste to the king.  He came the same morning from
Poitiers; he kneeled down to the king and held up his hands
and desired him for God's sake a little to abstain setting
forward till he had spoken with him: then he said: 'Sir,
ye have here all the flower of your realm against a handful
of Englishmen as to regard your company,<note place="foot" n="2"><p>
The meaning is, 'Ye have here all the flower of your realm against a
handful of people, for so the Englishmen are as compared with your
company.'</p></note> and, sir, if ye

<pb n="40"/>

may have them accorded to you without battle, it shall be
more profitable and honourable to have them by that manner
rather than to adventure so noble chivalry as ye have here
present.  Sir, I require you in the name of God and humility
that I may ride to the prince and shew him what danger ye
have him in.'  The king said: 'It pleaseth me well, but return
again shortly.'  The cardinal departed and diligently
he rode to the prince, who was among his men afoot: then
the cardinal alighted and came to the prince, who received
him courteously.  Then the cardinal after his salutation
made he said: 'Certainly, fair son, if you and your council
advise justly the puissance of the French king, ye will suffer
me to treat to make a peace between you, an I may.'  The
prince, who was young and lusty, said: 'Sir, the honour of
me and of my people saved, I would gladly fall to any
reasonable way.'  Then the cardinal said: 'Sir, ye say well,
and I shall accord you, an I can; for it should be great pity
if so many noblemen and other as be here on both parties
should come together by battle.'  Then the cardinal rode
again to the king and said: 'Sir, ye need not to make any
great haste to fight with your enemies, for they cannot fly
from you though they would, they be in such a ground:
wherefore, sir, I require you forbear for this day till tomorrow
the sun-rising.'  The king was loath to agree thereto,
for some of his council would not consent to it; but finally
the cardinal shewed such reasons, that the king accorded
that respite: and in the same place there was pight up a
pavilion of red silk fresh and rich, and gave leave for that
day every man to draw to their lodgings except the constable's
and marshals' battles.
</p>
<p>That Sunday all the day the cardinal travailed in riding
from the one host to the other gladly to agree them: but
the French king would not agree without he might have
four of the principallest of the Englishmen at his pleasure,
and the prince and all the other to yield themselves simply:
howbeit there were many great offers made.  The prince
offered to render into the king's hands all that ever he had
won in that voyage, towns and castles, and to quit all
prisoners that he or any of his men had taken in that season,
and also to swear not to be armed against the French king

<pb n="41"/>

in seven year after; but the king and his council would none
thereof: the uttermost that he would do was, that the prince
and a hundred of his knights should yield themselves into
the king's prison; otherwise he would not: the which the
prince would in no wise agree unto.
</p>
<p>In the mean season that the cardinal rode thus between
the hosts in trust to do some good, certain knights of France
and of England both rode forth the same Sunday, because
it was truce for that day, to coast the hosts and to behold
the dealing of their enemies.  So it fortuned that the lord
John Chandos rode the same day coasting the French host,
and in like manner the lord of Clermont, one of the French
marshals, had ridden forth and aviewed the state of the
English host; and as these two knights returned towards
their hosts, they met together: each of them bare one manner
of device, a blue lady embroidered in a sunbeam above
on their apparel.  Then the lord Clermont said: 'Chandos,
how long have ye taken on you to bear my device?'  'Nay,
ye bear mine,' said Chandos, 'for it is as well mine as yours.'
'I deny that,' said Clermont, 'but an it were not for the
truce this day between us, I should make it good on you
incontinent that ye have no right to bear my device.'  'Ah,
sir,' said Chandos, 'ye shall find me to-morrow ready to
defend you and to prove by feat of arms that it is as well
mine as yours.'  Then Clermont said: 'Chandos, these be
well the words of you Englishmen, for ye can devise nothing
of new, but all that ye see is good and fair.'  So they departed
without any more doing, and each of them returned
to their host.
</p>
<p>The cardinal of Perigord could in no wise that Sunday
make any agreement between the parties, and when it was
near night he returned to Poitiers.  That night the Frenchmen
took their ease; they had provision enough, and the
Englishmen had great default; they could get no forage,
nor they could not depart thence without danger of their
enemies.  That Sunday the Englishmen made great dikes
and hedges about their archers, to be the more stronger;
and on the Monday in the morning the prince and his company
were ready apparelled as they were before, and about
the sun-rising in like manner were the Frenchmen.  The

<pb n="42"/>

same morning betimes the cardinal came again to the French
host and thought by his preaching to pacify the parties; but
then the Frenchmen said to him: 'Return whither ye will:
bring hither no more words of treaty nor peace: and ye
love yourself depart shortly.'  When the cardinal saw that
he travailed in vain, he took leave of the king and then he
went to the prince and said: 'Sir, do what ye can: there
is no remedy but to abide the battle, for I can find none
accord in the French king.'  Then the prince said: 'The
same is our intent and all our people: God help the right!'
So the cardinal returned to Poitiers.  In his company there
were certain knights and squires, men of arms, who were
more favourable to the French king than to the prince: and
when they saw that the parties should fight, they stale from
their masters and went to the French host; and they made
their captain the chatelain of Amposte,<note place="foot" n="3"><p>
Amposta, a fortress in Catalonia.</p></note> who was as then
there with the cardinal, who knew nothing thereof till he
was come to Poitiers.
</p>
<p>The certainty of the order of the Englishmen was shewed
to the French king, except they had ordained three hundred
men a-horseback and as many archers a-horseback to coast
under covert of the mountain and to strike into the battle of
the duke of Normandy, who was under the mountain afoot.
This ordinance they had made of new, that the Frenchmen
knew not of.  The prince was with his battle down among
the vines and had closed in the weakest part with their
carriages.
</p>
<p>Now will I name some of the principal lords and knights
that were there with the prince: the earl of Warwick, the
earl of Suffolk, the earl of Salisbury, the earl of Oxford, the
lord Raynold Cobham, the lord Spencer, the lord James
Audley, the lord Peter his brother, the lord Berkeley, the
lord Bassett, the lord Warin, the lord Delaware, the lord
Manne, the lord Willoughby, the lord Bartholomew de
Burghersh, the lord of Felton, the lord Richard of Pembroke,
the lord Stephen of Cosington, the lord Bradetane
and other Englishmen; and of Gascon there was the lord of
Pommiers, the lord of Languiran, the captal of Buch, the
lord John of Caumont, the lord de Lesparre, the lord of

<pb n="43"/>

Rauzan, the lord of Condon, the lord of Montferrand, the
lord of Landiras, the lord soudic of Latrau and other that I
cannot name; and of Hainowes the lord Eustace d'Aubrecicourt,
the lord John of Ghistelles, and two other strangers,
the lord Daniel Pasele and the lord Denis of Morbeke:
all the prince's company passed not an eight thousand men
one and other, and the Frenchmen were a sixty thousand
fighting men, whereof there were more than three thousand
knights.
</p>
</div2>
<div2 type="section" id="d24">
<head>OF THE BATTLE OF POITIERS BETWEEN THE PRINCE OF
WALES<lb/>
AND THE FRENCH KING</head>

<p>WHEN the prince saw that he should have battle and that
the cardinal was gone without any peace or truce making,
and saw that the French king did set but little store by him,
he said then to his men: 'Now, sirs, though we be but a
small company as in regard to the puissance of our enemies,
let us not be abashed therefor; for the victory lieth not in
the multitude of people, but whereas God will send it.  If it
fortune that the journey be ours, we shall be the most honoured
people of all the world; and if we die in our right
quarrel, I have the king my father and brethren, and also
ye have good friends and kinsmen; these shall revenge us.
Therefore, sirs, for God's sake I require you do your devoirs
this day; for if God be pleased and Saint George, this day
ye shall see me a good knight.'  These words and such other
that the prince spake comforted all his people.  The lord
sir John Chandos that day never went from the prince, nor
also the lord James Audley of a great season; but when he
saw that they should needs fight, he said to the prince: 'Sir,
I have served always truly my lord your father and you
also, and shall do as long as I live.  I say this because I
made once a vow that the first battle that other the king your
father or any of his children should be at, how that I would
be one of the first setters on,<note place="foot" n="1"><p>'The first
setter-on and the best combatant.'</p></note> or else to die in the pain:
therefore I require your grace, as in reward for any service
that ever I did to the king your father or to you, that you
will give me licence to depart from you and to set myself

<pb n="44"/>

thereas I may accomplish my vow.'  The prince accorded
to his desire and said, 'Sir James, God give you this day that
grace to be the best knight of all other,' and so took him by
the hand.  Then the knight departed from the prince and
went to the foremost front of all the battles, all only accompanied
with four squires, who promised not to fail him.
This lord James was a right sage and a valiant knight, and
by him was much of the host ordained and governed the
day before.  Thus sir James was in front of the battle ready
to fight with the battle of the marshals of France.  In like
wise the lord Eustace d'Aubrecicourt did his pain to be one
of the foremost to set on.  When sir James Audley began
to set forward to his enemies, it fortuned to sir Eustace
d'Aubrecicourt as ye shall hear after.  Ye have heard before
how the Almains in the French host were appointed to be
still a-horseback.  Sir Eustace being a-horseback laid his
spear in the rest and ran into the French battle, and then
a knight of Almaine, called the lord Louis of Recombes, who
bare a shield silver, five roses gules, and sir Eustace bare
ermines, two branches of gules,<note place="foot" n="2"><p>That is,
two hamedes gules on a field ermine.</p></note> &mdash; when this Almain saw the
lord Eustace come from his company, he rode against him
and they met so rudely, that both knights fell to the earth.
The Almain was hurt in the shoulder, therefore he rose not
so quickly as did sir Eustace, who when he was up and had
taken his breath, he came to the other knight as he lay on
the ground; but then five other knights of Almaine came on
him all at once and bare him to the earth, and so perforce
there he was taken prisoner and brought to the earl of
Nassau, who as then took no heed of him; and I cannot say
whether they sware him prisoner or no, but they tied him
to a chare and there let him stand.<note place="foot" n="3"><p>
'They tied him on to a cart with their harness.'</p></note>
</p>
<p>Then the battle began on all parts, and the battles of the
marshals of France approached, and they set forth that were
appointed to break the array of the archers.  They entered
a-horseback into the way where the great hedges were on both
sides set full of archers.  As soon as the men of arms
entered, the archers began to shoot on both sides and did
slay and hurt horses and knights, so that the horses when

<pb n="45"/>

they felt the sharp arrows they would in no wise go forward,
but drew aback and flang and took on so fiercely, that many
of them fell on their masters, so that for press they could
not rise again; insomuch that the marshals' battle could
never come at the prince.  Certain knights and squires that
were well horsed passed through the archers and thought to
approach to the prince, but they could not.  The lord James
Audley with his four squires was in the front of that battle
and there did marvels in arms, and by great prowess he
came and fought with sir Arnold d'Audrehem under his
own banner, and there they fought long together and sir
Arnold was there sore handled.  The battle of the marshals
began to disorder by reason of the shot of the archers with
the aid of the men of arms, who came in among them and
slew of them and did what they list, and there was the lord
Arnold d'Audrehem taken prisoner by other men than by
sir James Audley or by his four squires; for that day he
never took prisoner, but always fought and went on his
enemies.
</p>
<p>Also on the French party the lord John Clermont fought
under his own banner as long as he could endure: but there
he was beaten down and could not be relieved nor ransomed,
but was slain without mercy: some said it was because of
the words that he had the day before to sir John Chandos.
So within a short space the marshals' battles were discomfited,
for they fell one upon another and could not go forth;
<note place="foot" n="4"><p>'Ne pooient aler avant.'</p></note>
and the Frenchmen that were behind and could not get forward
reculed back and came on the battle of the duke of
Normandy, the which was great and thick and were afoot,
but anon they began to open behind;<note place="foot" n="5"><p>
'Which was great and thick in front (pardevant), but anon
it became open and thin behind.'</p></note> for when they knew
that the marshals' battle was discomfited, they took their
horses and departed, he that might best.  Also they saw a
rout of Englishmen coming down a little mountain a-horseback,
and many archers with them, who brake in on the side
of the duke's battle.  True to say, the archers did their company
that day great advantage; for they shot so thick that
the Frenchmen wist not on what side to take heed, and little
and little the Englishmen won ground on them.
</p>
<pb n="46"/>
<p>And when the men of arms of England saw that the
marshals' battle was discomfited and that the duke's battle
began to disorder and open, they leapt then on their horses,
the which they had ready by them: then they assembled together
and cried, 'Saint George!  Guyenne!' and the lord
Chandos said to the prince: 'Sir, take your horse and ride
forth; this journey is yours: God is this day in your hands:
get us to the French king's battle, for their lieth all the sore
of the matter.  I think verily by his valiantness he will not
fly: I trust we shall have him by the grace of God and
Saint George, so he be well fought withal: and, sir, I heard
you say that this day I should see you a good knight.'  The
prince said, 'Let us go forth; ye shall not see me this day
return back,' and said, 'Advance, banner, in the name of
God and of Saint George.'  The knight that bare it did his
commandment: there was then a sore battle and a perilous,
and many a man overthrown, and he that was once down
could not be relieved again without great succour and aid.
As the prince rode and entered in among his enemies, he saw
on his right hand in a little bush lying dead the lord Robert
of Duras and his banner by him,<note place="foot" n="6"><p>The original
adds, 'qui estoit de France au sentoir (sautoir) de
gueulles.'</p></note> and a ten or twelve of his
men about him.  Then the prince said to two of his squires
and to three archers: 'Sirs, take the body of this knight on
a targe and bear him to Poitiers, and present him from me
to the cardinal of Perigord, and say how I salute him by that
token.'  And this was done.  The prince was informed that
the cardinal's men were on the field against him, the which
was not pertaining to the right order of arms, for men of
the church that cometh and goeth for treaty of peace ought
not by reason to bear harness nor to fight for neither of
the parties; they ought to be indifferent: and because these
men had done so, the prince was displeased with the cardinal,
and therefore he sent unto him his nephew the lord
Robert of Duras dead: and the chatelain of Amposte was
taken, and the prince would have had his head stricken off
because he was pertaining to the cardinal, but then the lord
Chandos said: 'Sir, suffer for a season: intend to a greater
matter: and peradventure the cardinal will make such excuse
that ye shall be content.'
</p>
<pb n="47"/>
<p>Then the prince and his company dressed them on the
battle of the duke of Athens, constable of France.  There
was many a man slain and cast to the earth.  As the Frenchmen
fought in companies, they cried, 'Mountjoy!  Saint
Denis!' and the Englishmen, 'Saint George!  Guyenne!'
Anon the prince with his company met with the battle of
Almains, whereof the earl of Sarrebruck, the earl Nassau
and the earl Nidau were captains, but in a short space they
were put to flight: the archers shot so wholly together that
none durst come in their dangers: they slew many a man
that could not come to no ransom: these three earls was
there slain, and divers other knights and squires of their
company, and there was the lord d'Aubrecicourt rescued
by his own men and set on horseback, and after he did that
day many feats of arms and took good prisoners.  When the
duke of Normandy's battle saw the prince approach, they
thought to save themselves, and so the duke and the king's
children, the earl of Poitiers and the earl of Touraine,
who were right young, believed their governours and so departed
from the field, and with them more than eight hundred
spears, that strake no stroke that day.  Howbeit the
lord Guichard d'Angle and the lord John of Saintre, who
were with the earl of Poitiers, would not fly, but entered
into the thickest press of the battle.  The king's three sons
took the way to Chauvigny, and the lord John of Landas
and the lord Thibauld of Vaudenay, who were set to await
on the duke of Normandy, when they had brought the duke
a long league from the battle, then they took leave of the
duke and desired the lord of Saint-Venant that he should
not leave the duke, but to bring him in safeguard, whereby
he should win more thank of the king than to abide still
in the field.  Then they met also the duke of Orleans and a
great company with him, who were also departed from the
field with clear hands: there were many good knights and
squires, though that their masters departed from the field,
yet they had rather a died than to have had any reproach.
</p>
<p>Then the king's battle came on the Englishmen: there was
a sore fight and many a great stroke given and received.
The king and his youngest son met with the battle of the
English marshals, the earl of Warwick and the earl of

<pb n="48"/>

Suffolk, and with them of Gascons the captal of Buch, the
lord of Pommiers, the lord Amery of Tastes, the lord of
Mussidan, the lord of Languiran and the lord de Latrau.  To
the French party there came time enough the lord John of
Landas and the lord of Vaudenay; they alighted afoot and
went into the king's battle, and a little beside fought the
duke of Athens, constable of France, and a little above him
the duke of Bourbon and many good knights of Bourbonnais
and of Picardy with him, and a little on the one side there
were the Poitevins, the lord de Pons, the lord of Partenay,
the lord of Dammartin, the lord of Tannay-Bouton, the lord
of Surgieres, the lord John Saintre, the lord Guichard
d'Angle, the lord Argenton, the lord of Linieres, the lord of
Montendre and divers other, also the viscount of Rochechouart
and the earl of Aunay;<note place="foot" n="7"><p>'Le conte
d'Aulnoy,' but it should be 'visconte.'</p></note> and of Burgoyne the lord
James of Beaujeu, the lord de Chateau-Vilain and other:
in another part there was the earl of Ventadour and of
Montpensier, the lord James of Bourbon, the lord John
d'Artois and also the lord James his brother, the lord Arnold
of Cervolles, called the archpriest, armed for the young earl
of Alencon; and of Auvergne there was the lord of Mercoeur,
the lord de la Tour, the lord of Chalencon, the lord of
Montaigu, the lord of Rochfort, the lord d'Acier, the lord
d'Acon; and of Limousin there was the lord de Melval, the
lord of Mareuil, the lord of Pierrebuffiere; and of Picardy
there was the lord William of Nesle, the lord Arnold of Rayneval,
the lord Geoffrey of Saint-Dizier, the lord of Chauny,
the lord of Helly, the lord of Montsault, the lord of Hangest
and divers other: and also in the king's battle there was
the earl Douglas of Scotland, who fought a season right
valiantly, but when he saw the discomfiture, he departed
and saved himself; for in no wise he would be taken of the
Englishmen, he had rather been there slain.  On the English
part the lord James Audley with the aid of his four squires
fought always in the chief of the battle: he was sore hurt
in the body and in the visage: as long as his breath served
him he fought; at last at the end of the battle his four
squires took and brought him out of the field and laid him
under a hedge side for to refresh him; and they unarmed

<pb n="49"/>

him and bound up his wounds as well as they could.  On
the French party king John was that day a full right good
knight: if the fourth part of his men had done their devoirs
as well as he did, the journey had been his by all likelihood.
Howbeit they were all slain and taken that were there, except
a few that saved themselves, that were with the king.
<note place="foot" n="8"><p>'Howbeit they that stayed acquitted
them as well as they might, so that they were all slain or taken.
Few escaped of those that set themselves with the king': or
according to the fuller text: 'Few escaped of those that
alighted down on the sand by the side of the king their lord.'</p></note>
There was slain the duke Peter of Bourbon, the lord
Guichard of Beaujeu, the lord of Landas, and the duke of
Athens, constable of France, the bishop of Chalons in Champagne,
the lord William of Nesle, the lord Eustace of Ribemont,
the lord de la Tour, the lord William of Montaigu,
sir Grismouton of Chambly, sir Baudrin de la Heuse, and
many other, as they fought by companies; and there were
taken prisoners the lord of Vaudenay, the lord of Pompadour,
and the archpriest, sore hurt, the earl of Vaudimont,
the earl of Mons, the earl of Joinville, the earl of Vendome,
sir Louis of Melval, the lord Pierrebuffiere and the lord of
Serignac: there were at that brunt, slain and taken more than
two hundred knights.<note place="foot" n="9"><p>The translator has
chosen to rearrange the above list of killed, wounded or taken,
which the French text gives in order as they fought, saying that
in one part there fell the duke of Bourbon, sir Guichard of
Beaujeu and sir John of Landas, and there were severely wounded
or taken the archpriest, sir Thibaud of Vodenay and sir Baudouin
d'Annequin; in another there were slain the duke of Athens and the
bishop of Chalons, and taken the earl of Vaudemont and Joinville
and the earl of Vendome: a little above this there were slain sir
William de Nesle, sir Eustace de Ribemont and others, and taken sir
Louis de Melval, the lord of Pierrebuffiere and the lord of Seregnach.</p></note>
</p>
</div2>
<div2 type="section" id="d25">
<head>OF TWO FRENCHMEN THAT FLED FROM THE BATTLE OF
POITIERS<lb/>
AND TWO ENGLISHMEN THAT FOLLOWED THEM</head>

<p>AMONG the battles, recounterings, chases and pursuits that
were made that day in the field, it fortuned so to sir Oudart
of Renty that when he departed from the field because he
saw the field was lost without recovery, he thought not to
abide the danger of the Englishmen; wherefore he fled all
alone and was gone out of the field a league, and an English
knight pursued him and ever cried to him and said,
'Return again, sir knight, it is a shame to fly away thus.'

<pb n="50"/>

Then the knight turned, and the English knight thought to
have stricken him with his spear in the targe, but he failed,
for sir Oudart swerved aside from the stroke, but he failed
not the English knight, for he strake him such a stroke on
the helm with his sword, that he was astonied and fell from
his horse to the earth and lay still.  Then sir Oudart alighted
and came to him or he could rise, and said, 'Yield you,
rescue or no rescue, or else I shall slay you.'  The Englishman
yielded and went with him, and afterward was ransomed.
Also it fortuned that another squire of Picardy
called John de Hellenes was fled from the battle and met
with his page, who delivered him a new fresh horse, whereon
he rode away alone.  The same season there was in the
field the lord Berkeley of England, a young lusty knight,
who the same day reared his banner, and he all alone
pursued the said John of Hellenes.  And when he had
followed the space of a league, the said John turned again
and laid his sword in the rest instead of a spear, and so
came running toward the lord Berkeley, who lift up his
sword to have stricken the squire; but when he saw the
stroke come, he turned from it, so that the Englishman
lost his stroke and John strake him as he passed on the
arm, that the lord Berkeley's sword fell into the field.
When he saw his sword down, he lighted suddenly off
his horse and came to the place where his sword lay,
and as he stooped down to take up his sword, the French
squire did pike his sword at him, and by hap strake him
through both the thighs, so that the knight fell to the earth
and could not help himself.  And John alighted off his
horse and took the knight's sword that lay on the ground,
and came to him and demanded if he would yield him or
not.  The knight then demanded his name.  'Sir,' said he,
'I hight John of Hellenes; but what is your name?'  'Certainly,'
said the knight, 'my name is Thomas and am lord
of Berkeley, a fair castle on the river of Severn in the
marches of Wales.'  'Well, sir,' quoth the squire, 'then ye
shall be my prisoner, and I shall bring you in safe-guard
and I shall see that you shall be healed of your hurt.'  'Well,'
said the knight, 'I am content to be your prisoner, for ye
have by law of arms won me.'  There he sware to be his

<pb n="51"/>

prisoner, rescue or no rescue.  Then the squire drew forth
the sword out of the knight's thighs and the wound was
open: then he wrapped and bound the wound and set him
on his horse and so brought him fair and easily to Chatelleraut,
and there tarried more than fifteen days for his sake
and did get him remedy for his hurt: and when he was
somewhat amended, then he gat him a litter and so brought
him at his ease to his house in Picardy.  There he was more
than a year till he was perfectly whole; and when he departed
he paid for his ransom six thousand nobles, and so
this squire was made a knight by reason of the profit that he
had of the lord Berkeley.
</p>
</div2>
<div2 type="section" id="d26">
<head>HOW KING JOHN WAS TAKEN PRISONER AT THE<lb/>
BATTLE OF POITIERS</head>

<p>OFTENTIMES the adventures of amours and of war are
more fortunate and marvellous than any man can think
or wish.  Truly this battle, the which was near to Poitiers in
the fields of Beauvoir and Maupertuis, was right great and
perilous, and many deeds of arms there was done the which
all came not to knowledge.  The fighters on both sides endured
much pain: king John with his own hands did that
day marvels in arms: he had an axe in his hands wherewith
he defended himself and fought in the breaking of the press.
Near to the king there was taken the earl of Tancarville,
sir Jaques of Bourbon earl of Ponthieu, and the lord John
of Artois earl of Eu, and a little above that under the banner
of the captal of Buch was taken sir Charles of Artois
and divers other knights and squires.  The chase endured
to the gates of Poitiers: there were many slain and beaten
down, horse and man, for they of Poitiers closed their
gates and would suffer none to enter; wherefore in the
street before the gate was horrible murder, men hurt and
beaten down.  The Frenchmen yielded themselves as far off
as they might know an Englishman: there were divers English
archers that had four, five or six prisoners: the lord of
Pons, a great baron of Poitou, was there slain, and many
other knights and squires; and there was taken the earl of
Rochechouart, the lord of Dammartin, the lord of Partenay,

<pb n="52"/>

and of Saintonge the lord of Montendre and the lord John
of Saintre, but he was so sore hurt that he had never health
after: he was reputed for one of the best knights in France.
And there was left for dead among other dead men the
lord Guichard d'Angle, who fought that day by the king
right valiantly, and so did the lord of Chamy, on whom
was great press, because he bare the sovereign banner
of the king's: his own banner was also in the field, the which
was of gules, three scutcheons silver.  So many Englishmen
and Gascons come to that part, that perforce they
opened the king's battle, so that the Frenchmen were so
mingled among their enemies that sometime there was five
men upon one gentleman.  There was taken the lord of
Pompadour and<note place="foot" n="1"><p>This 'and' should be
'by,' but the French text is responsible for the
mistake.</p></note> the lord Bartholomew de Burghersh, and
there was slain sir Geoffrey of Charny with the king's banner
in his hands: also the lord Raynold Cobham slew the
earl of Dammartin.  Then there was a great press to take
the king, and such as knew him cried, 'Sir, yield you, or
else ye are but dead.'  There was a knight of Saint-Omer's,
retained in wages with the king of England, called sir Denis
Morbeke, who had served the Englishmen five year before,
because in his youth he had forfeited the realm of France
for a murder that he did at Saint-Omer's.  It happened so
well for him, that he was next to the king when they were
about to take him: he stept forth into the press, and by
strength of his body and arms he came to the French king
and said in good French, 'Sir, yield you.'  The king beheld
the knight and said: 'To whom shall I yield me?  Where
is my cousin the prince of Wales?  If I might see him, I
would speak with him.'  Denis answered and said: 'Sir, he
is not here; but yield you to me and I shall bring you
to him.  'Who be you?' quoth the king.  'Sir,' quoth he, 'I
am Denis of Morbeke, a knight of Artois; but I serve the
king of England because I am banished the realm of France
and I have forfeited all that I had there.'  Then the king
gave him his right gauntlet, saying, 'I yield me to you.'
There was a great press about the king, for every man
enforced him to say,<note place="foot" n="2"><p>'S'efforcoit
de dire.'</p></note> 'I have taken him,' so that the king

<pb n="53"/>

could not go forward with his young son the lord Philip
with him because of the press.
</p>
<p>The prince of Wales, who was courageous and cruel as
a lion, took that day great pleasure to fight and to chase
his enemies.  The lord John Chandos, who was with him,
of all that day never left him nor never took heed of taking
of any prisoner: then at the end of the battle he said to the
prince: 'Sir, it were good that you rested here and set your
banner a-high in this bush, that your people may draw
hither, for they be sore spread abroad, nor I can see no more
banners nor pennons of the French party; wherefore, sir,
rest and refresh you, for ye be sore chafed.'  Then the
prince's banner was set up a-high on a bush, and trumpets
and clarions began to sown.  Then the prince did off his
bassenet, and the knights for his body and they of his
chamber were ready about him, and a red pavilion pight
up, and then drink was brought forth to the prince and for
such lords as were about him, the which still increased as
they came from the chase: there they tarried and their
prisoners with them.  And when the two marshals were come
to the prince, he demanded of them if they knew any tiding
of the French king.  They answered and said: 'Sir, we
hear none of certainty, but we think verily he is other
dead or taken, for he is not gone out of the battles.'  Then
the prince said to the earl of Warwick and to sir Raynold
Cobham: 'Sirs, I require you go forth and see what ye
can know, that at your return ye may shew me the truth.'
These two lords took their horses and departed from the
prince and rode up a little hill to look about them: then
they perceived a flock of men of arms coming together
right wearily:<note place="foot" n="3"><p>'Lentement.'</p></note>
there was the French king afoot in great
peril, for Englishmen and Gascons were his masters; they
had taken him from sir Denis Morbeke perforce, and such
as were most of force said, 'I have taken him.'  'Nay,' quoth
another, 'I have taken him': so they strave which should have
him.  Then the French king, to eschew that peril, said: 'Sirs,
strive not: lead me courteously, and my son, to my cousin the
prince, and strive not for my taking, for I am so great a
lord to make you all rich.'  The king's words somewhat appeased

<pb n="54"/>

them; howbeit ever as they went they made riot
and brawled for the taking of the king.  When the two
foresaid lords saw and heard that noise and strife among
them, they came to them and said: 'Sirs, what is the matter
that ye strive for?'  'Sirs,' said one of them, 'it is for the
French king, who is here taken prisoner, and there be more
than ten knights and squires that challengeth the taking of
him and of his son.'  Then the two lords entered into the
press and caused every man to draw aback, and commanded
them in the prince's name on pain of their heads to make no
more noise nor to approach the king no nearer, without they
were commanded.  Then every man gave room to the lords,
and they alighted and did their reverence to the king, and
so brought him and his son in peace and rest to the prince
of Wales.
</p>
</div2>
<div2 type="section" id="d27">
<head>OF THE GIFT THAT THE PRINCE GAVE TO THE LORD<lb/>
AUDLEY AFTER THE BATTLE OF POITIERS</head>

<p>As soon as the earl of Warwick and the lord Cobham were
departed from the prince, as ye have heard before, then the
prince demanded of the knights that were about him for the
lord Audley, if any knew anything of him.  Some knights
that were there answered and said: 'Sir, he is sore hurt
and lieth in a litter here beside.'  'By my faith,' said the
prince, 'of his hurts I am right sorry: go and know if he
may be brought hither, or else I will go and see him thereas
he is.'  Then two knights came to the lord Audley and said:
'Sir, the prince desireth greatly to see you, other ye must
go to him or else he will come to you.'  'Ah, sir,' said the
knight, 'I thank the prince when he thinketh on so poor
a knight as I am.'  Then he called eight of his servants and
caused them to bear him in his litter to the place whereas
the prince was.  Then the prince took him in his arms and
kissed him and made him great cheer and said: 'Sir James,
I ought greatly to honour you, for by your valiance ye have
this day achieved the grace and renown of us all, and ye
are reputed for the most valiant of all other.'  'Ah, sir,'
said the knight, 'ye say as it pleaseth you: I would it were
so: and if I have this day anything advanced myself to

<pb n="55"/>

serve you and to accomplish the vow that I made, it ought
not to be reputed to me any prowess.'  'Sir James,' said the
prince, 'I and all ours take you in this journey for the best
doer in arms, and to the intent to furnish you the better
to pursue the wars, I retain you for ever to be my knight
with five hundred marks of yearly revenues, the which I
shall assign you on mine heritage in England.'  'Sir,' said
the knight, 'God grant me to deserve the great goodness
that ye shew me': and so he took his leave of the prince,
for he was right feeble, and so his servants brought him to
his lodging.  And as soon as he was gone, the earl of Warwick
and the lord Cobham returned to the prince and presented
to him the French king.  The prince made lowly
reverence to the king and caused wine and spices to be
brought forth, and himself served the king in sign of great
love.
</p>
</div2>
<div2 type="section" id="d28">
<head>HOW THE ENGLISHMEN WON GREATLY AT THE<lb/>
BATTLE OF POITIERS</head>

<p>THUS, this battle was discomfited, as ye have heard, the
which was in the fields of Maupertuis a two leagues from
Poitiers the twenty-second day of September the year of
our Lord MCCCLVI.  It begun in the morning<note place="foot" n="1"><p>
'Environ heure de prime.'</p></note> and ended at
noon, but as then all the Englishmen were not returned from
the chase; therefore the prince's banner stood on a bush to
draw all his men together, but it was well nigh night or all
came from the chase.  And as it was reported, there was
slain all the flower of France, and there was taken with
the king and the lord Philip his son a seventeen earls, beside
barons, knights and squires, and slain a five or six thousand
of one and other.  When every man was come from
the chase, they had twice as many prisoners as they were
in number in all.  Then it was counselled among them because
of the great charge and doubt to keep so many, that
they should put many of them to ransom incontinent in the
field, and so they did: and the prisoners found the Englishmen
and Gascons right courteous; there were many that
day put to ransom and let go all only on their promise of

<pb n="56"/>

faith and truth to return again between that and Christmas
to Bordeaux with their ransoms.  Then that night they
lay in the field beside whereas the battle had been: some
unarmed them, but not all, and unarmed all their prisoners,
and every man made good cheer to his prisoner;
for that day whosoever took any prisoner, he was clear
his and might quit or ransom him at his pleasure.  All
such as were there with the prince were all made rich
with honour and goods, as well by ransoming of prisoners
as by winning of gold, silver, plate, jewels, that was there
found: there was no man that did set anything by rich harness,
whereof there was great plenty, for the Frenchmen
came thither richly beseen, weening to have had the journey
for them. </p>
</div2>
<div2 type="section" id="d29">
<head>HOW THE LORD JAMES AUDLEY GAVE TO HIS FOUR SQUIRES<lb/>
THE FIVE HUNDRED MARKS OF REVENUES THAT THE<lb/>
PRINCE HAD GIVEN HIM</head>

<p>WHEN sir James Audley was brought to his lodging, then
he sent for sir Peter Audley his brother and for the lord
Bartholomew of Burghersh, the lord Stephen of Cosington,
the lord of Willoughby and the lord Ralph Ferrers, all these
were of his lineage, and then he called before him his four
squires, that had served him that day well and truly.  Then
he said to the said lords: 'Sirs, it hath pleased my lord the
prince to give me five hundred marks of revenues by year
in heritage, for the which gift I have done him but small
service with my body.  Sirs, behold here these four squires,
who hath always served me truly and specially this day: that
honour that I have is by their valiantness.  Wherefore I
will reward them: I give and resign into their hands the
gift that my lord the prince hath given me of five hundred
marks of yearly revenues, to them and to their heirs for
ever, in like manner as it was given me.  I clearly disherit
me thereof and inherit them without any repeal
<note place="foot" n="1"><p>'Rappel,' i. e. power of recalling the
gift.  The word 'repeal' is a correction of 'rebell.'</p></note> or
condition.' The lords and other that ere there, every man beheld other
and said among themselves: 'It cometh of a great nobleness

<pb n="57"/>

to give this gift.'  They answered him with one voice: 'Sir,
be it as God will; we shall bear witness in this behalf wheresoever
we be come.'  Then they departed from him, and some
of them went to the prince, who the same night would make
a supper to the French king and to the prisoners, for they
had enough to do withal, of that the Frenchmen brought with
them,<note place="foot" n="2"><p>'Who was to give the king of France
a supper of his own provisions: for the French had brought great
abundance with them, and provisions had failed among the English,'
etc.</p></note> for the Englishmen wanted victual before, for some
in three days had no bread before.
</p>
</div2>
<div2 type="section" id="d30">
<head>HOW THE PRINCE MADE A SUPPER TO THE FRENCH<lb/>
KING THE SAME DAY OF THE BATTLE</head>

<p>THE same day of the battle at night the prince made a supper
in his lodging to the French king and to the most part
of the great lords that were prisoners.  The prince made
the king and his son, the lord James of Bourbon, the lord
John d'Artois, the earl of Tancarville, the earl of Estampes,
the earl Dammartin, the earl of Joinville and the lord of Partenay
to sit all at one board, and other lords, knights and
squires at other tables; and always the prince served before
the king as humbly as he could, and would not sit at the king's
board for any desire that the king could make, but he said
he was not sufficient to sit at the table with so great a prince
as the king was.  But then he said to the king: 'Sir, for
God's sake make none evil nor heavy cheer, though God
this day did not consent to follow your will; for, sir, surely
the king my father shall bear you as much honour and amity
as he may do, and shall accord with you so reasonably that
ye shall ever be friends together after.  And, sir, methinks ye
ought to rejoice, though the journey be not as ye would have
had it, for this day ye have won the high renown of prowess
and have passed this day in valiantness all other of your
party.  Sir, I say not this to mock you, for all that be on our
party, that saw every man's deeds, are plainly accorded by
true sentence to give you the prize and chaplet.'  Therewith
the Frenchmen began to murmur and said among themselves
how the prince had spoken nobly, and that by all estimation

<pb n="58"/>

he should prove a noble man, if God send him life and to
persevere in such good fortune.
</p>
</div2>
<div2 type="section" id="d31">
<head>HOW THE PRINCE RETURNED TO BORDEAUX<lb/>
AFTER THE BATTLE OF POITIERS</head>

<p>WHEN supper was done, every man went to his lodging
with their prisoners.  The same night they put many to
ransom and believed them on their faiths and troths, and
ransomed them but easily, for they said they would set no
knight's ransom so high, but that he might pay at his ease
and maintain still his degree.  The next day, when they
had heard mass and taken some repast and that everything
was trussed and ready, then they took their horses and rode
towards Poitiers.  The same night there was come to Poitiers
the lord of Roye with a hundred spears: he was not at the
battle, but he met the duke of Normandy near to Chauvigny,
and the duke sent him to Poitiers to keep the town till they
heard other tidings.  When the lord of Roye knew that the
Englishmen were so near coming to the city, he caused every
man to be armed and every man to go to his defence to the
walls, towers and gates; and the Englishmen passed by without
any approaching, for they were so laded with gold, silver
and prisoners, that in their returning they assaulted no fortress;
they thought it a great deed if they might bring the
French king, with their other prisoners and riches that they
had won, in safeguard to Bordeaux.  They rode but small
journeys because of their prisoners and great carriages that
they had: they rode in a day no more but four or five
leagues and lodged ever betimes, and rode close together in
good array saving the marshals' battles, who rode ever before
with five hundred men of arms to open the passages
as the prince should pass; but they found no encounters, for
all the country was so frayed that every man drew to the
fortresses.
</p>
<p>As the prince rode, it was shewed him how the lord
Audley had given to his four squires the gift of the five
hundred marks that he had given unto him: then the prince
sent for him and he was brought in his litter to the prince,
who received him courteously and said: 'Sir James, we

<pb n="59"/>

have knowledge that the revenues that we gave you, as
soon as ye came to your lodging, you gave the same to four
squires: we would know why ye did so, and whether the
gift was agreeable to you or not.'  'Sir,' said the knight,
'it is of truth I have given it to them, and I shall shew
you why I did so.  These four squires that be here present
have a long season served me well and truly in many great
businesses and, sir, in this last battle they served me in such
wise that an they had never done nothing else I was bound
to reward them, and before the same day they had never
nothing of me in reward.  Sir, I am but a man alone; but by
the aid and comfort of them I took on me to accomplish
my vow long before made.  I had been dead in the battle
an they had not been: wherefore, sir, when I considered the
love that they bare unto me, I had not been courteous if I
would not a rewarded them.  I thank God I have had and
shall have enough as long as I live: I will never be abashed
for lack of good.  Sir, if I have done this without your
pleasure, I require you to pardon me, for, sir, both I and
my squires shall serve you as well as ever we did.'  Then
the prince said: 'Sir James, for anything that ye have done
I cannot blame you, but can you good thank therefor; and
for the valiantness of these squires, whom ye praise so much,
I accord to them your gift, and I will render again to you
six hundred marks in like manner as ye had the other.'
</p>
<p>Thus the prince and his company did so much that they
passed through Poitou and Saintonge without damage and
came to Blaye, and there passed the river of Gironde and
arrived in the good city of Bordeaux.  It cannot be recorded
the great feast and cheer that they of the city with the clergy
made to the prince, and how honourably they were there
received.  The prince brought the French king into the
abbey of Saint Andrew's, and there they lodged both, the
king in one part and the prince in the other.  The prince
bought of the lords, knights and squires of Gascoyne the
most part of the earls of the realm of France, such as were
prisoners, and paid ready money for them.  There was
divers questions and challenges made between the knights
and squires of Gascoyne for taking of the French king;
howbeit Denis Morbeke by right of arms and by true

<pb n="60"/>

tokens that he shewed challenged him for his prisoner.
Another squire of Gascoyne called Bernard of Truttes said
how he had right to him: there was much ado and many
words before the prince and other lords that were there,
and because these two challenged each other to fight in that
quarrel, the prince caused the matter to rest till they came
in England and that no declaration should be made but
afore the king of England his father; but because the
French king himself aided to sustain the challenge of Denis
Morbeke, for he inclined more to him than to any other,
the prince therefore privily caused to be delivered to the
said sir Denis two thousand nobles to maintain withal his
estate.
</p>
<p>Anon after the prince came to Bordeaux, the cardinal
of Perigord came thither, who was sent from the pope in
legation, as it was said.  He was there more than fifteen
days or the prince would speak with him because of the
chatelain of Amposte and his men, who were against him
in the battle of Poitiers.  The prince believed that the
cardinal sent them thither, but the cardinal did so much by
the means of the lord of Caumont, the lord of Montferrand
and the captal of Buch, who were his cousins,
they shewed so good reasons to the prince, that he was
content to hear him speak.  And when he was before the
prince, he excused himself so sagely that the prince and
his council held him excused, and so he fell again into the
prince's love and redeemed out his men by reasonable ransoms;
and the chatelain was set to his ransom of ten thousand
franks, the which he paid after.  Then the cardinal
began to treat on the deliverance of the French king, but
I pass it briefly because nothing was done.  Thus the prince,
the Gascons and Englishmen tarried still at Bordeaux till
it was Lent in great mirth and revel, and spent foolishly
the gold and silver that they had won.  In England also
there was great joy when they heard tidings of the battle
of Poitiers, of the discomfiting of the Frenchmen and taking
of the king: great solemnities were made in all churches
and great fires and wakes throughout all England.  The
knights and squires, such as were come home from that
journey, were much made of and praised more than other.
</p>

<pb n="61"/>
</div2>
</div1>
<div1 type="chapter" n="3" id="d32">
<head>Wat Tyler's Rebellion</head>
<div2 type="section" id="d33">
<head>HOW THE COMMONS OF ENGLAND REBELLED AGAINST THE<lb/>
NOBLEMEN</head>

<p>IN the mean season while this treaty was, there fell
in England great mischief and rebellion of moving
of the common people, by which deed England was
at a point to have been lost without recovery.  There was
never realm nor country in so great adventure as it was
in that time, and all because of the ease and riches that
the common people were of, which moved them to this
rebellion, as sometime they did in France, the which did
much hurt, for by such incidents the realm of France hath
been greatly grieved.
</p>
<p>It was a marvellous thing and of poor foundation that
this mischief began in England, and to give ensample to
all manner of people I will speak thereof as it was done,
as I was informed, and of the incidents thereof.  There
was an usage in England, and yet is in divers countries,
that the noblemen hath great franchise over the commons
and keepeth them in servage, that is to say, their tenants
ought by custom to labour the lords' lands, to gather and
bring home their corns, and some to thresh and to fan, and
by servage to make their hay and to hew their wood and
bring it home.  All these things they ought to do by servage,
and there be more of these people in England than
in any other realm.  Thus the noblemen and prelates are
served by them, and especially in the county of Kent,
Essex, Sussex and Bedford.  These unhappy people of
these said countries began to stir, because they said they
were kept in great servage, and in the beginning of the
world, they said, there were no bondmen, wherefore they
maintained that none ought to be bond, without he did

<pb n="62"/>

treason to his lord, as Lucifer did to God; but they said
they could have no such battle,<note place="foot" n="1"><p>The
true text is, 'Mais ils n'avoient pas cette taille,' 'but
they were not of that nature.'  The translator found the
corruption 'bataille' for 'taille.'</p></note> for they were neither
angels nor spirits, but men formed to the similitude of
their lords, saying why should they then be kept so under
like beasts; the which they said they would no longer
suffer, for they would be all one, and if they laboured or
did anything for their lords, they would have wages therefor
as well as other.  And of this imagination was a foolish
priest in the country of Kent called John Ball, for the
which foolish words he had been three times in the bishop
of Canterbury's prison: for this priest used oftentimes on the
Sundays after mass, when the people were going out of
the minster, to go into the cloister and preach, and made
the people to assemble about him, and would say thus:
'Ah, ye good people, the matters goeth not well to pass in
England, nor shall not do till everything be common, and
that there be no villains nor gentlemen, but that we may
be all unied together, and that the lords be no greater
masters than we be.  What have we deserved, or why
should we be kept thus in servage?  We be all come from
one father and one mother, Adam and Eve: whereby can
they say or shew that they be greater lords than we be,
saving by that they cause us to win and labour for that
they dispend?  They are clothed in velvet and camlet furred
with grise, and we be vestured with poor cloth: they have
their wines, spices and good bread, and we have the drawing
out of the chaff<note place="foot" n="2"><p>Froissart says
'le seigle, le retrait et la paille,' 'the rye, the bran and
the straw.'  The translator's French text had 'le seigle, le
retraict de la paille.'</p></note> and drink water: they dwell in fair
houses, and we have the pain and travail, rain and wind in
the fields; and by that that cometh of our labours they keep
and maintain their estates: we be called their bondmen,
and without we do readily them service, we be beaten; and
we have no sovereign to whom we may complain, nor that
will hear us nor do us right.  Let us go to the king, he is
young, and shew him what servage we be in, and shew him
how we will have it otherwise, or else we will provide us
of some remedy; and if we go together, all manner of
people that be now in any bondage will follow us to the

<pb n="63"/>

intent to be made free; and when the king seeth us, we
shall have some remedy, either by fairness or otherwise.'
Thus John Ball said on Sundays, when the people issued
out of the churches in the villages; wherefore many of the
mean people loved him, and such as intended to no goodness
said how he said truth; and so they would murmur one
with another in the fields and in the ways as they went
together, affirming how John Ball said truth.
</p>
<p>The archbishop of Canterbury, who was informed of the
saying of this John Ball, caused him to be taken and put
in prison a two or three months to chastise him: howbeit,
it had been much better at the beginning that he had been
condemned to perpetual prison or else to have died, rather
than to have suffered him to have been again delivered
out of prison; but the bishop had conscience to let him
die.  And when this John Ball was out of prison, he
returned again to his error, as he did before.
</p>
<p>Of his words and deeds there were much people in London
informed, such as had great envy at them that were
rich and such as were noble; and then they began to speak
among them and said how the realm of England was right
evil governed, and how that gold and silver was taken from
them by them that were named noblemen: so thus these
unhappy men of London began to rebel and assembled them
together, and sent word to the foresaid countries that they
should come to London and bring their people with them,
promising them how they should find London open to receive
them and the commons of the city to be of the same
accord, saying how they would do so much to the king that
there should not be one bondman in all England.
</p>
<p>This promise moved so them of Kent, of Essex, of Sussex,
of Bedford and of the countries about, that they rose and
came towards London to the number of sixty thousand.
And they had a captain called Water Tyler, and with him
in company was Jack Straw and John Ball: these three were
chief sovereign captains, but the head of all was Water
Tyler, and he was indeed a tiler of houses, an ungracious
patron.  When these unhappy men began thus to stir, they
of London, except such as were of their band, were greatly
affrayed.  Then the mayor of London and the rich men of

<pb n="64"/>

the city took counsel together, and when they saw the
people thus coming on every side, they caused the gates of
the city to be closed and would suffer no man to enter into
the city.  But when they had well imagined, they advised
not so to do, for they thought they should thereby put their
suburbs in great peril to be brent; and so they opened again
the city, and there entered in at the gates in some place
a hundred, two hundred, by twenty and by thirty, and so
when they came to London, they entered and lodged: and
yet of truth the third part<note place="foot" n="3"><p>'Bien les
trois pars,' i. e. 'three-fourths.'</p></note>
of these people could not tell
what to ask or demand, but followed each other like beasts,
as the shepherds<note place="foot" n="4"><p>'Les pastoureaulx.' The
reference no doubt is to the Pastoureaux of 1320, who were
destroyed at Aigues-Mortes when attempting to obtain a passage
to the Holy Land.</p></note> did of old time, saying how they would
go conquer the Holy Land, and at last all came to nothing.
In like wise these villains and poor people came to London,
a hundred mile off, sixty mile, fifty mile, forty mile, and
twenty mile off, and from all countries about London, but
the most part came from the countries before named, and
as they came they demanded ever for the king.  The gentlemen
of the countries, knights and squires, began to doubt,
when they saw the people began to rebel; and though they
were in doubt, it was good reason; for a less occasion they
might have been affrayed.  So the gentlemen drew together
as well as they might.
</p>
<p>The same day that these unhappy people of Kent were
coming to London, there returned from Canterbury the king's
mother, princess of Wales, coming from her pilgrimage.  She
was in great jeopardy to have been lost, for these people
came to her chare and dealt rudely with her, whereof the
good lady was in great doubt lest they would have done
some villany to her or to her damosels.  Howbeit, God
kept her, and she came in one day from Canterbury to
London, for she never durst tarry by the way.  The same
time king Richard her son was at the Tower of London:
there his mother found him, and with him there was the
earl of Salisbury, the archbishop of Canterbury, sir Robert
of Namur, the lord of Gommegnies and divers other, who
were in doubt of these people that thus gathered together,

<pb n="65"/>

and wist not what they demanded.  This rebellion was well
known in the king's court, or any of these people began to
stir out of their houses; but the king nor his council did
provide no remedy therefor, which was great marvel.  And
to the intent that all lords and good people and such as
would nothing but good should take ensample to correct
them that be evil and rebellious, I shall shew you plainly
all the matter, as it was.
</p>
</div2>
<div2 type="section" id="d34">
<head>THE EVIL DEEDS THAT THESE COMMONS OF ENGLAND DID TO
THE<lb/>
KING'S OFFICERS, AND HOW THEY SENT A KNIGHT TO<lb/>
SPEAK WITH THE KING</head>

<p>THE Monday before the feast of Corpus Christi the year
of our Lord God a thousand three hundred and eighty-one
these people issued out of their houses to come to London
to speak with the king to be made free, for they would
have had no bondman in England.  And so first they came
to Saint Thomas of Canterbury, and there John Ball had
thought to have found the bishop of Canterbury, but he
was at London with the king.  When Wat Tyler and Jack
Straw entered into Canterbury, all the common people made
great feast, for all the town was of their assent; and there
they took counsel to go to London to the king, and to
send some of their company over the river of Thames
into Essex, into Sussex and into the counties of Stafford
and Bedford, to speak to the people that they should all
come to the farther side of London and thereby to close
London round about, so that the king should not stop their
passages, and that they should all meet together on Corpus
Christi day.  They that were at Canterbury entered into
Saint Thomas' church and did there much hurt, and robbed
and brake up the bishop's chamber, and in robbing and
bearing out their pillage they said: 'Ah, this chancellor
of England hath had a good market to get together all this
riches: he shall give us now account of the revenues of
England and of the great profits that he hath gathered
sith the king's coronation.'  When they had this Monday
thus broken the abbey of Saint Vincent, they departed in
the morning and all the people of Canterbury with them,

<pb n="66"/>

and so took the way to Rochester and sent their people to
the villages about.  And in their going they beat down
and robbed houses of advocates and procurers of the king's
court and of the archbishop, and had mercy of none.  And
when they were come to Rochester, they had there good
cheer; for the people of that town tarried for them, for they
were of the same sect, and then they went to the castle there
and took the knight that had the rule thereof, he was called
sir John Newton, and they said to him: 'Sir, it behoveth
you to go with us and you shall be our sovereign captain
and to do that we will have you.'  The knight excused himself
honestly and shewed them divers considerations and
excuses, but all availed him nothing, for they said unto
him: 'Sir John, if ye do not as we will have you, ye are
but dead.'  The knight, seeing these people in that fury
and ready to slay him, he then doubted death and agreed
to them, and so they took him with them against his inward
will; and in like wise did they of other counties in England,
as Essex, Sussex, Stafford, Bedford and Warwick, even to
Lincoln; for they brought the knights and gentlemen into
such obeisance, that they caused them to go with them,
whether they would or not, as the lord Moylays, a great
baron, sir Stephen of Hales and sir Thomas of Cosington
and other.
</p>
<p>Now behold the great fortune.  If they might have come
to their intents, they would have destroyed all the noblemen
of England, and thereafter all other nations would have
followed the same and have taken foot and ensample by
them and by them of Gaunt and Flanders, who rebelled
against their lord.  The same year the Parisians rebelled
in like wise and found out the mallets of iron, of whom
there were more than twenty thousand, as ye shall hear
after in this history; but first we will speak of them of
England.
</p>
<p>When these people thus lodged at Rochester departed,
and passed the river and came to Brentford, alway keeping
still their opinions, beating down before them and all about
the places and houses of advocates and procurers, and
striking off the heads of divers persons.  And so long they
went forward till they came within a four mile of London,

<pb n="67"/>

and there lodged on a hill called Blackheath; and as they
went, they said ever they were the king's men and the noble
commons of England:<note place="foot" n="1"><p>'That were for the
king and the noble commons (or commonwealth) of England.'</p></note>
and when they of London knew
that they were come so near to them, the mayor, as ye have
heard before, closed the gates and kept straitly all the passages.
This order caused the mayor, who was called
Nicholas Walworth,<note place="foot" n="2"><p>Froissart calls him John:
his name was really William.</p></note> and divers other rich burgesses
of the city, who were not of their sect; but there were in London
of their unhappy opinions more than thirty thousand.
</p>
<p>Then these people thus being lodged on Blackheath determined
to send their knight to speak with the king and to
shew him how all that they have done or will do is for
him and his honour, and how the realm of England hath
not been well governed a great space for the honour of
the realm nor for the common profit by his uncles and by
the clergy, and specially by the archbishop of Canterbury
his chancellor; whereof they would have account.  This
knight durst do none otherwise, but so came by the river
of Thames to the Tower.  The king and they that were
with him in the Tower, desiring to hear tidings, seeing
this knight coming made him way, and was brought before
the king into a chamber; and with the king was the princess
his mother and his two brethren, the earl of Kent and the
lord John Holland, the earl of Salisbury, the earl of Warwick,
the earl of Oxford, the archbishop of Canterbury,
the lord of Saint John's,<note place="foot" n="3"><p>That is, the
grand prior of the Hospital.</p></note> sir Robert of Namur, the lord of
Vertaing, the lord of Gommegnies, sir Henry of Senzeille,
the mayor of London and divers other notable burgesses.
This knight sir John Newton, who was well known among
them, for he was one of the king's officers, he kneeled down
before the king and said: 'My right redoubted lord, let it
not displease your grace the message that I must needs shew
you, for, dear sir, it is by force and against my will.'  'Sir
John,' said the king, 'say what ye will: I hold you excused.'
'Sir, the commons of this your realm hath sent me to you
to desire you to come and speak with them on Blackheath;
for they desire to have none but you: and, sir, ye need not to

<pb n="68"/>

have any doubt of your person, for they will do you no
hurt; for they hold and will hold you for their king.  But,
sir, they say they will shew you divers things, the which
shall be right necessary for you to take heed of, when they
speak with you; of the which things, sir, I have no charge
to shew you: but, sir, it may please you to give me an
answer such as may appease them and that they may know
for truth that I have spoken with you; for they have my children
in hostage till I return again to them, and without I
return again, they will slay my children incontinent.'
</p>
<p>Then the king made him an answer and said: 'Sir, ye
shall have an answer shortly.'  Then the king took counsel
what was best for him to do, and it was anon determined
that the next morning the king should go down the river
by water and without fail to speak with them.  And when
sir John Newton heard that answer, he desired nothing else
and so took his leave of the king and of the lords and returned
again into his vessel, and passed the Thames and
went to Blackheath, where he had left more than threescore
thousand men.  And there he answered them that the next
morning they should send some of their council to the
Thames, and there the king would come and speak with
them.  This answer greatly pleased them, and so passed
that night as well as they might, and the fourth part of
them<note place="foot" n="4"><p>'Les quatre pars d'eux,'
'four-fifths of them.'</p></note> fasted for lack of victual for
they had none, wherewith they were sore displeased, which was good reason.
</p>
<p>All this season the earl of Buckingham was in Wales,
for there he had fair heritages by reason of his wife, who
was daughter to the earl of Northumberland and Hereford;
but the voice was all through London how he was among
these people.  And some said certainly how they had seen
him there among them; and all was because there was one
Thomas in their company, a man of the county of Cambridge,
that was very like the earl.  Also the lords that lay
at Plymouth to go into Portugal were well informed of this
rebellion and of the people that thus began to rise; wherefore
they doubted lest their viage should have been broken,
or else they feared lest the commons about Hampton, Winchester
and Arundel would have come on them: wherefore

<pb n="69"/>

they weighed up their anchors and issued out of the haven
with great pain, for the wind was sore against them, and so
took the sea and there cast anchor abiding for the wind.
And the duke of Lancaster, who was in the marches of
Scotland between Moorlane and Roxburgh entreating with
the Scots, where it was shewed him of the rebellion, whereof
he was in doubt, for he knew well he was but little beloved
with the commons of England; howbeit, for all those tidings,
yet he did sagely demean himself as touching the treaty
with the Scots.  The earl Douglas, the earl of Moray, the
earl of Sutherland and the earl Thomas Versy, and the Scots
that were there for the treaty knew right well the rebellion
in England, how the common people in every part began to
rebel against the noblemen; wherefore the Scots thought
that England was in great danger to be lost, and therefore
in their treaties they were the more stiffer against the duke
of Lancaster and his council.
</p>
<p>Now let us speak of the commons of England and how
they persevered.
</p>
</div2>
<div2 type="section" id="d35">
<head>HOW THE COMMONS OF ENGLAND ENTERED INTO LONDON,
AND<lb/>
OF THE GREAT EVIL THAT THEY DID, AND OF THE DEATH<lb/>
OF THE BISHOP OF CANTERBURY AND DIVERS OTHER</head>

<p>IN the morning on Corpus Christi day king Richard heard
mass in the Tower of London, and all his lords, and then he
took his barge with the earl of Salisbury, the earl of Warwick,
the earl of Oxford and certain knights, and so rowed
down along the Thames to Rotherhithe, whereas was descended
down the hill a ten thousand men to see the king
and to speak with him.  And when they saw the king's barge
coming, they began to shout, and made such a cry, as though
all the devils of hell had been among them.  And they had
brought with them sir John Newton to the intent that, if
the king had not come, they would have stricken him all to
pieces, and so they had promised him.  And when the king
and his lords saw the demeanour of the people, the best
assured of them were in dread; and so the king was counselled
by his barons not to take any landing there, but so
rowed up and down the river.  And the king demanded of

<pb n="70"/>

them what they would, and said how he was come thither
to speak with them, and they said all with one voice: 'We
would that ye should come aland, and then we shall shew
you what we lack.'  Then the earl of Salisbury answered for
the king and said: 'Sirs, ye be not in such order nor array
that the king ought to speak with you.'  And so with those
words no more said: and then the king was counselled to
return again to the Tower of London, and so he did.
</p>
<p>And when these people saw that, they were inflamed with
ire and returned to the hill where the great band was, and
there shewed them what answer they had and how the king
was returned to the Tower of London.  Then they cried all
with one voice, 'Let us go to London,' and so they took
their way thither; and in their going they beat down abbeys
and houses of advocates and of men of the court, and so
came into the suburbs of London, which were great and
fair, and there beat down divers fair houses, and specially
they brake up the king's prisons, as the Marshalsea and
other, and delivered out all the prisoners that were within:
and there they did much hurt, and at the bridge foot they
threat them of London because the gates of the bridge
were closed, saying how they would bren all the suburbs and
so conquer London by force, and to slay and bren all the
commons of the city.  There were many within the city
of their accord, and so they drew together and said: 'Why
do we not let these good people enter into the city? they
are your fellows, and that that they do is for us.'  So therewith
the gates were opened, and then these people entered
into the city and went into houses and sat down to eat and
drink.  They desired nothing but it was incontinent brought
to them, for every man was ready to make them good cheer
and to give them meat and drink to appease them.
</p>
<p>Then the captains, as John Ball, Jack Straw and Wat
Tyler, went throughout London and a twenty thousand with
them, and so came to the Savoy in the way to Westminster,
which was a goodly house and it pertained to the duke of
Lancaster.  And when they entered, they slew the keepers
thereof and robbed and pilled the house, and when they had
so done, then they set fire on it and clean destroyed and brent
it. And when they had done that outrage, they left not

<pb n="71"/>

therewith, but went straight to the fair hospital of the
Rhodes called Saint John's,<note place="foot" n="1"><p>This is
called afterwards 'l'Ospital de Saint Jehan du Temple,' and
therefore would probably be the Temple, to which the Hospitallers
had succeeded.  They had, however, another house at Clerkenwell,
which also had been once the property of the Templars.</p></note>
and there they brent house,
hospital, minster and all.  Then they went from street to
street and slew all the Flemings that they could find in
church or in any other place, there was none respited from
death.  And they brake up divers houses of the Lombards
and robbed them and took their goods at their pleasure, for
there was none that durst say them nay.  And they slew
in the city a rich merchant called Richard Lyon, to whom
before that time Wat Tyler had done service in France;
and on a time this Richard Lyon had beaten him, while he
was his varlet, the which Wat Tyler then remembered and
so came to his house and stroke off his head and caused it
to be borne on a spear-point before him all about the city.
Thus these ungracious people demeaned themselves like
people enraged and wood, and so that day they did much
sorrow in London.
</p>
<p>And so against night they went to lodge at Saint Katherine's
before the Tower of London, saying how they would
never depart thence till they had the king at their pleasure
and till he had accorded to them all [they would ask, and]
that they would ask accounts of the chancellor of England,
to know where all the good was become that he had levied
through the realm, and without he made a good account to
them thereof, it should not be for his profit.  And so when
they had done all these evils to the strangers all the day,
at night they lodged before the Tower.
</p>
<p>Ye may well know and believe that it was great pity for
the danger that the king and such as were with him were in.
For some time these unhappy people shouted and cried so
loud, as though all the devils of hell had been among them.
In this evening the king was counselled by his brethren and
lords and by sir Nicholas Walworth, mayor of London,
and divers other notable and rich burgesses, that in the
night time they should issue out of the Tower and enter into
the city, and so to slay all these unhappy people, while
they were at their rest and asleep; for it was thought that

<pb n="72"/>

many of them were drunken, whereby they should be slain
like flies; also of twenty of them there was scant one in
harness.  And  surely the good men of London might well
have done this at their ease, for they had in their houses
secretly their friends and servants ready in harness, and
also sir Robert Knolles was in his lodging keeping his
treasure with a sixscore ready at his commandment; in
like wise was sir Perducas d'Albret, who was as then in
London, insomuch that there might well [have] assembled
together an eight thousand men ready in harness.  Howbeit,
there was nothing done, for the residue of the commons of
the city were sore doubted, lest they should rise also, and
the commons before were a threescore thousand or more.
Then the earl of Salisbury and the wise men about the king
said: 'Sir, if ye can appease them with fairness, it were
best and most profitable, and to grant them everything that
they desire, for if we should begin a thing the which we
could not achieve, we should never recover it again, but we
and our heirs ever to be disinherited.'  So this counsel was
taken and the mayor countermanded, and so commanded
that he should not stir; and he did as he was commanded,
as reason was.  And in the city with the mayor there were
twelve aldermen, whereof nine of them held with the king
and the other three took part with these ungracious people,
as it was after well known, the which they full dearly
bought.
</p>
<p>And on the Friday in the morning the people, being at
Saint Katherine's near to the Tower, began to apparel themselves
and to cry and shout, and said, without the king
would come out and speak with them, they would assail
the Tower and take it by force, and slay all them that were
within.  Then the king doubted these words and so was
counselled that he should issue out to speak with them: and
then the king sent to them that they should all draw to a
fair plain place called Mile-end, whereas the people of the
city did sport them in the summer season, and there the
king to grant them that they desired; and there it was cried
in the king's name, that whosoever would speak with the
king let him go to the said place, and there he should not
fail to find the king.  Then the people began to depart,

<pb n="73"/>

specially the commons of the villages, and went to the same
place: but all went not thither, for they were not all of
one condition; for there were some that desired nothing
but riches and the utter destruction of the noblemen and to
have London robbed and pilled; that was the principal matter
of their beginning, the which they well shewed; for as
soon as the Tower gate opened and that the king was issued
out with his two brethren and the earl of Salisbury,
the earl of Warwick, the earl of Oxford, sir Robert of
Namur, the lord of Vertaing, the lord Gommegnies and
divers other, then Wat Tyler, Jack Straw and John Ball
and more than four hundred entered into the Tower and
brake up chamber after chamber, and at last found the
archbishop of Canterbury, called Simon, a valiant man and
a wise, and chief chancellor of England, and a little before
he had said mass before the king.  These gluttons took
him and strake off his head, and also they beheaded the lord
of Saint John's and a friar minor, master in medicine,
pertaining to the duke of Lancaster, they slew him in
despite of his master, and a sergeant at arms called John
Leg; and these four heads were set on four long spears
and they made them to be borne before them through the
streets of London and at last set them a-high on London
bridge, as though they had been traitors to the king and to
the realm.  Also these gluttons entered into the princess'
chamber and brake her bed, whereby she was so sore affrayed
that she swooned; and there she was taken up and
borne to the water side and put into a barge and covered,
and so conveyed to a place called the Queen's Wardrobe;
<note place="foot" n="2"><p>The Queen's Wardrobe was in the 'Royal'
(called by Froissart or his copyist 'la Reole'), a palace near
Blackfriars.</p></note> and
there she was all that day and night like a woman half
dead, till she was comforted with the king her son, as ye
shall hear after.
</p>
</div2>
<div2 type="section" id="d36">
<head>HOW THE NOBLES OF ENGLAND WERE IN GREAT PERIL TO
HAVE<lb/>
BEEN DESTROYED, AND HOW THESE REBELS WERE PUNISHED <lb/>
AND SENT HOME TO THEIR OWN HOUSES</head>

<p>WHEN the king came to the said place of Mile-end without
London, he put out of his company his two brethren, the earl

<pb n="74"/>

of Kent and sir John Holland, and the lord of Gommegnies,
for they durst not appear before the people: and when the
king and his other lords were there, he found there a three-score thousand men of divers villages and of sundry countries
in England; so the king entered in among them and
said to them sweetly: 'Ah, ye good people, I am your king:
what lack ye? what will ye say?'  Then such as understood
him said: 'We will that ye make us free for ever, ourselves,
our heirs and our lands, and that we be called no more bond
nor so reputed.'  'Sirs,' said the king, 'I am well agreed
thereto.  Withdraw you home into your own houses and into
such villages as ye came from, and leave behind you of
every village two or three, and I shall cause writings to be
made and seal them with my seal, the which they shall have
with them, containing everything that ye demand; and to
the intent that ye shall be the better assured, I shall cause
my banners to be delivered into every bailiwick, shire and
countries.'
</p>
<p>These words appeased well the common people, such as
were simple and good plain men, that were come thither
and wist not why.  They said, 'It was well said, we desire
no better.'  Thus these people began to be appeased and began
to withdraw them into the city of London.  And the
king also said a word, the which greatly contented them.
He said: 'Sirs, among you good men of Kent ye shall have
one of my banners with you, and ye of Essex another, and
ye of Sussex, of Bedford, of Cambridge, of Yarmouth, of
Stafford and of Lynn, each of you one; and also I pardon
everything that ye have done hitherto, so that ye follow my
banners and return home to your houses.'  They all answered
how they would so do: thus these people departed
and went into London.  Then the king ordained more than
thirty clerks the same Friday, to write with all diligence
letter patents and sealed with the king's seal, and delivered
them to these people; and when they had received the writing,
they departed and returned into their own countries:
but the great venom remained still behind, for Wat Tyler,
Jack Straw and John Ball said, for all that these people
were thus appeased, yet they would not depart so, and they
had of their accord more than thirty thousand.  So they

<pb n="75"/>

abode still and made no press to have the king's writing
nor seal, for all their intents was to put the city to trouble
in such wise as to slay all the rich and honest persons and
to rob and pill their houses.  They of London were in great
fear of this, wherefore they kept their houses privily with
their friends and such servants as they had, every man according
to his puissance.  And when these said people were
this Friday thus somewhat appeased, and that they should
depart as soon as they had their writings, every man home
into his own country, then king Richard came into the
Royal, where the queen his mother was, right sore affrayed:
so he comforted her as well as he could and tarried there
with her all that night.
</p>
<p>Yet I shall shew you of an adventure that fell by these
ungracious people before the city of Norwich, by a captain
among them called Guilliam Lister of Stafford.  The same
day of Corpus Christi that these people entered into London
and brent the duke of Lancaster's house, called the Savoy,
and the hospital of Saint John's and brake up the king's
prisons and did all this hurt, as ye have heard before, the
same time there assembled together they of Stafford, of
Lynn, of Cambridge, of Bedford and of Yarmouth; and as
they were coming towards London, they had a captain
among them called Lister.  And as they came, they rested
them before Norwich, and in their coming they caused
every man to rise with them, so that they left no villains
behind them.  The cause why they rested before Norwich
I shall shew you.  There was a knight, captain of the town,
called sir Robert Sale.  He was no gentleman born, but he
had the grace to be reputed sage and valiant in arms, and
for his valiantness king Edward made him knight.  He was
of his body one of the biggest knights in all England.  Lister
and his company thought to have had this knight with them
and to make him their chief captain, to the intent to be the
more feared and beloved: so they sent to him that he should
come and speak with them in the field, or else they would
bren the town.  The knight considered that it was better
for him to go and speak with them rather than they should
do that outrage to the town: then he mounted on his horse
and issued out of the town all alone, and so came to speak

<pb n="76"/>

with them.  And when they saw him, they made him great
cheer and honoured him much, desiring him to alight off
his horse and to speak with them, and so he did: wherein
he did great folly; for when he was alighted, they came
round about him and began to speak fair to him and said:
'Sir Robert, ye are a knight and a man greatly beloved in
this country and renowned a valiant man; and though ye
be thus, yet we know you well, ye be no gentleman born,
but son to a villain such as we be.  Therefore come you with
us and be our master, and we shall make you so great a lord,
that one quarter of England shall be under your obeisance.'
When the knight heard them speak thus, it was greatly
contrarious to his mind, for he thought never to make any
such bargain, and answered them with a felonous regard:
'Fly away, ye ungracious people, false and evil traitors
that ye be: would you that I should forsake my natural lord
for such a company of knaves as ye be, to my dishonour
for ever?  I had rather ye were all hanged, as ye shall be;
for that shall be your end.'  And with those words he had
thought to have leapt again upon his horse, but he failed
of the stirrup and the horse started away.  Then they cried
all at him and said: 'Slay him without mercy.'  When he
heard those words, he let his horse go and drew out a good
sword and began to scrimmish with them, and made a great
place about him, that it was pleasure to behold him.  There
was none that durst approach near him: there were some
that approached near him, but at every stroke that he gave
he cut off other leg, head or arm: there was none so hardy
but that they feared him: he did there such deeds of arms
that it was marvel to regard.  But there were more than
forty thousand of these unhappy people: they shot and cast
at him, and he was unarmed: to say truth, if he had been
of iron or steel, yet he must needs have been slain; but yet,
or he died, he slew twelve out of hand, beside them that he
hurt.  Finally he was stricken to the earth, and they cut
off his arms and legs and then strake his body all to pieces.
This was the end of sir Robert Sale, which was great
damage; for which deed afterward all the knights and
squires of England were angry and sore displeased when
they heard thereof.
</p>
<pb n="77"/>

<p>Now let us return to the king.  The Saturday the king
departed from the Wardrobe in the Royal and went to
Westminster and heard mass in the church there, and all
his lords with him.  And beside the church there was a little
chapel with an image of our Lady, which did great miracles
and in whom the kings of England had ever great trust and
confidence.  The king made his orisons before this image
and did there his offering; and then he leapt on his horse,
and all his lords, and so the king rode toward London; and
when he had ridden a little way, on the left hand there was
a way to pass without London.<note place="foot" n="1"><p>Or rather,
'he found a place on the left hand to pass without London.'</p></note>
</p>
<p>The same proper morning Wat Tyler, Jack Straw and
John Ball had assembled their company to common together
in a place called Smithfield, whereas every Friday there is
a market of horses; and there were together all of affinity
more than twenty thousand, and yet there were many still
in the town, drinking and making merry in the taverns and
paid nothing, for they were happy that made them best
cheer.  And these people in Smithfield had with them the
king's banners, the which were delivered them the day before,
and all these gluttons were in mind to overrun and to
rob London the same day; for their captains said how they
had done nothing as yet.  'These liberties that the king
hath given us is to us but a small profit: therefore let us
be all of one accord and let us overrun this rich and puissant
city, or they of Essex, of Sussex, of Cambridge, of Bedford,
of Arundel, of Warwick, of Reading, of Oxford, of
Guildford, of Lynn, of Stafford, of Yarmouth, of Lincoln,
of York and of Durham do come hither.  For all these will
come hither; Baker and Lister will bring them hither; and
if we be first lords of London and have the possession of
the riches that is therein, we shall not repent us; for if we
leave it, they that come after will have it from us.'
</p>
<p>To this counsel they all agreed; and therewith the king
came the same way unware of them, for he had thought to
have passed that way without London, and with him a forty
horse.  And when he came before the abbey of Saint
Bartholomew and beheld all these people, then the king
rested and said how he would go no farther till he knew

<pb n="78"/>

what these people ailed, saying, if they were in any trouble,
how he would rappease them again.  The lords that were
with him tarried also, as reason was when they saw the
king tarry.  And when Wat Tyler saw the king tarry, he
said to his people: 'Sirs, yonder is the king: I will go and
speak with him.  Stir not from hence, without I make you
a sign; and when I make you that sign, come on and slay
all them except the king; but do the king no hurt, he is
young, we shall do with him as we list and shall lead him
with us all about England, and so shall we be lords of all
the realm without doubt.'  And there was a doublet-maker of
London called John Tycle, and he had brought to these
gluttons a sixty doublets, the which they ware: then he
demanded of these captains who should pay him for his
doublets; he demanded thirty mark.  Wat Tyler answered
him and said: 'Friend, appease yourself, thou shalt be
well paid or this day be ended.  Keep thee near me; I shall
be thy creditor.'  And therewith he spurred his horse and
departed from his company and came to the king, so near
him that his horse head touched the croup of the king's
horse, and the first word that he said was this: 'Sir king,
seest thou all yonder people?'  'Yea truly,' said the king,
'wherefore sayest thou?'  'Because,' said he, 'they be all
at my commandment and have sworn to me faith and truth,
to do all that I will have them.'  'In a good time,' said the
king, 'I will well it be so.'  Then Wat Tyler said, as he
that nothing demanded but riot: 'What believest thou,
king, that these people and as many more as be in London
at my commandment, that they will depart from thee thus
without having thy letters? '  'No,' said the king, 'ye shall
have them: they be ordained for you and shall be delivered
every one each after other.  Wherefore, good fellows, withdraw
fair and easily to your people and cause them to depart
out of London; for it is our intent that each of you by
villages and townships shall have letters patents, as I have
promised you.'
</p>
<p>With those words Wat Tyler cast his eyen on a squire
that was there with the king bearing the king's sword, and
Wat Tyler hated greatly the same squire, for the same squire
had displeased him before for words between them.  'What,

<pb n="79"/>

said Tyler, 'art thou there?  Give me thy dagger.'  'Nay,'
said the squire, 'that will I not do: wherefore should I give
it thee?'  The king beheld the squire and said: 'Give it him;
let him have it.'  And so the squire took it him sore against
his will.  And when this Wat Tyler had it, he began to play
therewith and turned it in his hand, and said again to the
squire: 'Give me also that sword.'  'Nay,' said the squire,
'it is the king's sword: thou art not worthy to have it, for
thou art but a knave; and if there were no more here but
thou and I, thou durst not speak those words for as much
gold in quantity as all yonder abbey.'<note place="foot" n="2"><p>The
full text has, 'for as much gold as that minster of Saint Paul is
great.'</p></note>  'By my faith,' said
Wat Tyler, 'I shall never eat meat till I have thy head':
and with those words the mayor of London came to the
king with a twelve horses well armed under their coats,
and so he brake the press and saw and heard how Wat Tyler
demeaned himself, and said to him: 'Ha, thou knave, how
art thou so hardy in the king's presence to speak such
words?  It is too much for thee so to do.'  Then the king
began to chafe and said to the mayor: 'Set hands on him.'
And while the king said so, Tyler said to the mayor: 'A
God's name what have I said to displease thee?'  'Yes
truly,' quoth the mayor, 'thou false stinking knave, shalt
thou speak thus in the presence of the king my natural lord?
I commit never to live, without thou shalt dearly abye it.'
<note place="foot" n="3"><p>'Jamais je veux vivre, si tu ne le compares.'</p></note>
And with those words the mayor drew out his sword and
strake Tyler so great a stroke on the head, that he fell
down at the feet of his horse, and as soon as he was fallen,
they environed him all about, whereby he was not seen of
his company.  Then a squire of the king's alighted, called
John Standish, and he drew out his sword and put it into
Wat Tyler's belly, and so he died.
</p>
<p>Then the ungracious people there assembled, perceiving
their captain slain, began to murmur among themselves and
said: 'Ah, our captain is slain, let us go and slay them all':
and therewith they arranged themselves on the place in
manner of battle, and their bows before them.  Thus the
king began a great outrage;<note place="foot" n="4"><p>'Outrage'
here means 'act of boldness,' as elsewhere, e. g. 'si fist une
grant apertisee d'armes et un grant outrage.'</p></note>
howbeit, all turned to the best:

<pb n="80"/>

for as soon as Tyler was on the earth, the king departed
from all his company and all alone he rode to these people,
and said to his own men: 'Sirs, none of you follow me; let
me alone.'  And so when he came before these ungracious
people, who put themselves in ordinance to revenge their
captain, then the king said to them: 'Sirs, what aileth you?
Ye shall have no captain but me: I am your king: be all in
rest and peace.'  And so the most part of the people that
heard the king speak and saw him among them, were shamefast
and began to wax peaceable and to depart; but some,
such as were malicious and evil, would not depart, but made
semblant as though they would do somewhat.
</p>
<p>Then the king returned to his own company and demanded
of them what was best to be done.  Then he was counselled
to draw into the field, for to fly away was no boot.  Then
said the mayor: 'It is good that we do so, for I think surely
we shall have shortly some comfort of them of London and
of such good men as be of our part, who are purveyed and
have their friends and men ready armed in their houses.'
And in the mean time voice and bruit ran through London
how these unhappy people were likely to slay the king and
the mayor in Smithfield; through the which noise all manner
of good men of the king's party issued out of their houses
and lodgings well armed, and so came all to Smithfield
and to the field where the king was, and they were anon to
the number of seven or eight thousand men well armed.
And first thither came sir Robert Knolles and sir Perducas
d'Albret, well accompanied, and divers of the aldermen of
London, and with them a six hundred men in harness, and
a puissant man of the city, who was the king's draper,
<note place="foot" n="5"><p>'Qui estoit des draps du roy.' He
owned large estates in Essex and also shops in London.  He
became one of the councillors of Richard II.</p></note>
called Nicholas Bramber, and he brought with him a great
company; and ever as they came, they ranged them afoot
in order of battle: and on the other part these unhappy
people were ready ranged, making semblance to give battle,
and they had with them divers of the king's banners.  There
the king made three knights, the one the mayor of London
sir Nicholas Walworth, sir John Standish and sir Nicholas
Bramber.  Then the lords said among themselves: 'What

<pb n="81"/>

shall we do?  We see here our enemies, who would gladly
slay us, if they might have the better hand of us.'  Sir
Robert Knolles counselled to go and fight with them and
slay them all; yet the king would not consent thereto, but
said: 'Nay, I will not so: I will send to them commanding
them to send me again my banners, and thereby we shall
see what they will do.  Howbeit, other by fairness or otherwise,
I will have them.'  'That is well said, sir,' quoth the
earl of Salisbury.  Then these new knights were sent to
them, and these knights made token to them not to shoot
at them, and when they came so near them that their speech
might be heard, they said:  'Sirs, the king commandeth you
to send to him again his banners, and we think he will have
mercy of you.'  And incontinent they delivered again the
banners and sent them to the king.  Also they were commanded
on pain of their heads, that all such as had letters
of the king to bring them forth and to send them again to
the king; and so many of them delivered their letters, but
not all.  Then the king made them to be all to-torn in their
presence; and as soon as the king's banners were delivered
again, these unhappy people kept none array, but the most
part of them did cast down their bows, and so brake their
array and returned into London.  Sir Robert Knolles was
sore displeased in that he might not go to slay them all:
but the king would not consent thereto, but said he would
be revenged of them well enough; and so he was after.
</p>
<p>Thus these foolish people departed, some one way and
some another; and the king and his lords and all his company
right ordinately entered into London with great joy.
And the first journey that the king made he went to the lady
princess his mother, who was in a castle in the Royal called
the Queen's Wardrobe, and there she had tarried two days
and two nights right sore abashed, as she had good reason;
and when she saw the king her son, she was greatly rejoiced
and said: 'Ah, fair son, what pain and great sorrow
that I have suffered for you this day!'  Then the king answered
and said: 'Certainly, madam, I know it well; but
now rejoice yourself and thank God, for now it is time.
I have this day recovered mine heritage and the realm of
England, the which I had near lost.'  Thus the king tarried

<pb n="82"/>

that day with his mother, and every lord went peaceably to
their own lodgings.  Then there was a cry made in every
street in the king's name, that all manner of men, not being
of the city of London and have not dwelt there the space
of one year, to depart; and if any such be found there the
Sunday by the sun-rising, that they should be taken as
traitors to the king and to lose their heads.  This cry thus
made, there was none that durst brake it, and so all manner
of people departed and sparkled abroad every man to their
own places.  John Ball and Jack Straw were found in an old
house hidden, thinking to have stolen away, but they could
not, for they were accused by their own men.  Of the
taking of them the king and his lords were glad, and then
strake off their heads and Wat Tyler's also, and they were
set on London bridge, and the valiant men's heads taken
down that they had set on the Thursday before.  These
tidings anon spread abroad, so that the people of the strange
countries, which were coming towards London, returned
back again to their own houses and durst come no farther.
</p>

<pb n="83"/>
</div2>
</div1>

<div1 type="chapter" n="4" id="d37">
<head>The Battle of Otterburn</head>
<div2 type="section" id="d38">
<head>HOW THE EARL DOUGLAS WON THE PENNON OF SIR HENRY
PERCY<lb/>
AT THE BARRIERS BEFORE NEWCASTLE-UPON-TYNE, AND<lb/>
HOW THE SCOTS BRENT THE CASTLE OF PONTLAND,<lb/>
AND HOW SIR HENRY PERCY AND SIR RALPH<lb/>
HIS BROTHER TOOK ADVICE TO FOLLOW<lb/>
THE SCOTS TO CONQUER AGAIN THE<lb/>
PENNON THAT WAS LOST AT<lb/>
THE SCRIMMISH</head>

<p>WHEN the English lords saw that their squire
returned not again at the time appointed, and
could know nothing what the Scots did, nor what
they were purposed to do, then they thought well that their
squire was taken.  The lords sent each to other, to be ready
whensoever they should hear that the Scots were abroad:
as for their messenger, they thought him but lost.
</p>
<p>Now let us speak of the earl Douglas and other, for they
had more to do than they that went by Carlisle.  When the
earls of Douglas, of Moray, of March, and Dunbar<note place="foot" n="1"><p>
George, earl of March and Dunbar: the text gives Mare, but there was
at this time no earl of Mar.</p></note> departed
from the great host, they took their way thinking to pass
the water and to enter into the bishopric of Durham, and to
ride to the town and then to return, brenning and exiling
the country and so to come to Newcastle and to lodge there
in the town in the despite of all the Englishmen.  And as
they determined, so they did assay to put it in use, for they
rode a great pace under covert without doing of any pillage
by the way or assaulting of any castle, tower or house,
but so came into the lord Percy's land and passed the river
of Tyne without any let a three leagues above Newcastle
not far from Brancepeth, and at last entered into the
bishopric of Durham, where they found a good country.


<pb n="84"/>

Then they began to make war, to slay people and to bren
villages and to do many sore displeasures.
</p>
<p>As at that time the earl of Northumberland and the other
lords and knights of that country knew nothing of their
coming.  When tidings came to Newcastle and to Durham
that the Scots were abroad, and that they might well see by
the fires and smoke abroad in the country, the earl sent to
Newcastle his two sons and sent commandment to every man
to draw to Newcastle, saying to his sons: 'Ye shall go to
Newcastle and all the country shall assemble there, and I
shall tarry at Alnwick, which is a passage that they must
pass by.  If we may enclose them, we shall speed well.'  Sir
Henry Percy and sir Ralph his brother obeyed their father's
commandment and came thither with them of the country.
The Scots rode burning and exiling the country, that the
smoke thereof came to Neweastle.  The Scots came to the
gates of Durham and scrimmished there; but they tarried not
long but returned, as they had ordained before to do, and that
they found by the way took and destroyed it.  Between
Durham and Newcastle is but twelve leagues English and a
good country: there was no town, without it were closed,
but it was brent, and they repassed the river of Tyne where
they had passed before, and then came before Newcastle
and there rested.  All the English knights and squires of the
country of York and bishopric of Durham were assembled
at Newcastle, and thither came the seneschal of York, sir
Ralph Lumley, sir Matthew Redman, captain of Berwick,
sir Robert Ogle, sir Thomas Grey, sir Thomas Holton, sir
John Felton, sir John Lilleburn, sir Thomas Abingdon, the
baron of Hilton, sir John Coppledike and divers other, so that
the town was so full of people that they wist not where to
lodge.
</p>
<p>When these three Scottish earls who were chief captains
had made their enterprise in the bishopric of Durham and
had sore overrun the country, then they returned to Newcastle
and there rested and tarried two days, and every day
they scrimmished.  The earl of Northumberland's two sons
were two young lusty knights and were ever foremost at the
barriers to scrimmish.  There were many proper feats of
arms done and achieved: there was fighting hand to hand:

<pb n="85"/>

among other there fought hand to hand the earl Douglas and
sir Henry Percy, and by force of arms the earl Douglas won
the pennon of sir Henry Percy's, wherewith he was sore
displeased and so were all the Englishmen.  And the earl
Douglas said to sir Henry Percy: 'Sir, I shall bear this token
of your prowess into Scotland and shall set it on high on my
castle of Dalkeith, that it may be seen far off.'  'Sir,' quoth
sir Henry, 'ye may be sure ye shall not pass the bounds of
this country till ye be met withal in such wise that ye shall
make none avaunt thereof.'  'Well, sir,' quoth the earl
Douglas, 'come this night to my lodging and seek for your
pennon: I shall set it before my lodging and see if ye will
come to take it away.'  So then it was late, and the Scots
withdrew to their lodgings and refreshed them with such as
they had.  They had flesh enough: they made that night good
watch, for they thought surely to be awaked for the words
they had spoken, but they were not, for sir Henry Percy was
counselled not so to do.
</p>
<p>The next day the Scots dislodged and returned towards
their own country, and so came to a castle and a town called
Pontland, whereof sir Edmund of Alphel was lord, who was
a right good knight.  There the Scots rested, for they came
thither betimes, and understood that the knight was in his
castle.  Then they ordained to assail the castle, and gave a
great assault, so that by force of arms they won it and the
knight within it.  Then the town and castle was brent; and
from thence the Scots went to the town and castle of Otterburn,
an eight English mile from Newcastle<note place="foot" n="2"><p>
Froissart says 'eight English leagues.' In the next chapter the
distance becomes 'seven little leagues,' and later on, 'a six
English miles,' where the original is 'lieues.'  The actual
distance is about thirty miles.  The translator gives the form
'Combur' here. but 'Ottenburge' in the next chapter, as the name
of the place.  It is remarkable indeed how little trouble
he seems to have taken generally to give English names correctly.
In this chapter we have 'Nymyche' for 'Alnwick' and 'Pouclan'
for 'Pontland,' forms rather less like the real names than those
which he found in the French text, viz.  Nynich and Ponclau.</p></note>
and there lodged.  That day they made none assault, but the next
morning they blew their horns and made ready to assail
the castle, which was strong, for it stood in the marish.
That day they assaulted till they were weary, and did nothing.
Then they sowned the retreat and returned to their lodgings.
Then the lords drew to council to determine what they

<pb n="86"/>

should do.  The most part were of the accord that the next
day they should dislodge without giving of any assault and
to draw fair and easily towards Carlisle.  But the earl
Douglas brake that counsel and said: 'In despite of sir
Henry Percy, who said he would come and win again his
pennon, let us not depart hence for two or three days.  Let
us assail this castle: it is pregnable: we shall have double
honour.  And then let us see if he will come and fetch his
pennon: he shall be well defended.'<note place="foot" n="3"><p>
Froissart says, 'if he comes, it shall be defended.'  The translator
perhaps means 'he shall be prevented.'</p></note>  Every man accorded
to his saying, what for their honour and for the love of him.
Also they lodged there at their ease, for there was none that
troubled them: they made many lodgings of boughs and great
herbs and fortified their camp sagely with the marish that
was thereby, and their carriages were set at the entry into
the marishes and had all their beasts within the marish.
Then they apparelled for to assault the next day: this was
their intention.
</p>
<p>Now let us speak of sir Henry Percy and of sir Ralph his
brother and shew somewhat what they did.  They were sore
displeased that the earl Douglas had won the pennon of their
arms: also it touched greatly their honours, if they did not
as sir Henry Percy said he would; for he had said to the earl
Douglas that he should not carry his pennon out of England,
and also he had openly spoken it before all the knights
and squires that were at Newcastle.  The Englishmen there
thought surely that the earl Douglas' band was but the Scots'
vanguard and that their host was left behind.  The knights
of the country, such as were well expert in arms, spake
against sir Henry Percy's opinion and said to him: 'Sir,
there fortuneth in war oftentimes many losses.  If the earl
Douglas have won your pennon, he bought it dear, for he
came to the gate to seek it and was well beaten:
<note place="foot" n="4"><p>i. e. 'well fought with.'</p></note> another
day ye shall win as much of him or more.  Sir, we say this
because we know well all the power of Scotland is abroad
in the fields, and if we issue out and be not men enow to
fight with them, and peradventure they have made this
scrimmish with us to the intent to draw us out of the
town, and the number that they be of, as it is said, above

<pb n="87"/>

forty thousand men, they may soon enclose us and do with
us what they will.  Yet it were better to lose a pennon than
two or three hundred knights and squires and put all our
country in adventure.'  These words refrained sir Henry
and his brother, for they would do nothing against counsel.
Then tidings came to them by such as had seen the Scots
and seen all their demeanour and what way they took and
where they rested.
</p>
</div2>
<div2 type="section" id="d39">
<head>HOW SIR HENRY PERCY AND HIS BROTHER WITH A GOOD
NUMBER<lb/>
OF MEN OF ARMS AND ARCHERS WENT AFTER THE<lb/>
SCOTS, TO WIN AGAIN HIS PENNON THAT<lb/>
THE EARL DOUGLAS HAD WON BEFORE<lb/>
NEWCASTLE-UPON-TYNE, AND HOW<lb/>
THEY ASSAILED THE SCOTS BEFORE <lb/>
OTTERBURN IN THEIR<lb/>
LODGINGS<lb/> </head>

<p>IT was shewed to sir Henry Percy and to his brother and
to the other knights and squires that were there, by such as
had followed the Scots from Newcastle and had well advised
their doing, who said to sir Henry and to sir Ralph: 'Sirs,
we have followed the Scots privily and have discovered all
the country.  The Scots be at Pontland and have taken sir
Edmund Alphel in his own castle, and from thence they
be gone to Otterburn and there they lay this night.  What
they will do to-morrow we know not: they are ordained to
abide there: and, sirs, surely their great host is not with
them, for in all they pass not there a three thousand men.'
When sir Henry heard that, he was joyful and said: 'Sirs,
let us leap on our horses, for by the faith I owe to God and
to my lord my father I will go seek for my pennon and dislodge
them this same night.'  Knights and squires that
heard him agreed thereto and were joyous, and every man
made him ready.
</p>
<p>The same evening the bishop of Durham came thither with
a good company, for he heard at Durham how the Scots were
before Newcastle and how that the lord Percy's sons with
other lords and knights should fight with the Scots: therefore
the bishop of Durham to come to the rescue had assembled

<pb n="88"/>

up all the country and so was coming to Newcastle.  But
sir Henry Percy would not abide his coming, for he had with
him six hundred spears, knights and squires, and an eight
thousand footmen.  They thought that sufficient number to
fight with the Scots, if they were not but three hundred
spears and three thousand of other.  Thus they departed
from Newcastle after dinner and set forth in good order, and
took the same way as the Scots had gone and rode to Otterburn,
a seven little leagues from thence and fair way, but
they could not ride fast because of their foot-men.  And
when the Scots had supped and some laid down to their
rest, and were weary of travailing and assaulting of the
castle all that day, and thought to rise early in the morning
in cool of the day to give a new assault, therewith suddenly
the Englishmen came on them and entered into the lodgings,
weening it had been the masters' lodgings, and therein were
but varlets and servants.  Then the Englishmen cried,
'Percy, Percy!' and entered into the lodgings, and ye know
well where such affray is noise is soon raised: and it fortuned
well for the Scots, for when they saw the Englishmen came
to wake them, then the lord sent a certain of their servants
of foot-men to scrimmish with the Englishmen at the
entry of the lodgings, and in the mean time they armed
and apparelled them, every man under his banner and
under his captain's pennon.  The night was far on, but the
moon shone so bright as an it had been in a manner day.
It was in the month of August and the weather fair and
temperate.
</p>
<p>Thus the Scots were drawn together and without any
noise departed from their lodgings and went about a little
mountain, which was greatly for their advantage.  For all
the day before they had well advised the place and said
among themselves: 'If the Englishmen come on us suddenly,
then we will do thus and thus, for it is a jeopardous thing
in the night if men of war enter into our lodgings.  If they
do, then we will draw to such a place, and thereby other we
shall win or lose.'  When the Englishmen entered into the
field, at the first they soon overcame the varlets, and as they
entered further in, always they found new men to busy them
and to scrimmish with them.  Then suddenly came the Scots

<pb n="89"/>

from about the mountain and set on the Englishmen or they
were ware, and cried their cries; whereof the Englishmen
were sore astonied.  Then they cried 'Percy!' and the other
party cried 'Douglas!'
</p>
<p>There began a cruel battle and at the first encounter many
were overthrown of both parties; and because the Englishmen
were a great number and greatly desired to vanquish
their enemies, and rested at their pace<note place="foot" n="1"><p>In
French, 'ilz se arresterent,' without 'and.'</p></note> and greatly
did put aback the Scots, so that the Scots were near discomfited.
Then the earl James Douglas, who was young and strong and
of great desire to get praise and grace, and was willing to
deserve to have it, and cared for no pain nor travail, came
forth with his banner and cried, 'Douglas, Douglas!' and
sir Henry Percy and sir Ralph his brother, who had great
indignation against the earl Douglas because he had won
the pennon of their arms at the barriers before Newcastle,
came to that part and cried, 'Percy!'  Their two banners
met and their men: there was a sore fight: the Englishmen
were so strong and fought so valiantly that they reculed
the Scots back.  There were two valiant knights of Scots
under the banner of the earl Douglas, called sir Patrick of
Hepbourn and sir Patrick his son.  They acquitted themselves
that day valiantly: the earl's banner had been won,
an they had not been: they defended it so valiantly and in
the rescuing thereof did such feats of arms, that it was
greatly to their recommendation and to their heirs' for ever
after.
</p>
<p>It was shewed me by such as had been at the same battle,
as well by knights and squires of England as of Scotland, at
the house of the earl of Foix, &mdash; for anon after this battle
was done I met at Orthez two squires of England called John
of Chateauneuf and John of Cantiron; also when I returned
to Avignon I found also there a knight and a squire of
Scotland; I knew them and they knew me by such tokens
as I shewed them of their country, for I, author of this book,
in my youth had ridden nigh over all the realm of Scotland,
and I was as then a fifteen days in the house of earl William
Douglas, father to the same earl James, of whom I spake
of now, in a castle of five leagues from Edinburgh in the

<pb n="90"/>

country, of Dalkeith;<note place="foot" n="2"><p>'Which is called
in the country Dalkeith.'  The French has 'que on nomme au pays
Dacquest,' of which the translator makes 'in the countrey
of Alquest.'</p></note> the same time I saw there this earl
James, a fair young child, and a sister of his called the lady
Blanche, &mdash; and I was informed by both these parties
<note place="foot" n="3"><p>By both sides,' i. e. Scotch and English.</p></note>
how this battle was as sore a battle fought as lightly hath been
heard of before of such a number; and I believe it well, for
Englishmen on the one party and Scots on the other party
are good men of war, for when they meet there is a hard
fight without sparing, there is no ho between them as long
as spears, swords, axes or daggers will endure, but lay on
each upon other, and when they be well beaten
<note place="foot" n="4"><p>'When they have well fought.'</p></note> and
that the one party hath obtained the victory, they then glorify so
in their deeds of arms and are so joyful, that such as be
taken they shall be ransomed or they go out of the field, so
that shortly each of them is so content with other that at
their departing courteously they will say, 'God thank you';
but in fighting one with another there is no play nor sparing,
and this is true, and that shall well appear by this said
rencounter, for it was as valiantly foughten as could be devised,
as ye shall hear.
</p>
</div2>
<div2 type="section" id="d40">
<head>HOW THE EARL JAMES DOUGLAS BY HIS VALIANTNESS
ENCOURAGED <lb/>
HIS MEN, WHO WERE RECULED AND IN A<lb/>
MANNER DISCOMFITED, AND IN HIS SO DOING<lb/>
HE WAS WOUNDED TO DEATH
</head>
<p>KNIGHTS and squires were of good courage on both parties
to fight valiantly: cowards there had no place, but hardiness
reigned with goodly feats of arms, for knights and
squires were so joined together at hand strokes, that archers
had no place of nother party.  There the Scots shewed
great hardiness and fought merrily with great desire of
honour: the Englishmen were three to one: howbeit, I say
not but Englishmen did nobly acquit themselves, for ever
the Englishmen had rather been slain or taken in the place
than to fly.  Thus, as I have said, the banners of Douglas
and Percy and their men were met each against other,

<pb n="91"/>

envious who should win the honour of that journey.  At the
beginning the Englishmen were so strong that they reculed
back their enemies: then the earl Douglas, who was of
great heart and high of enterprise, seeing his men recule
back, then to recover the place and to shew knightly valour
he took his axe in both his hands, and entered so into the
press that he made himself way in such wise, that none durst
approach near him, and he was so well armed that he
bare well off such strokes as he received.<note place="foot" n="1"><p>
'No man was so well armed that he did not fear the great strokes
which he gave.'</p></note>  Thus he went
ever forward like a hardy Hector, willing alone to conquer
the field and to discomfit his enemies: but at last he was encountered
with three spears all at once, the one strake him on
the shoulder, the other on the breast and the stroke glinted
down to his belly, and the third strake him in the thigh, and
sore hurt with all three strokes, so that he was borne perforce
to the earth and after that he could not be again
relieved.  Some of his knights and squires followed him,
but not all, for it was night, and no light but by the shining
of the moon.  The Englishmen knew well they had borne one
down to the earth, but they wist not who it was; for if
they had known that it had been the earl Douglas, they
had been thereof so joyful and so proud that the victory
had been theirs.  Nor also the Scots knew not of that adventure
till the end of the battle; for if they had known it,
they should have been so sore despaired and discouraged
that they would have fled away.  Thus as the earl Douglas
was felled to the earth, he was stricken into the head with
an axe, and another stroke through the thigh: the Englishmen
passed forth and took no heed of him: they thought none
otherwise but that they had slain a man of arms.  On the
other part the earl George de la March and of Dunbar fought
right valiantly and gave the Englishmen much ado, and
cried, 'Follow Douglas,' and set on the sons of Percy: also
earl John of Moray with his banner and men fought valiantly
and set fiercely on the Englishmen, and gave them so
much to do that they wist not to whom to attend.
</p>

<pb n="92"/>
</div2>
<div2 type="section" id="d41">
<head>HOW IN THIS BATTLE SIR RALPH PERCY WAS SORE HURT
AND<lb/>
TAKEN PRISONER BY A SCOTTISH KNIGHT</head>
<p>OF all the battles and encounterings that I have made mention
of herebefore in all this history, great or small, this
battle that I treat of now was one of the sorest and best
foughten without cowardice or faint hearts.  For there was
nother knight nor squire but that did his devoir and fought
hand to hand: this battle was like the battle of Becherel,
<note place="foot" n="1"><p>Or, according to another reading, 'Cocherel.'</p></note>
the which was valiantly fought and endured.  The earl
of Northumberland's sons, sir Henry and sir Ralph Percy,
who were chief sovereign captains, acquitted themselves
nobly, and sir Ralph Percy entered in so far among his
enemies that he was closed in and hurt, and so sore handled
that his breath was so short, that he was taken prisoner by
a knight of the earl of Moray's called sir John Maxwell.
In the taking the Scottish knight demanded what he was, for
it was in the night, so that he knew him not, and sir Ralph was
so sore overcome and bled fast, that at last he said: 'I am
Ralph Percy.'  Then the Scot said: 'Sir Ralph, rescue or
no rescue I take you for my prisoner: I am Maxwell.'
'Well,' quoth sir Ralph, 'I am content: but then take heed
to me, for I am sore hurt, my hosen and my greaves are full
of blood.'  Then the knight saw by him the earl Moray and
said: 'Sir, here I deliver to you sir Ralph Percy as prisoner;
but, sir, let good heed be taken to him, for he is sore hurt.'
The earl was joyful of these words and said: 'Maxwell, thou
hast well won thy spurs.'  Then he delivered sir Ralph Percy
to certain of his men, and they stopped and wrapped his
wounds: and still the battle endured, not knowing who had
as then the better, for there were many taken and rescued
again that came to no knowledge.
</p>
<p>Now let us speak of the young James earl of Douglas, who
did marvels in arms or he was beaten down.  When he was
overthrown, the press was great about him, so that he
could not relieve, for with an axe he had his death's wound.
His men followed him as near as they could, and there came
to him sir James Lindsay his cousin and sir John and sir

<pb n="93"/>

Walter Sinclair and other knights and squires.  And by him
was a gentle knight of his, who followed him all the day, and
a chaplain of his, not like a priest but like a valiant man of
arms, for all that night he followed the earl with a good
axe in his hands and still scrimmished about the earl there
as he lay, and reculed back some of the Englishmen with
great strokes that he gave.  Thus he was found fighting near
to his master, whereby he had great praise, and thereby the
same year he was made archdeacon of Aberdeen.  This
priest was called sir William of North Berwick: he was a
tall man and a hardy and was sore hurt.  When these knights
came to the earl, they found him in an evil case and a knight
of his lying by him called sir Robert Hart: he had a fifteen
wounds in one place and other.  Then sir John Sinclair demanded
of the earl how he did.  'Right evil, cousin,' quoth
the earl, 'but thanked be God there hath been but a few
of mine ancestors that hath died in their beds: but, cousin,
I require you think to revenge me, for I reckon myself
but dead, for my heart fainteth oftentimes.  My cousin
Walter and you, I pray you raise up again my banner
which lieth on the ground, and my squire Davie Collemine
slain: but, sirs, shew nother to friend nor foe in what
case ye see me in; for if mine enemies knew it, they
would rejoice, and our friends discomforted.'  The two
brethren of Sinclair and sir James Lindsay did as the earl
had desired them and raised up again his banner and cried
'Douglas!'  Such as were behind and heard that cry drew
together and set on their enemies valiantly and reculed back
the Englishmen and many overthrown, and so drave the
Englishmen back beyond the place whereas the earl lay, who
was by that time dead, and so came to the earl's banner,
the which sir John Sinclair held in his hands, and many good
knights and squires of Scotland about him, and still company
drew to the cry of 'Douglas.'  Thither came the earl Moray
with his banner well accompanied, and also the earl de la
March and of Dunbar, and when they saw the Englishmen
recule and their company assembled together, they renewed
again the battle and gave many hard and sad strokes.
</p>

<pb n="94"/>
</div2>
<div2 type="section" id="d42">
<head>HOW THE SCOTS WON THE BATTLE AGAINST THE
ENGLISHMEN<lb/>
BESIDE OTTERBURN, AND THERE WAS TAKEN PRISONERS SIR<lb/>
HENRY AND SIR RALPH PERCY, AND HOW AN ENGLISH<lb/>
SQUIRE WOULD NOT YIELD HIM, NO MORE WOULD<lb/>
A SCOTTISH SQUIRE, AND SO DIED BOTH; AND<lb/>
HOW THE BISHOP OF DURHAM AND HIS<lb/>
COMPANY WERE DISCOMFITED<lb/>
AMONG THEMSELVES
</head>

<p>To say truth, the Englishmen were sorer travailed than the
Scots, for they came the same day from Newcastle-upon-Tyne, a six English miles, and went a great pace to the
intent to find the Scots, which they did; so that by their
fast going they were near out of breath, and the Scots were
fresh and well rested, which greatly availed them when
time was of their business: for in the last scrimmish they
reculed back the Englishmen in such wise, that after that
they could no more assemble together, for the Scots passed
through their battles.  And it fortuned that sir Henry
Percy and the lord of Montgomery, a valiant knight of Scotland,
fought together hand to hand right valiantly without
letting of any other, for every man had enough to do.  So
long they two fought that per force of arms sir Henry
Percy was taken prisoner by the said lord of Montgomery.
</p>
<p>The knights and squires of Scotland, as sir Marc Adreman,
<note place="foot" n="1"><p>Perhaps 'Malcolm Drummond.'</p></note>
sir Thomas Erskine, sir William, sir James and sir
Alexander Lindsay, the lord of Fenton, sir John of Saint-Moreaulx,<note place="foot" n="2"><p>The true reading seems to be
'Sandilands.'</p></note> sir Patrick of Dunbar, sir John and sir Walter
Sinclair, sir John Maxwell, sir Guy Stuart, sir John Haliburton,
sir Alexander Ramsay, Robert Collemine
<note place="foot" n="3"><p>Perhaps 'Coningham.'</p></note> and his
two sons John and Robert; who were there made knights,
and a hundred knights and squires that I cannot name, all
these right valiantly did acquit themselves.  And on the
English party, before that the lord Percy was taken and
after, there fought valiantly sir Ralph Lumley, sir Matthew
Redman, sir Thomas Ogle, sir Thomas Gray, sir Thomas
Helton, sir Thomas Abingdon, sir John Lilleburn, sir
William Walsingham, the baron of Helton, sir John of

<pb n="95"/>

Colpedich,<note place="foot" n="4"><p>Either 'Copeland' or
'Copeldike.'</p></note> the seneschal of York and divers other
footmen.  Whereto should I write long process?  This was a
sore battle and well foughten; and as fortune is always
changeable, though the Englishmen were more in number
than the Scots and were right valiant men of war and well
expert, and that at the first front they reculed back the
Scots, yet finally the Scots obtained the place and victory,
and all the foresaid Englishmen taken, and a hundred more,
saving sir Matthew Redman, captain of Berwick, who when
he knew no remedy nor recoverance, and saw his company
fly from the Scots and yielded them on every side, then he
took his horse and departed to save himself.
</p>
<p>The same season about the end of this discomfiture there
was an English squire called Thomas Waltham, a goodly and
a valiant man, and that was well seen, for of all that night
he would nother fly nor yet yield him.  It was said he had
made a vow at a feast in England, that the first time that
ever he saw Englishmen and Scots in battle, he would so do
his devoir to his power, in such wise that either he would be
reputed for the best doer on both sides or else to die in the
pain.  He was called a valiant and a hardy man and did
so much by his prowess, that under the banner of the earl
of Moray he did such valiantness in arms, that the Scots had
marvel thereof, and so was slain in fighting: the Scots would
gladly have taken him alive, but he would never yield, he
hoped ever to have been rescued.  And with him there was
a Scottish squire slain, cousin to the king of Scots, called
Simon Glendowyn; his death was greatly complained of the
Scots.
</p>
<p>This battle was fierce and cruel till it came to the end of
the discomfiture; but when the Scots saw the Englishmen
recule and yield themselves, then the Scots were courteous
and set them to their ransom, and every man said to his
prisoner: 'Sirs, go and unarm you and take your ease; I
am your master:' and so made their prisoners as good cheer
as though they had been brethren, without doing to them
any damage.  The chase endured a five English miles, and
if the Scots had been men enow, there had none scaped, but
other they had been taken or slain.  And if Archambault


<pb n="96"/>

Douglas and the earl of Fife, the earl Sutherland and other
of the great company who were gone towards Carlisle had
been there, by all likelihood they had taken the bishop of
Durham and the town of Newcastle-upon-Tyne.  I shall
shew you how.  The same evening that the Percies departed
from Newcastle, as ye have heard before, the bishop of
Durham with the rearband came to Newcastle and supped:
and as he sat at the table, he had imagination in himself how
he did not acquit himself well to see the Englishmen in the
field and he to be within the town.  Incontinent he caused
the table to be taken away and commanded to saddle his
horses and to sown the trumpets, and called up men in
the town to arm themselves and to mount on their horses,
and foot-men to order themselves to depart.  And thus every
man departed out of the town to the number of seven thousand,
two thousand on horseback and five thousand afoot;
they took their way toward Otterburn, whereas the battle had
been.  And by that time they had gone two mile
<note place="foot" n="5"><p>The word 'lieue' is translated
'mile' throughout.</p></note> from
Newcastle tidings came to them how their men were fighting
with the Scots.  Therewith the bishop rested there, and
incontinent came more flying fast, that they were out of
breath.  Then they were demanded how the matter went.
They answered and said: 'Right evil; we be all discomfited:
here cometh the Scots chasing of us.'  These tidings troubled
the Englishmen, and began to doubt.  And again the third
time men came flying as fast as they might.  When the men
of the bishopric of Durham heard of these evil tidings, they
were abashed in such wise that they brake their array, so
that the bishop could not hold together the number of five
hundred.  It was thought that if the Scots had followed
them in any number, seeing that it was night, that in the
entering into the town, and the Englishmen so abashed, the
town had been won.
</p>
<p>The bishop of Durham, being in the field, had good will
to have succoured the Englishmen and recomforted his men
as much as he could; but he saw his own men fly as well
as other.  Then he demanded counsel of sir William Lucy
and of sir Thomas Clifford and of other knights, what was
best to do.  These knights for their honour would give him

<pb n="97"/>

no counsel; for they thought to return again and do nothing
should sown greatly to their blame, and to go forth might
be to their great damage; and so stood still and would give
none answer, and the longer they stood, the fewer they
were, for some still stale away.  Then the bishop said:
'Sirs, all things considered, it is none honour to put all in
peril, nor to make of one evil damage twain.  We hear
how our company be discomfited, and we cannot remedy it:
for to go to recover them, we know not with whom nor with
what number we shall meet.  Let us return fair and easily
for this night to Newcastle, and to-morrw let us draw
together and go look on our enemies.'  Every man answered:
'As God will, so be it.' Therewith they returned to
Newcastle.  Thus a man may consider the great default
that is in men that be abashed and discomfited: for if
they had kept them together and have turned again such
as fled, they had discomfited the Scots.  This was the
opinion of divers; and because they did not thus, the Scots
had the victory.
</p>
</div2>
<div2 type="section" id="d43">
<head>HOW SIR MATTHEW REDMAN DEPARTED FROM THE BATTLE<lb/>
TO SAVE HIMSELF; AND HOW SIR JAMES LINDSAY WAS<lb/>
TAKEN PRISONER BY THE BISHOP OF DURHAM; AND<lb/>
HOW AFTER THE BATTLE SCURRERS WERE SENT<lb/>
FORTH TO DISCOVER THE COUNTRY</head>

<p>I SHALL shew you of sir Matthew Redman, who was on
horseback to save himself, for he alone could not remedy
the matter.  At his departing sir James Lindsay was near to
him and saw how sir Matthew departed, and this sir James,
to win honour, followed in chase sir Matthew Redman,
and came so near him that he might have striken him with
his spear, if he had list.  Then he said: 'Ah, sir knight,
turn; it is a shame thus to fly: I am James of Lindsay: if
ye will not turn, I shall strike you on the back with my
spear.'  Sir Matthew spake no word, but strake his horse with
the spurs sorer than he did before.  In this manner he
chased him more than three miles, and at last sir Matthew
Redman's horse foundered and fell under him.  Then he
stept forth on the earth and drew out his sword, and took

<pb n="98"/>

courage to defend himself; and the Scot thought to have
stricken him on the breast, but sir Matthew Redman
swerved from the stroke, and the spear-point entered into
the earth.  Then sir Matthew strake asunder the spear with
his sword; and when sir James Lindsay saw how he had
lost his spear, he cast away the truncheon and lighted afoot,
and took a little battle-axe that he carried at his back and
handled it with his one hand quickly and deliverly, in
the which feat Scots be well expert, and then he set at
sir Matthew and he defended himself properly.  Thus
they tourneyed together, one with an axe and the other
with a sword, a long season, and no man to let them.
Finally sir James Lindsay gave the knight such strokes
and held him so short, that he was put out of breath in
such wise that he yielded himself, and said: 'Sir James
Lindsay, I yield me to you.'  'Well,' quoth he, 'and I
receive you, rescue or no rescue.'  'I am content,' quoth
Redman, 'so ye deal with me like a good companion.'  'I
shall not fail that,' quoth Lindsay, and so put up his sword.
'Well, sir,' quoth Redman, 'what will you now that I shall
do?  I am your prisoner, ye have conquered me.  I would
gladly go again to Newcastle, and within fifteen days I shall
come to you into Scotland, whereas ye shall assign me.'  'I
am content,' quoth Lindsay: 'ye shall promise by your faith
to present yourself within this three weeks at Edinboro, and
wheresoever ye go, to repute yourself my prisoner.'  All this
sir Matthew sware and promised to fulfil.  Then each of
them took their horses and took leave each of other.  Sir
James returned, and his intent was to go to his own company
the same way that he came, and sir Matthew Redman
to Newcastle.
</p>
<p>Sir James Lindsay could not keep the right way as he
came: it was dark and a mist, and he had not ridden half a
mile, but he met face to face with the bishop of Durham
and more than five hundred Englishmen with him.  He
might well escaped if he had would, but he supposed it had
been his own company, that had pursued the Englishmen.
When he was among them, one demanded of him what he
was.  'I am,' quoth he, 'sir James Lindsay.'  The bishop
heard those words and stept to him and said: 'Lindsay, ye

<pb n="99"/>

are taken: yield ye to me.'  'Who be you?' quoth Lindsay.
'I am,' quoth he, 'the bishop of Durham.'  'And from
whence come you, sir?' quoth Lindsay.  'I come from the
battle,' quoth the bishop, 'but I struck never a stroke there:
I go back to Newcastle for this night, and ye shall go with
me.'  'I may not choose,' quoth Lindsay, 'sith ye will have it
so.  I have taken and I am taken; such is the adventures of
arms.'  'Whom have ye taken?' quoth the bishop.  'Sir,'
quoth he, 'I took in the chase sir Matthew Redman.'  'And
where is he?' quoth the bishop.  'By my faith, sir, he is
returned to Newcastle: he desired me to trust him on his
faith for three weeks, and so have I done.'  'Well,' quoth
the bishop, 'let us go to Newcastle, and there ye shall speak
with him.'  Thus they rode to Newcastle together, and sir
James Lindsay was prisoner to the bishop of Durham.
</p>
<p>Under the banner of the earl de la March and of Dunbar
was taken a squire of Gascoyne, called John of Chateauneuf,
and under the banner of the earl of Moray was taken his
companion John de Cantiron.  Thus the field was clean
avoided, or the day appeared.  The Scots drew together and
took guides and sent out scurrers to see if any men were
in the way from Newcastle, to the intent that they would
not be troubled in their lodgings; wherein they did wisely,
for when the bishop of Durham was come again to Newcastle
and in his lodging, he was sore pensive and wist not
what to say nor do; for he heard say how his cousins the
Percies were slain or taken, and all the knights that were
with them.  Then he sent for all the knights and squires that
were in the town; and when they were come, he demanded
of them if they should leave the matter in that case, and
said: 'Sirs, we shall bear great blame if we thus return
without looking on our enemies.'  Then they concluded by
the sun-rising every man to be armed, and on horseback
and afoot to depart out of the town and to go to Otterburn
to fight with the Scots.  This was warned through the town
by a trumpet, and every man armed them and assembled
before the bridge, and by the sun-rising they departed by
the gate towards Berwick and took the way towards Otterburn
to the number of ten thousand, what afoot and a-horseback.
They were not gone past two mile from Newcastle,

<pb n="100"/>

when the Scots were signified that the bishop of Durham
was coming to themward to fight: this they knew by their
spies, such as they had set in the fields.
</p>
<p>After that sir Matthew Redman was returned to Newcastle
and had shewed to divers how he had been taken
prisoner by sir James Lindsay, then it was shewed him
how the bishop of Durham had taken the said sir James
Lindsay and how that he was there in the town as his
prisoner.  As soon as the bishop was departed, sir Matthew
Redman went to the bishop's lodging to see his master, and
there he found him in a study, lying in a window
<note place="foot" n="1"><p>Or rather, 'very pensive leaning against
a window,' and afterwards the expression 'came forth of the
study to him' should be 'broke off his thought and came towards
him.'</p></note> and said:
'What, sir James Lindsay, what make you here?'  Then
sir James came forth of the study to him and gave him good
morrow, and said: 'By my faith, sir Matthew, fortune hath
brought me hither; for as soon as I was departed from you,
I met by chance the bishop of Durham, to whom I am prisoner,
as ye be to me.  I believe ye shall not need to come to
Edinboro to me to make your finance: I think rather we
shall make an exchange one for another, if the bishop be
so content.'  'Well, sir,' quoth Redman, 'we shall accord
right well together, ye shall dine this day with me: the
bishop and our men be gone forth to fight with your men,
I cannot tell what shall fall, we shall know at their return.'
'I am content to dine with you,' quoth Lindsay.  Thus these
two knights dined together in Newcastle.
</p>
<p>When the knights of Scotland were informed how the
bishop of Durham came on them with ten thousand men,
they drew to council to see what was best for them to do,
other to depart or else to abide the adventure.  All things
considered, they concluded to abide, for they said they could
not be in a better nor a stronger place than they were in
already: they had many prisoners and they could not carry
them away, if they should have departed; and also they had
many of their men hurt and also some of their prisoners,
whom they thought they would not leave behind them.  Thus
they drew together and ordered so their field, that there was
no entry but one way, and they set all their prisoners together
and made them to promise how that, rescue or no

<pb n="101"/>

rescue, they should be their prisoners.  After that they made
all their minstrels to blow up all at once and made the
greatest revel of the world.  Lightly it is the usage of Scots,
that when they be thus assembled together in arms, the footmen
beareth about their necks horns in manner like hunters,
some great, some small, and of all sorts, so that when they
blow all at once, they make such a noise, that it may be heard
nigh four miles off: thus they do to abash their enemies
and to rejoice themselves.  When the bishop of Durham with
his banner and ten thousand men with him were approached
within a league, then the Scots blew their horns in such
wise, that it seemed that all the devils in hell had been
among them, so that such as heard them and knew not of
their usage were sore abashed.  This blowing and noise
endured a long space and then ceased: and by that time the
Englishmen were within less than a mile.  Then the Scots
began to blow again and made a great noise, and as long
endured as it did before.  Then the bishop approached with
his battle well ranged in good order and came within the
sight of the Scots, as within two bow-shot or less: then the
Scots blew again their horns a long space.  The bishop stood
still to see what the Scots would do and aviewed them well
and saw how they were in a strong ground greatly to their
advantage.  Then the bishop took counsel what was best for
him to do; but all things well advised, they were not in
purpose to enter in among the Scots to assail them, but returned
without doing of anything, for they saw well they
might rather lose than win.
</p>
<p>When the Scots saw the Englishmen recule and that they
should have no battle, they went to their lodgings and
made merry, and then ordained to depart from thence.
And because that sir Ralph Percy was sore hurt, he desired
of his master that he might return to Newcastle or into
some place, whereas it pleased him, unto such time as he
were whole of his hurts, promising, as soon as he were
able to ride, to return into Scotland, other to Edinboro or
into any other place appointed.  The earl of March, under
whom he was taken, agreed thereto and delivered him a
horse litter and sent him away; and by like covenant divers
other knights and squires were suffered to return and took

<pb n="102"/>

term other to return or else to pay their finance, such as
they were appointed unto.  It was shewed me by the information
of the Scots, such as had been at this said battle
that was between Newcastle and Otterburn in the year of
our Lord God a thousand three hundred fourscore and eight,
the nineteenth day of August, how that there were taken
prisoners of the English party a thousand and forty men,
one and other, and slain in the field and in the chase eighteen
hundred and forty, and sore hurt more than a thousand:
and of the Scots there were a hundred slain, and taken
in the chase more than two hundred; for as the Englishmen
fled, when they saw any advantage they returned again
and fought: by that means the Scots were taken and none
otherwise.  Every man may well consider that it was a
well fought field, when there were so many slain and taken
on both parties.
</p>
</div2>
<div2 type="section" id="d44">
<head>HOW THE SCOTS DEPARTED AND CARRIED WITH THEM THE<lb/>
EARL DOUGLAS DEAD, AND BURIED HIM IN THE ABBEY OF<lb/>
MELROSE; AND HOW SIR ARCHAMBAULT DOUGLAS AND<lb/>
HIS COMPANY DEPARTED FROM BEFORE CARLISLE<lb/>
AND RETURNED INTO SCOTLAND</head>

<p>AFTER this battle thus finished, every man returned,
<note place="foot" n="1"><p>That is, 'After the battle was over
and every man had returned,' but it should be, 'After all
this was done and everything was gathered together.'</p></note> and
the earl Douglas' dead body chested and laid in a chare,
and with him sir Robert Hart and Simon Glendowyn, then
they prepared to depart: so they departed and led with
them sir Henry Percy and more than forty knights of England,
and took the way to the abbey of Melrose.  At their
departing they set fire in their lodgings, and rode all the
day, and yet lay that night in the English ground: none
denied them.  The next day they dislodged early in the
morning and so came that day to Melrose.  It is an abbey
of black monks on the border between both realms.  There
they rested and buried the earl James Douglas.  The
second day after his obsequy was done reverently, and on
his body laid a tomb of stone and his banner hanging
over him.  Whether there were as then any more earls of
Douglas, to whom the land returned, or not, I cannot tell;

<pb n="103"/>

for I, sir John Froissart, author of this book, was in
Scotland in the earl's castle of Dalkeith, living earl William,
at which time he had two children, a son and a daughter;
but after there were many of the Douglases, for I have
seen a five brethren, all squires, bearing the name of Douglas,
in the king of Scotland's house, David; they were sons
to a knight in Scotland called sir James Douglas, and they
bare in their arms gold, three oreilles gules, but as for
the heritage, I know not who had it: as for sir Archambault
Douglas, of whom I have spoken before in this history
in divers places, who was a valiant knight, and greatly
redoubted of the Englishmen, he was but a bastard.
</p>
<p>When these Scots had been at Melrose abbey and done
there all that they came thither for, then they departed
each from other and went into their own countries, and
such as had prisoners, some led them away with them and
some were ransomed and suffered to return.  Thus the
Englishmen found the Scots right courteous and gentle
in their deliverance and ransom, so that they were well
content.  This was shewed me in the country of Bearn
in the earl of Foix's house by a knight named John of
Chateauneuf, who was taken prisoner at the same journey
under the banner of the earl of March and Dunbar: and he
greatly praised the said earl, for he suffered him to pass
in manner as he desired himself.
</p>
<p>Thus these men of war of Scotland departed, and ransomed
their prisoners as soon as they might right courteously,
and so returned little and little into their own
countries.  And it was shewed me and I believe it well,
that the Scots had by reason of that journey two hundred
thousand franks for ransoming of prisoners: for sith the
battle that was before Stirling in Scotland, whereas sir
Robert of Bruce, sir William Douglas, sir Robert Versy,
sir Simon Fraser and other Scots chased the Englishmen
three days, they never had journey so profitable nor so
honourable for them, as this was.  When tidings came to
the other company of the Scots that were beside Carlisle,
how their company had distressed the Englishmen beside
Otterburn, they were greatly rejoiced, and displeased in
their minds that they had not been there.  Then they determined

<pb n="104"/>

to dislodge and to draw into their own countries,
seeing their other company were withdrawn.  Thus they
dislodged and entered into Scotland.
</p>
<p>Now let us leave to speak of the Scots and of the Englishmen
for this time, and let us return to the young Charles
of France, who with a great people went into Almaine, to
bring the duke of Gueldres to reason.
</p>
<p>When the French king and all his army were past the
river of Meuse at the bridge of Morsay, they took the way
of Ardennes and of Luxembourg, and always the pioneers
were before, beating woods and bushes and making the
ways plain.  The duke of Juliers and his country greatly
doubted the coming of the French king, for they knew
well they should have the first assault and bear the first
burden: and the land of Juliers is a plain country; in one
day the men of war should do much damage there, and
destroy and waste all, except the castles and good towns.
Thus the French king entered into the country of Luxembourg
and came to an abbey, whereas Wenceslas sometime
duke of Brabant was buried.  There the king tarried two
days: then he departed and took the way through Bastogne,
and lodged within a league whereas the duchess of Brabant
lay.  She sent word of her being there to the duke of
Burgoyne, and he brought her into the field to speak with
the king, who received her right honourably, and there
communed together.  Then the duchess returned to Bastogne,
and thither she was conveyed with sir John of Vienne and
sir Guy of Tremouille; and the next day the king went
forward, approaching to the land of his enemies, and came
to the entering into Almaine, on the frontiers of the
duchy of Juliers.  But or he came so far forward, Arnold
bishop of Liege had been with the king and had greatly
entreated for the duke of Juliers, that the king should not
be miscontent with him, though he were father to the duke
of Gueldres; for he excused him of the defiance that his
son had made, affirming how it was not by his knowledge
nor consent, wherefore, he said, it were pity that the
father should bear the default of the son.  His excuse was
not sufficient to the king nor to his uncles: for the intent
of the king and his council was, without the duke of

<pb n="105"/>

Juliers would come and make other manner of excuse, and
to yield himself to the king's pleasure, his country should
be the first that should bear the burden.  Then the bishop
of Liege and the lords of Hesbaing and the councils of the
good towns offered to the king and his council wholly the
bishopric of Liege for his army to pass and repass paying
for their expenses, and to rest and refresh them there as
long as it pleased them.  The king thanked them, and so did
his uncles, and would not refuse their offer, for he knew
not what need he should have after.
</p>

</div2>
</div1>
</body>
</text>
</TEI.2>
