<?xml version="1.0"?>

<?dlps id="FroGrou"?>
<?dlps page-images="none" figure-images="no"?>
<?dlps transcription="other"?>

<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/tei-p4/tei2.dtd" [
<!ENTITY % POSTKB "INCLUDE">
<!ENTITY % TEI.extensions.ent SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.ent">
<!ENTITY % TEI.extensions.dtd SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.dtd">
<!ENTITY % ISOnum SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/charent/iso-num.ent"> %ISOnum;
<!ENTITY % ISOpub SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/charent/iso-pub.ent"> %ISOpub;

]>
<TEI.2 id="FroGrou">
<teiHeader type="migrated" creator="Etext">
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title type="main">A Group of Poems</title>
<title type="sort">group of poems</title>
<author>Frost, Robert</author>
<respStmt>
<resp>Creation of machine-readable version:</resp>
<name>Judy Boss</name>
<resp>Creation of digital images:</resp>
<name/>
<resp>Conversion to TEI.2-conformant markup:</resp>
<name>University of Virginia Library Electronic Text Center.</name>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt>
<extent>ca. <num type="kilobytes">10</num> kilobytes</extent>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>University of Virginia Library</publisher>
<pubPlace>Charlottesville, Virginia</pubPlace>
<idno type="ETC">FroGrou</idno>
<date value="1997">1997</date>
<availability status="public">
<p n="copyright">Copyright &copy; 1997 by the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia</p>
<p n="access">Publicly accessible</p>
</availability>
<idno type="uva-pid">uva-lib:475970</idno>
</publicationStmt>
<seriesStmt>
<title>University of Virginia Library, Text collection</title>
<idno type="uva-set">UVA-LIB-Text</idno>
</seriesStmt>
<notesStmt>
<note>
<p>This electronic text includes four poems by Robert Frost that appeared in the January 1921 edition of The Yale Review. The poems are: "Snow Dust", "The Onset", "A Star in a Stone-Boat", and "Misgiving".</p>
</note>
</notesStmt>
<sourceDesc>
<biblFull>
<titleStmt>
<title type="main">A Group of Poems</title>
<title level="j">The Yale Review</title>
<title type="sort">group of poems</title>
<author>Robert Frost</author>
</titleStmt>
<editionStmt>
<p>1st Edition</p>
</editionStmt>
<extent>pp. 258 -261</extent>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>Yale Publishing Association, Inc.</publisher>
<pubPlace>New Haven, CT</pubPlace>
<date value="1921-01">January, 1921</date>
<idno type="callNo">Print copy consulted: UVa Library copy, AP2 .Y2</idno>
</publicationStmt>
</biblFull>
</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc>
<encodingDesc>
<projectDesc>
<p>Prepared for the University of Virginia Library Electronic Text Center.</p>
</projectDesc>
<editorialDecl>
<p>All quotation marks retained as data.</p>
<p>All unambiguous end-of-line hyphens have been removed, and the trailing part of a word has been joined to the preceding line.</p>
<p>The images exist as archived TIFF images, one or more JPEG versions for general use, and thumbnail GIFs.</p>
<p>Keywords in the header are a local Electronic Text Center scheme to aid in establishing analytical groupings.</p>
</editorialDecl>
</encodingDesc>
<profileDesc>
<creation>
<date value="1921-01">January, 1921</date>
</creation>
<langUsage>
<language id="eng" usage="main">English</language>
</langUsage>
<textClass>
<keywords>
<term>fiction; poetry</term>
</keywords>
</textClass>
</profileDesc>
<revisionDesc>
<change>
<date value="1997-06">June 1997</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>corrector</resp>
<name>Craig A. Simmons</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Added TEI header and tags. Checked and parsed SGML tagging.</item>
</change>
<change>
<date value="2005-07">July 2005</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>Corrector</resp>
<name>John Ivor Carlson</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Converted SGML to XML. Fixed tagging.</item>
</change>
<change>
<date value="2007-09">September 2007</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>Migration</resp>
<name>Ethan Gruber, University of Virginia Library</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Converted XML markup from TEI Lite to uva-dl-tei (TEI P4 with local customizations).</item>
</change>
<change>
<date value="2008-01">January 2008</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>Migration</resp>
<name>Greg Murray, University of Virginia Library</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Programmatically updated TEI header markup (but not header content) for minimal compliance with current QA requirements.</item>
</change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text id="d1">
<body id="d2">



<div1 type="poem" id="d3"><pb n="258"/>
<head>Snow Dust</head>

<lg type="stanza">
<l>The way a crow
</l><l rend="indent">Shook down on me
</l><l>The dust of snow
</l><l rend="indent">From a hemlock tree
</l></lg>

<lg type="stanza">
<l>Has given my heart
</l><l rend="indent">A change of mood
</l><l>And saved some part
</l><l rend="indent">Of a day I had rued.
</l></lg>

</div1>

<div1 type="poem" id="d4">
<head>The Onset</head>

<lg type="stanza">
<l>Always the same when on a fated night
</l><l>At last the gathered snow lets down as white
</l><l rend="indent">As maybe in dark woods and with a song
</l><l rend="indent">It shall not make again all winter long
</l><l>Of hissing on the yet uncovered ground,
</l><l>I almost stumble looking up and round,
</l><l rend="indent">As one who overtaken by the end
</l><l rend="indent">Gives up his errand and lets death descend
</l><l>Upon him where he is, with nothing done
</l><l>To evil, no important triumph won
</l><l>More than if life had never been begun.
</l></lg>

<lg type="stanza">
<l>Yet all the precedent is on my side:
</l><l>I know that winter death has never tried
</l><l rend="indent">The earth but it has failed: the snow may heap
</l><l rend="indent">In long storms an undrifted four feet deep
</l>


<pb n="259"/>


<l>As measured against maple, birch, and oak;
</l><l>It cannot check the Peeper's silver croak;
</l><l rend="indent">And I shall see the snow all go down hill
</l><l rend="indent">In water of a slender April rill
</l><l>That flashes tail through last year's withered brake
</l><l>And dead weeds like a disappearing snake.
</l><l rend="indent">Nothing will be left white but here a birch
</l><l rend="indent">And there a clump of houses with a church.
</l></lg>

</div1>

<div1 type="poem" id="d5">
<head>A Star in a Stone-Boat</head>

<lg type="stanza">
<l>Never tell me that not one star of all
</l><l>That slip from heaven at night and softly fall
</l><l>Has been picked up with stones to build a wall.
</l></lg>

<lg type="stanza">
<l>Some laborer found one faded and stone cold,
</l><l>And saving that its weight suggested gold,
</l><l>And tugged it from his first too certain hold,
</l></lg>

<lg type="stanza">
<l>He noticed nothing in it to remark.
</l><l>He was not used to handling stars thrown dark
</l><l>And lifeless from an interrupted arc.
</l></lg>

<lg type="stanza">
<l>He did not recognize in that smooth coal
</l><l>The one thing palpable besides the soul
</l><l>To penetrate the air in which we roll.
</l></lg>

<lg type="stanza">
<l>He did not see how like a flying thing
</l><l>It brooded ant-eggs, and had one large wing,
</l><l>One not so large for flying in a ring,
</l></lg>

<lg type="stanza">
<l>And a long Bird of Paradise's tail,
</l><l>(Though these when not in use to fly and trail
</l><l>It drew back in its body like a snail);
</l></lg>

<lg type="stanza">
<l>Nor know that he might move it from the spot&mdash;
</l><l>The harm was done: from having been star shot
</l><l>The very nature of the soil was hot
</l></lg>


<pb n="260"/>


<lg type="stanza">
<l>And burning to yield flowers instead of grain,
</l><l>Flowers fanned and not put out by all the rain
</l><l>Poured on them by his prayers prayed in vain.
</l></lg>

<lg type="stanza">
<l>He moved it roughly with an iron bar,
</l><l>He loaded an old stone-boat with the star
</l><l>And not, as you might think, a flying car,
</l></lg>

<lg type="stanza">
<l>Such as even poets would admit perforce
</l><l>More practical than Pegasus the horse
</l><l>If it could put a star back in its course.
</l></lg>

<lg type="stanza">
<l>He dragged it through the ploughed ground at a pace
</l><l>But faintly reminiscent of the race
</l><l>Of jostling rock in interstellar space.
</l></lg>

<lg type="stanza">
<l>It went for building-stone, and I as though
</l><l>Commanded in a dream forever go
</l><l>To right the wrong that this should have been so.
</l></lg>

<lg type="stanza">
<l>Yet ask where else it could have gone as well,
</l><l>I do not know&mdash;I cannot stop to tell:
</l><l>He might have left it lying where it fell.
</l></lg>

<lg type="stanza">
<l>From following walls I never lift my eye
</l><l>Except at night to places in the sky
</l><l>Where showers of charted meteors let fly.
</l></lg>

<lg type="stanza">
<l>Some may know what they seek in school and church,
</l><l>And why they seek it there; for what I search
</l><l>I must go measuring stone walls, perch on perch;
</l></lg>

<lg type="stanza">
<l>Sure that though not a star of death and birth,
</l><l>So not to be compared, perhaps, in worth
</l><l>To such resorts of life as Mars and Earth,&mdash;
</l></lg>



<pb n="261"/>


<lg type="stanza">
<l>Though not, I say, a star of death and sin,
</l><l>It yet has poles, and only needs a spin
</l><l>To show its worldly nature and begin
</l></lg>

<lg type="stanza">
<l>To chafe and shuffle in my calloused palm
</l><l>And run off in strange tangents with my arm
</l><l>As fish do with the line in first alarm.
</l></lg>

<lg type="stanza">
<l>Such as it is, it promises the prize
</l><l>Of the one world complete in any size
</l><l>That I am like to compass, fool or wise.
</l></lg>

</div1>

<div1 type="poem" id="d6">
<head>Misgiving</head>

<lg type="stanza">
<l>All crying, "We will go with you, O Wind,"
</l><l rend="indent">The foliage follow him, leaf and stem,
</l><l>But a sleep oppresses them as they go,
</l><l rend="indent">And they end by bidding him stay with them.
</l></lg>

<lg type="stanza">
<l>Since ever they flung abroad in spring,
</l><l rend="indent">The leaves have promised themselves this flight,
</l><l>Who now would fain seek sheltering wall,
</l><l rend="indent">Or thicket, or hollow place for the night.
</l></lg>

<lg type="stanza">
<l>And now they answer the summoning blast
</l><l rend="indent">With an ever vaguer and vaguer stir,
</l><l>Or, at utmost, a little reluctant whirl
</l><l rend="indent">That drops them no further than where they were.
</l></lg>

<lg type="stanza">
<l>I only hope that when I am free,
</l><l rend="indent">As they are free, to go in quest
</l><l>Of the knowledge beyond the bounds of life,
</l><l rend="indent">It may not seem better to <hi rend="italic">me</hi> to rest.
</l></lg>

</div1>



</body>
</text>
</TEI.2>

