<?xml version="1.0"?>

<?dlps id="FulWife"?>
<?dlps page-images="none" figure-images="no"?>
<?dlps transcription="other"?>

<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/tei-p4/tei2.dtd" [
<!ENTITY % POSTKB "INCLUDE">
<!ENTITY % TEI.extensions.ent SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.ent">
<!ENTITY % TEI.extensions.dtd SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.dtd">
<!ENTITY % ISOnum SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/charent/iso-num.ent"> %ISOnum;
<!ENTITY % ISOpub SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/charent/iso-pub.ent"> %ISOpub;

]>

<TEI.2 id="FulWife">
<teiHeader type="migrated" creator="Etext">
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title type="main">A Wife Manufactured to Order</title>
<title type="sort">wife manufactured to order</title>
<author>Fuller, Alice W.</author>
<respStmt>
<resp>Creation of machine-readable version:</resp>
<name>Judy Boss</name>
<resp>Conversion to TEI.2-conformant markup:</resp>
<name>University of Virginia Library Electronic Text Center</name>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt>
<extent>ca. <num type="kilobytes">21</num> kilobytes</extent>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>University of Virginia Library</publisher>
<pubPlace>Charlottesville, Virginia</pubPlace>
<idno type="ETC">FulWife</idno>
<date value="1995">1995</date>
<availability status="public">
<p n="copyright">Copyright &copy; 1995 by the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia</p>
<p n="access">Publicly accessible</p>
</availability>
<idno type="uva-pid">uva-lib:475971</idno>
</publicationStmt>
<seriesStmt>
<title>University of Virginia Library, Text collection</title>
<idno type="uva-set">UVA-LIB-Text</idno>
</seriesStmt>
<sourceDesc>
<biblFull>
<titleStmt>
<title type="main">A Wife Manufactured to Order</title>
<title type="sort">wife manufactured to order</title>
<author>Alice W. Fuller</author>
</titleStmt>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>The Arena</publisher>
<pubPlace>Boston</pubPlace>
<date value="1895-07">July 1895</date>
</publicationStmt>
<seriesStmt>
<p>13</p>
</seriesStmt>
<notesStmt>
<note>
<p>Fuller, Alice W.  "A Wife Manufactured to Order."
<hi rend="italic">The Arena</hi> 13 (July 1895): 305-312.</p>
</note>
</notesStmt>
</biblFull>
</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc>
<encodingDesc>
<projectDesc>
<p>Prepared for the University of Virginia Library Electronic Text Center</p>
</projectDesc>
<editorialDecl>
<p>All quotation marks retained as data</p>
<p>All unambiguous end-of-line hyphens have been removed, and the
trailing part of a word has been joined to the preceding line.</p>
<p id="ETC">Keywords in the header are a local Electronic Text Center scheme
to aid in establishing analytical groupings</p>
</editorialDecl>
<refsDecl>
<p>ID elements are given for each page element and are composed of the text's
unique cryptogram and the given page number, as in AusEmma1 for page one of
Jane Austen's Emma.</p>
</refsDecl>
</encodingDesc>
<profileDesc>
<creation>
<date value="1895-07">July 1895</date>
</creation>
<langUsage>
<language id="eng" usage="main">English</language>
</langUsage>
<textClass>
<keywords>
<term>fiction ; prose</term>
<term>Women Writers</term>
</keywords>
</textClass>
</profileDesc>
<revisionDesc>
<change>
<date value="1995-07">July 1995</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>corrector</resp>
<name>Jamie L Spriggs, Electronic Text Center, University of Virginia</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Added header; Tagged with TEI2-compatible SGML tagging; Parsed against
"teilite" dtd.</item>
</change>
<change>
<date value="2005-07">July 2005</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>Corrector</resp>
<name>John Ivor Carlson</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Converted SGML to XML. Fixed tagging.</item>
</change>
<change>
<date value="2007-09">September 2007</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>Migration</resp>
<name>Ethan Gruber, University of Virginia Library</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Converted XML markup from TEI Lite to uva-dl-tei (TEI P4 with local customizations).</item>
</change>
<change>
<date value="2008-01">January 2008</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>Migration</resp>
<name>Greg Murray, University of Virginia Library</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Programmatically updated TEI header markup (but not header content) for minimal compliance with current QA requirements.</item>
</change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text id="d1">




<body id="d2">
<div1 type="story" id="d3">
	<pb n="305"/>
	<head>A WIFE MANUFACTURED TO ORDER.<lb/>
		BY ALICE W. FULLER.</head>
<p>AS I was going down G Street in the city of W&mdash; a strange
sign attracted my attention.  I stopped, looked, fairly rubbed my
eyes to see if they were rightly focused; yes, there it was plainly
lettered in gilt: "Wives made to order!  Satisfaction guaranteed or
money refunded."
</p><p>Well! well! does some lunatic live here, I wonder?  By Jove!
I will investigate.  I had inherited (I suppose from my mother) a
bit of curiosity, and the truth of the matter was this: now nearing
the age of forty, I thought it might be advisable to settle down in
a home of my own; but alas! to settle down to a life of strife and
turmoil, that would not be pleasant; and that I should have to do,
I knew very well, if I should marry any of my numerous lady
acquaintances&mdash;especially Florence Ward, the one I most admired.
She unfortunately had strong-minded ways, and inclinations to be
investigating woman's rights, politics, theosophy, and all that
sort of thing.  Bah!  I could never endure it.  I should be
miserable, and the outcome would be a separation; I knew it.  To be
dictated to, perhaps found fault with&mdash;no, no, it would never do;
better be a bachelor and at least live in peace.  But&mdash;what does
this sign mean?  I'll find out for myself.
</p><p>A ring of the bell brought a little white-haired, wiry sort of
a man to the door.  "Walk in, walk in, sir," he said.
</p><p>I asked for an explanation of the strange sign over the door.
</p><p>"Just step right in here and be seated, sir.  My master is
engaged at present, sir, with a great politician who had to
separate from his wife; was so fractious, sir, got so many strange
notions in her head; in fact, she wanted to hold the reins herself.
You may have seen it&mdash;the papers have been full of it.  Why, law
bless you, sir, the poor man couldn't say his soul was his own, and
he is here now making arrangements with master to make him a
quieter sort of <pb n="306"/>  wife, some one to do the honors of the home
without feelin' neglected if he happens to be a little courteous to
some of his young lady friends.  You see, master makes 'em to
order, makes 'em to think just as you do, just as you want 'em to;
then you've got a happy home, something to live for.  Beautiful&mdash;
golly!  I've seen some of the beautifulest women turned out, 'most
make your mouth water to look at."  And so the old man rattled on
until I was quite bewildered.
</p><p>I interrupted him by asking if I could see his master.
</p><p>"Oh, certainly, sir; you just make yourself comfortable and I
will let you know when he is through."
</p><p>I sat for some time like one in a dream, wondering if this
could be so, and with many wonderful modern inventions in mind I
began to think it possible.  And then there was a vision of a happy
home, a wife beautiful as a dream, gentle and loving, without a
thought for anyone but me; one who would never reproach me if I
didn't happen to get home just at what she thought was the proper
time; one who would not ask me to go to church when she knew it was
against my wishes; one who would never find fault with me if I
wished to go to a base-ball game on Sunday, or bother me to take
her to the theatre or opera.  A man, you know, can't give much time
to such things without interfering greatly with his comfort.  Oh!
could all this be realized?  But just then my reverie was broken by
the old man, who was saying: "Just step this way.  Master, let me
introduce you to Mr. Charles Fitzsimmons."
</p><p>Short, thick-set, florid complexion, pale blue eyes with a
sinister twinkle, was the description of Mr. Sharper, whom I
confronted.  Reaching out his hand, which was cold and clammy and
reminded me very much of a piece of cold boiled pork, he said:
</p><p>"Now, young man, what can I do for you?  Want a life-companion, a pleasant one?  Man of means, no doubt, and can enjoy
yourself; a little fun now and then with the boys and no harm at
all&mdash;none in the least.  When a man comes home tired, doesn't like
to be dictated to; want some one always to meet you with a smile,
some one that doesn't expect you to be fondlin' and pettin' 'em all
the time.  I understand it&mdash;I know just how it is.  Law bless my
soul, I'e made more'n one man happy, and I've only been in the
business a short time, too.  Now, sir, I can get you up any style
you want&mdash;<hi rend="italic">wax</hi>, but can't be detected."
</p><p>"Do you mean to say you manufacture a woman out of wax, who
will talk?"
</p><p>"That's just what I do; you give me the subjects you <pb n="307"/>
most enjoy talking upon, and tell me what kind of a looking wife
you want, and leave the rest to me, and you will never regret it.
I will furnish as many 'phones' as you wish; most men don't care
for such a variety for a wife&mdash;too much talk, you know;" and he
chuckled and laughed like a big baby.
</p><p>"What are your prices, may I ask?"
</p><p>"Well, it's owing a good deal to how they are got up&mdash;from
five hundred to a thousand dollars."
</p><p>"Well," I said, "I think that rather high."
</p><p>"Dear man alive, a pleasant companion for life for a few
hundred dollars!  Most men don't grumble at all for the sake of
having their own way and a pleasant home, and you see she ain't
always asking for money."  (Sure enough, I hadn't thought of that.)
</p><p>"Very well, I will decide upon the matter and let you know."
</p><p>"All right, young man; you'll come back.  They all do, them as
knows about it."
</p><p>I went to my room at the hotel and thought it all out, thought
of the pleasant evenings I could have with some one whose thoughts
were like my own, some one who would not vex me by differing in
opinion.  I wondered what Florence would say.  I really believed
she cared for me, but she knew how I disliked so many of the topics
she persisted in talking upon.  What mattered it to me what Emerson
said, or Edward Bellamy wrote, or Henry George, or Pentecost? what
did I care about Hume or Huxley or Stuart Mill? any of those
sciences, Christian Science or Divine Science or mind cure?&mdash;bah!
it was all nonsense.  The topics of the day were enough, and if I
attended closely to my business I needed recreation, not such
things as she would prescribe.  Still Florence was interesting to
talk to, and I rather liked her at times when she talked every-day
talk; but I could not marry her, and it was her own fault.  She
knew my sentiments, and if she would persist in going on as she did
I couldn't help it.
</p><p>Yes, I decided I would have a home of my own, and a wife made
to order at once.  Before leaving the city I made all necessary
arrangements, hurried home, rented a house, and went to see old
susan Tyler, whom I engaged as housekeeper; she was deaf and had an
impediment in her speech, but she was a fine housekeeper.  All my
preparations made, the ideal home!  Oh! how my heart beat as I
looked around!&mdash;what happiness to do as I liked, a beautiful,
uncomplaining wife ready to grant every wish and meet me with a
<pb n="308"/>
smile!  What would the boys say when, out a little late at
night, I should be so perfectly at ease?  I could just see jealousy
on their faces, and I laughed outright for joy.  To-morrow I was
going for my bride.  Side-looks and innuendos were thrust at me
from all quarters, but I was too happy to demur or explain.  When
I reached the city I could scarcely wait for the appointed time.
</p><p>Alighting from the carriage the door was opened, and I was
ushered into the presence of the most beautiful creature I had ever
beheld.  The hands extended towards mine, the lips opened, and a
low, sweet voice said, "Dear Charles, how glad I am you have come!"
I stood spellbound, and only a chuckle from Mr. Sharper brought me
to my senses.
</p><p>"Kiss your affianced, why don't you?" he said, and chuckled
again.
</p><p>I felt as though I wanted to knock him down for speaking so in
that beautiful creature's presence.  And then a little soft
rippling laugh, and she moved towards me.  Oh, could I get that
beast to leave the room!  Why did he stand there chuckling in that
manner?
</p><p>"Sir," I said, "you will oblige me by leaving the room for a
few moments."
</p><p>With that he chuckled still louder and muttered, "Bless me, I
really believe he thinks her alive."  Then to me: "To be sure, to
be sure, but you only have a short time before going to the
minister's, and I must show you how to adjust her.  When you get
home"&mdash;and he chuckled again&mdash;"you can be just as sentimental as
you please, but just now we will attend to business.  Here are a
box of tubes made to talk as you wished them.  They are adjusted
so.  Place the one you wish in your sleeve.  You can carelessly
touch her right here if there is any one around.  Here is a spring
in each hand and the tips of her fingers.  I will give you a book
of instructions, and you will soon learn to arrange her with very
little effort, just to suit yourself, and I am sure you will be
very happy.  Now, sir, the time is up; you can go to the
minister's."
</p><p>As I put her wraps around her and drew her arm through mine
she murmured so sweetly, "Thank you, dear."  How glad I was to get
out of the presence of that vile man who was constantly pulling or
pushing her; I could scarcely keep my hands off from him, and my
serene Margurette&mdash;for I decided to call her that&mdash;would only smile
and say, "Thank you!"  "Oh, how lovely!"  "Ah, indeed!"  I was
almost vexed with her to think she did not resent it.  I wanted her
all to myself where I could have the smiles, and <pb n="309"/>  thought I
should be thankful when we were in our own home.
</p><p>During our journey I could not help noticing the admiring
glances from my fellow travellers, but my beautiful wife did not
return any of their looks.  In fact, I overheard a couple of young
dudes say, "Just wait till that old codger's back is turned, and we
shall see whether she will have no smiles for any but him."  I had
half a notion to adjust her to give them some cutting reply and
then go into the smoker awhile, for I was sure they would try to
get into conversation with her; but pshaw!  I hadn't ordered any
tubes of that kind.  I believed I'd send and get one in case of an
emergency.  No, I wouldn't have such in the house; I wanted an
amiable wife, and when we were once at home it would not be
necessary.  I wouldn't <hi rend="italic">have</hi> to go with her anywhere unless
I wanted to.  Only think of that!&mdash;never feel that my wife would
ask me to go with her and I have to refuse, then ten to one have
her cry and make a fuss about it.  I knew how it was, for I had
seen too much of that sort of thing in the homes of my friends.
</p><p>Business ran smoothly; everything was perfect harmony; my home
was heaven on earth.  I smoked when I wished to, I went to my base-ball games, I stayed out as long as I pleased, played cards when I
wished, drank champagne or whatever I fancied, in fact had as good
a time as I did before marriage.  My male friends congratulated me
upon my good fortune, and I was considered the luckiest man
anywhere around.  No one knew how I had made the good luck for
myself.
</p><p>There are some things in life I could never understand.  One
of them is that, when everything seems so prosperous, calamity is
so often in the wake.  And that was the case with me.  After so
many prosperous years a financial crash came.  I tried to ward it
off; I was up early and late.  Margurette never complained, but was
always sweet and smiling, with the same endearing words.  Sometimes
as the years went by I felt as though I would not object to her
differing with me a little, for variety's sake; still it was best.
"When I would say, "Margurette, do you really think so?" and I
would speak so cross to her often&mdash;I don't know but that I did so
more than was necessary; still a man must have some place where he
can be himself, and if he can't have that privilege at home, what's
the use of having a home?&mdash;but she was never out of patience, and
my wife would only say, "Yes, darling," so low and sweet.  I
remember once I said, when I was worried more than usual, "I am
damned <pb n="310"/>  tired of this sort of thing," and she laughed so
sweetly and called me her "own precious boy."
</p><p>But the crash came, and there was no use trying to stay it any
longer.  I came home sick and tired.  It was nine o'clock at night,
with a cold, drizzling rain falling.  Susan had gone to bed sick,
and forgotten to light a fire in the grate.  I went into the
library, where Margurette always waited for me.  No lights; I
stumbled over a chair.  I accidentally touched Margurette.  She put
up her lips to kiss me and laughingly said, "Precious darling,
tired to-night?"  Great God!  I came very near striking her.
</p><p>"Margurette, don't call me darling, talk to me; talk to me
about something&mdash;anything sensible.  Don't you know I am a ruined
man?  Everything I have got has been swept away from me."
</p><p>"There, precious, I love you;" and she laughed again.
</p><p>"Did you not hear what I said?" I screamed.
</p><p>But she only laughed the more and said, "Oh, how lovely!"
</p><p>I rushed from the house.  I could not endure it longer; I was
like one mad.  My first thought was, Where can I go, to whom can I
go for sympathy?  I cannot stand this strain much longer, and to
show weakness to men, I could never do that.  I will go to
Florence, I said.  I will see what she says.  Strange I should
think of her just then!
</p><p>I asked the servant who admitted me for Miss Florence.
</p><p>"She is indisposed and cannot see anyone to-night."
</p><p>"But," I said, writing on a card hastily, "take this to her."
</p><p>Only a few moments elapsed and she came in, holding out her
hand in an assuring and friendly way.  "I am surprised to see you
to-night, Mr. Fitzsimmons."
</p><p>"O Florence!" I cried, "I am in trouble.  I believe I shall
lose my mind if I cannot have someone to go to; and you, dear
Florence, you will know my needs; you can counsel, you can
understand me."
</p><p>"Sir!" Florence said, "are you mad, that you come here to
insult me?"
</p><p>"But I love you.  I know it.  I love the traits that I once
thought I despised."
</p><p>"Stop where you are!  I did not receive you to hear such
language.  You forget yourself and me; you forget that you are a
married man&mdash;shame upon you for humiliating me so!"
</p><p>"Florence, Florence, I am not married; it is all a lie, a
deception."
</p><p>"Have you lost your reason, Mr. Fitzsimmons?  Sit down, pray,
and let me call my father.  You are ill." <pb n="311"/>
</p><p>"Stop," I cried, "I do not need your father.  I need you.
Listen to me.  I imagined I could never be happy with a wife who
differed in opinion from me.  In fact, I had almost decided to
remain single all the rest of my days, until I came across a man
who manufactured wives to order.  Wait, Florence, until I have
finished&mdash;do not look at me so.  I am indeed sane.  My wife was
manufactured to my own ideas, a perfect human being as I supposed."
</p><p>Mr. Fitzsimmons, let me call my father."  And Florence started
towards the door.  She was so pale that she frightened me, but I
clutched her frantically.
</p><p>"Listen," I said; "will you go with me?  I will prove that all
I have told you is true."
</p><p>My earnestness seemed to reassure her.  She stopped as if
carefully thinking, then asked me to repeat what I had already told
her.  Finally she said yes, she would go.
</p><p>We were soon in the presence of my beautiful Margurette, whom
I literally hated&mdash;I could not endure her face.  "Now, Florence,
see," I cried; and I had my wife talk the namby-pamby lingo I once
thought so sweet.  "Oh! how I hate her!" and I glared at her like
a madman.  "Florence, save me.  I am a ruined man.  Everything has
been swept away&mdash;the last to-day.  I am a pauper, an egotist, a
bigot, a selfish"&mdash;
</p><p>"Stop!" cried Florence.  "You wrong yourself; you are a man in
your prime.  What if your money has gone, you have your health and
your faculties, I guess" (and there was a merry twinkle in her
eyes); "the whole world is before you, and best of all, no one to
interfere with you or argue on disagreeable topics."
</p><p>"O Florence!  I am punished enough for my selfishness.  O
God!" and I threw myself on the couch, "were I not a pauper, too,
there might be some hope for happiness yet."
</p><p>"You are not a pauper," said Florence; "you are the master of
your fate, and if you are not happy it is your own fault."
</p><p>"Florence, I can never be happy without you.  I know now it is
too late."
</p><p>"Too late&mdash;never say that.  But could you be happy with me, 'a
woman wedded to an idea,' 'strongminded'?  Why, Charles, I am
liable to investigate all sorts of scientific subjects and reforms.
And then supposing I should talk about it sometimes; if it was not
for that I might think of the matter.  As far as money is
concerned, that would have little to do with my actions.  Still,
Charles, upon the whole I should be afraid to marry the 'divorced'
husband of so <pb n="312"/>  amiable a wife as your present one is.  I,
with my faults and imperfections!&mdash;the contrast would be too
great."
</p><p>"Florence, Florence," I said, "say no more.  All I ask is, can
you overlook my folly and take me for better, for worse?  I have
learned my lesson.  I see now it is only a petty and narrow type of
man who would wish to live only with his own personal echo.  I want
a woman, one who retains her individuality, a thinking woman.  Will
you be mine?"
</p><p>"I will consider the matter favorably," said Florence; "but we
shall have to wait a year, for opinion's sake, as I suppose there
are not many who know how you had your late wife manufactured to
order."
</p><p>And we both laughed.
</p>

</div1>
</body>
</text>
</TEI.2>
