<?xml version="1.0"?>

<?dlps id="FurCour"?>
<?dlps page-images="none" figure-images="no"?>
<?dlps transcription="other"?>

<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/tei-p4/tei2.dtd" [
<!ENTITY % POSTKB "INCLUDE">
<!ENTITY % TEI.extensions.ent SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.ent">
<!ENTITY % TEI.extensions.dtd SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.dtd">
<!ENTITY % ISOnum SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/charent/iso-num.ent"> %ISOnum;
<!ENTITY % ISOpub SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/charent/iso-pub.ent"> %ISOpub;

]>
<TEI.2 id="FurCour">
<teiHeader type="migrated" creator="Etext">
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title type="main">The Course of True Love: Kentucky Mountain Sketch</title>
<title type="sort">course of true love kentucky mountain sketch</title>
<author>Furman, Lucy S.</author>
<respStmt>
<resp>Creation of machine-readable version:</resp>
<name>Judy Boss</name>
<resp>Conversion to TEI.2-conformant markup:</resp>
<name>University of Virginia Library Electronic Text Center.</name>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt>
<extent>ca. <num type="kilobytes">34</num> kilobytes</extent>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>University of Virginia Library</publisher>
<pubPlace>Charlottesville, Virginia</pubPlace>
<idno type="ETC">FurCour</idno>
<date value="2000">2000</date>
<availability status="public">
<p n="copyright">Copyright &copy; 2000 by the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia</p>
<p n="access">Publicly accessible</p>
</availability>
<idno type="uva-pid">uva-lib:475972</idno>
</publicationStmt>
<seriesStmt>
<title>University of Virginia Library, Text collection</title>
<idno type="uva-set">UVA-LIB-Text</idno>
</seriesStmt>
<sourceDesc>
<biblFull>
<titleStmt>
<title type="main">The Course of True Love: Kentucky Mountain Sketch</title>
<title level="j">The Century Magazine</title>
<title type="sort">course of true love kentucky mountain sketch</title>
<author>Lucy Furman</author>
</titleStmt>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>The Century Co.</publisher>
<pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
<date value="1912-08">August 1912</date>
<idno type="callNo">Source copy consulted: AP2.C4</idno>
</publicationStmt>
</biblFull>
</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc>
<encodingDesc>
<projectDesc>
<p>Prepared for the University of Virginia Library Electronic Text Center.</p>
</projectDesc>
<editorialDecl>
<p>All unambiguous end-of-line hyphens have been removed, and the  trailing part of a word has been joined to the preceding line.</p>
<p id="ETC">Some keywords in the header are a local Electronic Text Center scheme  to aid in establishing analytical groupings.</p>
</editorialDecl>
</encodingDesc>
<profileDesc>
<creation>
<date value="1912">1912</date>
</creation>
<langUsage>
<language id="eng" usage="main">English</language>
</langUsage>
<textClass>
<keywords>
<term>fiction</term>
<term>prose</term>
<term>feminine</term>
<term>Women Writers</term>
</keywords>
</textClass>
</profileDesc>
<revisionDesc>
<change>
<date value="2001-04">April 2001</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>corrector</resp>
<name>Karen Wikander</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Added TEI header and tags.</item>
</change>
<change>
<date value="2005-07">July 2005</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>Corrector</resp>
<name>John Ivor Carlson</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Converted SGML to XML. Fixed tagging.</item>
</change>
<change>
<date value="2007-09">September 2007</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>Migration</resp>
<name>Ethan Gruber, University of Virginia Library</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Converted XML markup from TEI Lite to uva-dl-tei (TEI P4 with local customizations).</item>
</change>
<change>
<date value="2008-01">January 2008</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>Migration</resp>
<name>Greg Murray, University of Virginia Library</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Programmatically updated TEI header markup (but not header content) for minimal compliance with current QA requirements.</item>
</change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text id="d1">
<body id="d2">

<div1 type="story" id="d3"><pb n="498"/>
<head>THE COURSE OF TRUE LOVE<lb/>
KENTUCKY MOUNTAIN SKETCH</head>

<byline><docAuthor>BY LUCY FURMAN</docAuthor>
Author of "Mothering on Perilous," etc.</byline>

<p>THE story of the falling in love of Philip Floyd at the
Settlement School on Perilous Creek soon after his thirteenth birthday,
and of the transforming effects of the tender passion upon his person
and character, has already been related.<ref target="n1">[1]</ref>
Under the exacting requirements of little Dilsey Warrick, his
earwashings, head-combings, tooth-brushings, and clothes-mendings, not
to speak of his violent attacks of manners and generosity, were such as
to make Miss Loring wish that each and every one of her twelve boys
might quickly experience a like metamorphosis.

</p><p>When the school-term closed in early May and the boys and girls
went home to hoe corn for three months, Philip, who was to remain in the
school to work during the summer, asked for a week's holiday, that he
might go and visit Nucky Marrs. Nucky lived on Trigger Branch of
Powderhorn, and Dilsey on Powderhorn itself, not four miles distant. As
the group of children from that neighborhood set off from the school on
their twentyodd-mile walk, Philip, with the light of bliss in his dark
eyes, strode manfully along at the head of the other boys, while on the
far side of the road Dilsey, accompanied by Rosabel and Narcissa, walked
along with her usual dignity and propriety. Philip would not have
dreamed of such a liberty as walking beside her; but he could at least
hear her voice, see the golden braids that swung below her sunbonnet,
and, when she turned her head far enough, catch a glimpse of the austere
blue eyes that were his heaven.

</p><p>That matters progressed favorably with him during the summer was
evident from his letters to Miss Loring: "Dear Freind:  I am well
hopeing these few lines will find you the Same I payed a visit to Dilsey
whilst I was over on Trigger and holp her and her famaly ho corn three
days her pa says I am rite smart of a good worker gee he aught to see me
Carpenter annyboddy can ho corn. Your Truly Friend Philip Floyd." "Dear
Frend: this leaves me injoying health I hope it finds you the same it is
loansome here at the school with Dilsey and you gone I wisht it was next
school I bought her a fine brest Pin off Geordie Yonts we are working on
the new hospittal I make sixty cents a day it would very near support a
famaly. Yours Respectably Philip Floyd." "Dear Freiend:  I now rite you
these few lines to inform you I am Well and hope you are the Same I
would of rote before but it keeps me Buizzey riting to Dilsey what spair
time I got I bought her a Silk Hankerchef with Blossoms all imbroyded in
the corner off G. Yonts theres few girls gets the money spent on them
she does. Your Best Frieind Philip Floyd."

</p><p>When school reopened in August, it was the general expectation
that the love, or, rather, the privilege of loving, so expensively
purchased by Philip, would continue his. But, alas! for the instability
of the feminine heart!  Within a week there was a deep line between
Philip's brows and a return to some of his original bruskness of speech
and manner. These were accounted for one morning when Hen Salyer,
resting on his shovel from his labors of cleaning the stable, held forth
to Miss Loring as follows:

</p><p>"You ricollect me a-telling you last spring about 'Lige Munn
a-passing on his


<pb n="499"/>

paw's nag one day whilst Philip and Dilsey was talking on the front
porch, and taking off his hat so polite to Dilse, and her a-telling
Philip she <hi rend="italic">liked</hi> manners?  Well, Philip he turnt in and scratched
him up enough manners after that to satisfy ten women; but some females
hain't never suited, dag gone 'em, and when 'Lige started in a-bowing
and a-scraping to Dilse the first day of this new school, what did Dilse
do but bow and scrape back at him as bigoty as ever you seed. Then 'Lige
he ups and brings her a fine apple next day, and five sticks of
peppermint the next, and a poke of liquorice-draps the next. And if that
'ere girl didn't take and eat 'em right spang under Philip's eyes, with
four or five presents from him there in her desk, too!  I wished I may
never see the beat!  And a girl of her raising, too!  But th' ain't no
depending on females." Here Hen shook his head and pondered awhile
before resuming: "Of course 'Lige being fifteen and a head taller and a
town boy, and his paw keeping store, all goes ag'in' Philip. Women they
like size and style and presents, the scurvy little jades!"

</p><p>"But Dilsey isn't that kind at all," said Miss Loring. "She is an
unusually nice and sensible little girl."

</p><p>"She were <hi rend="italic">last</hi> year," admitted Hen; "but that hain't
<hi rend="italic">this</hi>. You got a heap to learn about women if you think you can
tell one year what they liable to do the next. That 'ere Dilse is next
to the prettiest girl in school this year,&mdash;th' ain't nobody can outlook
her but Poppet,&mdash;and lemme tell you this: not one in a hunderd of 'em is
able to stand it; they git their heads turnt every time." Hen spoke from
the accumulated wisdom of his ten years, as well as from special recent
experience.  During the previous term he had been the youngest of Poppet
Beverley's admirers (they ranged all the way from twentynine to ten) and
an observant student of her methods. Neither his knowledge of these,
however, nor his three-months' absence from her had had power to lessen
his loyalty, and on the evening of his return to the school he had sat
at the supper-table with food untouched for at least five minutes,
feasting his eyes on Poppet across the room, before exclaiming, with
unquenchable gallantry, "Dag gone!  I could butt stumps for that woman!"

</p><p>Miss Loring hoped that Hen's acute mind had drawn mistaken
conclusions in regard to Dilsey; but signs of their correctness
multiplied. There was first a vivid outbreak of neckties on Philip-pink,
yellow, green, heliotrope, a fresh kind each day. But, as Hen said,
'Lige, having his paw's whole store behind him, could outdo Philip in
that. Then, on Sunday, Miss Loring was pained and shocked to see Philip
walk into church late, in a hideous "store suit," with an ill-shaped,
wrinkly coat and baggy, long trousers, in which he looked like a
shriveled little old man, instead of the beautiful boy he was in the
belted coat and knickerbockers he usually wore on Sundays. Miss Loring
also saw Dilsey's fastidious eyes shrink from him and turn with relief
to 'Lige's slender, well-fitted figure.

</p><p>"Where did you get that dreadful suit?" Miss Loring inquired
later

</p><p>"Off of Geordie. It's a brand-new one he bought in Virginia this
summer."

</p><p>"What did he charge you for it?"

</p><p>"Four dollars and forty-five cents."

</p><p>"That suit," said Miss Loring, "was probably bought by Geordie at
secondhand for not more than a dollar. And now you have let him palm it
off on you, though you know him as well as I do.  Oh, if you could only
see yourself in it!"

</p><p>Philip burst out savagely: "Yes, you and Dilsey and 'Lige and all
of you think I hain't enough of a man to wear long breeches, just like
Geordie said. But I'll show you. I'm more of a man than 'Lige Munn ever
was or ever will be, and he'll live to feel it. And don't you think you
can ever get me back into short pants no more; I'd ruther be dead."

</p><p>In the matter of clothes 'Lige had indeed a cruel advantage, and
not on Sundays only, for all the week he could and now did wear his
Sunday suit and pointed shoes to school, while Philip raged in the
regulation gingham shirt and overalls of the cottage boys. And clothes
were by no means the worst. A few months before, 'Lige had visited
Frankfort with his father, who was a member of the legislature, and had
not only "rid on the railroad, bought store clothes, and seed the
world," but during his stay had also acquired all the polish and graces
of a finished society man. Where is the woman or girl who is not dazzled
by these, and

<pb n="500"/>

made blind to more serious faults than 'Lige's laziness and lack of
ambition?

</p><p>Not that Dilsey gave anybody active encouragement, her role being
to tolerate and accept, never under any circumstances to give. She
simply permitted herself to be the shrine before which gifts and
accomplishments might be offered up, and seemed entirely willing to have
two devotees. "She aims to keep 'em both," reported Hen, a few days
later. "She had on two breastpins a-Monday, one of Philip's and one of
'Lige's; and at recess Philip he snatched 'Lige's off of her, and
throwed it on the ground, and told her not to think ary girl of his
could ever wear other boys' jewelries. And she stiffed up the grandest
and chilliest ever you beheld, and told him how did he <hi rend="italic">dare</hi> to
claim the likes of her, and lay down the law on her! That she give him
to understand she never took orders from <hi rend="italic">nobody</hi>, and would be
friendly with <hi rend="italic">ten</hi> boys if she wanted. Now, did you ever hear such
talk from a rightraised female? Gee! I don't know what the women are
coming to. Then she picked up 'Lige's pin and fastened it on ag'in. I
tell you that 'ere girl is a-treading dangerous paths, and if she don't
look out, there'll be war in these parts, sure as you set on that bench.
If I was Philip, I don't know as I'd go to the trouble, though. I'd git
the old charm-doctor over on Clinch to lay a charm on 'Lige; that would
fix him the easiest.  Th' ain't nothing he can't charm away.  When Keats
had the quinsy, he took 'n' stood him up ag'in' a tree, and cut a hole
in it right over his head, and plugged a lock of his hair up in it, and
said when he growed up to that plug he'd be shet of the quinsy. And dag
gone if he wasn't!  And when Monroe Teed took Dave Antigo's girl away
from him, the charm-doctor he tied two leetle bitty sticks crossways
with a horsehair, and told Dave to burn 'em in a burying-ground at
midnight, and scatter the ashes on Monroe, unbeknownst, and, by Heck! if
Monroe didn't git throwed from his nag at election-time, and broke up so
bad he couldn't go courting all winter, and by spring Dave had her
married. I could tell you a dozen: all the young folks gits charms from
him. But Philip says he'd ruther charm 'Lige hisself."

</p><p>The following week a strange, unwonted calm descended upon the
cottage.  During playtime Miss Loring would find the boys skulking about
in whispering groups behind stable and corn-crib, or in fence corners;
and although at her approach they would pick up bats or shinnysticks,
their efforts at play were evidently efforts.

</p><p>Then one day at afternoon recess, when the pupils streamed from
the school-house into the yard, out of a clear sky Philip sprang upon
'Lige Munn and felled him to the ground. 'Lige quickly regained his
feet, and a battle began. The girls drew back and grouped themselves on
the steps, Dilsey in the front row, while the boys, large and small,
formed a thick ring about the fighters. They seemed well-matched,
'Lige's superior length being offset by Philip's solidity, skill, and
fury. Interest was intense. Finally 'Lige wearied and wavered, and in a
flash Philip had him face down on the ground, and sat upon him with a
triumphant yell. During the combat a close observer might have noticed
that the cottage boys had worked their way through the ring to the inner
circle, of which they now formed a solid half, while the other half was
composed of a number of Munns, Drakes, and Somerses, brothers and
cousins of 'Lige. At the instant of the triumphant yell from Philip, a
dozen of the latter charged in upon him, to be met more than half-way,
however, by an impregnable wall of cottage boys: Taulbee and Absalom,
dogged and fierce; Joab, quick and keen; Nucky and Killis, renowned,
invincible heroes; the two Salyers, worthy sons of a fighting race;
Hosea and Iry, gentle in peace, but terrible in war; Jason Wyatt, the
youngest, but possibly the "fightingest," of all, Geordie Yonts alone
being conspicuous by his absence. Over the humbled 'Lige the battle
raged. The Munn side had the greater numbers, but the Floyd side the
greater fighters. Now, indeed, the interest was breathless. When the
bell rang for close of recess, not a boy or girl entered the
school-house. When the teachers came forth to see what was the matter,
they, too, stood rooted to the spot. The combatants met, grappled,
fought tooth and nail. Blood flowed freely. Philip, Nucky, and Killis
were glorious in battle; joyously they met the foe and flung aside the
disabled. Little Jason Wyatt had several

<pb n="501"/>

small victims in a pile at his side.  The cottage boys were covering
themselves with glory and the enemy with blood.  Miss Holmes, the
principal, ordered the grown-up boys to stop the fight. They did not
(possibly could not) budge. The situation was becoming serious when Miss
Loring saw Darcy Peel, the young deputy sheriff, come riding down the
road, and called frantically to him. Lightly taking the fence with his
nag, he dashed into the fray, carelessly waving a revolver. The boys
scattered like chaff before him and would have vanished, but he called
them to a halt and gave them a severe talk on the heinousness of
disturbing "the women's" peace. At first he threatened to take them all
to jail, but, later, relented, and released them on their word of honor
to fight no more in the school-grounds. Then gracefully waving them into
the school-house with the careless revolver, he went on his way.

</p><p>From Hen that night, after the others were in bed, Miss Loring
had fuller light on the subject of the fight. "Gee-oh!  hain't this here
Floyd-Munn war aiming to be a sizable one!" he exclaimed delightedly,
slipping into her room, and closing the door carefully behind him. "Did
you ever see the equal of the fighting us Floyds done to-day? By Ned!
own brothers hain't nothing to blood-brothers!"

</p><p>"What do you mean?" inquired Miss Loring.

</p><p>"Well, you see Philip he aimed to whoop-out 'Lige, and knowed he
could do it easy enough, only then he'd have all the Munns and Drakes
and Somerses down on him in a twinkle, and maybe git kilt, 'Lige having
so many kin, and him none in these parts. So he said them that broke
bread and et salt together all the time ought to act the same as
blood-kin, and if us cottage boys would stand by him, he knowed he could
wipe out the whole Munn biling, and make Dilsey Warrick ashamed she ever
bit into a Munn apple. And we told him we were his men, by grab! and
then he took us out under the corn-crib, and cut his arm with his
knife-p'int, and bled hisself into a bottle, and then he passed the
knife and the bottle around. When it come to Geordie, he drawed back,
the little runagate, and said he weren't able to stand the sight of
blood. Philip said all right; we'd tie a meal-poke over his head and do
it for him. So we done it, and he hollered so we very near had to choke
him to death. And then Philip said we was all blood-brothers now, and
corked the bottle, and before he buried it, made us all swear on it to
stand by him, thick or thin, blood or water, up or down, going or
coming. Then he ricollected about Geordie having gone pardners with
'Lige on keeps all last spring, and he said any turncoat, straddle-pole,
or tattle-tale was to git strung up on a meat-hook. And Geordie he give
him his hand over and over to stand by him and tell no tales (of course
he aims to keep in with Philip long as he can sell him anything), and
Philip he believed him, which is more'n I'd 'a' done, not on a stack of
Bibles tall as that sycamore. And, sure enough, when Geordie heared the
fight was a-coming off to-day, he took a bad belly-ache and went to the
hospital; and I hope by now he's sick as a dog and all tied up in knots
from that 'ere physic Miss Shippen allus gives us.  And I'll bound you
that misbegotten little jackanapes don't strike nary lick through this
whole war; and, what's more, I'll wager he give 'Lige some inkling what
was a-coming to-day, or there'd 'a' never been so many Munns and Drakes
and Somerses in school at one time. We'd 'a' kilt the last one if you
hadn't 'a' called Darcy in when you did. Philip says he'll remember that
ag'in' you to your dying day."

</p><p>For the next day or two the cottage boys went about swelling
visibly in more senses than one, the lectures and punishments they
received failing to cast the slightest shadow upon their radiant
satisfaction.  But when Philip, with the perfect confidence of the
conquering male in having the females flock to his standard, laid a fine
pawpaw on the table where Dilsey was washing dishes, she promptly flung
it out of the window, with the scornful and enigmatical remark, "Some
folkses are smarter than they're wise."

</p><p>The forces set in motion could not have been stayed, however, had
she capitulated then and there. The following Sunday, as the cottage
boys, accompanied by Miss Loring, were on their way to church in the
village, they were "laywayed" by a large Munn contingent as they rounded
the post-office corner, and there, in full view of the church and
congregation, another terrible battle raged until the deacons and

<pb n="502"/>

pillars sallied forth and, with much difficulty and some damage, broke it up.

</p><p>This time, too, Geordie Yonts was not present, but was loudly
singing hymns in the church. He had had an engagement to help sweep out
the "church-house," and had been permitted to go down an hour early.
This spasm of industry appeared somewhat strange at the time, and on
fuller consideration Miss Loring was half inclined to agree with Hen's
conclusion:  "That 'ere mischievious little devil is a-standing in with
them Munns, and holp 'em plan to layway us, I'll bet my next winter's
shoes. But of course nobody can't prove it on him. By Ned!" he added,
"if it hadn't 'a' been church-time, and all them men gathered, we'd 'a'
laid the Munns out of all remembrance! We had 'em very near finished,
and there was six or seven extrys among 'em, too."

</p><p>"It seemed to me just the other way-that you Floyds were getting
decidedly the worst of it, and should have been most thankful for the
interruption," declared Miss Loring. The best result of this fray was
that Philip had his hideous long trousers and wrinkly coat torn into
shreds, so that he could not possibly wear them again.

</p><p>The next engagement in the "war" was on a Sunday afternoon
shortly afterward, when, as usual, Miss Loring and her boys went for a
walk. Some distance up Perilous, on a mountain-slope about fifty yards
above the creek, was a clump of chestnuttrees thickly embowered in wild
grapevine. Neither chestnuts nor grapes were ripe, but they were at that
stage when no living boy could pass without investigating.  Miss Loring
followed the boys up to the trees. On her arrival, somewhat to her
surprise, Philip suggested that "all hands get up in the trees and set
awhile and tell ha'nt stories." The day was warm, the rest welcome. The
boys vied with one another in lifting and "boosting" her up, and in
finding a good limb for her to sit on; and then Taulbee, the most gifted
narrator, began in a low voice on the "ha'nts."  Had she been out in the
open, instead of sitting in the embowered coolness, with her back to the
creek and road, she would have seen the girls of the school approaching
along the road in charge of one of the teachers, and, at a respectful
distance in their rear, the usual group of village boys.  As it was, she
understood things only after the event. The girls passed on along the
road below, uninterested in chestnuts and "'possum"-grapes; but the boys
following them ('Lige and some of his supporters) ran up to have a look.
Just as they got beneath, down from their ambush dropped the Floyds,
with terrific yells and pockets full of chestnut-burs. The burs, when
rubbed vigorously into face, neck, and eyes, make resistless weapons.
Nothing can withstand them. In a few seconds the Munns were in full
flight down the slope, past the astonished girls, pursued by burs,
rocks, and execrations.

</p><p>During the fight Geordie had never once left his safe retreat in
the boughs beside Miss Loring; also, as the Munns approached
unsuspectingly up the hill, he had accidentally (so he said) "fallen a
piece," exposing beneath the cover a fat foot and leg. He was now
accused of both cowardice and treachery. He protested: "I tell you, I'm
a man of peace, like the Bible says. I don't follow fighting. I'd ruther
love my enemies than to fight 'em any day." But it was useless, and he
had his face rubbed with burs, and was mauled and pounded within an inch
of his life before Miss Loring could rescue him.

</p><p>Then the girls came trooping up to hear particulars and to
congratulate the Floyds, &mdash;all of them except Dilsey, who remained, a
scornful, solitary little figure, down in the road, and who remarked in
a scathing voice when Philip and the other victors came triumphantly
down, "Some boys would never eat nothing but fire, or drink nothing but
blood, if they had their wishes." The next morning in school she passed
a note to 'Lige over Philip's very head, and in full view of the entire
room.

</p><p>Then came the period of real darkness and despair to Philip. If
devotion, if royal generosity, if bravery and prowess, fail to recapture
straying affections, what is left to be done? Deep gloom settled upon
him; he moped sullenly about, absorbed in his own cogitations; he ceased
to wash his ears, or to brush his hair and teeth; permitted his clothes
to fall into raggedness; his manners to drop from him like a garment,
his generosity like a hot cake. As to the "war," he merely kept his
forces on the defensive. But no further attack came, for 'Lige was not
of heroic stuff. War was not his meat and drink. For him defeat in
battle was easily swallowed up by

<pb n="503"/>

victory in love. He walked about with a
satisfied smile, paying more and more daring attentions to Dilsey.

</p><p>It was at this psychological moment that, in the evenings and
other leisure moments at the cottage, Geordie Yonts began to sing and
pick a song that he had not hitherto attempted, and the words of which
were as follows:</p>

<lg type="verse">
<l>As I were rambling out one day,</l>
<l>I met up with Wild Bill Jones,</l>
<l>A-walking and a-talking with my dovey little gal,</l>
<l>And I warned him to leave her alone.</l>
<l>He looked me up, he looked me down,</l>
<l>And he smiled one scornful smile,</l>
<l>Said, "Lady, will you take this arm of mine,</l>
<l>And walk another while?"</l>
<l>I am the age of twenty-one,</l>
<l>Too old for to be controlled; I drawed my revolver from my side,</l>
<l>And destroyed that poor man's soul.</l></lg>

<p>Who can estimate the power of suggestion, though possibly it may
not have been needed in this case, or who could dream that in Geordie's
famous locked box, among the treasures which surely beguiled the last
cent from every cottage and day-school boy, at that moment lay two
ancient pistols, picked up goodness knows when or where, and crying out
to be advantageously disposed of? In all human probability, the "Wild
Bill Jones" song, which could as readily be made to convey warning to
'Lige as incentive to Philip, did double duty to this end. Certain it is
that when all was over, these were found to be the pistols that figured
in the final catastrophe. It was an ill wind that blew Geordie no good.
For once, however, he overreached himself, for his beloved box, with all
its contents, was thereafter confiscated by "the women," and the "born
trader" was further discouraged by the promise of expulsion at the next
sale or deal of any description.

</p><p>One day in mid-October, Aunt Lucinda Tollett rode in on her nag
and invited the school women and all the children, and, before she was
through with it, the entire village and neighborhood, to the "stir-off"
at her home up Right Fork two evenings later. Great was the excitement
in the school as the hour approached. Supper was hurried through, all
hands helped with the dishes, and by half-past six everybody set forth
on the three-mile walk, village and neighborhood young folks falling
into line all along the way. The procession was a gay and anticipative
one, "stir-offs" being important social events in the mountains.

</p><p>Dilsey started out flanked by her usual guards, Narcissa and
Rosabel; but, with unparalleled audacity, 'Lige Munn politely shouldered
Narcissa away and walked jauntily along at Dilsey's side, under the very
eyes of the heads and teachers. A shock ran through the entire company
of girls. The cottage boys stopped in their tracks and looked toward
Philip. He walked sternly along, however, and made no sign.

</p><p>The crescent moon and pale stars brightened in the sky as the
procession straggled along the wild and beautiful banks of Right Fork.
Then in the distance appeared the red glow of the fire where the sorghum
was being boiled down, and soon the Tollett house, with fields and
orchard rising steeply behind, stood forth in the glare. Piles of cane,
crushed out by the gin, lay about the yard, and in the midst of them, in
the huge, shallow, ten-foot pan propped table-high over the fire, the
juice itself bubbled and boiled and sent up delicious odors, and was
stirred, skimmed, and assisted from compartment to compartment by Uncle
Bolivar The boiling had already proceeded for ten hours, and was about
finished.

</p><p>The eager crowd swarmed about the pan, with sticks of cane, which
were dipped into the thickening sweetness and then rapturously sucked.
People stood four or five deep, reaching over heads and shoulders.
Needless to say, the cottage boys achieved places in the front row.
Having won his, Philip had just dipped in his cane and conveyed it
half-way to his mouth when his eyes were blasted, his sweet turned to
bitter, by the sight of 'Lige and Dilsey immediately across the pan from
him. Slowly passing the piece of cane to his left hand, he stood
awaiting developments. There is a custom at "stiroffs" which is
equivalent to a formal betrothal or the publishing of banns in other
regions. When a pair of lovers use only one piece of cane to suck the
sorghum from, it is well understood that nothing

<pb n="504"/>

but the marriage-ceremony is needed to seal the compact.

</p><p>As Philip looked, he saw 'Lige dip in a piece of cane, lick it
delicately, to test its hotness, and then, with an elegant flourish,
pass it on to Dilsey, who calmly and thoroughly sucked off the remaining
sorghum.  During the whole of this proceeding, 'Lige kept the corner of
an eye carefully fixed on Philip.

</p><p>Then blind, titanic rage swept over Philip's soul. His hand flew
to his hippocket. 'Lige's instantaneously followed suit. A shot rang
out, and Philip crumpled down on the ground.

</p><p>There was an instant of horrified silence, then tremendous
excitement broke forth. With one accord the cottage boys rushed for
'Lige, who stood, dazed, pistol in hand, repeating over and over, "I
never done it, I never had time to fire," and would have cast him bodily
into the flames had not the deputy sheriff, Darcy Peel, stepped forward
and laid a hand on his shoulder. Other young men, under Miss Shippen's
direction, were lifting Philip to a pile of cane, and clearing space
about him for air. Reviving in a moment, he looked angrily about and
fumbled for his pocket.

</p><p>"Where is that 'Lige?" he demanded.  "Gimme another try at him!
My daggone trigger caught in this here ragged pocket and shot me in the
leg this time, but I'll git him the next."

</p><p>The offending weapon was quickly removed from his pocket, and
Miss Shippen propped and bandaged the injured leg to stop the profuse
bleeding, and ordered a stretcher made of bean-poles and wild grapevine.
After this was made comfortable with Aunt Lucinda's soft coverlets,
Philip was lifted upon it, and the bearers started with him for the
school, followed by a crowd of weeping and wailing girls and wildly
excited boys, from whom 'Lige and Geordie found it best to seek
protection by clinging to the arm of the law in the person of Darcy
Peel.

</p><p>Near the head of the procession, and immediately following the
stretcher and its attendants, walked a beautiful, fair-haired little
mourner, beating her breast, wringing her hands, refusing consolation
and hope, all her pride and reserve for once broken down.

</p><p>"Oh, my poor boy!, my poor boy! I have gone and killed him that I
liked better than anything on this green earth!  I have broke his heart
for him, and been the death of him, by my ill behavior, and showing
civilities to that contemptible 'Lige Munn, that I never, never cared
nary grain about no way, and that never could hold no kind of a candle
to Philip!  No, Rosabel, he <hi rend="italic">hain't</hi> a-going to get well, neither.
He's aiming to die,&mdash;I know that for certain,&mdash;he's aiming to depart
from this world that hain't fitten for him to tread on, and from me that
treated him so scandalous and dog-mean! Oh, he was the prettiest and
most manliest boy that ever I seed the likes of, Narcissa, and now
they're a-carrying him feet foremost! Oh, I'll never speak to nary
'nother boy long as I live, much less eat candy and apples off of 'em,
and dip sorghum with 'em!"

LATE in the night, when the school hospital had been reached, the bullet probed for
and found, the wound dressed, and Philip
lay weak from suffering, but once more at
ease, a miserable, weary, tear-stained little
Dilsey came haltingly into the small dispensary where Miss Shippen and Miss
Loring still lingered.

</p><p>"Miss Shippen," she began, with difficulty, "do you reckon it
would hurt anything if you was to let me say just four words to Philip?"

</p><p>"Can't I say them for you?"

</p><p>"No, ma'am."

</p><p>"Is it anything that will excite or trouble him? Because nothing
must do that now on any account."

</p><p>"No, ma'am," replied the little petitioner, humbly; "it is
something that is liable to swage him down and pacify him a right
smart."

</p><p>Miss Shippen and Miss Loring exchanged amused glances. "Very
well," said Miss Shippen, gravely, "come on in." She led the way in to
Philip's bedside. "Here is Dilsey wanting to speak to you," she said.

</p><p>Philip turned away his head with a deep groan; but Dilsey laid a
compelling hand on his shoulder, leaned down over him, and spoke these
words distinctly, slowly, and forcibly into his ear:

</p><p>"I despise 'Lige Munn!"

</p><p>Philip opened his eyes, looked at her intently, and then gave a
long, long sigh, as if incredible burdens were rolling from him.

</p><p>"Gee!" he said feebly, "I wished I'd 'a' got shot sooner!"</p>

<p><note id="n1"><seg type="note-symbol">[1]</seg> <p>See "The Tender Passion," in <hi rend="italic">THE CENTURY</hi>
for May, 1911.</p></note></p>

</div1>
</body>
</text>
</TEI.2>
