<?xml version="1.0"?>

<?dlps id="GarCran"?>
<?dlps page-images="none" figure-images="no"?>
<?dlps transcription="other"?>

<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/tei-p4/tei2.dtd" [
<!ENTITY % POSTKB "INCLUDE">
<!ENTITY % TEI.extensions.ent SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.ent">
<!ENTITY % TEI.extensions.dtd SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.dtd">
<!ENTITY % ISOnum SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/charent/iso-num.ent"> %ISOnum;
<!ENTITY % ISOpub SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/charent/iso-pub.ent"> %ISOpub;
]>


<TEI.2 id="GarCran">
<teiHeader type="migrated" creator="Etext">
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title type="main">Drifting Crane</title>
<title type="sort">drifting crane</title>
<author>Garland, Hamlin</author>
<respStmt>
<resp>Creation of machine-readable version:</resp>
<name>Judy Boss</name>
<resp>Conversion to TEI.2-conformant markup:</resp>
<name>University of Virginia Library Electronic Text Center</name>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt>
<extent>ca. <num type="kilobytes">17</num> kilobytes</extent>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>University of Virginia Library</publisher>
<pubPlace>Charlottesville, Virginia</pubPlace>
<idno type="ETC">GarCran</idno>
<date value="1995">1995</date>
<availability status="public">
<p n="copyright">Copyright &copy; 1995 by the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia</p>
<p n="access">Publicly accessible</p>
</availability>
<idno type="uva-pid">uva-lib:475977</idno>
</publicationStmt>
<seriesStmt>
<title>University of Virginia Library, Text collection</title>
<idno type="uva-set">UVA-LIB-Text</idno>
</seriesStmt>
<sourceDesc>
<biblFull>
<titleStmt>
<title type="main">Drifting Crane</title>
<title type="sort">drifting crane</title>
<author>Hamlin Garland</author>
</titleStmt>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>Harper's Weekly</publisher>
<pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
<date value="1890-05-31">31 May 1890</date>
</publicationStmt>
<notesStmt>
<note>
<p>Garland, Hamlin.  "Drifting Crane."  <hi rend="italic">Harper's Weekly</hi>,
31 May 1890: 421-422.</p>
</note>
</notesStmt>
</biblFull>
</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc>
<encodingDesc>
<projectDesc>
<p>Prepared for the University of Virginia Library Electronic Text Center</p>
</projectDesc>
<editorialDecl>
<p>All quotation marks retained as data</p>
<p>All unambiguous end-of-line hyphens have been removed, and the
trailing part of a word has been joined to the preceding line.</p>
<p id="ETC">Keywords in the header are a local Electronic Text Center scheme
to aid in establishing analytical groupings</p>
</editorialDecl>
<refsDecl>
<p>ID elements are given for each page element and are composed of the text's
unique cryptogram and the given page number, as in AusEmma1 for page one of
Jane Austen's Emma.</p>
</refsDecl>
</encodingDesc>
<profileDesc>
<creation>
<date value="1890-05-31">31 May 1890</date>
</creation>
<langUsage>
<language id="eng" usage="main">English</language>
</langUsage>
<textClass>
<keywords>
<term>fiction ; prose</term>
<term>Native American</term>
</keywords>
</textClass>
</profileDesc>
<revisionDesc>
<change>
<date value="1995-08">August 1995</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>corrector</resp>
<name>Jamie L Spriggs, Electronic Text Center, University of Virginia</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Added header, Tagged with TEI.2-compatible SGML, Parsed against "teilite" dtd</item>
</change>
<change>
<date value="2005-07">July 2005</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>Corrector</resp>
<name>John Ivor Carlson</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Converted SGML to XML. Fixed tagging.</item>
</change>
<change>
<date value="2007-09">September 2007</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>Migration</resp>
<name>Ethan Gruber, University of Virginia Library</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Converted XML markup from TEI Lite to uva-dl-tei (TEI P4 with local customizations).</item>
</change>
<change>
<date value="2008-01">January 2008</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>Migration</resp>
<name>Greg Murray, University of Virginia Library</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Programmatically updated TEI header markup (but not header content) for minimal compliance with current QA requirements.</item>
</change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text id="d1">

<body id="d2">

<div1 type="story" id="d3"><pb n="421"/>
<head>DRIFTING CRANE.<lb/>
	<lb/>
BY HAMLIN GARLAND.</head>

<p>THE people of Boomtown invariably spoke of Henry Wilson as the
oldest settler in the Jim Valley, as he was of Buster County; but
the Eastern man, with his ideas of an "old settler," was surprised
as he met the short, silent, middle-aged man, who was very loath to
tell anything about himself, and about whom many strange and
thrilling stories were told by good story-tellers.  In 1870 he was
the only settler in the upper part of the valley, living alone on
the banks of the Elm, a slow, tortuous stream pulsing lazily down
the valley, too small to be called a river and too long to be
called a creek.  For two years, it is said, Wilson had only the
company of his cattle, especially during the winter-time, and now
and then a visit from an Indian, or a trapper after mink and musk-rats.
</p><p>Between his ranch and the settlements in eastern Dakota there
was the wedge-shaped reservation known as the "Sisseton Indian
Reserve," on which was stationed the customary agency and company
of soldiers.  But of course at that time the Indians were not
restricted closely to the bounds of the reserve, but ranged freely
over the vast and beautiful prairie lying between the coteaux or
ranges of low hills which mark out "the Jim Valley."  The valley
was unsurveyed for the most part, and the Indians naturally felt a
sort of proprietorship in it, and when Wilson drove his cattle down
into the valley and "squatted," the chief, Drifting Crane, welcomed
him as a host might to an abundant feast whose hospitality was
presumed upon, but who felt the need of sustaining his reputation
as a host, and submitted graciously.
</p><p>The Indians during the first summer got to know Wilson, and
liked him for his silence, his courage, his generosity; but the
older men pondered upon the matter a great deal and watched with
grave faces to see him ploughing up the sod for his garden.  There
was something strange in this solitary man thus deserting his
kindred, coming here to live alone with his cattle; they could not
understand it.  What they said in those pathetic, dimly lighted
lodges will never be known; but when winter came, and the new-comer
did not drive his cattle back over the hills as they thought he
would, then the old chieftains took long counsel upon it.  Night
after night they smoked upon it, and at last Drifting Crane said to
two of his young men, "Go ask this cattleman why he remains in the
cold and snow with his cattle.  Ask him why he does not drive his
cattle home."
</p><p>This was in March, and one evening a couple of days later, as
Wilson was about re-entering his shanty at the close of his day's
work, he was confronted by two stalwart Indians, who greeted him
pleasantly.
</p><p>"How d'e do?  How d'e do?" he said in reply.  "Come in.  Come
in and take a snack."
</p><p>The Indians entered and sat silently while he put some food on
the table.  They hardly spoke till after they had eaten.  The
Indian is always hungry, for the reason that his food supply is
insufficient and his clothing poor.  When they sat on the cracker
boxes and soap boxes which served as seats, they spoke.  They told
him of the chieftain's message.  They said they had come to assist
him in driving his cattle back across the hills; that he must go.
</p><p>To all this talk in the Indian's epigrammatic way, and in the
dialect which has never been written, the rancher replied almost as
briefly: "You go back and tell Drifting Crane that I like this
place; that I'm here to stay; that I don't want any help to drive
my cattle.  I'm on the lands of the Great Father at Washington, and
Drifting Crane 'ain't got any say about it.  Now that signs the
whole thing up.  I 'ain't got anything against you nor against him,
but I'm a settler; that's my constitution; and now I'm settled I'm
going to stay."
</p><p>While the Indians discussed his words between themselves he
made a bed of blankets on the floor and said: "I never turn anybody
out.  A white man is just as good as an Indian as long as he
behaves himself as well.  You can bunk here."
</p><p>The Indians didn't understand his words fully, but they did
understand his gesture, and they smiled and accepted the courtesy
so like their own rude hospitality.  Then they all smoked a pipe of
tobacco in silence, and at last Wilson turned in and went serenely
off to sleep, hearing the mutter of the Indians lying before the
fire.
</p><p>In the morning he gave them as good a breakfast as he had&mdash;
bacon and potatoes, with coffee and crackers.  Then he shook hands,
saying: "Come again.  I 'ain't got anything against you.  You've
done y'r duty.  Now go back and tell your chief what I've said.
I'm at home every day.  Good-day."
</p><p>The Indians smiled kindly, and drawing their blankets over
their arms, went away toward the east.
</p><p>During April and May two or three reconnoitring parties of
land hunters drifted over the hills and found him out.  He was glad
to see them, for, to tell the truth, the solitude of his life was
telling on him.  The winter had been severe, and he had hardly
caught a glimpse of a white face during the three midwinter months,
and his provisions were scanty.
</p><p>These parties brought great news.  One of them was the advance
surveying party for the great northern railroad, and they said a
line of road was to be surveyed during the summer if their report
was favorable.
</p><p>"Well, what d'ye think of it?" Wilson asked, with a smile.
</p><p>"Think!  It's immense!" said a small man in the party, whom
the rest called "Judge" Balser.  "Why, they'll be a town of four
thousand inhabitants in this valley before snow flies.  We'll send
the surveyors right over the divide next month."
</p><p>They sent some papers to Wilson a few weeks later, which he
devoured as a hungry dog would devour a plate of bacon.  The papers
were full of the wonderful resources of the Jim Valley.  It spoke
of the nutritious grasses for stock.  It spoke of the successful
venture of the lonely settler Wilson, how his stock fattened upon
the winter grasses without shelter, etc., what vegetables he grew,
etc., etc.
</p><p>Wilson was reading this paper for the sixth time one evening
in May.  He had laid off his boots, his pipe was freshly filled,
and he sat in the doorway in vast content, unmindful of the glory
of color that filled the western sky, and the superb evening chorus
of the prairie-chickens, holding conventions on every hillock.  He
felt something touch him on the shoulder, and looked up to see a
tall Indian gazing down upon him with a look of strange pride and
gravity.  Wilson sprang to his feet and held out his hand.
</p><p>"Drifting Crane, how d'e do?"
</p><p>The Indian bowed, but did not take the settler's hand.
Drifting Crane would have been called old if he had been a white
man, and there was a look of age in the fixed lines of his
powerful, strongly modelled face, but no suspicion of weakness in
the splendid poise of his broad, muscular body.  There was a
smileless gravity about his lips and eyes which was very
impressive.
</p><p>"I'm glad to see you.  Come in and get something to eat," said
Wilson, after a moment's pause.
</p><p>The chief entered the cabin, and took a seat near the door.
He took a cup of milk and some meat and bread silently, and ate
while listening to the talk of the settler.
</p><p>"I don't brag on my biscuits, chief, but they <hi rend="italic">eat</hi>, if a
man is hungry enough.  An' the milk's all right.  I suppose you've
come to see why I ain't moseying back over the divide?"
</p><p>The chief, after a long pause, began to speak in a low, slow
voice, as if choosing his words.  He spoke in broken English, of
course, but his speech was very direct and plain, and had none of
those absurd figures of rhetoric which romancers invariably put
into the mouths of Indians.  His voice was almost lion-like in
depth, and yet was not unpleasant.  It was easy to see that he was
a chief by virtue of his own personality.
</p><p>"Cattle-man, my young men brought me bad message from you.
They brought your words to me, saying he will not go away."
</p><p>"That's about the way the thing stood," replied Wilson, in
response to the question that was in the old chief's steady eyes.
"I'm here to stay.  This ain't your land.  This is Uncle Sam's
land, and part of it'll be mine as soon as the surveyors come to
measure it off."
</p><p>"Who gave it away?" asked the chief.  "My people were cheated
out of it.  They didn't know what they were doing."
</p><p>"I can't help that.  That's fer Congress to say.  That's the
business of the Great Father at Washington."  Wilson's voice
changed.  He knew and liked the chief; he didn't want to offend
him.  "They ain't no use making a fuss, chief.  You won't gain
anything."
</p><p>There was a look of deep sorrow in the old man's face.  At
last he spoke again.  "The cattle-man is welcome; but he must go,
because wherever one white man goes and calls it good, the others
come.  Drifting Crane has seen it far in the east twice.  The white
men come thick as the grass.  They tear up the sod.  They build
houses.  They scare the buffalo away.  They spoil my young men with
whiskey.  Already they begin to climb the eastern hills.  Soon they
will fill the valley, and Drifting Crane and his people will be
surrounded.  The sod would be all torn up." <pb n="422"/>
</p><p>"I hope you're right," was the rancher's grim reply.
</p><p>"But they will not come if the cattle-man go back to say the
water is not good.  There is no grass, and the Indians own the
land."
</p><p>Wilson smiled at the childish faith of the chief.  "Won't do,
chief&mdash;won't do.  That won't do any good.  I might as well stay."
</p><p>The chief rose.  He was touched by the settler's laugh: his
eyes flashed; his voice took on a sterner note.  "The white man <hi rend="italic">
 must</hi> go!"
</p><p>Wilson rose also.  He was not a large man, but he was a very
resolute one.  "I sha'n't go!" he said, through his clinched teeth.
Each man understood the tones of the other perfectly.
</p><p>It was a thrilling, a significant scene.  It was in absolute
truth the meeting of the modern vidette of civilization with one of
the rear-guard of retreating barbarism.  Each man was a type; each
was wrong, and each was right.  The Indian as true and noble from
the barbaric point of view as the white man.  He was a warrior and
hunter&mdash;made so by circumstances over which he had no control.
Guiltless as the panther, because war to a savage is the necessity
of life.
</p><p>The settler represented the unflagging energy and fearless
heart of the American pioneer.  Narrow-minded, partly brutalized by
hard labor and a lonely life, yet an admirable figure for all that.
As he looked into the Indian's face he seemed to grow in height.
He felt behind him all the weight of the millions of Westward-moving settlers; he stood the representative of an unborn State.
He took down a rifle from the wall&mdash;the magazine rifle, most modern
of guns; he patted the stock, pulled the crank, throwing a shell
into view.
</p><p>"You know this thing, chief?"
</p><p>The Indian nodded slightly.
</p><p>"Well, I'll go when&mdash;this&mdash;is&mdash;empty."
</p><p>"But my young men are many."
</p><p>"So are the white men&mdash;my brothers."
</p><p>The chief's head dropped forward.  Wilson, ashamed of his
boasting, put the rifle back on the wall.
</p><p>"I'm not here to fight.  You can kill me any time.  You could
'a' killed me to-night, but it wouldn't do any good.  It 'ud only
make it worse for you.  Why, they'll be a town in here bigger'n all
your tribe before two grass from now.  It ain't no use, Drifting
Crane; it's <hi rend="italic">got</hi> to be.  You an' I can't help n'r hinder it.  I
know just how you feel about it, but I tell yeh it ain't no use to
fight."
</p><p>Drifting Crane turned his head, and gazed out on the western
sky still red with the light of the fallen sun.  His face was rigid
as bronze, but there was a dreaming, prophetic look in his eyes.
A lump came into the settler's throat; for the first time in his
life he got a glimpse of the infinite despair of the Indian.  He
forgot that Drifting Crane was the representative of a "vagabond
race"; he saw in him, or rather <hi rend="italic">felt</hi> in him, something almost
magnetic.  He was a <hi rend="italic">man</hi>, and a man of sorrows.  The settler's
voice was husky when he spoke again, and his lips trembled.
</p><p>"Chief, I'd go to-morrow if it 'ud do any good, but it won't&mdash;
not a particle.  You know that when you stop to think a minute.
What good did it do to massa<hi rend="italic">cree</hi> all them settlers at New Ulm?
What good will it do to murder me and a hundred others?  Not a bit.
A thousand others would take our places.  So I might just as well
stay, and we might just as well keep good friends.  Killin' is out
o' fashion; don't do any good."
</p><p>There was a twitching about the stern mouth of the Indian
chief.  He understood all too well the irresistible logic of the
pioneer.  He kept his martial attitude, but his broad chest heaved
painfully, and his eyes grew dim.  At last he said: "Good-by.
Cattle-man right; Drifting Crane wrong.  Shake hands.  Good-by."
He turned and strode away.
</p><p>The rancher watched him till he mounted his pony picketed down
by the river; watched him as, with drooping head and rein flung
loose upon the neck of his horse, he rode away into the dusk,
hungry, weary, and despairing, to face his problem alone.  Again,
for the thousandth time, the impotence of the Indian's arm and the
hopelessness of his fate were shown as perfectly as if two armies
had met and soaked the beautiful prairie sod with blood.
</p><p>"This is all wrong," muttered the settler.  "There's land
enough for us all, or ought to be.  I don't understand&mdash;  Well,
I'll leave it to Uncle Sam anyway."  He ended with a sigh.


</p>

</div1>
</body>
</text>
</TEI.2>
