<?xml version="1.0"?>

<?dlps id="GarOkla"?>
<?dlps page-images="none" figure-images="no"?>
<?dlps transcription="other"?>

<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/tei-p4/tei2.dtd" [
<!ENTITY % POSTKB "INCLUDE">
<!ENTITY % TEI.extensions.ent SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.ent">
<!ENTITY % TEI.extensions.dtd SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.dtd">
<!ENTITY % ISOnum SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/charent/iso-num.ent"> %ISOnum;
<!ENTITY % ISOpub SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/charent/iso-pub.ent"> %ISOpub;

]>

<TEI.2 id="GarOkla">
<teiHeader type="migrated" creator="Etext">
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title type="main">Two Stories of Oklahoma</title>
<title type="sort">two stories of oklahoma</title>
<author>Garland, Hamlin</author>
<respStmt>
<resp>Creation of machine-readable version</resp>
<name>Judy Boss, University of Omaha</name>
</respStmt>
<respStmt>
<resp>Conversion to TEI-conformant markup</resp>
<name>University of Virginia Library Electronic Text Center</name>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt>
<extent>ca. <num type="kilobytes">9</num> kilobytes</extent>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>University of Virginia Library</publisher>
<pubPlace>Charlottesville, Virginia</pubPlace>
<idno type="ETC">GarOkla</idno>
<date value="1994">1994</date>
<availability status="public">
<p n="copyright">Copyright &copy; 1994 by the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia</p>
<p n="access">Publicly accessible</p>
</availability>
<idno type="uva-pid">uva-lib:475979</idno>
</publicationStmt>
<seriesStmt>
<title>University of Virginia Library, Text collection</title>
<idno type="uva-set">UVA-LIB-Text</idno>
</seriesStmt>
<sourceDesc>
<biblFull>
<titleStmt>
<title type="main">Two Stories of Oklahoma</title>
<title type="sort">two stories of oklahoma</title>
<author>Hamlin Garland</author>
</titleStmt>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>Century Magazine</publisher>
<pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
<date value="1904">1904</date>
</publicationStmt>
<seriesStmt>
<p>Volume 68</p>
</seriesStmt>
<notesStmt>
<note>
<p>pp. 328-329</p>
</note>
</notesStmt>
</biblFull>
</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc>
<encodingDesc>
<projectDesc>
<p>Prepared for the University of Virginia Library Electronic Text Center</p>
</projectDesc>
<editorialDecl>
<p>All quotation marks retained as data</p>
<p>All unambiguous end-of-line hyphens have been removed, and the
trailing part of a word has been joined to the preceding line.</p>
<p id="ETC">Keywords in the header are a local Electronic Text Center scheme
to aid in establishing analytical groupings</p>
</editorialDecl>
<refsDecl>
<p>ID elements are given for each page element and are composed of the text's
unique cryptogram and the given page number, as in SpeFQue1 for page one of
Spenser's Faerie Queene.</p>
</refsDecl>
</encodingDesc>
<profileDesc>
<creation>
<date value="1904">1904</date>
</creation>
<langUsage>
<language id="eng" usage="main">English</language>
</langUsage>
<textClass>
<keywords>
<term>fiction; prose</term>
<term>Native American</term>
</keywords>
</textClass>
</profileDesc>
<revisionDesc>
<change>
<date value="1994-10">October 1994</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>corrector</resp>
<name>Kelly Tetterton</name>
</respStmt>
<item>minimal TEI tagging</item>
</change>
<change>
<date value="2005-07">July 2005</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>Corrector</resp>
<name>John Ivor Carlson</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Converted SGML to XML. Fixed tagging.</item>
</change>
<change>
<date value="2007-09">September 2007</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>Migration</resp>
<name>Ethan Gruber, University of Virginia Library</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Converted XML markup from TEI Lite to uva-dl-tei (TEI P4 with local customizations).</item>
</change>
<change>
<date value="2008-01">January 2008</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>Migration</resp>
<name>Greg Murray, University of Virginia Library</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Programmatically updated TEI header markup (but not header content) for minimal compliance with current QA requirements.</item>
</change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>
<text id="d1">
<body id="d2">
<div1 type="story" n="1" id="d3"><pb n="328"/>
<head>
                        I.  NUKO'S REVENGE
</head>
<p>NUKO, an Arapahoe warrior, owned a rooster which he kept in his
camp near the agency on the Canadian River of Oklahoma.  He guarded
his pet with zealous care.  It was his inseparable companion, often
carried under his arm as he galloped across the prairie on his
visits to his friends and relatives.  No ridicule could cause him
to neglect his pet.
</p><p>One day the camp police &mdash; the Dog Soldiers &mdash; passed through the
village, ordering the tepees to be packed, announcing that the
tribe was about to start on a buffalo-hunt in the foothills to the
west.
</p><p>Nuko, much concerned about his pet, went at once to the agency
doctor, and presenting the rooster very tenderly in his hands, thus
began:
</p><p>"My friend, I am about to go on the hunting-trail with my
people, and I want to leave my chicken with you.  You see him, how
gaily colored he is, how tame.  I wish to have him well cared for,
therefore I bring him to you.  Keep him for me.  I am very fond of
him.  He sits every night on my couch.  He has a fine voice &mdash; you
will enjoy hearing him cry out at dawn.  It is like a soldier's
bugle, his song.  He will always tell you when the light is coming.
You will never oversleep while he sits on your bed.  You will never
be lonely.  He helps to pass the time.  Like me, you have no wife.
He will therefore be company for you, and if he is sick you can
give him medicine to make him well."
</p><p>The doctor declined the rooster with many thanks, but very
definitely, and Nuko went away disconsolate and deeply disappointed
with his friend.
</p><p>The agency farmer listened to his plea and consented to take
the rooster.  "I don't want him in the house," said he, "but I will
put him among the fowls of my barn-yard."  To this Nuko consented,
and went away on the western hunting-trail quite cheerfully.
</p><p>Some months later, as the farmer was soundly sleeping after
his Sunday dinner, Nuko entered and touched him on the shoulder.
"How, how, my friend!  I have returned, you see.  My tepee is again
in its place, and I have come for my rooster."
</p><p>The farmer looked surprised and a little disturbed, and after
a moment's hesitation said:
</p><p>"Nuko, your rooster is dead."  Then, as Nuko's face fell and
his lips quivered, the white man added, exultantly, with intent to
console: "But he died like a warrior.  He fell in battle.  He
fought every other rooster in the barnyard and beat them all &mdash; only
the turkey-gobbler could master him.  There is the killer of your
pet."
</p><p>He pointed from the door at the puffed-out, vainglorious,
insolent turkey-cock, strutting with rustling wings about one of
his meek and complacent wives.
</p><p>A fierce gleam came into Nuko's eyes.  "Ho!" said he, "so you
are the assassin of my little brave.  You shall be punished."  And
flinging his hunting-knife with miraculous skill, he snipped the
head from the arrogant boaster's neck.
</p><p>"Hold!" shouted the farmer, "that turkey belongs to the Great
Father at Washington."
</p><p>"Nevertheless, I shall eat him," replied Nuko.  "He slew my
little Golden Voice, and now, behold, I take his scalp.  It is the
law of my people."
</p><p>Thereupon he flung the fallen braggart over his shoulder and
strode away.
</p>
</div1>
<div1 type="story" n="2" id="d4">
<head>
           II.  A RED MAN'S VIEW OF EVOLUTION<lb/>
</head>
<p>ONE time, while we were camped on the Washita, said the agency
farmer, we were visited by an old Kiowa, a dignified and serious
old man.
</p><p>I was introduced to him as the "white father," out there to
help the red men work and to show them the white man's road.
</p><p>The old man said, "Aye, is that so!" but didn't seem very much
impressed.  After a moment's silence he got out his buffalo-horn
tinder-box, and, after carefully examining the punk with which it
was filled, began pecking with his flint in an effort to light his
tinder-box.
</p><p>I watched him pecking away for a while, sometimes hitting the
flint, oftener barking his leathery fingers, and at last I said to
a Cheyenne: "Why doesn't he use a match and done with it, not sit
there pecking away all night?"
</p><p>This being translated to the old Kiowa, he began to speak, but
never for a moment interrupted his play with the flint, and this is
what he said:
</p><p>"You white men think you are very wise [<hi rend="italic">peck, peck</hi>].  You
have made little fire-sticks, and you think the red men can't get
along without them [<hi rend="italic">peck, peck</hi>].  I will tell you, we didn't
have so much trouble in the good old days as we do now [<hi rend="italic">peck,
peck</hi>.  The old man's stroke grew a little vicious.]  Before the
red man had the white man's fire-stick, we didn't have so many
fires and we didn't have to move every few days on account of the
prairie burning black."  At this point he struck out his spark and
hurriedly lighted his pipe.  After puffing vigorously a few times,
he continued calmly: "Now the red man uses the white man's fire-stick; he lights his pipe, he throws away the end: the grass blazes
up, and then the ponies grow hungry.  It is all bad business."
</p><p>The old man smoked in silence for a few moments, but at last
resumed: "Yes, these white men think they are very clever, but
<pb n="329"/>
they are really very foolish; they are very ridiculous [<hi rend="italic">
puff, puff</hi>].  They think they are men, but look at them [<hi rend="italic">
puff</hi>], see the hair on their faces; they are not men, they are
only hair-covered animals."
</p><p>At this everybody in the tepee cried out with delight, and I,
in self-defense, joined in the laughter, but the old man remained
as grave as a bronze image.  Reaching up with his forefinger, he
outlined the beard upon my face and said slowly, hopefully, as if
to be gently encouraging: "But they are changing.  You see, the
hair is wearing away &mdash; in spots."  Then settling back, he blew out
a great cloud of smoke, and with patient paternal benignity
concluded: "They'll be men by and by."
</p>
<trailer>                              <hi rend="italic">Hamlin Garland.</hi>
<lb/>
WEST SALEM, WISCONSIN.
</trailer>

</div1>
</body>
</text>
</TEI.2>
