<?xml version="1.0"?>

<?dlps id="GilEdga"?>
<?dlps page-images="none" figure-images="no"?>
<?dlps transcription="other"?>

<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/tei-p4/tei2.dtd" [
<!ENTITY % POSTKB "INCLUDE">
<!ENTITY % TEI.extensions.ent SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.ent">
<!ENTITY % TEI.extensions.dtd SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.dtd">
<!ENTITY % ISOnum SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/charent/iso-num.ent"> %ISOnum;
<!ENTITY % ISOlat1 SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/charent/iso-lat1.ent"> %ISOlat1;
<!ENTITY % ISOpub SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/charent/iso-pub.ent"> %ISOpub;

]>
<TEI.2 id="GilEdga">
<teiHeader type="migrated" creator="Etext">
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title type="main">Edgar Allan Poe&mdash;After Fifty Years</title>
<title type="sort">edgar allan poe&mdash;after fifty years</title>
<author>Gill, William Fearing</author>
<respStmt>
<resp>Creation of machine-readable version:</resp>
<name>Judy Boss</name>
<resp>Conversion to TEI.2-conformant markup:</resp>
<name>University of Virginia Library Electronic Text Center.</name>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt>
<extent>ca. <num type="kilobytes">11</num> kilobytes</extent>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>University of Virginia Library</publisher>
<pubPlace>Charlottesville, Virginia</pubPlace>
<idno type="ETC">GilEdga</idno>
<date value="1996">1996</date>
<availability status="public">
<p n="copyright">Copyright &copy; 1996 by the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia</p>
<p n="access">Publicly accessible</p>
</availability>
<idno type="uva-pid">uva-lib:475981</idno>
</publicationStmt>
<seriesStmt>
<title>University of Virginia Library, Text collection</title>
<idno type="uva-set">UVA-LIB-Text</idno>
</seriesStmt>
<sourceDesc>
<biblFull>
<titleStmt>
<title type="main">Edgar Allan Poe&mdash;After Fifty Years</title>
<title level="j">The Arena</title>
<title type="sort">edgar allan poe&mdash;after fifty years</title>
<author>William Fearing Gill</author>
</titleStmt>
<extent>pp. 526-529</extent>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>Arena Publishing Company</publisher>
<pubPlace>Boston</pubPlace>
<date value="1899">1899</date>
<idno type="callNo">Print copy consulted: print source not available.</idno>
</publicationStmt>
</biblFull>
</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc>
<encodingDesc>
<projectDesc>
<p>Prepared for the University of Virginia Library Electronic Text Center.</p>
</projectDesc>
<editorialDecl>
<p>All quotation marks retained as data.</p>
<p>All unambiguous end-of-line hyphens have been removed, and the trailing part of a word has been joined to the preceding line.</p>
<p>Keywords in the header are a local Electronic Text Center scheme to aid in establishing analytical groupings.</p>
</editorialDecl>
</encodingDesc>
<profileDesc>
<creation>
<date value="1899">1899</date>
</creation>
<langUsage>
<language id="eng" usage="main">English</language>
</langUsage>
<textClass>
<keywords>
<term>nonfiction; prose</term>
</keywords>
</textClass>
</profileDesc>
<revisionDesc>
<change>
<date value="1996-11">November 1996</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>corrector</resp>
<name>Stephen Ramsay</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Added TEI header and tags.</item>
</change>
<change>
<date value="2005-07">July 2005</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>Corrector</resp>
<name>John Ivor Carlson</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Converted SGML to XML. Fixed tagging.</item>
</change>
<change>
<date value="2007-09">September 2007</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>Migration</resp>
<name>Ethan Gruber, University of Virginia Library</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Converted XML markup from TEI Lite to uva-dl-tei (TEI P4 with local customizations).</item>
</change>
<change>
<date value="2008-01">January 2008</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>Migration</resp>
<name>Greg Murray, University of Virginia Library</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Programmatically updated TEI header markup (but not header content) for minimal compliance with current QA requirements.</item>
</change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text id="d1">
<body id="d2">
<div1 type="essay" id="d3">
<pb n="526"/>
<head>EDGAR ALLAN POE&mdash;AFTER FIFTY YEARS.</head>

<p>WHEN Rufus W. Griswold, "the pedagogue vampire," as he was aptly
termed by one of his contemporaries, committed the immortal infamy
of blighting a collection of Edgar Allan Poe's works, which he
found ready at hand, by supplementing his perfunctory labors with
a calumniating memoir of the poet, nearly fifty years ago, there
were many protests uttered by the poet's contemporaries at home and
abroad.  Charles Baudelaire, the Poe of French literature, in his
tribute to the dead poet, indignantly wrote: "What is the matter
with America?  Are there, then, no regulations there to keep the
curs out of the cemeteries?"  In view of the fact that the Griswold
biography of Poe has been incontestably discredited, and proved to
be merely a scaffolding of malevolent falsehoods&mdash;the outcome of
malice and mendacity&mdash;the deference paid to Griswold and his
baleful work in the memoir accompanying the latest publication of
Poe's writings seems well-nigh incomprehensible.  Professor
Woodberry excuses the detractions of Poe's vilifier, "in view of
the contemporary uncertainty of Poe's fame, the difficulty of
obtaining a publisher, and the fact that the editorial work was not
paid for."  Most amazing reasons, indeed, in justification of
Griswold's interposition as the poet's biographer&mdash;an office that
had been specially bequeathed by the dying genius to his bosom
friend, Nathaniel P. Willis.  Had Willis shirked this
responsibility, there might have been some excuse for Griswold and
his horde of gutter-snipes, who wreaked their venom upon the name
of Poe, outraging every tenet of common decency; but Willis
performed his delegated duty reverently, sympathetically, and
adequately.  No publisher with any sense of justice would have
presumed to include any other memoir than that of Willis in the
original edition of Poe's works.
</p><p>The Griswold memoir was, on its face, a piece of officious
audacity&mdash;not only a libel upon Poe's fair fame, but an insult
<pb n="527"/>
to the best standards of literary biography.  It is
certainly
to be wondered at that so enterprising a city as Chicago should
have been unable to find fresher material at hand for a biography
of America's most original genius than a <hi rend="italic">rechauff&eacute;</hi> of
the scandalous estimate of "the Catullus of American literature,"
voiced by one who frankly wrote, forty years ago, speaking of his
attitude toward Poe: "I was not his friend, nor was he mine."
</p><p>It may be safely answered that, in the present instance, the
"editorial work" of this malicious biography, which accuses the
poet of "a habit of intoxication," which no literary expert in his
sober judgment can honestly believe existed, was, probably, not
given to the publishers without adequate compensation, however
Griswold may have fared with his disingenuous original memoir.  The
calumnies of puritanical bigots, like the late Charles F. Briggs,
should not be permitted to stand against the poet's own analysis
and the testimony of many near associates, during his life&mdash;as N.
P. Willis, Thomas Cottrell Clarke, William Gowans, and George R.
Graham.
</p><p>Poe's own defense of himself from the attack upon his
character by William E. Burton, which, unfortunately, was not made
known by the late Dr. J. E. Snodgrass until long after Griswold's
memoir of Poe was published, cannot with impunity be ignored in any
printed record of the poet's career.  In a long and exhaustive
reply to Burton's charges, Poe writes to Dr. Snodgrass:
</p><p>"In fine, I pledge you before God the solemn word of a
gentleman that I am temperate even to rigor.  From the hour in
which I first saw this basest of calumniators to the hour in which
I retired from his office in incontrollable disgust at his
chicanery, arrogance, ignorance, and brutality, nothing stronger
than water ever passed my lips.  It is, however, due to candor that
I inform you upon what foundation he has erected his slanders.  At
no period of life was I ever what men call intemperate; I never was
in the <hi rend="italic">habit</hi> of intoxication [the italics are Poe's]; I
never drank drams, <hi rend="italic">et cetera;</hi> but for a brief period, while
I resided in Richmond and edited the <hi rend="italic">Messenger</hi>, I
certainly
<pb n="528"/>
did give way, at long intervals, to the temptation held
out on all sides to the spirit of Southern conviviality.  My
sensitive temperament could not stand an excitement which was an
every-day matter to my companions.  For some days after each excess
I was invariably confined to bed.  But it is now quite four years
since I have abandoned every kind of alcoholic drink&mdash;four years,
with the exception of a single deviation that occurred shortly
after my leaving Burton, and when I was induced to resort to the
occasional use of cider with the hope of relieving a nervous
attack.  You will thus see, frankly stated, the whole amount of my
sin.
</p><p>"The accusation (Burton's) can be disproved by each and every
man with whom I am in the habit of daily intercourse.  I have now
only to repeat to you, in general, my solemn assurance that my
habits are as far removed from intemperance as the day from the
night."
</p><p>And this was also the consensus of opinion of those who knew
Poe intimately up to the time of his death.  He had unquestionably
an abnormal sensitiveness to drink&mdash;a single glass of the mildest
liquor would affect him to the point of stupefaction; but he was in
no sense a habitual drinker or a dissolute man, as he has been
painted by his detractors for fully half a century&mdash;since his
untimely death at the hands of the political "repeaters" of
Baltimore.  Alas, poor Poe!  Was not your punishment in life, your
poverty, your anguish of privation, a sufficiently terrible
expiation for your occasional lapses of will, that your memory
should be held up to the execration of posterity by those unfit to
loose the latchets of your shoes?
</p><p>To-day we honor Willis, who in life fraternized with Poe as a
companion and a gentleman, worthy of the friendship of the ideal
Chevalier Bayard of his time.  We concede the laurel of genius to
the lamented Poe, but we stab him in the back while proffering it,
and prelude the study of his matchless genius with materialistic
and abhorrent pictures of his personal character.
</p><p>We are told that a Poe propaganda, which will reform all the
injustice that has been done to the immortal author of "The
<pb n="529"/>
Raven," is to illumine the closing hours of the waning century.  We
who honor not our own prophets, but have given most liberally of
our tribute to the memorials of English authors and have aided in
preserving the homes of Shakespeare, Carlyle, and other luminaries
of the mother tongue, are asked to believe that public interest
will, at no distant day, be awakened in "the unhappy master whom
unmerciful disaster followed fast and followed faster."
</p><p>In the half-century that has passed since the spirit of Poe
"conquered the fever called living" in his untimely death at
Baltimore, the world of letters has awakened to a realizing sense
of the majestic proportions of this chameleon-like genius&mdash;"this
diamond that sparkled even in the darkness," as the late Edwin P.
Whipple has said.  And when another decade has rounded out a full
century since his birth in that eventful year (1809) which also
gave to the literary world a Charles Dickens and an Oliver Wendell
Holmes, we may look for a recognition of the great Southern poet
that shall be worthy of his peerless genius.
</p>
<closer>
<signed>WILLIAM FEARING GILL.</signed>
                              <dateline>Paris, France.</dateline>
</closer>

</div1>
</body>
</text>
</TEI.2>
