<?xml version="1.0"?>

<?dlps id="GilWome"?>
<?dlps page-images="none" figure-images="no"?>
<?dlps transcription="other"?>

<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/tei-p4/tei2.dtd" [
<!ENTITY % POSTKB "INCLUDE">
<!ENTITY % TEI.extensions.ent SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.ent">
<!ENTITY % TEI.extensions.dtd SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.dtd">
<!ENTITY % ISOnum SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/charent/iso-num.ent"> %ISOnum;
<!ENTITY % ISOpub SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/charent/iso-pub.ent"> %ISOpub;

]>

<TEI.2 id="GilWome">
<teiHeader type="migrated" creator="Etext">
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title type="main">Women Who Go to College</title>
<title type="sort">women who go to college</title>
<author>Gilman, Arthur</author>
<respStmt>
<resp>Creation of machine-readable version</resp>
<name>Judy Boss</name>
</respStmt>
<respStmt>
<resp>Conversion to TEI-conformant markup</resp>
<name>University of Virginia Library Electronic Text Center</name>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt>
<extent>ca. <num type="kilobytes">25</num> kilobytes</extent>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>University of Virginia Library</publisher>
<pubPlace>Charlottesville, Virginia</pubPlace>
<idno type="ETC">GilWome</idno>
<date value="1994">1994</date>
<availability status="public">
<p n="copyright">Copyright &copy; 1994 by the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia</p>
<p n="access">Publicly accessible</p>
</availability>
<idno type="uva-pid">uva-lib:475985</idno>
</publicationStmt>
<seriesStmt>
<title>University of Virginia Library, Text collection</title>
<idno type="uva-set">UVA-LIB-Text</idno>
</seriesStmt>
<sourceDesc>
<biblFull>
<titleStmt>
<title type="main">Women Who Go to College</title>
<title type="sort">women who go to college</title>
<author>Arthur Gilman</author>
</titleStmt>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>Century Magazine</publisher>
<pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
<date value="1888">1888</date>
</publicationStmt>
<seriesStmt>
<p>Volume 36</p>
</seriesStmt>
</biblFull>
</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc>
<encodingDesc>
<projectDesc>
<p>Prepared for the University of Virginia Library Electronic Text Center</p>
</projectDesc>
<editorialDecl>
<p>All quotation marks retained as data</p>
<p>All unambiguous end-of-line hyphens have been removed, and the
trailing part of a word has been joined to the preceding line.</p>
<p id="ETC">Keywords in the header are a local Electronic Text Center scheme
to aid in establishing analytical groupings</p>
</editorialDecl>
<refsDecl>
<p>ID elements are given for each page element and are composed of the text's
unique cryptogram and the given page number, as in SpeFQue1 for page one of
Spenser's Faerie Queene.</p>
</refsDecl>
</encodingDesc>
<profileDesc>
<creation>
<date value="1888">1888</date>
</creation>
<langUsage>
<language id="eng" usage="main">English</language>
</langUsage>
<textClass>
<keywords>
<term>non-fiction; prose</term>
</keywords>
</textClass>
</profileDesc>
<revisionDesc>
<change>
<date value="1994-10">October 1994</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>corrector</resp>
<name>Monique Dull</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Conversion to basic TEI-conformant markup</item>
</change>
<change>
<date value="2005-07">July 2005</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>Corrector</resp>
<name>John Ivor Carlson</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Converted SGML to XML. Fixed tagging.</item>
</change>
<change>
<date value="2007-09">September 2007</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>Migration</resp>
<name>Ethan Gruber, University of Virginia Library</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Converted XML markup from TEI Lite to uva-dl-tei (TEI P4 with local customizations).</item>
</change>
<change>
<date value="2008-01">January 2008</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>Migration</resp>
<name>Greg Murray, University of Virginia Library</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Programmatically updated TEI header markup (but not header content) for minimal compliance with current QA requirements.</item>
</change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text id="d1">
<body id="d2">
	<div1 type="essay" id="d3"><pb n="714"/>
<head>Gilman, Arthur.  "Women Who Go to College."  <hi rend="italic"> Century Magazine</hi>
36 (1888): 714-718.
</head>

<p>It could be truthfully said thirty years ago that there was no
system in woman's education, and one need not go far backward in
the history of the subject to reach the time when, so far as any
advanced instruction whatever is concerned, woman was almost
completely overlooked.  In the Middle Ages, when education was an
accomplishment of the very few, and was considered a necessity for
no one except the professional clerics, and not always for them,
women had a chance to get the small measure of learning that was
within the reach of common men.  As the world in general grew
wiser, women were left behind and were obliged to satisfy in
private any scholarly longings that they might have, or to sit
illiterate in their towers embroidering shields for graceless
Launcelots and singing the "song of love and death."
</p><p>It happened that at the time when Chaucer was in Italy
learning the story of Patient Griselda,&mdash;in 1372,&mdash;the subject of
the education of women was brought to the attention of a worthy
father in France by thoughts of his three motherless daughters.
He, the knight of La Tour Landry, was led to prepare a book to be
used for the education of his own girls and of others.  The
treatise has been called a "monument of medieval literature."  It
is a phenomenally indecent book, and if it were exposed for sale
to-day would be carried off by the police.  This fond father
limited the intellectual progress of his daughters to the reading
of this book&mdash;and what reading!  They might sew and brush and do
the thousand and one housewifely works that have always been
considered commendable in the sex; but as for any training of the
mind, it could not be allowed.  Down to our own time many persons
have not advanced far beyond this father of La Tour Landry.  They
have thought that if women were suffered to eat of the tree of
knowledge the rest of the family would at once "be reduced to the
same kind of aerial diet," as Sydney Smith said; and have believed
that an educated mother would be "in danger of deserting her infant
for a quadratic equation."  It was but the other day that a
philosophical lecturer in a British capital declared that women, if
educated, will cease to be sympathetic; they will be "cultured,"
but not "self-denying"; they will lack a thousand nameless graces
and charms of manner which uneducated women are probably supposed
to possess.
</p><p>It is not worth our while to contemplate the ages between
Chaucer and our own days.  We need only refer to Milton's scheme
for education, confined as it was to men only.  Any plan of
instruction for the weaker sex was not to be expected from an
author who could put into the mouth of his despondent hero the
words:
</p>
<lg type="verse">
<l>                        Oh, why did God,</l>
<l>Creator wise, that peopled highest heaven</l>
<l>With spirits masculine, create at last</l>
<l>This novelty on earth, this fair defect</l>
<l>Of Nature, and not fill the earth at once</l>
<l>With men as angels?</l>
</lg>
<p>The story of the progress of the education of women, even in
the most favored portions of the world, is one of strange
reluctance to give any advantage to the sex.  Many of us have been
taught to point to the inhabitants of New England as examples of
remarkable care for education.  We picture them as planting the
school by the side of the meeting-house when they landed, and as
building the college when the air was still lurid with the flames
of their smoking cabins and their lives in danger from the
tomahawk; but we forget that their schools were not for women.
They thought that education was something adapted to fit a boy to
be a minister, or to prepare him for some other liberal calling;
but as for mothers and sisters, they might still sit and spin, they
might embroider and cook, they might read and write (if they did
not print anything), but as for looking into a work on science, or
a book in Latin or Greek, that could hardly be imagined.  Schools
were provided, it is true, at an early period for "all children,"
but there was only one sex thought of in that connection.  It is
less than a century ago that a school was established in Boston for
both boys and girls, and even then the girls were allowed to attend
but half of the year.  The first high school for girls was not
opened there until 1825, and it was soon shut up because it was too
expensive!  Forty-five hundred dollars had been wasted in eight
months on a few girls.  They were after that kept out of the high
school until 1852; and before 1877, when a Latin school was
established for their special convenience, they were debarred from
that mode of preparing for college.
</p><p>In the mean time Vassar College had begun
<pb n="715"/>  its good
work.  The opening of that institution, in 1865, marks an era.
During the years of civil war, when the armies of the republic were
engaged in their great struggle and the fortunes of the nation hung
in the balance, the millionaire of Poughkeepsie was quietly
preparing the foundation for the first fully endowed institution
for the collegiate instruction of women that the world ever saw.
Mr. Vassar said that it was his intention to accomplish for women
"what our colleges are accomplishing for men."  This was simple
enough and broad enough.  It is charming to observe how deeply the
pioneer trustees of this woman's college were impressed by the
grandeur of their work, and how naively they expressed their
sentiments.  It was "of vital consequence"; it was "a grand and
novel enterprise"; they were burdened with "responsibilities before
the world"; they were "clothed by the majesty of the law with
power" to carry out the generous purpose of the "munificent donor,"
whose act was excelled by none among the memorable events which
signalized the early months of the year 1861, a time certainly rich
in events of profound interest.  They said that they looked forward
to the opening of Vassar College as the beginning of a new era in
the education of women.
</p><p>The power of the time-honored opinions regarding the sphere of
woman is plain enough.  Deference to them led the projectors to lay
much stress upon the domestic, home influences that were to be
exerted; to warrant parents that there would be "comfort," and
"abundant food"; that the students would be surrounded by
"softening" and "elevating" influences&mdash;lest, perhaps, they should
degenerate into barbarism!  The idea was emphasized still more in
the statement that there should be no day pupils, because there are
no such in the home.
</p><p>A protest was made against some of the methods that were said
to be thoroughly established in our old institutions, and a
determination was expressed that Vassar, having no traditions to
bind it, should begin aright.  It was assumed that the students
would not be looking to the learned professions, like men, for
teaching was at the time not supposed to fall into that category.
</p><p>Arguments were brought against the usual order of college
studies, and especially against the required four-years' course,
then nearly universal.  Vassar was to follow "the order of nature,"
and to make provision for "a diversity of tastes, aptitudes, and
inclinations"&mdash;for different conditions and circumstances as to
age, health, and property.  The curriculum was to be no "bed of
Procrustes, to which every girl must adjust herself, however great
the violence done to her nature."  Students were not to be told
that there was a certain number of text-books to be studied from
Preface to Index each year, nor encouraged to plod contentedly
through them in the best way they were able, whether the subjects
proved attractive or not.
</p><p>It was the plan of the first president and the founder that
the college should be arranged in departments, and the students
were to carry on their work by subjects, and be largely left to
their own choice, though required to accomplish a definite amount
before graduation; text-books were to be discarded from the class-room.  Thus the tendency towards the elective system, now so strong
in most colleges for men, and so much more desirable for women, was
anticipated.  The founders of the new college aimed at thorough and
vigorous cultivation, rather than at too comprehensive and
superficial training.  The students were to be taught to "direct
the faculties with their utmost power to the accomplishment of any
task"; time was not to be taken into the account, in order to avoid
feverish haste and to make it possible to cultivate the desired
thoroughness without fear of falling behind in a race limited to
four brief years.  The college diplomas were to show that certain
work had been done and well done, to represent something real, and
not simply to indicate that the young woman had "been in college
four years and paid her bills."  Finally, Vassar promised to
educate woman on the religious side, and to care assiduously also
for her physical life.  Acting in the spirit of the founder, the
trustees declared that they "utterly loathed and repudiated" the
spirit of sectarianism, and ordained that "all teaching of human
creeds, dogmas, and ceremonials, of sectarian views and
denominational distinctions," should be "strictly and forever
forbidden."
</p><p>Thus, upon a firm and broad foundation, Vassar began its work
in 1865, and the first admission examinations showed that it was
needed, for they proved that the education of woman at the time was
confused, barren, undisciplined, wasteful, and superficial.  The
candidates had earnestness of purpose, but they did not know what
they needed.  They declared, in the language of the young lady of
the day, that they were "passionately fond" of one study, and
"utterly detested" another, though they were not well enough
acquainted with either to give intelligent reasons for the tastes
that they so strongly expressed.  They thought, for instance, that
chemistry was desirable, because it might help them in the kitchen;
and French, because
<pb n="716"/>  it would serve in case of a foreign
tour; though they had no knowledge of educational discipline and
cared less for it.
</p><p>No wonder that the faculty had difficulty in dealing with the
students thus cast upon them.  In the heterogeneous medley there
were some who appreciated the difficulties, and supported their
instructors in their efforts to set up and maintain a high
standard, and by the end of the first year college opinion was all
one way.  The same sentiment has prevailed in all colleges for
women; the students have uniformly demanded that the standard
should be kept up, and that they should be submitted to the
strictest tests required in any institution for men.
</p><p>Collegiate instruction for women in America encountered the
usual reception given to all innovations.  Vassar College and its
students became the objects of many weak jokes.  The students were
jibed at as women who "wanted to be men," as college women have
been jibed at elsewhere.  The name Vassar was carried everywhere.
It became typical, and still is.  Other colleges have risen, but
Vassar remains the woman's college at which the small wit hurls his
puny darts.  The "Vassar girl" still stands for the girl who goes
to college, and about her we hear all sorts of stories, more or
less apocryphal.  The new college encountered opposition from even
good people; many had grave doubts; but the select few welcomed it,
and it went steadily on its way.  It was followed by Wellesley,
Smith, Wells, and Bryn Mawr, and the "Harvard Annex," as it is
called, also entered upon its successful career.
</p><p>There is variety in the colleges for women.  At Vassar the
students are sheltered in one great building and are taught by both
men and women.  At Wellesley there was at first the same sort of
grand dormitory, but it has become the center of a group which
allows smaller clusters of students to gather under more home-like
conditions.  The teachers there are women only.  At Smith men and
women teach together, as at Vassar, but the students are separated
into small groups under different roofs.  The "Harvard Annex" has
a character all its own.  It did not seek to gather a new faculty,
nor to erect imposing dormitories, but simply to repeat to women
instruction already given to men in an institution that has been in
successful operation two and a half centuries.  It carries out the
"home" principle farther than either Vassar or Smith or Wellesley,
for it aims to place its students by twos and by threes in
established families.
</p><p>Certainly woman has now obtained opportunity for the
collegiate education.  Wherever she has been admitted to college,
and whenever she has been permitted to compete with men on equal
terms for intellectual honors, she has done herself credit.
Nowhere has this been so emphatically true as in conservative
England.  In a paper on the mental inferiority of woman to man,
published in the "Nineteenth Century," it was shown that "the
average brain-weight of women is about five ounces less than that
of men," and by an elaborate and interesting argument woman's
"marked inferiority of intellectual power" was proved in detail.
We were told that women are more apt then men to break away from
the restraints of reason; that they have greater fondness for
emotional excitement of all kinds; that in judgment their minds are
considerably below those of men; that in creative thought and in
simple acquisition there is a marked difference; that women are
less deep and thorough than men; that "their physique is not
sufficiently robust to stand the strain of severe study," and so
on.</p><note place="foot" n="1"><p>1The author of this paper, Mr. George J.
Romanes, writes with evident calmness and self-restraint.  He frankly
confesses that as a matter of fact he has met "wonderfully
few cases of serious break-downs"; which only goes to show,
he says, "of what good stuff our English girls are made."
Since American observers notice the same phenomenon, we are
at liberty to reply that the fact mentioned does <hi rend="italic"> not</hi> go to
show "of what good stuff our English girls are made," but
rather to prove that the "physique of young women as a class"
<hi rend="italic"> is</hi> "sufficiently robust to stand the strain of severe
study" and actually to improve under it.</p></note>

<p>Scarcely had this argument for the general inferiority of
women in "acquisition, origination, and judgment" reached us when
the telegraph flashed the news that Miss Ramsay, a student at
Girton College, Cambridge, England, had distanced all the men in
the university in the race for classical honors, and that Miss
Hervey, of the same college, had won like distinction in the
department of Medieval and Modern Languages.  The London "Times"
said in this connection:
</p><p>
Miss Ramsay has done what no Senior Classic before her has
ever done.  The great names of Kennedy, Lushington, Wordsworth,
Maine, and more recently of Butler and Jebb, have come first in the
Classical Tripos; Miss Ramsay alone has been placed in a division
to which no one but herself has been found deserving of admittance.
. . .  No one has ventured to think that four years' work could be
enough to make a Senior Classic.  We have proof that it is ample.
Most of Miss Ramsay's competitors will have taken fourteen years to
do less than she has contrived to do in four years.  Miss Ramsay's
example suggests a possibility that men may have something to learn
in the management of a department of study which they have claimed
as peculiarly their own.

</p><p>To this it may be added that Miss Ramsay kept herself in full
health, did not overwork, and accomplished her examinations easily.
<pb n="717"/>
</p><p>In the face of facts like these and of many more that might be
adduced, we cannot believe that nature has placed before woman any
constitutional barrier to the collegiate life, but that so far as
physical reasons are concerned, she may enter upon it with no more
fear than a man may.  That an increasing number of women will do
this, and that it is best for the state that all should do it who
are destined to be instructors of the youth of the republic, is in
my mind not at all doubtful.
</p><p>What is to be the result?  That is the crucial question.  On
the physical health of the educated woman it will be beneficial.
Observation, so far as it is now possible, shows that the work of
the full college course is favorable to bodily health.  The
regularity of life, the satisfaction of attainment, the pleasant
companionship, the general broadening of the girl-nature, tend in
that direction.  Speaking of "nervous or neuropathic" young women,
Dr. Charles Follen Folsom, of the department of nervous diseases in
the Boston Hospital, writes that it is his opinion that "the higher
education is a conservative rather than a destructive
force."<note place="foot" n="1"><p>1"Relations of our Public Schools
to the Disorders of the Nervous System," p. 187.</p></note>
</p>
<p>On schools I have already said that the effect is good.  The
grade of instruction in establishments for girls has been
materially raised since Vassar College began, and those pupils who
go no further than the primary schools are much benefited.  The
influence is reflex, for the educated girls become in turn
teachers, and they are better teachers than their predecessors.
Many college-bred girls never teach.  Neither do all college-bred
men.  They go out into the world and raise the average of general
intelligence; they elevate their own households and exert an
influence in the sphere of the private citizen.  The standard is
raised at home, and home is the fountainhead.
</p><p>Women who marry after having been liberally educated make more
satisfactory unions than they otherwise would have made.  Women
were formerly trained to no outlook but matrimony, and were
encouraged to cultivate no accomplishments not considered useful to
that end.  When, therefore, that end was missed, all was missed.
There was no outlet of action in which the energies of her feelings
might be discharged.  Such a defective education, adapted to
heighten emotional sensibility, and to weaken the reasoning powers,
tended to increase the predominance of the affective life and to
lead woman to base her judgment upon feelings and intuitive
perceptions rather than upon rational processes, and to direct her
conduct by impulse rather than to control it by will.
</p><p>Educated women marry as naturally as others; but the fact that
mental training has led them to subject their impulses to reason
gives them an advantage in the choice of husbands, and it may well
be expected that ill-considered marriages will be decreased in
number.  The rector of the University of Liege devoted his
inaugural address in 1862 to the subject of the education of women,
and remarked:
</p><p>
In Belgium and France most young persons in the higher
classes&mdash;sons of the rich or of those who expect to be rich&mdash;are
sunk in deplorable ignorance.  They pursue no kind of higher
studies, or if they enter upon them, they are very soon
discouraged.  To what does this tend?  It causes them to be almost
always without any inspiration to the taste, without any habit of
serious occupation.  They live in an atmosphere in which
intellectual labor is not honored, in which, far from considering
it a glorious or even a worthy duty, it is placed below the
satisfaction of the love of pleasure.  This deplorable situation
arises from the false education given to the women of the higher
classes.  As a general rule they cannot comprehend what constitutes
the true power and dignity of a man, and therefore they accept as
husbands men as ignorant and as idle as themselves.  As a natural
consequence they cannot bring up their sons to be men; they cannot
give to their country well-instructed, devoted, and energetic
citizens.

</p><p>I have been told, even in cultivated, intellectual circles,
that a young woman had better be in the kitchen or laundry than in
the laboratory or class-room of a college.  "Women should be
trained," such persons say, "to be wives and mothers."  The finger
of scorn has been lightly pointed at the mentally cultivated
mothers and daughters who are unable to cook and scrub, who cannot
make a mince-pie or a plum-pudding.  Such persons forget with
surprising facility all the cases of women who neglect the kitchen
to indulge in the love-sick sentimentality to which they have been
trained; who think too much of possible matrimonial chances to
endanger them by scrubbing, or by giving ground for the suspicion
that they cultivate any other faculty than the power to
apostrophize the moonlight and to long for a lover.  They do not
care to remember that it is no whit better to wither under the
influence of ignorance or sentiment, to cultivate a fondness for
"gush," than to dry up the sensibilities like a book-worm, or grow
rigid and priggish as a pedant.  It is as bad to stunt human nature
as to over-stimulate it&mdash;to stop its progress in one way as in
another.  The danger is in going to extremes.  The mass of men
choose the golden mean, and we may trust women to avoid
extravagance in the pursuit of learning.  We may and ought to give
her every help in the direction of life that her brothers possess.
It is no <pb n="718"/>  longer doubtful, it is plain, that whatever other
rights woman should have, those of the intellectual kingdom ought
to be hers fully and freely.  She should be the judge herself of
how far she should go in exploring the mysteries of nature and of
science.
</p><p>It is not a question of putting all our girls through college;
it is not even a question of their being taught in the same
institutions and classes with men when they go to college.  The
form in which women shall be taught and the subjects that they
shall study are of minor importance at the moment, and time will
settle them in a natural way.  The great desideratum is that they
be given the collegiate education when they need it, and that they
be the judges of their own needs.
</p>
<signed> <hi rend="italic"> Arthur Gilman.</hi></signed>

</div1>
</body>
</text>
</TEI.2>
