<?xml version="1.0"?>

<?dlps id="GlaFles"?>
<?dlps page-images="none" figure-images="no"?>
<?dlps transcription="other"?>

<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/tei-p4/tei2.dtd" [
<!ENTITY % POSTKB "INCLUDE">
<!ENTITY % TEI.extensions.ent SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.ent">
<!ENTITY % TEI.extensions.dtd SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.dtd">
<!ENTITY % ISOnum SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/charent/iso-num.ent"> %ISOnum;
<!ENTITY % ISOpub SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/charent/iso-pub.ent"> %ISOpub;
]>

<TEI.2 id="GlaFles">
<teiHeader type="migrated" creator="Etext">
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title type="main">The Man of Flesh and Blood.</title>
<title type="sort">man of flesh and blood</title>
<author>Glaspell, Susan, 1882-1948</author>
<respStmt>
<resp>Creation of machine-readable version:</resp>
<name>Judy Boss</name>
<resp>Conversion to TEI.2-conformant markup:</resp>
<name>University of Virginia Library Electronic Text Center</name>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt>
<extent>ca. <num type="kilobytes">33</num> kilobytes</extent>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>University of Virginia Library</publisher>
<pubPlace>Charlottesville, Virginia</pubPlace>
<idno type="ETC">GlaFles</idno>
<date value="1995">1995</date>
<availability status="public">
<p n="copyright">Copyright &copy; 1995 by the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia</p>
<p n="access">Publicly accessible</p>
</availability>
<idno type="uva-pid">uva-lib:475987</idno>
</publicationStmt>
<seriesStmt>
<title>University of Virginia Library, Text collection</title>
<idno type="uva-set">UVA-LIB-Text</idno>
</seriesStmt>
<sourceDesc>
<biblFull>
<titleStmt>
<title type="main">The Man of Flesh and Blood</title>
<title type="sort">man of flesh and blood</title>
<author>Susan Keating Glaspell</author>
</titleStmt>
<editionStmt>
<p>1st Edition</p>
</editionStmt>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>Harper's Monthly</publisher>
<pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
<date value="1904">1904</date>
</publicationStmt>
</biblFull>
</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc>
<encodingDesc>
<projectDesc>
<p>Prepared for the University of Virginia Library Electronic Text Center</p>
</projectDesc>
<editorialDecl>
<p>All quotation marks retained as data</p>
<p>Verification made against printed text.</p>
<p>All unambiguous end-of-line hyphens have been removed, and the
trailing part of a word has been joined to the preceding line.</p>
<p id="ETC">Keywords in the header are a local Electronic Text Center scheme
to aid in establishing analytical groupings</p>
</editorialDecl>
<refsDecl>
<p>ID elements are given for each page element and are composed of the text's
unique cryptogram and the given page number, as in AusEmma1 for page one of
Jane Austen's Emma.</p>
</refsDecl>
</encodingDesc>
<profileDesc>
<creation>
<date value="1908">1908</date>
</creation>
<langUsage>
<language id="eng" usage="main">English</language>
</langUsage>
<textClass>
<keywords>
<term>fiction ; prose</term>
<term>Women Writers</term>
</keywords>
</textClass>
</profileDesc>
<revisionDesc>
<change>
<date value="1995-04">April 1995</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>corrector</resp>
<name>Kelly Moulton</name>
</respStmt>
<item>TEI tagging</item>
</change>
<change>
<date value="2005-07">July 2005</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>Corrector</resp>
<name>John Ivor Carlson</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Converted SGML to XML. Fixed tagging.</item>
</change>
<change>
<date value="2007-09">September 2007</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>Migration</resp>
<name>Ethan Gruber, University of Virginia Library</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Converted XML markup from TEI Lite to uva-dl-tei (TEI P4 with local customizations).</item>
</change>
<change>
<date value="2008-01">January 2008</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>Migration</resp>
<name>Greg Murray, University of Virginia Library</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Programmatically updated TEI header markup (but not header content) for minimal compliance with current QA requirements.</item>
</change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>
<text id="d1">
<body id="d2">

<div1 type="story" id="d3">

<pb n="957"/>
	<head>
		Glaspell, Susan Keating.  "The Man of Flesh and Blood."  <lb/>
		<hi rend="italic"> Harper's Monthly</hi> 108 (May 1904): 957-963.
	</head>
<p>THE elements without were not in harmony with the spirit which it
was desired should be engendered within.  By music, by gay
decorations, by speeches from prominent men, the board in charge of
the boys' reformatory was striving to throw about this dedication
of the new building an atmosphere of cheerfulness and good-will &mdash;
an atmosphere vibrant with the kindness and generosity which emanated
from the State, and the thankfulness, appreciation, and loyalty
which it was felt should emanate from the boys.</p><p>
     Outside the world was sobbing.  Some young trees which had
been planted along the driveway of the reformatory grounds, and
which it was desired should grow up in the way they should go,
were
rocking back and forth in passionate insurrection.  Fallen leaves
were being spit viciously through the air.  It was a
sullen-looking
landscape which Philip Grayson, he who was to be the last speaker
of the afternoon, saw stretching itself down the hill, across the
little valley, and up another little hill.  In his ears was the
death wail of the summer.  It seemed the spirit of the
out-of-doors
was sending itself up in mournful, hopeless cries.</p><p>
     The speaker who had been delivering himself of pedantic
encouragement about the open arms with which the world stood
ready
to receive the most degraded one, would that degraded one but
come
to the world in proper spirit, sat down amid perfunctory applause
led by the officers and attendants of the institution, and the
boys
rose to sing.  The brightening of their faces told that their
work
as performers was more to their liking than their position as
auditors.  They threw back their heads, and waited with a kind of
well-disciplined eagerness for the signal to begin.  Then, with
the
strength and native music there are in some three hundred boys'
throats, there rolled out the words of the song of the
State.</p><p>
     There were lips which opened only because they must, but as
a
whole they sang with the same heartiness, the same joy in
singing,
that he had heard a crowd of public-school boys put into the song
only the week before.  When the last word had died away, there
was
over the whole crowd of them a look of well-defined regret, and
it
seemed to Philip Grayson that the sigh of the world without was
giving voice to the sigh of the world within as the well-behaved
crowd of boys sat down to resume their duties as auditors.</p><p>
     And then one of the most important of the professors from
the
State University was telling them about the kindness of the
State:
the State had provided for them this beautiful home; it gave them
comfortable, neat clothing and well-tasting, nutritious food; it
provided that fine gymnasium in which to train their bodies; it
provided books and teachers to train their minds; it provided
those
fitted to train their souls, to work against the unfortunate
tendencies&mdash;the professor stumbled a little there&mdash;which had led
to
their coming.  The State gave liberally, gladly, and in return it
asked but one thing: that they come out into the world and make
useful, upright citizens, citizens of which any State might be
proud.  Was that asking too much? the professor from the State
University was saying.</p><p>
     The sobbing of the world without was growing more intense.
Many pairs of eyes from among the auditors were straying out to
where the summer lay a-dying.  Did they know&mdash;those boys whom the
State classed as unfortunates&mdash;that out of this death there would
come again life?  Or did they see but the darkness&mdash;the decay&mdash;of
to-day?</p><p>
     The professor from the State University was putting the case
very fairly.  There were no flaws&mdash;seemingly&mdash;to be picked in his
logic.  The State had been kind; the boys were obligated to good

<pb n="958"/>  citizenship.  But the coldness!&mdash;comfortlessness!&mdash;of it
all.
The open arms of the world!&mdash;how mocking in its abstractness.
What
did it mean?  Did it mean that they&mdash;the men who uttered the
phrase
so easily&mdash;would be willing to give those boys aid, friendship,
when they came out into the world?  What would they say, those
boys
whose ears were filled with high-sounding, non-committal phrases,
if some man were to stand before them and say, "And so, fellows,
when you get away from this place, and are ready to get your
start
in the world, just come around to my office and I'll help you get
a job"?  At thought of it there came from Philip Grayson a queer,
partly audible laugh, which caused those nearest him to look his
way in surprise.</p><p>
     But he was all unconscious of their looks of inquiry, for
his
brain was growing hot with the thoughts that crowded upon it.
How
far away the world&mdash;his kind of people&mdash;must seem to those boys
of
the State Reform School.  The speeches they had heard, the
training
that had been given them, had taught them&mdash;unconsciously perhaps,
but surely&mdash;to divide the world into two great classes: the lucky
and the unlucky, those who made speeches and those who must
listen,
the so-called good and the so-called bad; perhaps&mdash;he smiled a
little at his own cynicism&mdash;those who were caught and those who
were not.</p><p>
     There came over him then those divinely human words from a
poet whom he had always loved:
</p><p>
     In men whom men pronounce as ill,</p><p>
     I find so much of goodness still;</p><p>
     In men whom men pronounce divine,</p><p>
        I find so much of sin and blot;</p><p>
     I hesitate to draw the line</p><p>
        Between the two, when God has not.
</p><p>
     When God has not!  The words seemed to get into the very
bone
and fibre of Philip Grayson.  He turned and looked out at the
sullen sky, returning, as all men do at times&mdash;to that conception
of his childhood that somewhere beyond the clouds was God.  God!
Did God care for the boys of the State Reformatory?  Was that
poet
of the Western mountains right when he said that God was not a
drawer of lines, but a seer of the good that was in the so-called
bad, and of the bad that was in the so-called good, and a lover
of
them both?</p><p>
     If that was God, it was not the God the boys of the
reformatory had been taught to know.  They had been told that God
would forgive the wicked, but it had been made clear to them&mdash;if
not in words, in implications&mdash;that it was they who were the
wicked.  And the so-called godly men, men of such exemplary
character as had been chosen to address them that afternoon, had
so
much of the spirit of God that they, too, were willing to
forgive,
be tolerant, and&mdash;Philip Grayson looked out at the bending trees
with a smile&mdash;disburse generalities about the open arms of the
world.</p><p>
     What would they think&mdash;those three hundred speech-tired boys
of the State Reformatory&mdash;if some man who had been held before
them
as exemplary were to rise and lay bare his own life&mdash;its
weaknesses, its faults, its sins, perhaps its crimes&mdash;and tell
them
there was good and there was bad in every human being, and that
the
world-old struggle of life was to conquer one's bad with one's
good.</p><p>
     The idea took him in mighty grip.  It seemed the method of
the
world&mdash;at any rate it had been the method of that afternoon&mdash;for
the men who stood before their fellows with clean hands to plant
themselves on the far side of a chasm of conventions, or narrow
self-esteem, of easily bought virtue, and say to those beings who
struggled on the other side of that chasm&mdash;to those human beings
whose souls had never gone to school: "Look at us!  Our hands are
clean, our hearts are pure.  See how beautiful it is to be good!
Come ye, poor sinners, and be good also."  And the poor sinners,
the untaught, birthmarked human souls, would look over at the
self-acclaimed goodness which they could see far across the chasm, and
though they might feel somewhere deep within them faint stirrings
of that passion for good which, asleep or awake, is in everything
that is of God, they were uncertain about the depth of the chasm,
uncertain about that thing which awaited them beyond, and so the
passions which had behind them the strength of years outmatched
that passion which was but a possibility, and the untaught,
birthmarked human souls looked purposelessly across the man-made
chasm, and went on <pb n="959"/>  with the working out of
that thing which
is called destiny.</p><p>
     He was lost to the speaker now, lost to everything save this
great thought which was burning through and through him, and to
the
sobbing minor of the world without.  Was this chasm&mdash;this whole
idea&mdash;but a wild creation of his fancy?  With one of those great
sweeps which the human mind can make in moments of white heat, he
went back from the struggles of a primitive world up to the law-bounded philanthropy of his own time, and it seemed to him
then&mdash;he
could read it through the teachings of good and great men, and
through the policies of good and great kings&mdash;that the aloofness,
the self-centredness, the complacency of the good&mdash;</p><p>
     It was the shrill coughing of one of the three hundred which
brought him sharply back to the concrete.  He scanned the three
hundred faces of the auditors, and then he looked into the faces
of
those few men who had been set up as embodying the other side of
things.  And the world of concrete things to which he had
returned
but moved him to a new sense of the absurdity of that man-made
chasm, which was so real to him now that the chill from its
depths
seemed to blow over him and make him cold.  Were they not of the
same clay&mdash;the three hundred and the three?  Had they not the
same
fights to make, and the same sorrows to know?  If there was a
difference, it was only that the three had fought their fight,
had
known their sorrow, and should it be that they were among those
for
whom the battle of self was an easy battle, then out of an easy
victory should have been born a greater tolerance.</p><p>
     With what arrogance they had flaunted their virtue&mdash;their
position!  How condescendingly they had spoken of the home which
we, the good, prepare for you, the bad, and what namby-pambyness
there was, after all, in that sentiment which all of them had
voiced&mdash;and now you must pay us back by being good!</p><p>
     Oh for a man of flesh and blood to stand up and tell how he
himself had sinned and suffered!  For a man who could bridge that
damning chasm with strong, broad, human understanding and human
sympathies&mdash;a man who could stand among them pulse-beat to pulse-beat and cry out, "I know!  I understand!  I fought it, and I'll
help you fight it too!"</p><p>
     The sound of his own name broke the passionate, exalted
spell
that was upon him.  He looked to the centre of the stage and saw
that the professor from the State University had seated himself
and
that the superintendent of the institution was occupying the
place
of the speaker.  And the superintendent was saying:</p><p>
     "We may esteem ourselves especially fortunate in having him
with us this afternoon.  He is one of the great men of the State,
one of the men who by high living, by integrity and industry, has
raised himself to a position of great honor among his fellow men.

A great party&mdash;may I say the greatest of all parties?&mdash;has shown
its unbounded confidence in him by giving him the nomination for
the Governorship of the State.  No man in the State is held in
higher esteem to-day than he.  And so it is with special pleasure
that I introduce to you that man of the future&mdash;Philip
Grayson."</p><p>
     The superintendent sat down then, and he himself&mdash;Philip
Grayson&mdash;was standing in the place where the other speakers had
stood.  It was with a mighty rush which almost swept away his
outward show of calm that it came to him that he&mdash;candidate for
the
Governorship&mdash;was well fitted to be that man of flesh and blood
for
whom in his dreamy exaltation he had sighed.  That he&mdash;even
he&mdash;was
within grasp of an opportunity to get beneath the jackets and
into
the very hearts and souls of these boys, and make them feel that
a
man of sins and virtues, of weaknesses and strength, a man who
had
had much to conquer, and for whom the fight would never be quite
done, was standing before them stripped of his coat of
conventions
and platitudes, and in nakedness of soul and sincerity of heart
was
talking to them as a man who understood.</p><p>
     Almost with the inception of the idea was born the
consciousness of what it might cost.  And as in answer to the
silent, blunt question, Is it worth it? there looked up at him
three hundred pairs of eyes&mdash;eyes behind which there was good as
well as bad&mdash;eyes which had burned with the fatal rush of
passion,
and had burned, too, with the hot tears <pb n="960"/>  of
remorse&mdash;eyes
which no mother had ever kissed&mdash;eyes which had opened&mdash;</p><p>
     And then the eyes of Philip Grayson could not see those
other
eyes which were before him, and he put up his hand to break the
blinding mist&mdash;little caring what those men upon the platform
would
think of him, little thinking what effect the words which were
crowding into his heart would have upon his candidacy.  But one
thing was vital to him now: to bring upon that ugly chasm the
levelling forces of a throbbing humanity, and to make those boys
who were of his clay feel that a being who had fallen and risen
again, a being for whom life would always mean a falling and a
rising again, was standing before them, and&mdash;not as the
embodiment
of a distant goodness, not as a pattern, but as one among them,
verily as man to man&mdash;was telling them a few things which his own
life had taught him were true.</p><p>
     It was his very consecration which made it hard to begin.
He
was fearful of estranging them in the beginning, of putting
between
them and him that very thing he was determined there should not
be.
And it was not easy to unlock the chamber of one's heart when
that
chamber held much of which the world did not know.</p><p>
     "I have a strange feeling," he said, with a winning little
smile which had helped the candidate for Governor up many a
round,
"that if I were to open my heart to-day, just open it clear up
the
way I'd like to if I could, that you boys would look into it, and
then jump back in a scared kind of way and cry, 'Why&mdash;that's me!'

You would be a little surprised&mdash;wouldn't you?&mdash;if you could look
back and see the kind of boy I was, and find I was much the kind
of
boy you are?</p><p>
     "Do you know what I think?  I think hypocrisy is the worst
thing in the world.  I think it's worse than stealing, or lying,
or
any of the other bad things you can name.  And do you know where
I
think lots of the hypocrisy comes from?  I think it comes from
the
so-called self-made men&mdash;from the real good men, the men who say,
'I haven't got one bad thing charged up to my account.'</p><p>
     "Now the men out campaigning for me call me a self-made man.

Your superintendent just now spoke of my integrity, of the
confidence reposed in me, and all that.  But do you know what is
the honest truth?  If I am any kind of a man worth mentioning, if
I am deserving of any honor, any confidence, it is not because I
was born with my heart filled with good and beautiful things, for
I was not.  It is because I was born with much in my heart that
we
call the bad, and because, after that bad had grown stronger and
stronger through the years it was unchecked, and after it had
brought me the great shock, the great sorrow of my life, I began
then, when older than you boys are now, to see a little of that
great truth, which you can put, briefly, into these words: 'There
is good and there is bad in every human heart, and it is the
struggle of life to conquer the bad with the good.'  What I am
trying to say is, that if I am worthy any one's confidence
to-day,
it is because, having seen that truth, I have been able, through
never ceasing trying, through slow conquering, to crowd out some
of
the bad, and to make room for a little of the good.</p><p>
     "You see," he went on, three hundred pairs of eyes hard upon
him now, "some of us are born to a harder struggle than others.
There are people who study what is called ethics who might make a
fuss about that statement, and there are lots of people who would
object to my saying it to you, even if I believed it.  They would
say you would make the fact of being born with much against which
to struggle an excuse for being bad.  But look here a minute; if
you were born with a body not as strong as other boys' bodies, if
you couldn't run as far, or jump as high, you wouldn't be
eternally
saying, 'I can't be expected to do much; I wasn't born right.'
Not
a bit of it.  You'd make it your business to get as strong as you
could, and you wouldn't make any parade of the fact that you
weren't as strong as you should be.  We don't like people who
whine, whether it's about weak bodies or weak souls.</p><p>
     "I've been sitting here this afternoon wondering what to say
to you boys.  I had intended telling some funny stories about
things which happened to me when I was a boy.  But for some
reason
a sort of serious mood has come over me, and I
<pb n="961"/>  don't feel
just like those stories now.  I haven't been thinking of the
funny
side of life in the last half-hour.  I've been thinking instead
of
how much suffering I've endured since the days when I, too, was a
boy."</p><p>
     He paused then, his face twitching with earnestness.  At
last
he went on, his voice testing to the utmost the silence of the
room: "There is lots of sorrow in this old world.  It is sin
causes
most of the sorrow, and we all know there is plenty of sin.
Maybe
I'm on the wrong track, but as I see it to-day human beings are
making a much harder thing of their existence than there is any
need of.  There are millions and millions of them, and year after
year, generation after generation, they fight over the same old
battles, live through the same old sorrows.  Doesn't it seem all
wrong that after the battle has been fought a hundred million
times
it can't be made a little easier for those who still have it
before
them?</p><p>
     "If a farmer had gone over a very bad road, and the next day
saw another farmer about to start over the same road, wouldn't he
send him back?  Doesn't it seem too bad that in things which
concern one's whole life people can't be as decent as they are
about things which involve only an inconvenience?  Doesn't it
seem
that when we human beings have so much in common we might stand
together a little better?  I'll tell you what's the matter,&mdash;most
of the people of this world are coated round and round with self-esteem, and they're afraid to admit any understanding of the
things
which aren't good.  Suppose the farmer had thought it a disgrace
to
admit he had been over that road, and so had said: 'From what I
have read in books, and from what I have learned in a general
way,
I fancy that road isn't good.'  Would the other farmer have gone
back?  I rather think he would have said he'd take his chances.
But you see the farmer said he <hi rend="italic"> knew</hi>, and how did he know?
Why,
because he'd been over the road himself."</p><p>
     He looked down at them then with the almost overpowering
sense
of three hundred lives having been put in his keeping.  Deep down
in three hundred stormy and perhaps little understood hearts was
a
something which held wrapped within its own self the
possibilities
of manhood.  Looking down into the three hundred faces now turned
eagerly up to him, he was stern in the consciousness that if that
potential manhood, that something which could germinate into the
good, was not stirred to-day, it might enter soon upon its death
sleep.  It was with new force shining in his face he took a step
nearer the edge of the platform.  What he had done they could
do&mdash;
it was that he must show them.  As to the hurt it might do his
own
career, that was disposed of by the simpleness of the ratio of
three hundred to one.</p><p>
     It was thus he began, slowly, the telling of his life
story:</p><p>
     "I was born with strange, wild passions in my heart.  I
don't
know where they came from; I only knew they were there.  I
resented
authority.  If some one who had a right to dictate to me said,
'Philip, do this,' then Philip would immediately begin to think
how
much he would rather do the other thing.  And," he smiled a
little,
and some of the boys smiled with him in anticipation, "it was the
other thing which Philip usually did.</p><p>
     "I didn't go to a reform school, for the very good reason
that
there wasn't any in the State where I lived."  Some of the boys
smiled again, and he could hear the nervous coughing of one of
the
party managers sitting close to him.  "I was what you would call
a
very bad boy.  I didn't mind any one.  I was defiant&mdash;insolent.
I
did bad things just because I knew they were bad, and&mdash;and I took
a great deal of satisfaction out of it."</p><p>
     The sighing of the world without was the only sound which
vibrated through the room.  "I say," he went on, "that I got a
great deal of satisfaction out of it.  I did not say I got
happiness; there is a vast difference between a kind of momentary
satisfaction and that thing&mdash;that most precious of all things&mdash;
which we call happiness.  Indeed, I was very far from happy.  I
had
hours when I was so morose and miserable that I hated the whole
world.  And do you know what I thought?  I thought there was no
one
in all the world who had the same kind of things surging up in
their hearts that I did.  I thought there was no one else with
whom
it was as easy to be bad, or as hard to be good.  I thought that
no
<pb n="962"/>  one understood.  I thought that I was all
alone.</p><p>
     "Did you ever feel like that?  Did you ever feel that no one
ever knew anything about the feelings you had?  Did you ever feel
that here was you, and there was the rest of the world, and that
the rest of the world didn't know anything about you, and was
just
generally down on you?  Now that's the very thing I want to talk
away from you to-day.  You're not the only one.  We're all made
of
the same kind of stuff, and there's none of us made of stuff
that's
flawless.  We all have a fight: some an easy one, and some a big
one, and if you have formed the idea that there is a kind of
dividing-line in the world, and that on the one side is the good,
and on the other side is the bad, why, all I can say is that you
have a very ridiculous notion of things.</p><p>
     "Well, I grew up to be a man, and because I hadn't fought
against any of the bad things in my heart they kept growing
stronger and stronger.  I did lots of wild, bad things, things of
which I am bitterly ashamed.  I went to another place, and I fell
in with just the sort of set you can imagine I felt at home with.

I had been told when I was a boy that it was wrong to drink and
gamble.  I think that was the chief reason I took to drink and
gambling."</p><p>
     There was another cough, more pronounced this time, from the
party manager, and the superintendent was twisting rather
uneasily
in his seat.  It was the strangest speech that had ever been
delivered at the boys' reformatory.  The boys were leaning
forward
in their seats&mdash;self-forgetful, intent.  "One night I was playing
cards with a crowd of my friends, and one of the men, the best
friend I had, said something that made me mad.  There was a
revolver right there which one of the men had been showing us.
Some kind of a demon got hold of me, and without so much as a
thought I picked up that revolver and fired at my friend."</p><p>
     The party manager gave way to an audible exclamation of
horror, and the superintendent half rose from his seat.  But
before
any one could say a word Philip Grayson continued, looking at the
half-frightened faces before him: "I suppose you wonder why I am
not in the penitentiary.  I was wildly excited, and I missed my
aim, and I was with friends, and it was smoothed over."</p><p>
     He rested his hand upon the desk, and looked out at the
sullen
landscape.  His voice was not just steady as he went on: "It's
not
an easy thing to talk about, boys.  I never talked about it to
any
one before in all my life.  I'm not telling it now just to
entertain you or to create a sensation.  I'm telling it," his
voice
grew terrible in its earnestness, "because I believe in my heart
of
hearts that this world could be made a better and a sweeter place
if those who have lived, and sinned, and suffered would not be
afraid to reach out their hands and cry: 'I know that road&mdash;it's
bad!  I steered off to a better place, and I'll help you steer
off,
too.'"</p><p>
     There was not one of the three hundred pairs of eyes but was
riveted upon the speaker's colorless face.  The masks of
sullenness
and defiance had fallen from them.  They were listening now&mdash;not
because they must, but because into their hungry and thirsty
souls
was being poured the very sustenance for which&mdash;unknowingly&mdash;they
had yearned.</p><p>
     "We sometimes hear people say," resumed the candidate for
Governor, "that they have lived through hell.  If by that they
mean
they've lived through the deepest torments the human heart can
know, then I can say that I, too, have lived through hell.  What
I
suffered after I went home that night no one in this world will
ever know.  Words couldn't tell it; it's not the kind of thing
words can come anywhere near.  My whole life spread itself out
before me, and I saw it then in its blackness and its
hideousness.
But at last, boys, out of the depths of my darkness, I began to
get
a little light.  I began to get some understanding of the battle
which it falls to the lot of some of us human beings to wage.
There was good in me, you see, or I wouldn't have cared like
that,
and it came to me then, all alone that terrible night, that it is
the good which lies buried away somewhere in our hearts must
fight
out the bad.  And so&mdash;all alone, boys&mdash;I began the battle of
trying
to conquer the evil that was in my own soul.  And do you
know&mdash;this
is God's truth&mdash;it was with the beginning of that battle I got my
first taste of <pb n="963"/>  happiness.  There is no joy
in all the world
so great as that of winning, in your own heart, a victory for
good.
It was not easy&mdash;the power that is above me can testify to that.
I spent hours such as I hope few men have ever known, but out of
every victory came possibilities of victories to come.  I am not
standing here to-day and asking you to look upon me as a man who
has come into complete mastery of himself.  There are many times
when the old demonlike passion flames up within me; but I can say
in all humility that I have fought a great fight, and that I have
had some measure of success."</p><p>
     He leaned upon the table then, as though very weary.  "I
don't
know, I am sure, what the people of my State will think of all
this.  Perhaps they won't want a man for their Governor who once
tried to kill another man.  But," he looked around at them with
that smile of his which some way could go straight to men's
hearts,
"there's only one of me, and there's three hundred of you, and
how
do I know but that in telling you of that stretch of bad road
ahead
I've made a dozen Governors this very afternoon!  Wouldn't it be
a
greater thing to make a dozen Governors than to make just
one?"</p><p>
     He looked from row to row of them, trying to think of some
last word which would leave them with a sense of his sincerity.
What he did say was: "And so, boys, when you get away from here,
and go out into the world to get your start, if you find the arms
of that world aren't quite as wide open as you were told they
would
be, if there seems no place where you can get a hold, and you are
saying to yourself, 'It's no use&mdash;I'll not try,' before you
finally
give up just remember there was one man who said he knew all
about
it, and give that one man a chance to show he meant what he said.

So look me up, if luck goes all against you, and maybe I can give
you a little lift."  He took a backward step, as though to resume
his seat, and then he said, with a dry little smile which took
any
suggestion of heroics from what had gone before, "If I'm not at
the
State-house, you'll find my name in the directory of the city
where
I live."</p><p>
     He sat down, and there followed a moment of eloquent
silence.
Then full-souled, heart-given, came the applause.  It was not led
by the attendants this time; it was the attendants who rose at
last
to stop it.  And when the clapping of the hands had ceased, many
of
those hands were raised to brush away the tears which stood for
gratitude and hope.</p><p>
     The exercises were drawn to a speedy close, and he found the
party manager standing by his side.  "It was very grand," he
sneered, "very high-sounding and heroic, but I suppose you know,"
jerking his hand angrily toward a table where a reporter for the
leading paper of the opposition was writing, "that you've given
them the winning card."</p><p>
     As he replied, in far-off tone, "I hope so," the candidate
for
Governor, he who had laid bare his soul in all its one-time
blackness in order that out of that blackness the world might
know
a greater light, was looking, not at the reporter who was sending
out a new cry for the opposition, but into those faces aglow with
the light of greater understanding and brighter hopes.  He stood
there watching them filing out into the corridor, craning their
necks in order to throw him one last look of gratitude, and as he
turned then and looked from the window it was to see that the
storm
had sobbed itself away, and that along the driveway of the
reformatory grounds the young trees&mdash;unbroken and unhurt&mdash;were
rearing their heads towards God's heaven.</p>

</div1>
</body>
</text>
</TEI.2>
