<?xml version="1.0"?>

<?dlps id="GlaPoin"?>
<?dlps page-images="none" figure-images="no"?>
<?dlps transcription="other"?>

<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/tei-p4/tei2.dtd" [
<!ENTITY % POSTKB "INCLUDE">
<!ENTITY % TEI.extensions.ent SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.ent">
<!ENTITY % TEI.extensions.dtd SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.dtd">
<!ENTITY % ISOnum SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/charent/iso-num.ent"> %ISOnum;
<!ENTITY % ISOpub SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/charent/iso-pub.ent"> %ISOpub;
]>

<TEI.2 id="GlaPoin">
<teiHeader type="migrated" creator="Etext">
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title type="main">"A Point in Morals"</title>
<title type="sort">a point in morals</title>
<author>Glasgow, Ellen</author>
<respStmt>
<resp>Creation of machine-readable version:</resp>
<name>Judy Boss</name>
<resp>Conversion to TEI.2-conformant markup:</resp>
<name>University of Virginia Library Electronic Text Center</name>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt>
<extent>ca. <num type="kilobytes">30</num> kilobytes</extent>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>University of Virginia Library</publisher>
<pubPlace>Charlottesville, Virginia</pubPlace>
<idno type="ETC">GlaPoin</idno>
<date value="1995">1995</date>
<availability status="public">
<p n="copyright">Copyright &copy; 1995 by the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia</p>
<p n="access">Publicly accessible</p>
</availability>
<idno type="uva-pid">uva-lib:475990</idno>
</publicationStmt>
<seriesStmt>
<title>University of Virginia Library, Text collection</title>
<idno type="uva-set">UVA-LIB-Text</idno>
</seriesStmt>
<sourceDesc>
<biblFull>
<titleStmt>
<title type="main">"A Point in Morals"</title>
<title>
<hi rend="italic">Harper's New Monthly Magazine</hi> 98</title>
<title type="sort">a point in morals</title>
<author>Ellen Glasgow</author>
</titleStmt>
<publicationStmt>
<pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
<date value="1899-05">May 1899</date>
</publicationStmt>
<notesStmt>
<note>
<p>This story first appeared in Harper's New
Monthly Magazine 98, pages 976-982</p>
</note>
</notesStmt>
</biblFull>
</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc>
<encodingDesc>
<projectDesc>
<p>Prepared for the University of Virginia Library Electronic Text Center</p>
</projectDesc>
<editorialDecl>
<p>All quotation marks retained as data</p>
<p>All unambiguous end-of-line hyphens have been removed, and the
trailing part of a word has been joined to the preceding line.</p>
<p>The images exist as archived TIFF images, one or more JPEG versions
for general use, and thumbnail GIFs.</p>
<p id="ETC">Keywords in the header are a local Electronic Text Center scheme
to aid in establishing analytical groupings</p>
</editorialDecl>
<refsDecl>
<p>ID elements are given for each page element and are composed of the text's
unique cryptogram and the given page number, as in AusEmma1 for page one of
Jane Austen's Emma.</p>
</refsDecl>
</encodingDesc>
<profileDesc>
<creation>
<date value="1899-05">May 1899</date>
</creation>
<langUsage>
<language id="eng" usage="main">English</language>
</langUsage>
<textClass>
<keywords>
<term>fiction; prose</term>
<term>Women Writers</term>
</keywords>
</textClass>
</profileDesc>
<revisionDesc>
<change>
<date value="1995-12-13">December 13, 1995</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>corrector</resp>
<name>Jennifer Hanna</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Added TEI-compatible header and tags.</item>
</change>
<change>
<date value="2005-07">July 2005</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>Corrector</resp>
<name>John Ivor Carlson</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Converted SGML to XML. Fixed tagging.</item>
</change>
<change>
<date value="2007-09">September 2007</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>Migration</resp>
<name>Ethan Gruber, University of Virginia Library</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Converted XML markup from TEI Lite to uva-dl-tei (TEI P4 with local customizations).</item>
</change>
<change>
<date value="2008-01">January 2008</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>Migration</resp>
<name>Greg Murray, University of Virginia Library</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Programmatically updated TEI header markup (but not header content) for minimal compliance with current QA requirements.</item>
</change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text id="d1">
<body id="d2">
<div1 type="article" id="d3">
<head>A POINT IN MORALS.<lb/>
<lb/>
BY ELLEN GLASGOW.</head>
<pb n="976"/>
<p>"THE question seems to be&mdash;" began the Englishman.  He looked
up and bowed to a girl in a yachting-cap who had just come in from
deck and was taking the seat beside him.  "The question seems to
be&mdash;"  The girl was having some difficulty in removing her coat,
and he turned to assist her.
</p><p>"In my opinion," broke in a well-known alienist on his way to
a convention in Vienna, "the question is simply whether or not
civilization, in placing an exorbitant value upon human life, is
defeating its own aims."  He leaned forward authoritatively, and
spoke with a half-foreign precision of accent. <pb n="977"/>
</p><p>"You mean that the survival of the fittest is checkmated,"
remarked a young journalist travelling in the interest of a New
York daily, "that civilization should practise artificial
selection, as it were?"
</p><p>The alienist shrugged his shoulders deprecatingly.  "My dear
sir," he protested,  "I don't mean anything.  It is the question
that means something."
</p><p>"Well, as I was saying," began the Englishman again, reaching
for the salt and upsetting a spoonful, "the question seems to be
whether or not, under any circumstances, the saving of a human life
may become positively immoral."
</p><p>"Upon that point&mdash;" began the alienist:  but a young lady in
a pink blouse who was seated on the Captain's right interrupted
him.
</p><p>"How could it?" she asked.  "At least I don't see how it
could; do you, Captain?"
</p><p>"There is no doubt," remarked the journalist, looking up from
a conversation he had drifted into with a lawyer from one of the
Western States, "that the more humane spirit pervading modern
civilization has not worked wholly for good in the development of
the species.  Probably, for instance, if we had followed the
Spartan practice of exposing unhealthy infants, we should have
retained something of the Spartan hardihood.  Certainly if we had
been content to remain barbarians both our digestions and our
nerves would have been the better for it, and melancholia would
perhaps have been unknown.  But, at the same time, the loss of a
number of the more heroic virtues is overbalanced by an increase of
the softer ones.  Notably, human life has never before been
regarded so sacredly."
</p><p>"On the other side," observed the lawyer, lifting his hand to
adjust his eye-glasses, and pausing to brush a crumb from his coat,
"though it may all be very well to be philanthropic to the point of
pauperizing half a community and of growing squeamish about capital
punishment, the whole thing sometimes takes a disgustingly morbid
turn.  Why, it seems as if criminals were the real American heroes!
Only last week I visited a man sentenced to death for the murder of
his two wives, and, by Jove, the jailer was literally besieged by
women sympathizers.  I counted six bunches of heliotrope in his
cell, and at least fifty notes."
</p><p>"Oh, but that is a form of nervous hysteria!" said the girl in
the yachting-cap, "and must be considered separately.  Every
sentiment has its fanatics&mdash;philanthropy as well as religion.  But
we don't judge a movement by a few overwrought disciples."
</p><p>"That is true," said the Englishman, quietly.  He was a
middle-aged man, with an insistently optimistic countenance, and a
build suggestive of general solidity.  "But to return to the
original proposition.  I suppose we will all accept as a
fundamental postulate the statement that the highest civilization
is the one in which the highest value is placed upon individual
life&mdash;"
</p><p>"And happiness," added the girl in the yachting cap.
</p><p>"And happiness," assented the Englishman.
</p><p>"And yet," commented the lawyer, "I think that most of us will
admit that such a society, where life is regarded as sacred because
it is valuable to the individual, and not because it is valuable to
the state, tends to the non-production of heroes&mdash;"
</p><p>"That the average will be higher and the exception lower,"
observed the journalist.  "In other words, that there will be a
general elevation of the mass, accompanied by a corresponding
lowering of the few."
</p><p>"On the whole, I think our system does very well," said the
Englishman, carefully measuring the horseradish he was placing upon
his oysters.  "A mean between two extremes is apt to be
satisfactory in results.  If we don't produce a Marcus Aurelius or
a Seneca, neither do we produce a Nero or a Phocas.  We may have
lost patriotism, but we have gained cosmopolitanism, which is
better.  If we have lost chivalry, we have acquired decency; and if
we have ceased to be picturesque, we have become cleanly, which is
considerably more to be desired."
</p><p>"I have never felt the romanticism of the Middle Ages,"
remarked the girl in the yachting-cap.  "When I read of the glories
of the Crusaders, I can't help remembering that a knight wore a
single garment for a lifetime, and hacked his horse to pieces for
a whim.  Just as I never think of that chivalrous brute, Richard
the Lion-Hearted, that I don't see him chopping off the heads of
his three thousand prisoners."
</p><p>"Oh, I don't think that any of us are sighing for a revival of
the Middle Ages," <pb n="978"/>  returned the journalist.  "The worship of
the past has usually for its devotees people who have only known
the present&mdash;"
</p><p>"Which is as it should be," commented the lawyer.  "If man was
confined to the worship of the knowable, all the world would lapse
into atheism."
</p><p>"Just as the great lovers of humanity were generally hermits,"
added the girl in the yachting-cap.  "I had an uncle who used to
say that he never really loved mankind until he went to live in the
wilderness."
</p><p>"I think we are drifting from the point," said the alienist,
helping himself to potatoes.  "Was it not&mdash;can the saving of a
human life ever prove to be an immoral act?  I once held that it
could."
</p><p>"Did you act upon it?" asked the lawyer, with rising interest.
"I maintain that no proposition can be said to exist until it is
acted upon.  Otherwise it is in merely an embryonic state&mdash;"
</p><p>The alienist laid down his fork and leaned forward.  He was a
notable-looking man of some thirty-odd years, who had made a sudden
leap into popularity through several successful cases.  He had a
nervous, muscular face, with singularly penetrating eyes, and hair
of a light sandy color.  His hands were white and well shaped.
</p><p>"It was some years ago," he said, bending a scintillant glance
around the table.  "If you will listen&mdash;"
</p><p>There followed a stir of assent, accompanied by a nod from the
young lady upon the Captain's right.  "I feel as if it would be a
ghost story," she declared.
</p><p>"It is not a story at all," returned the alienist, lifting his
wineglass and holding it against the light.  "It is merely a fact."
</p><p>Then he glanced swiftly around the table as if challenging
attention.
</p><p>"As I said," he began, slowly, "it was some few years ago.
Just what year does not matter, but at that time I had completed a
course at Heidelberg, and expected shortly to set out with an
exploring party for South Africa.  It turned out afterwards that I
did not go, but for the purpose of the present story it is
sufficient that I intended to do so, and had made my preparations
accordingly.  At Heidelberg I had lived among a set of German
students who were permeated with the metaphysics of Schopenhauer,
von Hartmann, and the rest, and I was pretty well saturated myself.
At that age I was an ardent disciple of pessimism.  I am still a
disciple, but my ardor has abated&mdash;which is not the fault of
pessimism, but the virtue of middle age&mdash;"
</p><p>"A man is usually called conservative when he has passed the
twenties," interrupted the journalist, "yet it is not that he grows
more conservative, but that he grows less radical&mdash;"
</p><p>"Rather that he grows less in every direction," added the
Englishman, "except in physical bulk."
</p><p>The alienist accepted the suggestions with an inclination, and
continued.  "One of my most cherished convictions," he said, "was
to the effect that every man is the sole arbiter of his fate.  As
Schopenhauer has it, '<hi rend="italic">that there is nothing to which a man has
a more unassailable title than to his own life and person</hi>.'
Indeed, that particular sentence had become a kind of motto with
our set, and some of my companions even went so far as to preach
the proper ending of life with the ending of the power of
individual usefulness."
</p><p>He paused to help himself to salad.
</p><p>"I was in Scotland at the time, where I had spent a fortnight
with my parents, in a small village on the Kyles of Bute.  While
there I had been treating an invalid cousin who had acquired the
morphine habit, and who, under my care, had determined to uproot
it.  Before leaving I had secured from her the amount of the drug
which she had in her possession&mdash;some thirty grains&mdash;done up in a
sealed package, and labelled by a London chemist.  As I was in
haste, I put it in my bag, thinking that I would add it to my case
of medicines when I reached Leicester, where I was to spend the
night with an old schoolmate.  I took the boat at Tighnabruaich,
the small village, found a local train at Gourock to reach Glasgow
with one minute in which to catch the first express to London.  I
made the change and secured a first-class smoking-compartment,
which I at first thought to be vacant, but when the train had
started a man came from the dressing-room and took the seat across
from me.  At first I paid no heed to him, but upon looking up once
or twice and finding his eyes upon me, I became unpleasantly
conscious of his presence.  He was thin al-<pb n="979"/> most to
emaciation, and yet there was a muscular suggestion of physical
force about him which it was difficult to account for, since he was
both short and slight.  His clothes were shabby, but well made, and
his cravat had the appearance of having been tied in haste or by
nervous fingers.  There was a trace of sensuality about the mouth,
over which he wore a drooping yellow mustache tinged with gray, and
he was somewhat bald upon the crown of his head, which lent a
deceptive hint of intellectuality to his uncovered forehead.  As he
crossed his legs I saw that his boots were carefully blacked, and
that they were long and slender, tapering to a decided point."
</p><p>"I have always held," interpolated the lawyer, "that to judge
a man's character you must read his feet."
</p><p>The alienist sipped his claret and took up his words:
</p><p>"After passing the first stop I remembered a book at the
bottom of my bag, and, unfastening the strap, in my search for the
book I laid a number of small articles upon the seat beside me,
among them the sealed package bearing the morphine label and the
name of the London chemist.  Having found the book, I turned to
replace the articles, when I noticed that the man across from me
was gazing attentively at the labelled package.  For a moment his
expression startled me, and I stared back at him from across my
open bag, into which I had dropped the articles.  There was in his
eyes a curious mixture of passion and repulsion, and, beyond it
all, the look of a hungry hound when he sees food.  Thinking that
I had chanced upon a victim of the opium craving, I closed the bag,
placed it in the net above my head, and opened my book.
</p><p>"For a while we rode in silence.  Nothing was heard except the
noise of the train and the clicking of our bags as they jostled
each other in the receptacle above.  I remember these details very
vividly, because since then I have recalled the slightest fact in
connection with the incident.  I knew that the man across from me
drew a cigar from his case, felt in his pocket for an instant, and
then turned to me for a match.  At the same time I experienced the
feeling that the request veiled a larger purpose, and that there
were matches in the pocket into which he thrust his fingers.
</p><p>"But, as I complied with his request, he glanced indifferently
out of the window, and following his gaze, I saw that we were
passing a group of low-lying hills flecked with stray patches of
heather, and that across the hills a flock of sheep were filing,
followed by a peasant girl in a short skirt.  It was the last faint
suggestion of the Highlands.
</p><p>"The man across from me leaned out, looking back upon the
neutral sky, the sparse patches of heather, and the flock of sheep.
</p><p>"'What a tone the heather gives to a landscape!' he remarked,
and his voice sounded forced and affected.
</p><p>"I bowed without replying, and as he turned from the window,
and I sat upon the back seat in the draught of cinders, I bent
forward to lower the sash.  In a moment he spoke again:
</p><p>"'Do you go to London?'
</p><p>"'To Leicester,' I answered, laying the book aside, impelled
by a sudden interest.  'Why do you ask?'
</p><p>"He flushed nervously.
</p><p>"'I&mdash;oh, nothing,' he answered, and drew from me.
</p><p>"Then, as if with swift determination, he reached forward and
lifted the book I had laid upon the seat.  It was a treatise of von
Hartmann's in German.
</p><p>"'I had judged that you were a physician,' he said&mdash;'a
student, perhaps, from a German university?'
</p><p>"'I am.'
</p><p>"He paused for an instant, and then spoke in absent-minded
reiteration, 'So you don't go on to London?'
</p><p>"'No,' I returned, impatiently; 'but can I do anything for
you?'
</p><p>"He handed me the book, regarding me resolutely as he did so.
</p><p>"'Are you a sensible man?'
</p><p>"I bowed.
</p><p>"'And a philosopher?'
</p><p>"'In amateur fashion.'
</p><p>"With fevered energy he went on more quickly, 'You have in
your possession,' he said, 'something for which I would give my
whole fortune.'  He laid two half-sovereigns and some odd silver in
the palm of his hand.  'This is all I possess,' he continued, 'but
I would give it gladly.'
</p><p>"I looked at him curiously.
</p><p>"'You mean the morphia?' I demanded.
</p><p>"He nodded.  'I don't ask you to give it to me,' he said; 'I
only ask&mdash;' <pb n="980"/>
</p><p>"I interrupted him.  'Are you in pain?'
</p><p>"He laughed softly, and I really believe he felt a tinge of
amusement.  'It is a question of expediency,' he explained.  'If
you happen to be a moralist&mdash;'
</p><p>"He broke off.  'What of it?' I inquired.
</p><p>"He settled himself in his corner, resting his head against
the cushions.
</p><p>"'You get out at Leicester,' he said, recklessly.  'I go on to
London, where Providence, represented by Scotland Yard, is awaiting
me.'
</p><p>"I started.  'For what?'
</p><p>"'They call it murder, I believe,' he returned; 'but what they
call it matters very little.  I call it justifiable homicide&mdash;that
also matters very little.  The point is&mdash;I will arrive, they will
be there before me.  That is settled.  Every station along the road
is watched.'
</p><p>"I glanced out of the window.
</p><p>"'But you came from Glasgow,' I suggested.
</p><p>"'Worse luck!  I waited in the dressing-room until the train
started.  I hoped to have the compartment alone, but&mdash;'  He leaned
forward and lowered the window-shade.  'If you don't object,' he
said, apologetically; 'I find the glare trying.  It is a question
for a moralist,' he repeated.  'Indeed, I may call myself a
question for a moralist,' and he smiled again with that ugly humor.
'To begin with the beginning, the question is bred in the bone and
it's out in the blood.'  He nodded at my look of surprise.  'You
are an American,' he continued, 'and so am I.  I was born in
Washington some thirty years ago.  My father was a politician of
note, whose honor was held to be unimpeachable&mdash;which was a
mistake.  His name doesn't matter, but he became very wealthy
through judicious speculations&mdash;in votes and other things.  My
mother has always suffered from an incipient hysteria, which
developed shortly before my birth.'  He wiped his forehead with his
pocket-handkerchief, and knocked the ashes from his cigar with a
flick of his finger.  'The motive for this is not far to seek,' he
said, with a glance at my travelling-bag.  He had the coolest
bravado I have ever met.  'As a child,' he went on, 'I gave great
promise.  Indeed, we moved to England that I might be educated at
Oxford.  My father considered the atmospheric ecclesiasticism to be
beneficial.  But while at college I got into trouble with a woman,
and I left.  My father died, his fortune burst like a bubble, and
my mother moved to the country.  I was put into a banking office,
but I got into more trouble with women&mdash;this time two of them.  One
was a low variety actress, and I married her.  I didn't want to do
it.  I tried not to, but I couldn't help it, and I did it.  A month
later I left her.  I changed my name and went to Belfast, where I
resolved to become an honest man.  It was a tough job, but I
labored and I succeeded&mdash;for a time.  The variety actress began
looking for me, but I escaped her, and have escaped her so far.
That was eight years ago.  And several years after reaching Belfast
I met another woman.  She was different.  I fell ill of fever in
Ireland, and she nursed me.  She was a good woman, with a broad
Irish face, strong hands, and motherly shoulders.  I was weak and
she was strong, and I fell in love with her.  I tried to tell her
about the variety actress, but somehow I couldn't, and I married
her.'  He shot the stump of his cigar through the opposite window
and lighted another, this time drawing the match from his pocket.
'She is an honest woman,' he said&mdash;'as honest as the day.  She
believes in me.  It would kill her to know about the variety
actress&mdash;and all the others.  There is one child, a girl&mdash;a
freckle-faced mite just like her mother&mdash;and another is coming.'
</p><p>"'She knows nothing of this affair?'
</p><p>"'Not a blamed thing.  She is the kind of woman who is good
because she can't help herself.  She enjoys it.  I never did.  My
mother is different, too.  She would die if other people knew of
this; my wife would die if she knew of it herself.  Well, I got
tired, and I wanted money, so I left her and went to Dublin.  I
changed my name and got a clerkship in a shipping office.  My wife
thinks I went to America to get work, and if she never hears of me
she'll probably think no worse.  I did intend going to America, but
somehow I didn't.  I got in with a man who signed somebody's name
to a check and got me to present it.  Then we quarrelled about the
money, and the man threw the job on me and the affair came out.
But before they arrested me I ran him down and shot him.  I was
ridding the world of a damned traitor.' <pb n="981"/>
</p><p>"He raised the shade with a nervous hand, but the sun flashed
into his eyes, and he lowered it.
</p><p>"'I suppose I'd hang for it,' he said; 'there isn't much doubt
of that.  If I waited I'd hang for it, but I am not going to wait.
I am going to die.  It is the only thing left, and I am going to do
it.'
</p><p>"'And how?'
</p><p>"'Before this train reaches London,' he replied, 'I am a dead
man.  There are two ways.  I might say three, except that a pitch
from the carriage might mean only a broken leg.  But there is
this&mdash;'  He drew a vial from his pocket and held it to the light.
It contained an ounce or so of carbolic acid.
</p><p>"'One of the most corrosive of irritants,' I observed.
</p><p>"'And there is&mdash;your package.'
</p><p>"My first impulse promised me to force the vial from him.  He
was a slight man, and I could have overcome him with but little
exertion.  But the exertion I did not make.  I should as soon have
thought, when my rational humor reasserted itself, of knocking a
man down on Broadway and robbing him of his watch.  The acid was as
exclusively his property as the clothes he wore, and equally his
life was his own.  Had he declared his intention to hurl himself
from the window I might not have made way for him, but I should
certainly not have obstructed his passage.
</p><p>"But the morphia was mine, and that I should assist him was
another matter, so I said,
</p><p>"'The package belongs to me.'
</p><p>"'And you will not exchange?'
</p><p>"'Certainly not.'
</p><p>"He answered, almost angrily:
</p><p>"'Why not be reasonable?  You admit that I am in a mess of
it?'
</p><p>"'Readily.'
</p><p>"'You also admit that my life is morally my own?'
</p><p>"'Equally.'
</p><p>"'That its continuance could in no wise prove to be of benefit
to society?'
</p><p>"'I do.'
</p><p>"'That for all connected with me it would be better that I
should die unknown and under an assumed name than that I should end
upon the scaffold, my wife and mother wrecked for life, my children
discovered to be illegitimate?'
</p><p>"'Yes.'
</p><p>"'Then you admit also that the best I can do is to kill myself
before reaching London?'
</p><p>"'Perhaps.'
</p><p>"'So you will leave me the morphine when you get off at
Leicester?'
</p><p>"'No.'
</p><p>"He struck the window-sill impatiently with the palm of his
hand.
</p><p>"'And why not?'
</p><p>"I hesitated an instant.
</p><p>"'Because, upon the whole, I do not care to be the instrument
of your self-destruction.'
</p><p>"'Don't be a fool!' he retorted.  'Speak honestly, and say
that because of a little moral shrinkage on your part you prefer to
leave a human being to a death of agony.  I don't like physical
pain.  I am like a woman about it, but it is better than hanging,
or life-imprisonment, or any jury finding.'
</p><p>"I became exhortatory.
</p><p>"'Why not face it like a man and take your chances?  Who
knows&mdash;'
</p><p>"'I have had my chances,' he returned.  'I have squandered
more chances than most men ever lay eyes on&mdash;and I don't care.  If
I had the opportunity, I'd squander them again.  It is the only
thing chances are made for.'
</p><p>"'What a scoundrel you are!' I exclaimed.
</p><p>"'Well, I don't know,' he answered; 'there have been worse
men.  I never said a harsh word to a woman, and I never hit a man
when he was down&mdash;'
</p><p>"I blushed.  'Oh, I didn't mean to hit you,' I responded.
</p><p>"He took no notice.
</p><p>"'I like my wife,' he said.  'She is a good woman, and I'd do
a good deal to keep her and the children from knowing the truth.
Perhaps I'd kill myself even if I didn't want to.  I don't know,
but I am tired&mdash;damned tired.'
</p><p>"'And yet you deserted her.'
</p><p>"'I did.  I tried not to, but I couldn't help it.  If I was
free to go back to her to-morrow, unless I was ill and wanted
nursing, I'd see that she had grown shapeless, and that her hands
were coarse.'  He stretched out his own, which were singularly
white and delicate.  'I believe I'd leave her in a week,' he said.
</p><p>"Then with an eager movement he pointed to my bag.
</p><p>"'That is the ending of the difficulty,' he added, 'otherwise
I swear that before <pb n="982"/>  the train gets to London I will swallow
this stuff, and die like a rat.'
</p><p>"'I admit your right to die in any manner you choose, but I
don't see that it is my place to assist you.  It is an ugly job.'
</p><p>"'So am I,' he retorted, grimly.  'At any rate, if you leave
the train with that package in your bag it will be cowardice&mdash;sheer
cowardice.  And for the sake of your cowardice you will damn me to
this&mdash;'  He touched the vial.
</p><p>"'It won't be pleasant,' I said, and we were silent.
</p><p>"I knew that the man had spoken the truth.  I was accustomed
to lies, and had learned to detect them.  I knew, also, that the
world would be well rid of him and his kind.  Why I should preserve
him for death upon the gallows I did not see.  The majesty of the
law would be in no way ruffled by his premature departure; and if
I could trust that part of his story, the lives of innocent women
and children would, in the other case, suffer considerably.  And
even if I and my unopened bag alighted at Leicester, I was sure
that he would never reach London alive.  He was a desperate man,
this I read in his set face, his dazed eyes, his nervous hands.  He
was a poor devil, and I was sorry for him as it was.  Why, then,
should I contribute, by my refusal to comply with his request, an
additional hour of agony to his existence?  Could I, with my
pretence of philosophic latitudinarianism, alight at my station,
leaving him to swallow the acid and die like a rat in a cage before
the journey was over?  I remembered that I had once seen a guinea-pig die from the effects of carbolic acid, and the remembrance
sickened me suddenly.
</p><p>"As I sat there listening to the noise of the slackening
train, which was nearing Leicester, I thought of a hundred things.
I thought of Schopenhauer and von Hartmann.  I thought of the dying
guinea-pig.  I thought of the broad-faced Irish wife and the two
children.
</p><p>"Then 'Leicester' flashed before me, and the train stopped.
I rose, gathered my coat and rug, and lifted the volume of von
Hartmann from the seat.  The man remained motionless in the corner
of the compartment, but his eyes followed me.
</p><p>"I stooped, opened by bag, and laid the chemist's package upon
the seat.  Then I stepped out, closing the door after me."  As the
speaker finished, he reached forward, selected an almond from the
stand of nuts, fitted it carefully between the crackers, and
cracked it slowly.
</p><p>The young lady upon the Captain's right shook herself with a
shudder.
</p><p>"What a horrible story!" she exclaimed; "for it is a story,
after all, and not a fact."
</p><p>"A point, rather," suggested the Englishman; "but is that
all?"
</p><p>"All of the point," returned the alienist.  "The next day I
saw in the <hi rend="italic">Times</hi> that a man, supposed to be James Morganson,
who was wanted for murder, was found dead in a first-class smoking-compartment of the Midland Railway, Coroner's verdict, 'Death
resulting from an overdose of morphia, taken with suicidal
intent.'"
</p><p>The journalist dropped a lump of sugar in his cup and watched
it attentively.
</p><p>"I don't think I could have done it," he said.  "I might have
left him with his carbolic.  But I couldn't have deliberately given
him his death-potion."
</p><p>"But as long as he was going to die," responded the girl in
the yachting-cap, "it was better to let him die painlessly."
</p><p>The Englishman smiled.  "Can a woman ever consider the ethical
side of a question when the sympathetic one is visible?" he asked.
</p><p>The alienist cracked another almond.  "I was sincere," he
said.  "Of that there is no doubt.  I thought I did right.  The
question is&mdash;did I do right?"
</p><p>"It would have been wiser," began the lawyer, argumentatively,
"since you were stronger than he, to take the vial from him, and to
leave him to the care of the law."
</p><p>"But the wife and children," replied the girl in the yachting-cap.  "And hanging is so horrible!"
</p><p>"So is murder," responded the lawyer, dryly.
</p><p>The young lady on the Captain's right laid her napkin upon the
table and rose.  "I don't know what was right," she said, "but I do
know that in your place I should have felt like a murderer."
</p><p>The alienist smiled half cynically.  "So I did," he answered;
"but there is such a thing, my dear young lady, as a conscientious
murderer."</p>

</div1>
</body>
</text>
</TEI.2>
