<?xml version="1.0"?>

<?dlps id="Gle1115"?>
<?dlps page-images="none" figure-images="no"?>
<?dlps transcription="other"?>

<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/tei-p4/tei2.dtd" [
<!ENTITY % POSTKB "INCLUDE">
<!ENTITY % TEI.extensions.ent SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.ent">
<!ENTITY % TEI.extensions.dtd SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.dtd">
<!ENTITY % ISOnum SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/charent/iso-num.ent"> %ISOnum;
<!ENTITY % ISOpub SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/charent/iso-pub.ent"> %ISOpub;
]>
<TEI.2 id="Gle1115">
<teiHeader type="migrated" creator="Etext">
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title type="main">Whitehall: The Board of Trade to Governor James Glen, November 15, 1750 (excerpt) / by the Board of Trade</title>
<title type="sort">whitehall the board of trade to governor james glen, november 15 1750 excerpt by the board of trade</title>
<author>Brock: Board of Trade</author>
<respStmt>
<resp>Creation of machine-readable version:</resp>
<name>Ronald Michener, University of Virginia</name>
<resp>Conversion to TEI.2-conformant markup:</resp>
<name>University of Virginia Library Electronic Text Center.</name>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt>
<extent>ca. <num type="kilobytes">16</num> kilobytes</extent>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>University of Virginia Library</publisher>
<pubPlace>Charlottesville, Virginia</pubPlace>
<idno type="ETC">Gle1115</idno>
<date value="2000">2000</date>
<availability status="public">
<p n="copyright">Copyright &copy; 2000 by the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia</p>
<p n="access">Publicly accessible</p>
</availability>
<idno type="uva-pid">uva-lib:475993</idno>
</publicationStmt>
<seriesStmt>
<title>University of Virginia Library, Text collection</title>
<idno type="uva-set">UVA-LIB-Text</idno>
</seriesStmt>
<seriesStmt>
<p>This text is part of the collection for the Leslie Brock Center for the Study of Colonial Currency.</p>
</seriesStmt>
<sourceDesc>
<biblFull>
<titleStmt>
<title type="main">Whitehall: The Board of Trade to Governor James Glen, November 15, 1750</title>
<title level="m">Records in the British Public Records Office  Relating to South Carolina</title>
<title type="sort">whitehall the board of trade to governor james glen, november 15 1750</title>
<author>Board of Trade</author>
</titleStmt>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>Leslie Van Horn</publisher>
<pubPlace>Charlottesville, Virginia</pubPlace>
<date value="1750-11-15">November 15, 1750</date>
<idno type="callNo">Source copy consulted: Special Collections, University of Virginia microfilm, Access number 10715, roll 12,
XXIV</idno>
</publicationStmt>
<seriesStmt>
<p>Papers of Leslie Van Horn, 1600-1986</p>
</seriesStmt>
</biblFull>
</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc>
<encodingDesc>
<projectDesc>
<p>Prepared for the University of Virginia Library Electronic Text Center.</p>
</projectDesc>
<editorialDecl>
<p>All unambiguous end-of-line hyphens have been removed, and the trailing part of a word has been joined to the preceding line.</p>
<p id="ETC">Some keywords in the header are a local Electronic Text Center scheme to aid in establishing analytical groupings.</p>
</editorialDecl>
</encodingDesc>
<profileDesc>
<creation>
<date value="1750-11-15">November 15, 1750</date>
</creation>
<langUsage>
<language id="eng" usage="main">English</language>
</langUsage>
<textClass>
<keywords>
<term>nonfiction</term>
<term>prose</term>
<term>masculine</term>
<term>Special Collections</term>
</keywords>
</textClass>
</profileDesc>
<revisionDesc>
<change>
<date value="2000-05">May, 2000</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>corrector</resp>
<name>Cynthia Filer, The Electronic Text Center</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Added TEI header and tags.</item>
</change>
<change>
<date value="2005-07">July 2005</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>Corrector</resp>
<name>John Ivor Carlson</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Converted SGML to XML. Fixed tagging.</item>
</change>
<change>
<date value="2007-09">September 2007</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>Migration</resp>
<name>Ethan Gruber, University of Virginia Library</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Converted XML markup from TEI Lite to uva-dl-tei (TEI P4 with local customizations).</item>
</change>
<change>
<date value="2008-01">January 2008</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>Migration</resp>
<name>Greg Murray, University of Virginia Library</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Programmatically updated TEI header markup (but not header content) for minimal compliance with current QA requirements.</item>
</change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>
<text id="d1">

<front id="d2">
<div1 type="introduction" id="d3">
<head>The Board of Trade to Governor Glen (1750)</head>

<p>When the Board of Trade received Governor Glen's
letter, they composed an acid response, which was transmitted to
Governor Glen on November 15, 1750. The Board implied the information
that had been sent them was inaccurate, and that South Carolina actually
had no need for paper money.  Source: Records in the British Public
Records Office relating to South Carolina, XXIV, pp. 158-68.</p>
</div1>
</front>

<body id="d4">
<div1 type="letter" id="d5">
<pb n="158"/>
<p>We come now to that Letter of yours which relates to the internal State
of Your Government.  And before we make any observations

<pb n="159"/>
on the Reasons given in your Letter to evince the Necessity of a Paper
Currency in your Province and what else you have said upon the Subject,
it will be proper to tell you that the Report of the Committee of
Conference which you have sent us on the present State of Paper Currency
in your Province, and the Bills now outstanding differs from an Account
which we have had prepared here for our Use from the several Acts of
Assembly which have been passed in your Government for emitting such
Currency. We will state to you what We understand to be the Amount of
the Paper Currency at present outstanding in your Province and the
operations which every Act has had, that you may compare our State with
that of the Committee and explain the Reason of their differing.</p>

<p>From the year 1703, when the Province of South Carolina first began
to issue Paper Money, to the year 1743 there were issued as follows
viz.</p>

<p>
<table>
<row><cell>8<hi rend="super">th</hi> May 1703</cell>
<cell>&mdash; </cell>
<cell>6,000</cell></row>
<row><cell>5<hi rend="super">th</hi> July 1707</cell>
<cell>&mdash;</cell>
<cell>8,000</cell></row>
<row><cell>4<hi rend="super">th</hi> Feb. 1707</cell>
<cell>&mdash;</cell>
<cell>3,000 </cell></row>

<pb n="160"/>
<row><cell>24<hi rend="super">th</hi> Apl 1708</cell>
<cell>&mdash;</cell>
<cell>5,000</cell></row>
<row><cell>1<hi rend="super">st</hi> Mar. 1710</cell>
<cell>&mdash;</cell>
<cell>3,000</cell></row>
<row><cell>10<hi rend="super">th</hi> Nov. 1711</cell>
<cell>&mdash;</cell>
<cell>4,000</cell></row>
<row><cell>7<hi rend="super">th</hi> June 1712</cell>
<cell>&mdash;</cell>
<cell>36,000</cell></row>
<row><cell>27<hi rend="super">th</hi> Aug 1715</cell>
<cell>&mdash;</cell>
<cell>30,000</cell></row>
<row><cell>24<hi rend="super">th</hi> Mar. 1715</cell>
<cell>&mdash;</cell>
<cell>5,000</cell></row>
<row><cell>21<hi rend="super">st</hi> June 1716</cell>
<cell>&mdash;</cell>
<cell>15,000</cell></row>
<row><cell>23<hi rend="super">rd</hi> Feb. 1719</cell>
<cell>&mdash;</cell>
<cell>34,000</cell></row>
<row><cell>D<hi rend="super">o</hi> 1722</cell>
<cell>&mdash;</cell>
<cell>40,000</cell></row>
<row><cell>&nbsp;</cell>
<cell>&nbsp;</cell>
<cell>&pound;194,000</cell></row></table></p>


<p>The several Laws upon which these Sums were issued, provided Funds
for the due payment of them, upon which the Bills were to be sunk &amp;
Cancelled; but as these Provisions were set aside the obligation of many
of the Acts broke thro, and the Funds diverted to other purposes, there
remained outstanding in the year 1723 &pound;120,000.</p>

<p>On the 15<hi rend="super">th</hi> of February 1723, an Act was passed entitled
an Act for calling and sinking the Publick Bills of Credit, in which
Provision was made for Cancelling the Sum of &pound;55,000 only of the said
Bills &amp;c. the Remainder of &pound;65,000 was continued current.</p>

<p>By the operation of this Act &pound;13,500 was

<pb n="161"/>
sunk, but in
1727, the Assembly suspended the Execution of this Act applying the
Duties appropriated for sinking the Bills of Credit to defray the
Charges of an Expedition to S<hi rend="super">t</hi> Augustine. </p>

<p>After this Expedition the Merchants trading to Carolina petition'd
the Crown in 1731, further to suspend the Execution of the sinking Fund
Act for seven years and that the Duties arising from it might be applied
to the settling Foreign Protestants. The Petition was complied with, and
upon an Instruction to the Governor an Act was passed for that purpose,
but the Assembly were so far from Appropriating those Duties to the
Purpose for which they were intended that they passed a Law for
appropriating them to the Cancelling certain publick orders which had
been issued for the Services of Government.</p>

<p>Upon the complaint of the Merchants this Act was repealed, and in
1735, An Act passed for appropriating the Duties of the Sinking Fund Act
to the Settlement of Poor Protestants, in which Provision was also made
for sinking the Publick Orders. </p>

<p>In the Year 1739 both the sinking

<pb n="162"/>
Fund and appropriation
Acts expired, so that there remained outstanding without any Funds for
calling them in &pound;106,500. </p>

<p>Since that time there have been issued the following Sums in publick
orders, viz.</p>

<p>
<table>
<row><cell>5<hi rend="super">th</hi> March 1736/7</cell>
<cell>35010</cell></row>
<row><cell>5<hi rend="super">th</hi> April 1740</cell>
<cell>25000</cell></row>
<row><cell>19<hi rend="super">th</hi> Sept. 1740</cell>
<cell>11508</cell></row>
<row><cell>10<hi rend="super">th</hi> July 1742</cell>
<cell>63000</cell></row>
<row><cell>21<hi rend="super">st</hi> May 1745</cell>
<cell>20000</cell></row>
<row><cell>Of these Sums there appear to have been Cancelled</cell>
<cell>72,800</cell></row>
<row><cell>remains outstanding in old Bills</cell>
<cell>106,500</cell></row>
<row><cell>Publick Orders</cell>
<cell>81,718</cell></row>
<row><cell>&nbsp;</cell>
<cell>&nbsp;</cell>
<cell>188,218</cell></row></table></p>

<p>You observe that this State agrees exactly with yours as to the old
Bills of Credit, but it differs greatly from it as to the Publick
Orders, of which the Committee state only 63000 to have been issued. The
Difference upon the whole is 55,173 . 5 . 0</p>

<p>The Reason you urge to shew the necessity of permitting some Paper
Currency in your Province are the strongest and most convincing that can


<pb n="163"/>
be urged to prove that it does not want it.  You tell us that
you are a new and improving Province, that you doubt not but your
exported Produce sufficiently Pays for all your Importations from Great
Britain and leaves a Surplus in your favour of several Thousand Pounds
Sterling; and if this be the state of your Trade, that Balance which you
say you have is the best Proof that you want not a Paper Currency, which
is only necessary to a People, who have not the Balance of Trade in
their Favour, and who having no Goods or Gold, to remit to pay for the
Exceeding of their Imports, are the only Country which in its Trade can
want a Paper Currency. We observe that in a Report published by order of
the General Assembly of your Government in 1739, on the state of paper
Currency the Necessity of a Paper Currency is argued entirely from a
Supposition that the Imports of So. Carolina exceed the Exports it is
there admitted that where the Balance of Trade is in favour of the
Colony the Trade itself will supply what is the Established and best
Medium of Trade, and nothing is urged in that Report to shew that the
Imports of your Province do exceed

<pb n="164"/>
your Exports, but an
assertion that there is no Gold or Silver to be ever found in the
Province, which is more easily accounted for, by the Quantity of Paper
Currency itself, which naturally drives away the Currency of Gold and
Silver wherever it prevails. If you had sent us over an account of the
Imports as well as the Exports of your Province, We should have been
better able to judge of the truth of the Real Balance of your Trade, by
having a full State of it before us, but at present, from the Lights We
have We are inclined to think with you that the balance of your whole
Trade, is in favour of your Government.</p>

<p>You say it would be imprudent in the Province to buy Gold and Silver
w<hi rend="super">th</hi> this Balance in which We are at a loss to discover your
meaning, for if in your Barter with other Nations there remains a
Surplus due to you, which we suppose is in no case left a Debt, how can
that Balance be remitted to you, but in Gold or Silver? You add also
that it is Wisest in the Province to buy Slaves with it, which Slaves
will raise more Rice &amp;c. which you say will increase this Balance,
and which, if you will

<pb n="165"/>
pursue your Reasoning throughout, will
as necessarily increase the Gold and Silver, &amp; consequently in
proportion as it increases, make Paper Currency, the substitute of
Bullion still more unnecessary.</p>

<p>We did not expect to hear the manner in which the Paper Currency of
your Government has been conducted urged as a Reason for continuing it,
&amp; it is with a degree of Astonishment We find your Province praised
for having punctually observed the appropriations of these Acts and kept
the Publick Faith inviolable. Is it possible you should have ever
examined any State of your Paper Currency, and not seen the Evasive
manner in which from time to time upon pretence of Necessity &amp; upon
every general Reason of State the greater number of these Acts have been
prevented in their due operation? Insomuch that every Currency Bill from
1703 to this Day has a Clause for issuing more money and a Clause for
cancelling the whole then in being the first of which is always executed
and the latter has been never once performed agreeable to Law?</p>

<p>As to the Payment of Quit Rents which

<pb n="166"/>
you give as a Reason
for allowing some Paper Currency, you might have remembered that by your
106<hi rend="super">th</hi> Instruction all Quit Rents are directed to be
<unclear cert="good">passed</unclear> in Proclamation Money. </p>

<p>You cannot but be sensible that your opinion with regard to the
necessity of a paper Currency has been suddenly and greatly altered:
Since in your Letter to us dated the 14<hi rend="super">th</hi> of April 1748,
wherein you give us an Account of your refusal to pass a Law for issuing
Paper Money, you say you begged the Assembly to consider the fatal
Consequences w<hi rend="super">ch</hi> had attended such Measures in other
parts of America, for that some Provinces by giving way to such
temporary Expedients, and opening these Flood gates and Sluices, had
been overwhelmed with an Inundation of Paper Money. And in another
Letter dated the 24<hi rend="super">th</hi> of July following you say that
the Province was in a Condition to have raised the Money wanted, by an
additional Tax without having recourse to such an Expedient as Paper in
Lieu of Money, and then state to us the Trade of the Province, the
Exceedings of the Exports, and the Charges of Government. </p>

<pb n="167"/>
<p>But whatever Reasons you may think there are to shew the necessity of
admitting some Paper Currency in your Province, there cannot even upon
your own Reasoning be any for permitting an Increase of the present
quantity. What has been sufficient for the Occasions of your Government
and Commerce of it of late years when your Trade has ben in it's Infancy
and Expences incurred on great and Extraordinary Service will doubtless
very amply Answer every occasion which can arise in your Province
atpresent when you are in a State of Peace advancing every year in your
Trade and adding to the Balance of it. You say yourself that you are a
new and improvingd rovince, Your Exports last year Amounted to
&pound;146000 which is &pound;46000 more than they were the first year after
the War, the Charges of Government are but &pound;9000, and for these
Reasons We have resolved, and We think it proper to inform you of it to
recommend it to the Crown to revoke your 99<hi rend="super">th</hi> Instruction,
and that you should be Instructed never gain to give your consent to any
Act for emitting any additional Bills of Credit, but to

<pb n="168"/>
use the most pressing Endeavours with the General Assembly of your
Province to get Funds Established by proper Acts for the Payment of the
106000 now outstanding, the Funds for the Payment of which are expired. </p>

<p>See Governor Glen's response.</p>

</div1>
</body>
</text>
</TEI.2>
