<?xml version="1.0"?>

<?dlps id="GogEven"?>
<?dlps page-images="none" figure-images="no"?>
<?dlps transcription="other"?>

<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/tei-p4/tei2.dtd" [
<!ENTITY % POSTKB "INCLUDE">
<!ENTITY % TEI.extensions.ent SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.ent">
<!ENTITY % TEI.extensions.dtd SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.dtd">
<!ENTITY % ISOnum SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/charent/iso-num.ent"> %ISOnum;
<!ENTITY % ISOpub SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/charent/iso-pub.ent"> %ISOpub;

]>

<TEI.2 id="GogEven">
<teiHeader type="migrated" creator="Etext">
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title type="main">A May Evening</title>
<title type="sort">may evening</title>
<author>Gogol, Nikolai Vasilievich</author>
<respStmt>
<resp>Creation of machine-readable version</resp>
<name>Judy Boss</name>
</respStmt>
<respStmt>
<resp>Conversion to TEI-conformant markup</resp>
<name>University of Virginia Library Electronic Text Center</name>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt>
<extent>ca. <num type="kilobytes">14</num> kilobytes</extent>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>University of Virginia Library</publisher>
<pubPlace>Charlottesville, Virginia</pubPlace>
<idno type="ETC">GogEven</idno>
<date value="1994">1994</date>
<availability status="public">
<p n="copyright">Copyright &copy; 1994 by the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia</p>
<p n="access">Publicly accessible</p>
</availability>
<idno type="uva-pid">uva-lib:475996</idno>
</publicationStmt>
<seriesStmt>
<title>University of Virginia Library, Text collection</title>
<idno type="uva-set">UVA-LIB-Text</idno>
</seriesStmt>
<sourceDesc>
<biblFull>
<titleStmt>
<title type="main">A May Evening</title>
<title type="sort">may evening</title>
<author>Nikolai Vasilievich Gogol</author>
</titleStmt>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>Cosmopolitan</publisher>
<pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
<date value="1887">1887</date>
</publicationStmt>
<seriesStmt>
<p>Volume 3</p>
</seriesStmt>
<notesStmt>
<note>
<p>pp. 186-188</p>
</note>
</notesStmt>
</biblFull>
</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc>
<encodingDesc>
<projectDesc>
<p>Prepared for the University of Virginia Library Electronic Text Center</p>
</projectDesc>
<editorialDecl>
<p>All quotation marks retained as data</p>
<p>All unambiguous end-of-line hyphens have been removed, and the
trailing part of a word has been joined to the preceding line.</p>
<p id="ETC">Keywords in the header are a local Electronic Text
Center scheme to aid in establishing analytical groupings</p>
</editorialDecl>
<refsDecl>
<p>ID elements are given for each page element and are composed of
the text's unique cryptogram and the given page number, as in
SpeFQue1 for page one of Spenser's Faerie Queene.</p>
</refsDecl>
</encodingDesc>
<profileDesc>
<creation>
<date value="1887">1887</date>
</creation>
<langUsage>
<language id="eng" usage="main">English</language>
</langUsage>
<textClass>
<keywords>
<term>fiction; prose</term>
<term>Literature in Translation</term>
</keywords>
</textClass>
</profileDesc>
<revisionDesc>
<change>
<date value="1994-03">March 1994</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>corrector</resp>
<name>Timothy Jarrett</name>
</respStmt>
<item>converted COCOA markings to TEI markings</item>
</change>
<change>
<date value="2005-07">July 2005</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>Corrector</resp>
<name>John Ivor Carlson</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Converted SGML to XML. Fixed tagging.</item>
</change>
<change>
<date value="2007-09">September 2007</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>Migration</resp>
<name>Ethan Gruber, University of Virginia Library</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Converted XML markup from TEI Lite to uva-dl-tei (TEI P4 with local customizations).</item>
</change>
<change>
<date value="2008-01">January 2008</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>Migration</resp>
<name>Greg Murray, University of Virginia Library</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Programmatically updated TEI header markup (but not header content) for minimal compliance with current QA requirements.</item>
</change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text id="d1">
<body id="d2">


<div1 type="story" id="d3"><pb n="186"/>
<head>Gogol, Nikikolai Vasilievitch.  "A May Evening."  Cosmopolitan 3
(May 1887): 186-188. <lb/> </head>

<p>THERE were sounds of merriment in the village, and a chorus of
song murmured, stream-like, through its single street.  It was the hour
when lads and lasses, after their hard day's work, meet in the mellow
gloaming to express their feelings in melodies which, though glad, are
never without a strain of sadness.  The pensive eventide was dreamily
embracing the blue heaven, and transforming every visible object into
something vague, shadowy, and ghost-like.  The brooding gloom settled
into night, and still the stream of song flowed on without
surcease.</p>
<p>Guitar in hand, the eldest son of the village headman steals away
from his comrades, and makes toward a house that is half hidden by a
screen of pink-blossomed cherry-trees.  As he walks, the young Cossack
strikes a few notes on the instrument, and steps a measure to his own
music.  When he reaches the house, he stops, and, after a short pause,
touches his guitar again, and sings a song of love, soft and low: </p>
<p>     "The sun is low, the night is near,</p>
<p>     Come, oh, come to me, sweetheart, dear!" </p>
<p>"No use," murmured the Cossack when he had finished his song,
at the same time drawing near to the window.  "My darling is asleep.
Hahn!  Hahn!<note n="1" place="foot" type="au"><p> A pet diminutive for
Hanna</p></note> are you asleep, or don't you like to expose your pretty
face to the cold?  Or maybe you won't come out for fear we may be
seen together.  But there is nothing to fear.  The night is warm, and
there is nobody near.  And if anybody does come, I will hide you in my
arms, and none shall see you.  And if the wind blows cold, I will press
you to my heart, warm you with kisses, and put my cap on your tiny
feet, my darling.  Only look out for one moment: put your hand out of
the window that I may touch your rosy fingers. </p>
<p>"No, you're not asleep!" he adds, passionately, after waiting in
vain for an answer.  "You are laughing at me.  Well, laugh if it pleases
you.  Good-bye!"</p>
<p>He turns round, throws back his cap, and, still gently touching his
guitar, draws a few paces away.  Almost at the same moment the
wooden handle of the door begins to stir, the door opens with a squeak,
and a girl in the spring of seventeen appears on the threshold, and, still
holding the handle, she looks furtively around.  Her eyes shine in the
dusk like little stars, and even the pink flush on her cheeks is not
unobserved by the young Cossack.</p>
<p>"How impatient you are!" she whispers.  "You were actually
getting angry!  Why did you come when there were so many people
about?  I am all of a tremble."</p>
<p>"Never mind, my darling; come closer to

<pb n="187"/>
me," replied the lover, laying aside his guitar, and sitting down on the
door-step.  "You know that to be one hour without seeing you is a great
trial for me."</p>
<p>"Do you know what I am thinking?" interrupts the girl, looking at
him pensively.  "I am thinking &mdash; something tells me that in the future
we shall not be able to see each other so often.  I don't think the people
hereabouts are good people.  The lasses look jealous; and as for the
young men &mdash;   My mother, too, she has begun to watch me more of
late.  I own I was happier amongst strangers before I came here."  And
a shade of sadness settled for a moment on her beautiful face.</p>
<p>"Only two short months in your native village, and you are already
unhappy!  Perhaps you are getting tired of it and &mdash; of me?"</p>
<p>"Oh, no; I am not tired of you," she answers, with a smile.  "I
love you, you dark-browed Cossack!  I love you for your hazel eyes; and
when they look into mine, my soul answers back, and I feel happy and
glad.  And I like to hear you play on your guitar, and see you walk
about the street.  Oh, I like it so much!"</p>
<p>"My own Hahn!" exclaims the Cossack, in an ecstasy, kissing the
girl and drawing her closer to him.</p>
<p>"Wait, Leoko!  That is enough.  Now, tell me, did you speak to
my father?"</p>
<p>"Wha-at!" he asks, as if suddenly waking from a dream.  "Speak
to your father!  Yes, I said that I wanted to marry &mdash; to have you for my
wife.  Yes, I spoke to him."</p>
<p>The words "I spoke" seemed to fall from his lips reluctantly and
almost sadly.</p>
<p>"Well?"</p>
<p>"What can you make of him?  The old curmudgeon pretends to be
deaf.  He won't hear, and keeps scolding because I go about with the
boys.  But don't think about it, Hahn.  On the word of a Cossack, I'll
bend him to my will before I've done."</p>
<p>"You have only to say a word, Leoko.  It shall be as you wish.  I
know that by myself.  At any other time I should not have listened.
Now, in spite of myself, I could not help doing whatever you ask
me."</p>
<p>"Look! look!" she went on, resting her head on his shoulder and
raising her eyes to the warm sky.  "Look there!  Far, far away are
glimmering little stars: one, two, three, four, five.  Is it not true that
those are angels, opening the windows of their bright little homes, and
looking down on us?  Is it not so, my Leoko?  Are they not looking on
our earth?  What if men had wings, and could fly up there!  Yet, not one
of our trees reaches the heavens.  Still, people say there is a land where
grows a tree whose topmost branches touch the sky, and that, on
Ascension Day, God comes down by it to earth."</p>
<p>"No, Hahn!  God has a ladder which stretches from Heaven to
earth.  On Ascension Day holy angels let down this ladder, and, as soon
as God puts his foot on the first rung, all evil spirits take to flight and
fall headlong into hell.  That is why, on the Lord's Day, there are no
evil spirits on earth."</p>
<p>"How gently stirs the water &mdash; just like a babe in a cradle!" says
Hanna, pointing to a pool hard by, begirt with weeping willows, whose
melancholy branches drooped in the water.</p>
<p>On a hillock near a pine wood, slumbered an old wooden house,
with closed shutters; the roof was covered with moss and weeds, the
windows were half hidden with apple-trees, the dark pines veiled it with
shadows and gave it a weird and specter-like look.</p>
<p>"I remember as though it were a dream," went on Hanna, keeping
her eyes on Leoko, "that long, long ago, when I was very, very little
and lived with mother, I used to hear terrible stories about that house.  I
am sure, Leoko, you know all about it."</p>
<p>"God be with it, my darling!  Don't mind what old women and
fools say.  You would only be frightened and would not sleep if I told
you."</p>
<p>"Oh, no; go on and tell me, like a dear good boy!" she said,
throwing her arms round his neck, and pressing her cheek to his.  "You
don't love me; I know you don't: you only pretend.  You have another
sweetheart; I am sure you have.  You must tell me about the old house.
I shall not be afraid, and I shall sleep all the same.  But if you don't tell
me, I shall not sleep a bit; I shall be thinking, thinking all the night
through.  Do tell me, Leoko!"</p>
<p>"I shall think soon that what people say is true: every woman is
possessed by her own peculiar devil of curiosity.  Well, listen.  Long,
long ago there lived in that

<pb n="188"/>
house an old man, who had an only daughter.  She was handsome; her
face was as white as snow &mdash; just like yours.  Her father was a widower,
on the look-out for a second wife.  'Will you continue to love me as you
do now when you marry again, father?' she would ask him.  And then
he would say: 'I shall, my daughter; I shall love you more ardently than
ever, and go on giving you earrings and ornaments as I have always
done.'</p>
<p>"The old man married and brought home his young wife.  She was
a fine woman, that wife of his, with a blooming red-and-white
complexion and big black eyes; but she cast such an evil glance at her
step-daughter that the girl shrieked in deadly fear, but not a word did the
step-mother speak to her all day long.  When night came and the father
and his wife retired, the girl locked herself up in her own room, and,
feeling sad, bent her head and fell a-weeping.  A little while after,
happening to look around, she spied a fierce-looking black cat creeping
toward her.  Its fur was all a-flame, and its claws struck on the floor
like iron.  In her terror the girl jumped on a chair; the cat followed her.
She sprang into bed; the cat sprang after her, and, flying at her throat,
began to choke her.  Tearing the creature away, with a cry she flung it
on the ground; but the next moment it was again crawling toward her, its
savage eyes burning with rage.  Rendered desperate by terror, the girl
seized her father's sword, which hung on the wall, and with a single
stroke cut off the cat's left paw; whereupon the cat immediately
disappeared.</p>
<p>"All the following day and the day after, the young wife kept her
room.  When she came out on the third day, her left hand was bandaged,
and she carried the arm in a sling.  Then the poor girl knew that her
mother was a witch, and that she had cut off her hand.  On the fourth
day the old man ordered his daughter to hew wood, draw water, and
scrub the floors, as if she was a menial servant or a common peasant.
On the fifth he chased her from the house, without giving her either
shoes for her feet or bread of money for a journey.  The poor girl could
bear it no longer, and, covering her face with her hands, she wept bitter
tears.</p>
<p>"'You have ruined your daughter, my father!' she cried.  'The
witch has cast her spell over you, and wrecked your soul.  May God
forgive you!  As for me, He has not willed that I should remain much
longer in the world.'</p>
<p>"And look!" went on Leoko, pointing toward the house.  "Do you
see that high bank?  Well, from that bank she threw herself into the
pool, and since then she belongs no more to the world.  That, Hahn, is
what the old folks say; but they say so many things!  The present owner
wants to sell the house, and they talk about turning it into a brewery.
But I think I hear voices.  The lads and lasses are coming home.  Good
night, darling; don't think about that old woman's tale.  I dare say it is
all nonsense."</p>
<p>And then, after embracing and kissing her, he went away.</p>
<p>"Good night, Leoko!" answered Hanna, whose gaze was still fixed
on the dark pine wood.</p>
<p>As she looked, a great fiery ball rose slowly from the shadows,
and seemed to fill the earth with a triumphant splendor.  The pool was
lighted up with a shower of sparks, and the pine wood on the hill began
to stand out from the background of dark green.</p>
<p>When the merrymakers had passed, and their voices had died in
the distance, every sound was hushed, night covered the earth with a
mantle of silence, and Hanna, after a last, wistful glance in the direction
taken by her lover, drew back into the house, and closed and bolted the
door.</p>

</div1>
</body>
</text>
</TEI.2>

