<?xml version="1.0"?>

<?dlps id="GolNewy"?>
<?dlps page-images="none" figure-images="no"?>
<?dlps transcription="other"?>

<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/tei-p4/tei2.dtd" [
<!ENTITY % POSTKB "INCLUDE">
<!ENTITY % TEI.extensions.ent SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.ent">
<!ENTITY % TEI.extensions.dtd SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.dtd">
<!ENTITY % ISOnum SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/charent/iso-num.ent"> %ISOnum;
<!ENTITY % ISOlat1 SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/charent/iso-lat1.ent"> %ISOlat1;
<!ENTITY % ISOpub SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/charent/iso-pub.ent"> %ISOpub;

]>
<TEI.2 id="GolNewy">
<teiHeader type="migrated" creator="Etext">
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title type="main">New York's Yiddish Writers</title>
<title type="sort">new yorks yiddish writers</title>
<author>Goldberg, Isaac</author>
<respStmt>
<resp>Creation of machine-readable version:</resp>
<name>Judy Boss</name>
<resp>Creation of digital images:</resp>
<name/>
<resp>Conversion to TEI.2-conformant markup:</resp>
<name>University of Virginia Library Electronic Text Center.</name>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt>
<extent>ca. <num type="kilobytes">25</num> kilobytes</extent>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>University of Virginia Library</publisher>
<pubPlace>Charlottesville, Virginia</pubPlace>
<idno type="ETC">GolNewy</idno>
<date value="1998">1998</date>
<availability status="public">
<p n="copyright">Copyright &copy; 1998 by the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia</p>
<p n="access">Publicly accessible</p>
</availability>
<idno type="uva-pid">uva-lib:475998</idno>
</publicationStmt>
<seriesStmt>
<title>University of Virginia Library, Text collection</title>
<idno type="uva-set">UVA-LIB-Text</idno>
</seriesStmt>
<notesStmt>
<note>
<p>Judy Boss has made the following changes in this electronic version: p. 688: "incidentally,," ] "incidentally,"; p. 688: "Badacker" ] "Baedecker"</p>
</note>
</notesStmt>
<sourceDesc>
<biblFull>
<titleStmt>
<title type="main">New York's Yiddish Writers</title>
<title level="j">The Bookman, volume 46</title>
<title type="sort">new yorks yiddish writers</title>
<author>Isaac Goldberg</author>
</titleStmt>
<extent>pp. 684-689</extent>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>Dodd, Mead &amp; Company</publisher>
<pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
<date value="1918">1918</date>
<idno type="callNo">Print copy consulted: The University of Virginia Library, call number AP2.B78, volume 46</idno>
</publicationStmt>
</biblFull>
</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc>
<encodingDesc>
<projectDesc>
<p>Prepared for the University of Virginia Library Electronic Text Center.</p>
</projectDesc>
<editorialDecl>
<p>All unambiguous end-of-line hyphens have been removed, and the trailing part of a word has been joined to the preceding line.</p>
<p>Some keywords in the header are a local Electronic Text Center scheme to aid in establishing analytical groupings.</p>
</editorialDecl>
</encodingDesc>
<profileDesc>
<creation>
<date value="1918">1918</date>
</creation>
<langUsage>
<language id="eng" usage="main">English</language>
</langUsage>
<textClass>
<keywords>
<term>nonfiction</term>
<term>prose</term>
<term>masculine</term>
</keywords>
</textClass>
</profileDesc>
<revisionDesc>
<change>
<date value="1998-06">June 1998</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>corrector</resp>
<name>Anne Stinehart, Electronic Text Center</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Added TEI header and tags.</item>
</change>
<change>
<date value="2005-07">July 2005</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>Corrector</resp>
<name>John Ivor Carlson</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Converted SGML to XML. Fixed tagging.</item>
</change>
<change>
<date value="2007-09">September 2007</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>Migration</resp>
<name>Ethan Gruber, University of Virginia Library</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Converted XML markup from TEI Lite to uva-dl-tei (TEI P4 with local customizations).</item>
</change>
<change>
<date value="2008-01">January 2008</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>Migration</resp>
<name>Greg Murray, University of Virginia Library</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Programmatically updated TEI header markup (but not header content) for minimal compliance with current QA requirements.</item>
</change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>


<text id="d1">

<body id="d2">



<div1 type="essay" id="d3"> <pb n="684"/>
<head>NEW YORK'S YIDDISH WRITERS<lb/>
BY ISAAC GOLDBERG</head>

<p>
STRANGELY enough, it has long been a question to many, not
alone whether the modern Jews have any literature, but whether
Yiddish itself is a language.  Many have been the prophecies which
predicted the immediate extinction of the tongue, and yet, like the
fabled Phoenix of old, it has risen new-born from its own ashes.  Let
prophets deal in futures &mdash; and it must be admitted that from certain
signs familiar to students of linguistic evolution Yiddish would
seem to be eventually doomed &mdash; the fact remains that to-day it is
enjoying what amounts practically to a renaissance.  And the
question whether modern Jews have a literature is settled by a
reading of the works themselves.
</p><p>To Americans it is of added interest to learn that the latest
phase of this renaissance has taken place almost entirely in New
York, which, since the beginning of the European war, has fairly
wrested from Warsaw the position of literary capital of the Jews.
And thus, in a metropolis which contains nations within a nation, is
born a literature within a literature.
</p><p>The one thing that must strike even the superficial observer of
Yiddish literature in New York is the fact that it rises almost wholly
from the radical movements.  Take up anything by Pinski, Asch,
Raisin, Kobrin or Libin, for instance.  You are immediately made
aware of a revolutionary outlook upon life.  There is an atmosphere
of frustrated hope, crushing disillusionment, overwork that blunts
the finer instincts, tenement life that saps the bodily strength.  There
is humour, too; a humour which is all too often the grin of the
skull's teeth, yet which has its less ironic moments, and at its best
can produce such a figure as the late Sholom Aleichem, long known
and revered as the Yiddish Mark Twain.
</p><p>This revolutionary strain is, of course, in line with the
foundations of Yiddish literature, which from its beginning has been
forced to be in large measure a literature of propaganda and of
enlightenment.  The great Isaac Leib Perez, who was one of the
most significant of nineteenth century writers in any tongue, outside
of his generally worthless dramas fused this propaganda element
with the highest type of pure artistry.  His successors rise to
uncommon worth in just the proportion in which their art triumphs
over their propaganda.
</p><p>As to the drama, here we deal with an evolution more rapid
and more complex.  Yiddish drama, speaking from the standpoint of
actual stage production, is but little over forty years old.  It began in
1876, in Roumania, with Abraham Goldfaden, came to Russia two
years later, was there stifled by official decree in 1883, and soon
found its way to New York, where it has flourished ever since
through various phases of achievement.  Beginning in Roumania
with the operettas of Goldfaden, in America the stage underwent a
realistic reaction, at the head of which towered Jacob Gordin.
Gordin, mainly concerned with the problem play, ransacked the
world's library for subjects.  He adapted Shakespeare, Ibsen,
Goethe, Hebbel, Ostrovsky, and who not else, and the pendulum of
realistic reaction swung often to the extreme of naturalism and
grotesquerie.  Gordin, like Goldfaden, left a tradition, but both were
soon to be surpassed by a master who was to bring Yiddish drama
into the light of universal literature.  This David Pinski has but
lately accomplished with his <hi rend="italic">The Treasure</hi> recently
characterised by Professor Baker of Harvard as one of the greatest
dramatic products of the twentieth century.
   <pb n="685"/>
</p><p>Yet the Yiddish stage, despite the fact that it has produced its
greatest dramatists only yesterday, as it were (both Goldfaden and
Gordin, like Sholom Aleichem, died in New York) is already,
despite its financial successes, next door to extinction.  That same
spreading of secular education, that same melting-pot influence
which has taken its best client&egrave;le away to the Gentile
theatres, will perhaps one day withdraw from Yiddish literature,
too, that intelligent public which alone can call forth and reward an
author's worthiest efforts.
</p><p>That such a literature, with all its internal and external
drawbacks should in so short a time have produced a Perez, a
Pinski, an Asch, is nothing less than remarkable.  New York to-day
holds a group of writers who, did they write in English, would
easily stand beside the best we can show, and in several instances
rise above.
</p><p>At their head stand David Pinski and Sholom Asch.  The first
represents what is most artistic in his people's literary development;
the second, that which is most vigorously effective.  The first is the
soul of modern Israel; the second its body.  They are
complementary personalities; each at times reveals in his work
those elements which are more characteristic of the other; to know
the modern Jew one must read both.
</p><p>Pinski was born in Mohliv, Russia, forty-five years ago.  Like
so many youths of the day, he was destined to the career of a rabbi,
and at the age of ten was a recognised Talmudist.  Again like so
many youths, he yearned for a broader life, and was early attracted
to writing.  It was not until he had reached his seventeenth year that
he decided definitely to abandon Hebrew and Russian as literary
media, and to write thenceforth in Yiddish.  His early successes
were achieved in the field of the short story; he has, in fact, been
called by his nation's critics the discoverer of the Yiddish proletariat
in fiction.  Various vicissitudes brought him soon to Berlin, where
he studied philosophy and literature, and made the acquaintance of
Germany's foremost literary lights.  It was here, under their
influence, that he wrote his first significant drama, <hi rend="italic">Isaac
Sheftel</hi>, in 1899, &mdash; a powerful study of the soul of a Jewish
worker, whose deep vision is so far beyond his stunted mental
powers that he is at last driven to suicide.  Here at the very outset of
his dramatic career Pinski reveals the artistry that has only lately
won him universal recognition.  There is not a word of propaganda
in the play, great as the temptation must have been to include anti-capitalist tirades.  Isaac Sheftel rises into a world-wide symbol.  He
is man's better self in combat with the crass materialism of life; he
is our intuition of greater glories baffled by the limitations of our
present intelligence.
</p><p>Pinski's reputation was now so widespread among the Jews
that he was invited to become an editor upon a New York radical
weekly.  He accepted, not so much for the position, as for the fact
that New York then possessed the only real Yiddish stage, and he
felt that here was an opportunity to have <hi rend="italic">Isaac Sheftel</hi>
produced.  But he reckoned without the managers; this gentry
refused even to look at the manuscript, because, forsooth, it was
written in three acts!  And is it not the first commandment of the
Yiddish theatre that all plays must be written in four?  From that
time on Pinski has gone his own way.  All his plays, except
<hi rend="italic">Isaac Sheftel</hi>, have thus been written in New York.  They
are the logical offspring of his ideals, written with an artistry
hitherto foreign to the Yiddish drama; at their best they leap across
the borders of the pale and take their place beside what is most
significant in universal drama.
</p><p>Thus, his <hi rend="italic">Zwie Family</hi>, finished in 1904 upon the day
for which his "Ph.D." examination was set at Columbia University,
is far more than a mere pogrom-drama, for which superficial readers
have mistaken it.  The figure of Moses Zwie, the old grandfather,
last of the pious Jews, who sees in his son and his three grandsons
the disintegration of the Jewish race, is likewise something
   <pb n="686"/>
more than a mere patriarch that has outlived his days.  Old Zwie
becomes a human symbol, a sort of Yiddish Brand, and the play
depicts the world-struggle between the Old and the New.  <hi rend="italic">The
Zwie Family</hi> was accepted for production at the Moscow Art
Theatre by Stanislavsky, but was forbidden by the censor.  What are
human symbols to censors, when the mention of pogroms can place
Russian officialdom &mdash; now happily overthrown &mdash; in an unenviable
light?  Societies for the production of the <hi rend="italic">Zwie Family</hi>
sprang into existence all over Russia, and the play had to be
smuggled into the country, as its production was a criminal offence.
It is interesting to know that Pinski never took his Ph.D.
examination.
</p><p>As playwright Pinski, even in his symbolic plays, belongs to
the realistic school.  He builds from character, and conventional
situations, climaxes, and so forth, are meaningless to him unless
they germinate from the inner soul of his men and women.  Hence
his <hi rend="italic">The Treasure</hi>, written in 1906 and produced in a German
version in 1910 by Max Reinhardt at the Deutsches Theatre, Berlin,
is a masterly satire upon the power of wealth, real or imaginary,
with a mystic epilogue that rises most naturally from the action that
precedes.  In general, his work may be divided into three manners:
the plays inspired by proletarian and domestic problems, his sex
dramas, and his biblical plays.  Of the first, <hi rend="italic">Isaac Sheftel</hi> is
the chief representative; the one-act <hi rend="italic">Forgotten Souls</hi> has
been hailed by Professor Burton as a masterpiece; of the second,
<hi rend="italic">Gabriel and the Women</hi> (comparable in some respects to
Shaw's <hi rend="italic">Candida</hi> and Ibsen's <hi rend="italic">Lady of the Sea</hi>) and
<hi rend="italic">Mary Magdalene</hi>, which is an entirely original and
unconventional treatment of the theme, in which Mary symbolises
woman's will to power.  In respect of humour and passion,
psychological insight and the suggestion of fascination, Pinski in
this play surpasses both Paul Heyse and Maurice Maeterlinck's
treatment of the same figure.  The biblical plays are biblical in
suggestion only; they deal with live men and women who are kin to
us and our day.  <hi rend="italic">The Wives of King David</hi> is a beautiful
series of one-act plays, five in all.  <hi rend="italic">The Dumb Messiah</hi>, one
of a group of dramas founded upon the Messianic idea, is a
masterpiece of colour, movement and poetic fire.  Here, too, the
figure of Menachem Penini, whose dream that he is the Messiah is
finally wrecked, with the result that he jumps from a high cliff into
the ocean, becomes a symbol of human disillusionment.  It is
almost incredible that a masterpiece of such deep appeal should
have been written at high emotional pressure in four days.
</p><p>Pinski, at his best, writes a Yiddish prose that is his own
discovery: a limpid, crystalline, melodious line that rivals the flow
of a Maeterlinck, a Yeats or a Dunsany.  His latest piece, <hi rend="italic">Little
Heroes</hi>, a one-act playlet of the present war in which the oldest
character is but fourteen and the youngest ten, is one of the most
touching artistic products of the conflict.  Its tender humanity would
have warmed the heart of Dickens; those same angels who, in their
lighter moments, have been said to sing Gilbert and Sullivan in the
heavens, would read <hi rend="italic">Little Heroes</hi> to the cherubim.  Pinski
is still a young man, and his best work may lie yet in the future.
</p><p>Sholom Asch is some seven or eight years younger than
Pinski.  Unlike the latter, he has been a resident of New York only
since the war, and was one of the arrivals that helped swing the
Yiddish literary centre of gravity from Warsaw to New York.
Again unlike Pinski, who is a Socialist and Jewish nationalist, Asch
is an individualist.  Russian by birth, he is by predilection
cosmopolitan.  At the age of twenty-four he started his literary
career with flying colours, with his drama <hi rend="italic">Returned</hi> and his
<hi rend="italic">The Town</hi>, a series of pictures of Jewish life which may, in
some respects, be likened to Phillpotts's charming <hi rend="italic">Widecombe
Fair</hi>.
</p><p>Asch has been hailed as the successor of Perez, but despite a
positive flair for the melodramatic, the theatrical, the effective,
   <pb n="687"/>
he has not cultivated, as yet, the vision and the art of the
genius who fostered him.  Asch, perhaps the most popular of living
Yiddish writers, has done much to earn that popularity.  He is at
times inclined, however, to be guided by, rather than to guide, his
readers.  A writer of undoubted power, humour, pathos, he is so
prolific, and his work is in such demand, that he shirks the sterner
dictates of adequate planning and technical mastery.  Yet more than
one of his earlier short stories, which have earned him the sobriquet
"the Yiddish Maupassant," is a masterpiece in its kind.  At his best
he is unsurpassed as a story-teller; one feels, and feels strongly,
positively, that he is much better than he sometimes cares to write
himself down.  His intense <hi rend="italic">God of Vengeance</hi>, produced in
German by Max Reinhardt in 1910, at the Deutsches Theatre, is a
drama that presents the terrible retribution visited upon parents who
keep a brothel into which their own daughter is at last ensnared,
despite the pious gifts with which they had hoped to buy their
child's purity as a compensation for their evil life.  The crushing
power of the final scene, where the father thrusts his daughter into
the cellar with the rest of his prostitutes, is as undeniable as it is
revolting.  <hi rend="italic">Jepthah's Daughter</hi>, a symbolic play upon the
theme of sex, is remarkable for its Dyonisiac frankness &mdash; a theme,
moreover, which is treated by Yiddish writers with far greater
freedom than would be permitted to their American
confr&egrave;res.  The play has beauty, poetry and elemental
power.  It is surpassed, however, by the one-act <hi rend="italic">The Sinner</hi>,
where the symbolism, though a little less clear at first, is united to a
plot where there is less insistence upon mere sex and more upon the
age-old struggle between orthodoxy and heterodoxy.  The latter
theme is one which has fascinated &mdash; and naturally, more than one of
the Yiddish writers.  Asch has treated it again in <hi rend="italic">With the
Current</hi> and <hi rend="italic">Our Faith</hi>.  He is not afraid to adopt an
unorthodox standpoint.  His latest play (excepting the recent
dramatisation of his novel <hi rend="italic">Mottke the Scamp</hi>) is <hi rend="italic">A String
of Pearls</hi>, in which the purity of the Yiddish race is framed
against a background, neutral in tone, of the present war.
</p><p>It is natural that Asch should have been accused of eroticism,
yet it should be constantly borne in mind that the Yiddish public
will listen to and read, without hiding it, much of what the
American public would affect not to care for, only to read it
surreptitiously.  The racial sense of humour is so strong, so
elemental, often so Rabelaisian, let us say, that what to outsiders
would appear a question of morality is really nothing but a problem
in humour.  At other times the presentation of certain scenes is an
artistic obligation which the author cannot shirk.  Thus, in Asch's
<hi rend="italic">Mottke the Scamp</hi>, which ran serially in the columns of the
New York <hi rend="italic">Forward</hi>, the world's largest Yiddish daily, and
was afterward published in book form, achieving an enormous sale,
there are certain passages to which Comstockian readers would
certainly object strongly in an English version.  And yet, the story of
Mottke's progress, or retrogression, from his birth in the cellar so
common to Jewish fiction, to his final imprisonment for self-confessed murder, demands those scenes and is spoiled without
them.  American squeamishness and hyper-puritanism have much to
profit from Yiddish fiction and Asch's healthy elementalism in
particular.
</p><p>Perhaps better even than <hi rend="italic">Mottke the Vagabond</hi>, which
is the title of the novel in its English translation, are Asch's two
older novels <hi rend="italic">Meri</hi> and <hi rend="italic">The Road to Self</hi>, which
present, in a wealth of colour, passion and frequent pages of
consummate artistry, the epic of the revolutionary and Zionistic
movement among the young Jews of Russia in the crucial days of
1905.
</p><p>The works of Abraham Raisin, who was recently accorded a
Jubilee at Carnegie Hall, in honour of his twenty-five years' service
to Yiddish literature, run to twelve solid volumes of poems, tales
and an occasional play.  His style is so
   <pb n="688"/>
simple, so unaffected, that at first one is misled into believing there
is little behind it.  He has been compared, by his admirers, to
Tchekov, for just this simplicity, this readiness to forsake the easier
field of sharply marked climaxes for the story that often has no real
ending &mdash; an unframed picture, as it were.  None knows better than
Raisin the soul of the wanderer; he is himself a Jewish Bohemian.
The Jewish reader, moreover, is not so insistent as the American
upon a rising climax in his tales, and many of Raisin's stories are in
reality fine genre pictures: snap-shots from life, flashlights of
character, related with a minimum of words and a maximum of
effect.  He appeals to people in their quieter, more contemplative
moods, even as his work has itself blossomed from reflection rather
than action.  His poetry has at times so well spoken for his people
that some of his verse is a national possession.
</p><p>Although Perez Hirschbein left New York a few months ago
for a circuitous journey to Russia, a few words should be said here
for the conscientious artistry of this writer.  He is about the same
age as Asch.  Although some of his work is spoiled by an
overinsistence upon symbolism, which he imbibed from the French,
and much of his drama is too poetic to endure before the footlights,
he is a highly successful seeker after beauty and truth.  The five
volumes of his plays published in 1916, containing twenty-six of his
dramatic works, and representing, incidentally, some of the best
bookmaking that has yet appeared with a Yiddish imprint, hold
between their covers much that should be known in English.
</p><p>None of the preceding writers has devoted much attention to
Yiddish life in America; Pinski says that the psychological types
which he prefers do not abound among the Jews on this side of the
water; Asch does not yet know America well enough.  It has been
left to Leon Kobrin and Zalmon Libin to write the drama and
comedy of the East Side.  Libin, who early made a name for himself
as a writer of powerful sketches, and has been called "the O. Henry
of the East Side," knows the trials of the immigrant as few of his
people do; he has lived through all he writes; he is, in fact, largely
autobiographical.  To read the tales of Kobrin and Libin, indeed, is
to peruse the best Baedecker to the East Side that one could desire.
Of the two Kobrin is the psychologist and Libin the anatomist, as it
were.  One sees the effect upon the immigrant's mind of his new
environment &mdash; follows it in its various stages, chronicles it with
minute detail; the other catches its more external, yet none the less
essential aspects, and endears himself to his race by his faithful
transcript of their daily trials.  Of late, however, Libin has
abandoned his natural field for the more lucrative writing of
theatrical thrillers.  Although he has been mentioned as the
compromiser, on the stage, between the purely literary drama and
popular trash, there is altogether too little literature in the
compromise.  Libin makes his living from his plays; he will live
through his tales.
</p><p>As dramatist Kobrin began by collaborating with Jacob
Gordin.  He has been identified with the fight of the better
playwrights against managerial tyranny, and dramas like <hi rend="italic">Israel's
Hope</hi> and <hi rend="italic">Children of Nature</hi> (which was lately
produced with much success, in a Russian version, at the Moscow
Art Theatre) rise far above the average pieces that draw East Side
audiences.
</p><p>Of those who are concerned exclusively with poetry, and
whose work, from the very nature of the medium they employ,
suffers most by translation, there lacks space to treat adequately.  I
should like to call attention to the neglect, in our tongue, of such a
spirit as Yehoash (Sol Bloomgarden).  Yiddish already has its
school of "young" poets, too.  The poetic consciousness of the race
cannot help being strongly stimulated by the recent appearance, in
two large, splendid volumes, of Bassin's anthology, entitled <hi rend="italic">Five
Hundred Years of Yiddish Poetry</hi>.  For Yiddish poetry dates
back to 1410.
</p><p>The "young" literary group as a whole reveals that same
restlessness and groping
   <pb n="689"/>
as characterises the youthful Americans.  Youth is youth,
whatever the tongue.  It is highly significant, too, that Noah
Steinberg's volume of criticism of the "young" spirits is called
<hi rend="italic">Young America</hi>.  For the new group of Yiddish writers
writes not only in, but on and of America.
</p><p>What the effect of the recent Russian revolution will be upon
Yiddish literature in New York is hard to tell.  At the end of the war
there may be a literary exodus to the old country; the removal of
restrictions against the Jews, and freedom to use their latent powers
in a country which they have never ceased to love may betoken new
things for Yiddish literature abroad.  Perhaps Warsaw will yet be
the capital of Jewish letters once again.  With the brightening of
hopes for Zion may come an era of Yiddish letters for which the
present renaissance may be but a preparation.  If America would
understand its great population of Jews, nothing could lead to such
an understanding better than a knowledge of New York's Yiddish
writers.
</p>

</div1>


</body>
</text>
</TEI.2>

