<?xml version="1.0"?>

<?dlps id="GorBill"?>
<?dlps page-images="none" figure-images="no"?>
<?dlps transcription="other"?>

<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/tei-p4/tei2.dtd" [
<!ENTITY % POSTKB "INCLUDE">
<!ENTITY % TEI.extensions.ent SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.ent">
<!ENTITY % TEI.extensions.dtd SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.dtd">
<!ENTITY % ISOnum SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/charent/iso-num.ent"> %ISOnum;
<!ENTITY % ISOlat1 SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/charent/iso-lat1.ent"> %ISOlat1;
<!ENTITY % ISOpub SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/charent/iso-pub.ent"> %ISOpub;

]>

<TEI.2 id="GorBill">
<teiHeader type="migrated" creator="Etext">
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title type="main">The Billionaire</title>
<title type="sort">billionaire</title>
<author>Gorky, Maxim</author>
<respStmt>
<resp>Creation of machine-readable version:</resp>
<name>Judy Boss</name>
<resp>Creation of digital images:</resp>
<name/>
<resp>Conversion to TEI.2-conformant markup:</resp>
<name>University of Virginia Library Electronic Text Center.</name>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt>
<extent>ca. <num type="kilobytes">11</num> kilobytes</extent>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>University of Virginia Library</publisher>
<pubPlace>Charlottesville, Virginia</pubPlace>
<idno type="ETC">GorBill</idno>
<date value="1996">1996</date>
<availability status="public">
<p n="copyright">Copyright &copy; 1996 by the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia</p>
<p n="access">Publicly accessible</p>
</availability>
<idno type="uva-pid">uva-lib:475999</idno>
</publicationStmt>
<seriesStmt>
<title>University of Virginia Library, Text collection</title>
<idno type="uva-set">UVA-LIB-Text</idno>
</seriesStmt>
<sourceDesc>
<biblFull>
<titleStmt>
<title type="main">The Billionaire</title>
<title level="j">The Arena</title>
<title type="sort">billionaire</title>
<author>Maxim Gorky</author>
<respStmt>
<resp>Translator</resp>
<name>Dunbar, Newell</name>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt>
<extent>pp 126-127</extent>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>Arena Publishing Company</publisher>
<pubPlace>Boston</pubPlace>
<date value="1907">1907</date>
<idno type="callNo">Print copy consulted: Alderman Library, Microfilm S-147 reel 98.</idno>
</publicationStmt>
<notesStmt>
<note>
<p>The Arena, Vol. 37, Feb. 1907</p>
</note>
</notesStmt>
</biblFull>
</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc>
<encodingDesc>
<projectDesc>
<p>Prepared for the University of Virginia Library Electronic Text Center.</p>
</projectDesc>
<editorialDecl>
<p>All quotation marks retained as data.</p>
<p>All unambiguous end-of-line hyphens have been removed, and the trailing part of a word has been joined to the preceding line.</p>
<p>Keywords in the header are a local Electronic Text Center scheme to aid in establishing analytical groupings.</p>
</editorialDecl>
</encodingDesc>
<profileDesc>
<creation>
<date value="1907">1907</date>
</creation>
<langUsage>
<language id="eng" usage="main">English</language>
</langUsage>
<textClass>
<keywords>
<term>non-fiction; prose</term>
<term>Literature in Translation</term>
</keywords>
</textClass>
</profileDesc>
<revisionDesc>
<change>
<date value="1996-10">October 1996</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>corrector</resp>
<name>Stephen Ramsay, Electronic Text Center</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Added TEI header and tags.</item>
</change>
<change>
<date value="2005-07">July 2005</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>Corrector</resp>
<name>John Ivor Carlson</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Converted SGML to XML. Fixed tagging.</item>
</change>
<change>
<date value="2007-09">September 2007</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>Migration</resp>
<name>Ethan Gruber, University of Virginia Library</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Converted XML markup from TEI Lite to uva-dl-tei (TEI P4 with local customizations).</item>
</change>
<change>
<date value="2008-01">January 2008</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>Migration</resp>
<name>Greg Murray, University of Virginia Library</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Programmatically updated TEI header markup (but not header content) for minimal compliance with current QA requirements.</item>
</change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>
<text id="d1">

<body id="d2">



<div1 type="essay" id="d3"><pb n="126"/>
<head>THE BILLIONAIRE.<ref target="n126">[note]</ref><lb/>
BY MAXIM GORKI.</head>

<p>THE KINGS of steel, of petroleum, and all the other kings of the
United States have always in a high degree excited my power of
imagination.  It seemed to me certain that these people who possess
so much money could not be like other mortals.
</p><p>Each of them (so I said to myself) must call his own, at least,
three stomachs and a hundred and fifty teeth.  I did not doubt that
the millionaire ate without intermission, from six o'clock in the
morning till midnight.  It goes without saying, the most exquisite
and sumptuous viands!  Toward evening, then, he must be tired of
the hard chewing, to such a degree that (so I pictured to myself) he
gave orders to his darkies to <hi rend="italic">digest</hi> the meals that he had
swallowed with satisfaction during the day.  Completely limp,
covered with sweat and almost suffocated, he had to be put to bed
by his servants, in order that on the next morning at six o'clock he
might be able to begin again his work of eating.
</p><p>Nevertheless, it must be impossible for such a man&mdash;whatever
pains he might take&mdash;to consume merely the half of the interest of
his wealth.
</p><p>To be sure, such a life is awful, but what is one to do?  For
what is one a millionaire&mdash;what am I saying?&mdash;a <hi rend="italic">billionaire</hi>,
if one cannot eat more than every other common mortal!  I pictured
to myself that this privileged being wore cloth-of-gold
underclothing, shoes with gold nails, and instead of a hat a diadem
of diamonds on his head.  His clothes, made of the most expensive
velvet, must be at least fifty feet long and fastened with three
hundred gold buttons; and on holidays he must be compelled by
dire necessity to put on over each other six pairs of costly trousers.
Such a costume is certainly very uncomfortable.  But, if one is rich
like that, one can't after all dress like all the world.
</p><p>The pocket of a billionaire, I pictured to myself so big that
therein easily a church or the whole senate could find room.  The
paunch of such a gentleman I conceived to myself like the hull of an
ocean steamer, the length and breadth of which I was not able to
think out.  Of the bulk, too, of a billionaire I could never give
myself a clear idea; but I supposed that the coverlet under which he
sleeps measures a dozen hundred square yards.  If he chews
tobacco, it was unquestionably only the best kind, of which he
always sticks two pounds at a time into his mouth.  And on taking
snuff (I thought to myself) he must use up a pound at a pinch.
Indeed, money will be spent!
</p><p>His fingers must possess the magic power of lengthening at
will.  In spirit, I saw a New York billionaire as he stretched out his
hand across Bering Strait and brought back a dollar that had rolled
somewhere toward Siberia, without especially exerting himself
thereby.
</p><p>Curiously, I could form to myself no clear conception of the
<hi rend="italic">head</hi> of this monster.  In this organism consisting of gigantic
muscles and bones that is made for squeezing money out of all
things, a head seemed to me really quite superfluous.
</p><p>Who, now, can conceive my astonishment when, standing facing one of
these fabulous beings, I arrived at the conviction that
a billionaire is a human being like all the rest!
</p><p>I saw there comfortably reclining in an armchair a long,
wizened old man, who held his brown, sinewy hands folded across a
body of quite ordinary dimensions.  The flabby skin of his face was
carefully shaved.  The underlip, which
<pb n="127"/>
hung loosely down, covered solidly built jaws, in which gilded teeth
were stuck.  The upper lip, smooth, narrow and pallid, scarcely
moved when the old man spoke.  Colorless eyes without brows, a
perfectly bald skull.  It might be thought that a little skin was
wanting to this reddish face, to this countenance that was
expressionless and puckered like that of one new-born.  Was this
being just beginning its life, or was it already nearing its end?
</p><p>Nothing in his dress distinguished him from the ordinary
mortal.  A ring, a watch, and his teeth were all the gold he carried
with him.  Scarcely half a pound, all told!  Taken altogether, the
appearance of the man recalled that of an old servant of an
aristocratic family in Europe.
</p><p>The furnishing of the room in which he received me had
nothing unusually luxurious about it.  The furniture was solid; that
is all that can be said.  Oftentimes elephants probably come into this
house, I involuntarily thought at the sight of the heavy, substantial
pieces of furniture.
</p><p>"Are you the billionaire?" I asked, since I could not trust my
eyes.
</p><p>"Yes, indeed," he answered, nodding convincingly with his
head.
</p><p>"How much meat can you consume for breakfast?"
</p><p>"I eat no meat in the morning," he avowed.  "A quarter of an
orange, an egg, a small cup of tea, that's all . . ."
</p><p>His innocent child's-eyes blinked with a feeble luster, like two
drops of muddy water.
</p><p>"Good," I began again, half disconcerted.  "But be honest with
me; tell me the truth.  How often in the day do you eat?"
</p><p>"Twice," he answered, peacefully.  "Breakfast and dinner
suffice me.  At noon I take soup, a little white meat, vegetables,
fruit, a cup of coffee, a cigar . . ."
</p><p>My surprise grew apace.  I drew breath, and went on:
</p><p>"But, if that's true, what do you do with your money?"
</p><p>"Make more money!"
</p><p>"What for?"
</p><p>"To make more money out of that!"
</p><p>"What for?" I repeated.
</p><p>He leaned toward me, his hands supported by the arms of his
chair, and with some curiosity in his expression he said:
</p><p>"You are probably cracked?"
</p><p>"And you?" I said . . .
</p><p>The old man inclined his head, and, whistling softly through
the gold of his teeth, he said:
</p><p>"Droll wag! . . .  You are the first human being of your species
that I ever became acquainted with."
</p><p>Then he bent his head back and looked at me some time,
silently and scrutinizingly.
</p><p>"What do you do?" I began again.
</p><p>"Make money," he answered, shortly.
</p><p>"Oh, you're a counterfeiter!" I exclaimed, joyfully, for I
thought I had finally got to the bottom of the mystery.  But the
billionaire flew into a passion.  His whole body shook, his eyes
rolled actively.
</p><p>"That is unheard of!" he said, when he had calmed down.
Then he inflated his cheeks, I don't know why.
</p><p>I considered, and put further the following question to him:
</p><p>"How do you make money?"
</p><p>"Oh, that's very simple.  I possess railroads; the farmers
produce useful commodities, which I transport to the markets.  I
calculate exactly to myself how much money I must leave the
farmer, in order that he may not starve and be able to produce
further.  The rest I keep myself as transportation charges.  That's
surely very simple!"
</p><p>"And are the farmers satisfied with it?"
</p><p>"Not all, I believe," he answered, with a na&iuml;ve
childishness.  "But they say that the people are never satisfied.
There are always odd characters who want still more . . ."</p>
                                     <signed>MAXIM GORKI.</signed>
</div1>
<div1 type="notes" id="d4">
<note id="n126"><seg type="note-symbol">[note]</seg> <p>Translated from the German for THE ARENA, by
NEWELL DUNBAR.</p></note>
</div1>

</body>
</text>
</TEI.2>
