<?xml version="1.0"?>

<?dlps id="GorHear"?>
<?dlps page-images="none" figure-images="no"?>
<?dlps transcription="other"?>

<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/tei-p4/tei2.dtd" [
<!ENTITY % POSTKB "INCLUDE">
<!ENTITY % TEI.extensions.ent SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.ent">
<!ENTITY % TEI.extensions.dtd SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.dtd">
<!ENTITY % ISOnum SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/charent/iso-num.ent"> %ISOnum;
<!ENTITY % ISOpub SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/charent/iso-pub.ent"> %ISOpub;

]>
<TEI.2 id="GorHear">
<teiHeader type="migrated" creator="Etext">
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title type="main">The Heart of a Beggar: A Story by Gorky</title>
<title type="sort">heart of a beggar a story by gorky</title>
<author>Gorky, Maxim</author>
<respStmt>
<resp>Translator</resp>
<name>Paull, Montressor</name>
<resp>Creation of machine-readable version:</resp>
<name>Judy Boss</name>
<resp>Conversion to TEI.2-conformant markup:</resp>
<name>University of Virginia Library Electronic Text Center.</name>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt>
<extent>ca. <num type="kilobytes">15</num> kilobytes</extent>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>University of Virginia Library</publisher>
<pubPlace>Charlottesville, Virginia</pubPlace>
<idno type="ETC">GorHear</idno>
<date value="1999">1999</date>
<availability status="public">
<p n="copyright">Copyright &copy; 1999 by the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia</p>
<p n="access">Publicly accessible</p>
</availability>
<idno type="uva-pid">uva-lib:476000</idno>
</publicationStmt>
<seriesStmt>
<title>University of Virginia Library, Text collection</title>
<idno type="uva-set">UVA-LIB-Text</idno>
</seriesStmt>
<notesStmt>
<note>
<p>In the final paragraph, Judy Boss changed "commited" to "committed"</p>
</note>
</notesStmt>
<sourceDesc>
<biblFull>
<titleStmt>
<title type="main">The Heart of a Beggar</title>
<title level="j">Current Literature</title>
<title type="sort">heart of a beggar</title>
<author>Maxim Gorky</author>
<respStmt>
<resp>Translator</resp>
<name>Montressor Paull</name>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>Current Literature Pub.</publisher>
<pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
<date value="1909">1888-1912</date>
<idno type="callNo">Source copy consulted: UVa Library, s-147</idno>
</publicationStmt>
<notesStmt>
<note>
<p>This story appeared in v. 47 (Aug 1909), p. 220-221.</p>
</note>
</notesStmt>
</biblFull>
</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc>
<encodingDesc>
<projectDesc>
<p>Prepared for the University of Virginia Library Electronic Text Center.</p>
</projectDesc>
<editorialDecl>
<p>All unambiguous end-of-line hyphens have been removed, and the  trailing part of a word has been joined to the preceding line.</p>
<p id="ETC">Some keywords in the header are a local Electronic Text Center scheme  to aid in establishing analytical groupings.</p>
</editorialDecl>
</encodingDesc>
<profileDesc>
<creation>
<date value="1909">1909</date>
</creation>
<langUsage>
<language id="eng" usage="main">English</language>
</langUsage>
<textClass>
<keywords>
<term>fiction</term>
<term>prose</term>
<term>masculine</term>
<term>Literature in Translation</term>
</keywords>
</textClass>
</profileDesc>
<revisionDesc>
<change>
<date value="1999-03">March 1999</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>corrector</resp>
<name>June Griffin, Electronic Text Center</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Added TEI header and tags.</item>
</change>
<change>
<date value="2005-07">July 2005</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>Corrector</resp>
<name>John Ivor Carlson</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Converted SGML to XML. Fixed tagging.</item>
</change>
<change>
<date value="2007-09">September 2007</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>Migration</resp>
<name>Ethan Gruber, University of Virginia Library</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Converted XML markup from TEI Lite to uva-dl-tei (TEI P4 with local customizations).</item>
</change>
<change>
<date value="2008-01">January 2008</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>Migration</resp>
<name>Greg Murray, University of Virginia Library</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Programmatically updated TEI header markup (but not header content) for minimal compliance with current QA requirements.</item>
</change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>
<text id="d1">

<body id="d2">



<div1 type="story" id="d3"><head>THE HEART OF A BEGGAR    &mdash;    A STORY BY GORKY</head>

<p>Maxim Gorky is always vivid and usually terrible in his
portrayal of the underworld of Russia.  In this little character-sketch
(translated for us by Montressor Paull), he strikes a note of
tenderness that is less usual with him.

</p><p>A VAGRANT, a brother of beggars, a vagabond like himself, whom
he met at a turn of the country road as night came, said to him, "If
you wish to do a neat trick, walk straight forward, go across the
bridge and follow the edge of the wood, and on the right you will
find a villa that looks like a castle.  There is no outer wall, and there
is no moat.  There is nobody guarding it    &mdash;    the gentleman and his
family have not yet returned, and the gardener is sick abed.  And
there is no dog,    &mdash;    a little while ago I stroked his snout with this
stick.  Once in the house you will be highly puzzled to make a
choice.  If you have a heart in your body," said the vagabond in
conclusion, "don't fail to use this opportunity.  You can turn the
neatest kind of a trick there, sure thing!"
</p><p>Uttering not a word of comment, Red Fox, as he was known
among his fellows, followed this suggestion promptly.  After a night
spent in the open air of the fields    &mdash;    it was in July and the sun was
glowing upon the earth with scorching heat    &mdash;    he had gone his way
at break of day.  A fresh breath was caressing the horizon, and a
light, transparent blue vapor was rising from the meadows.  The
expanses where the ears swayed on high stalks seemed to be living
carpets, and the river in its sinuous passage through the plain looked
like a bright, clear, silvered ribbon.
</p><p>The Red Fox strode across the bridge and thence to the edge of
the wood, where he began to walk hastily along, expecting the villa
soon to come into sight.  Clad in dull tatters and with noiseless
shoes of coarse cloth on his feet, he seemed to glide like a gray
shadow through the grass, that was now glistening with patches of
liveliest color.
</p><p>His face was that of a prematurely old man, furrowed and
devastated by most bitter privations long suffered.  It seemed to
have not the faintest expression.  Only in his eyes was there a gleam
of life.  And only the foxy hair of his scalp and his beard seemed to
distinguish him from the other beggars who were slinking up and
down the country road.  For this reason, too, he was known as the
Red Fox among his companions in suffering, and among the
farmers who sometimes gave him shelter and did not know his
name.

</p><p>The wood lay behind him, and before him, almost a hundred
yards from the road, an occasional portion of the villa was visible
where the luxuriant bushes of bloom of the great garden-beds were
not a delightful screen.  The various shapes of its roof covered with
slate, the walls of brick trimmed with blocks of stone, its coquettish
slim towers and the broad, distinguished stairway of its portico,    &mdash;
all these gave to the villa an air of elegant majesty as it stood facing
the horizon.  They dominated the whole vicinity and seemed to say,
"Look at this!  All this belongs to us!  We are the masters!"
</p><p>The stroller stood still; but before he made a final, stern
resolve, he let himself sink into the grass.  A kind of swoon, as it
were, was pervading his very soul.  It was the first time he found
himself engrossed by an intention to steal.
</p><p>Certainly till the present day he had been wont to commit
numberless little sins along the many country roads over which fate
had led him.  Never, however, had he broken open a door or
climbed a wall or taken in any criminal manner the most trivial sum
of money.  And, indeed, why should he have done such a thing?
Did he not feel, after all, that a life of vigor was bounding through
his veins, and who could persuade him to believe that he was not
happy?
</p><p>It was sheer accident that had brought together him and the old
beggar who had taught him to weave baskets.  Having acquired a
trade, he wandered from one neighborhood to another, working in
summer among willow bushes along charming streams, and in
winter beside some hospitable hearth.  Wherever he went he found a
ready sale for his light baskets.  They looked as if they had been
woven of the switches of willow of gold.

</p><p>In the twilight of an evening of spring he had met a woman at
a well that was near a village that seemed lost to the rest of the
world.  She was neither beautiful nor pretty, but she had tender eyes
and a smile of humility and resignation.  Her face bore the
expression that is given only by great suffering.  She was an orphan,
a poor girl of the country, who had been treated harshly by her
employer.  The vagabond and this unhappy woman saw and loved
each other.  He vaunted the freedom there was under the
immeasurable skies whose sun shone down so kindly upon the poor.
She followed him, and from this day on they wandered together
through the moist valleys in which the rushes grew like great
scepters.
</p><p>The years had glided away.  As the wanderers felt no concern
for time they never gave to it the slightest thought.  Then one day
came a child.  Yes, between these two miserable persons there
forced its way a little, still more miserable creature that, in spite of
circumstance, soon became so pretty, so rosy, so graceful, so blond,
that anyone who saw it would have taken it for a child of wealth
who had come to the world in laces.  Father and mother were
astounded at this unexpected gift from fate, their souls were wondrously


<pb n="221"/>

enthralled by it, and they were filled with admiration.  This
son became their idol.  So that he might feel well and be vigorous,
so that he might always have enough to eat, so that he might sleep
in most refreshing comfort, they sacrificed themselves eagerly,
abandoned themselves to toil by day and by night, suffering, and
without a word of complaint.

</p><p>The child grew larger.  It was four years old when its mother
suddenly died.  "She caught the fever from being near the water so
often and so long," a farmer said to the basket-maker.  "Take care, I
tell you.  If he, still so young, lies round in the willow bushes the
little fellow will surely come to the same thing."
</p><p>The father gave no heed to this warning.  Now as formerly he
led the same life.  His tenderness for his departed comrade, this
tenderness which as time passed became a jealous, wild passion, he
transferred to the child, for the child was the living reminder of the
dead woman and the pledge of her love.  Yes, it was still more    &mdash;    it
was the hope, the pride, indeed, of this vagabond, it was his ideal of
gentleness and of beauty!  Ah, the fine curly hair, the deep, deep
eyes, the rosy smile on the little white teeth!  How insistently the
father loved all this!  What a tremor of joy rushed through him
when he contemplated all this!
</p><p>But why had he found so trivial the advice that had been given
him, the warning?  The child, too, was consumed by fever.  In the
first weeks of summer it died, precisely as the mother had died.
And the vagabond    &mdash;    perhaps for the first time in his life    &mdash;    cried
bitterly.
</p><p>He cried, but his tears brought him no alleviation.  He felt as if
the blood had ebbed from his veins, as if everything around him had
become hideously black, as if the beats in his bosom had ceased.
Ever his eyes were seeking the child.  Ever he tried to conjure it up
before him in spirit    &mdash;    its dear picture    &mdash;    its smile    &mdash;    its movements.
His endeavor was vain, grimly vain.  And not a single familiar
object of the dead little fellow's group of treasures remained for the
father, whose pain became the more persistent and cruel the more
he felt the lack of every token of remembrance.
</p><p>From this day forward this man became bad.  A blind hatred
rose steadily in his sore heart, and at the same time he was
conscious of an impulse to do evil and to destroy.
</p><p>"Whether apples or gold coins are stolen there is really no
difference," a companion of the road had said to him in a whisper
one day.  Tacitly he had said to himself, "Indeed, yes, and like the
others I intend to steal now, too."
</p><p>The Red Fox, stretched out at his full length in the grass, had
just repeated this oath.  He rose now, sprang across the shallow
ditch near him and soon went striding through the deserted avenues
of the park.  The nearer he came to it the less shy he felt of the
majestic villa.  When he began to touch its walls he thought of it
with contempt, as a man despises some defenceless creature he
intends to torment.
</p><p>Slowly he crept around the house.  On the side where many
trees were planted he discovered a glass door that was almost even
with the ground.  No one saw him.  With his knife he destroyed the
lock, he broke in a pane, and soon the door yielded.  He was now
inside.
</p><p>At first he saw nothing.  The lowered venetian blinds kept the
room <orig reg="thoroughly">thoroly</orig> dark.  But slowly, very slowly, his eyes
accustomed themselves to the deep twilight.  Suddenly he stood still
as if transfixed.  A refreshing coolness prevailed in the salon he had
entered and it seemed to him that he noticed the odor of faded
flowers.  On the walls between golden arabesques, old paintings
were smiling.  Glistening oak and lacquer furniture surrounded him.
Everywhere were costly and rare objects of vertu in abundance.
Never had the beggar seen so many wonders.  His astonishment at
the sight of all these elegant and frivolous things was most keen.
He sought to fathom the purpose of them, and a new fear pregnant
with veneration came over him.
</p><p>Yet he must act!  But what of the many things here should he
take with him?  If some day he should attempt to sell the most
trivial of these objects he would betray himself.  Suddenly he
caught sight of a secretary and opened one of its drawers.  Two gold
coins, which had been forgotten here, lay gleaming in the shadow.
Already he was stretching forth his hand when his glance fell
abruptly on a photograph that stood on the blotter before him.
Astonished, confused, enraptured, he stood still, his hand in poise.
It was the head of a child in a neat frame.
</p><p>He contemplated the bewitching face, the fine curly hair, the
deep, deep eyes, the rosy smile showing the little white teeth.
Without a doubt it was the son of the master of the villa.  But to the
vagabond this picture was that of his own son.  He again found the
grace of the little beggar and his features in the picture of this rich
child that had come to the world in laces.  Not for a moment did it
occur to him that this was only an accidental resemblance.  Only
one thing seemed to him certain    &mdash;    he possessed not one token of
remembrance of the dead child, and this dead child lived again in
this picture.
</p><p>The vagabond made no further delay.  He seized the portrait,
covered it with kisses, stuck it in the pocket over his heart and fled.
</p><p>All his hate had disappeared.  He had just committed his first
theft, and also his last.  All other things, of whatever value, gave
him no concern, for he now possessed a reminder of his child, on
whom he had always showered such hot love from the heart of a
beggar.</p>

</div1>

</body>

</text>

</TEI.2>
