<?xml version="1.0"?>

<?dlps id="GorLife"?>
<?dlps page-images="none" figure-images="no"?>
<?dlps transcription="other"?>

<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/tei-p4/tei2.dtd" [
<!ENTITY % POSTKB "INCLUDE">
<!ENTITY % TEI.extensions.ent SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.ent">
<!ENTITY % TEI.extensions.dtd SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.dtd">
<!ENTITY % ISOnum SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/charent/iso-num.ent"> %ISOnum;
<!ENTITY % ISOpub SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/charent/iso-pub.ent"> %ISOpub;

]>

<TEI.2 id="GorLife">
<teiHeader type="migrated" creator="Etext">
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title type="main">"Confronting Life"</title>
<title type="sort">confronting life</title>
<author>Gorky, Maxim</author>
<respStmt>
<resp>Creation of machine-readable version: Judy Boss</resp>
<name>Tom Lukas</name>
<resp>Conversion to TEI.2-conformant markup:</resp>
<name>University of Virginia Library Electronic Text Center.</name>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt>
<extent>ca. <num type="kilobytes">8</num> kilobytes</extent>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>University of Virginia Library</publisher>
<pubPlace>Charlottesville, Virginia</pubPlace>
<idno type="ETC">GorLife</idno>
<date value="1996">1996</date>
<availability status="public">
<p n="copyright">Copyright &copy; 1996 by the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia</p>
<p n="access">Publicly accessible</p>
</availability>
<idno type="uva-pid">uva-lib:476001</idno>
</publicationStmt>
<seriesStmt>
<title>University of Virginia Library, Text collection</title>
<idno type="uva-set">UVA-LIB-Text</idno>
</seriesStmt>
<notesStmt>
<note>
<p>(Judy Boss) In line 47 I have changed "crums" to "crumbs" and in line 52 I
have added the missing terminal quotation mark after "demand."</p>
</note>
</notesStmt>
<sourceDesc>
<biblFull>
<titleStmt>
<title type="main">"Confronting Life"</title>
<title level="j">Cosmopolitan Vol. 38</title>
<title type="sort">confronting life</title>
<author>Maxim Gorky</author>
<respStmt>
<resp>translator</resp>
<name>Frances Kovitch</name>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt>
<extent>p. 717</extent>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>Cosmopolitan Publishing Company</publisher>
<pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
<date value="1905-04">April 1905</date>
</publicationStmt>
<notesStmt>
<note>
<p>University of Virginia Library Call no: AP2 .C8</p>
</note>
</notesStmt>
</biblFull>
</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc>
<encodingDesc>
<projectDesc>
<p>Prepared for the University of Virginia Library Electronic Text
Center.</p>
</projectDesc>
<editorialDecl>
<p>All quotation marks retained as data.</p>
<p>Spell-check and verification made
against printed text using WordPerfect spell checker.</p>
<p>All unambiguous end-of-line hyphens have been removed, and the
trailing part of a word has been joined to the preceding line.</p>
<p>The images exist as archived TIFF images, one or more JPEG versions
for general use, and thumbnail GIFs.</p>
<p id="ETC">Keywords in the header are a local Electronic Text Center scheme
to aid in establishing analytical groupings.</p>
</editorialDecl>
<refsDecl>
<p>ID elements are given for each page element and are composed of the text's
unique cryptogram and the given page number, as in AusEmma1 for page one of
Jane Austen's Emma.</p>
</refsDecl>
</encodingDesc>
<profileDesc>
<creation>
<date value="1905">1905</date>
</creation>
<langUsage>
<language id="eng" usage="main">English</language>
</langUsage>
<textClass>
<keywords>
<term>fiction; prose</term>
<term>Literature in Translation</term>
</keywords>
</textClass>
</profileDesc>
<revisionDesc>
<change>
<date value="1996-06">June 1996</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>corrector</resp>
<name>Tom Lukas</name>
</respStmt>
<item>added TEI.2 tags and header</item>
</change>
<change>
<date value="2005-07">July 2005</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>Corrector</resp>
<name>John Ivor Carlson</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Converted SGML to XML. Fixed tagging.</item>
</change>
<change>
<date value="2007-09">September 2007</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>Migration</resp>
<name>Ethan Gruber, University of Virginia Library</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Converted XML markup from TEI Lite to uva-dl-tei (TEI P4 with local customizations).</item>
</change>
<change>
<date value="2008-01">January 2008</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>Migration</resp>
<name>Greg Murray, University of Virginia Library</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Programmatically updated TEI header markup (but not header content) for minimal compliance with current QA requirements.</item>
</change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text id="d1">
<body id="d2">

<div1 type="story" id="d3"><pb n="717"/>  <head><hi rend="bold">CONFRONTING LIFE</hi><ref target="n1">[1]</ref><lb/>
By MAXIM GORKY</head>

<p>CONFRONTING Life, two people stood&mdash;both discontent.  And to the
question, "What do you expect of me?" one made answer with weary
voice: "I am distracted by the cruelty of thy contradictions.  Feebly my
reason strives to understand the meaning of existence, and with
perplexing gloom my heart is filled before thee.  My consciousness doth
tell me man is the highest of creations."</p>
     <p>"What wouldst thou have of me?" fearless, questioned Life.</p>
     <p>"Happiness!  For my happiness it is necessary that thou shouldst
reconcile two endless chains of contradictions in my breast, brought
about by my 'I will' and thy 'Thou must.'"</p>
     <p>"Will that which for me thou must," Life sternly said.</p>
     <p>"I do not wish to be thy victim!" the man exclaimed.  "I wish to be
the sovereign of life, and am compelled to bend the neck beneath her
yoke of laws&mdash;wherefore?"</p>
     <p>"Speak plainer," put in the other fellow, standing nearer Life; but,
heedless of his companion's words, the first went on:</p>
     <p>"I wish for freedom&mdash;to live in harmony with my desires, and do not
want to be unto my neighbor, from sense of duty, either a brother or a
servant.  I would be that which I should freely choose&mdash;a slave or brother.
I do not wish that in society I shall constitute a black, of which society
may dispose at will.  I am a man, the mind, the spirit of life; I must be
free!"</p>
     <p>"One moment," interrupted Life, smiling sternly.  "Thou didst speak
at length, and all that thou wouldst further say is known to me.  Thou
wouldst be free?  Well&mdash;be so!  Wrestle, subdue me and become my
master; then will I be thy slave.  Thou knowest I am not partial and ever
yielded readily to conquerors.  But thou must conquer.  Art thou prepared
to battle with me for thy freedom's sake?  Yes?  Art strong enough for
victory, and in thy strength hast confidence?"</p>
     <p>And the man said, mournfully: "Thou hast set me at war with mine
own self; thou hast made keen my reason like a blade&mdash;deep, deep it
plunged into my heart and crushed it."</p>
     <p>"Be more severe with the tyrant; stop complaining," again put in the
other man.</p>
     <p>But the first continued: "I want a respite from thy oppression.  Give
me a taste of happiness!"</p>
     <p>Life smiled again, a smile like gleaming ice:</p>
     <p>"Tell me, when thus thou speakest, dost thou demand or
beg?"</p>
     <p>"I beg," came like an echo from the man.</p>
     <p>"You beg, like a habitual mendicant.  But I must tell thee, poor
unfortunate, Life bestows no alms.  And&mdash;do you know?&mdash;the free ask not,
they take my gifts themselves.  Why, thou, thou art but the slave of thy
desires, no more.  Free is he who hath the power to withdraw himself
from all desires and throw his total strength into but one.  Didst
understand?  Away!"</p>
     <p>He understood, and, crouching dog-like at Life's indifferent feet,
made ready to pick up submissively the stray crumbs that fell from off
her table, her leavings.</p>
     <p>Then did the lack-luster eyes of stern Life glance at the
other man&mdash;his was a rough but kindly face:</p>
     <p>"What do you ask?"</p>
     <p>"I ask not, I demand."</p>
     <p>"What?"</p>
     <p>"Justice!  Come, give her up.  All else I will take later; meantime I
do insist on naught but justice.  I waited long; patiently I waited; my days
were spent in labor, sans rest, sans light!  I waited&mdash;  But enough!  I seek
for justice!"</p>
     <p>And unto him Life calmly answered: "Take."</p>
</div1>

<div1 type="note" id="d4">
<note id="n1"><seg type="note-symbol">1.</seg> <p>This is one of three sketches by Gorky, whose publication was
prohibited in Russia.  It has been translated for "The Cosmopolitan" by
Frances Kovitch.</p></note>
</div1>

</body>
</text>
</TEI.2>

