<?xml version="1.0"?>

<?dlps id="GreAddi"?>
<?dlps page-images="none" figure-images="no"?>
<?dlps transcription="other"?>

<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/tei-p4/tei2.dtd" [
<!ENTITY % POSTKB "INCLUDE">
<!ENTITY % TEI.extensions.ent SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.ent">
<!ENTITY % TEI.extensions.dtd SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.dtd">
<!ENTITY % ISOnum SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/charent/iso-num.ent"> %ISOnum;
]><TEI.2 id="GreAddi">
<teiHeader type="migrated" creator="Etext">
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title type="main">Additional Texts - Yuchi</title>
<title type="sort">additional texts yuchi</title>
<author>Gregory, James Roane</author>
<respStmt>
<resp>Editor</resp>
<name>Cox, Barbara</name>
<resp>Creation of machine-readable version:</resp>
<name>Thompson, Carolyn</name>
<resp>Creation of digital images:</resp>
<name>Thompson, Carolyn</name>
<resp>Conversion to TEI.2-conformant markup:</resp>
<name>American Native Press Archives and Sequoyah Research Center, University of Arkansas at Little Rock (http://www.anpa.ualr.edu)</name>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt>
<extent>ca. <num type="kilobytes">72</num> kilobytes</extent>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>University of Virginia Library</publisher>
<pubPlace>Charlottesville, Virginia</pubPlace>
<idno type="ETC">GreAddi</idno>
<date value="2004-07-22">July 22, 2004</date>
<availability status="public">
<p n="copyright">Copyright &copy; 2004 by the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia</p>
<p n="access">Publicly accessible</p>
</availability>
<idno type="uva-pid">uva-lib:476007</idno>
</publicationStmt>
<seriesStmt>
<title>University of Virginia Library, Text collection</title>
<idno type="uva-set">UVA-LIB-Text</idno>
</seriesStmt>
<sourceDesc>
<biblFull>
<titleStmt>
<title type="main">Additional Texts - Yuchi</title>
<title type="sort">additional texts yuchi</title>
<author>James Roane Gregory</author>
<respStmt>
<resp>Editor</resp>
<name>Barbara Cox</name>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt>
<editionStmt>
<p>1st Edition. <date value="2004-07-24">July 24, 2004</date>
</p>
</editionStmt>
<publicationStmt>
<pubPlace>Little Rock, Ar.</pubPlace>
<date value="2004-07-24">July 24, 2004</date>
</publicationStmt>
</biblFull>
</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc>
<encodingDesc>
<projectDesc>
<p>Prepared for the UALR American Native Press Archives and Sequoyah Research Center.</p>
</projectDesc>
<editorialDecl>
<p>Spell-check made against printed text using Microsoft Word spell checker.</p>
<p>All unambiguous end-of-line hyphens have been removed, and the trailing part of a
word has been joined to the preceding line.</p>
</editorialDecl>
<refsDecl>
<p>ID elements are given for each page element and are composed of the text's unique
cryptogram and the given page number, as in AusEmma1 for page one of Jane
Austen's Emma.</p>
</refsDecl>
</encodingDesc>
<profileDesc>
<langUsage>
<language id="eng" usage="main">English</language>
</langUsage>
<textClass>
<keywords>
<term>Indians of North America--essays, Indians of North America--Muscogee, Indian Territory--in literature, Indian Territory (Okla.)--essays, American literature--Indian authors</term>
</keywords>
</textClass>
</profileDesc>
<revisionDesc>
<change>
<date value="2005-07">July 2005</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>Corrector</resp>
<name>John Ivor Carlson</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Converted SGML to XML. Fixed tagging.</item>
</change>
<change>
<date value="2007-09">September 2007</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>Migration</resp>
<name>Ethan Gruber, University of Virginia Library</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Converted XML markup from TEI Lite to uva-dl-tei (TEI P4 with local customizations).</item>
</change>
<change>
<date value="2008-01">January 2008</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>Migration</resp>
<name>Greg Murray, University of Virginia Library</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Programmatically updated TEI header markup (but not header content) for minimal compliance with current QA requirements.</item>
</change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>
<text id="d1">
<body id="d2">
<div1 type="text" id="d3">
<head>Additional Texts - Yuchi</head>
<div2 type="statement" id="d4">
<head>Note About the Editor</head>
<p>Barbara Cox is a descendent of James Roane Gregory. These texts are of two
types, histories and correspondence. The histories follow the pattern of
those published above.</p>
<p>The correspondence includes letters Gregory sent to two prominent Indian
Territory figures, Emmet Starr and Pleasant Porter. It is included because
of the light it sheds on Gregory's concepts of American Indian history and culture.</p>
<p>Starr was a native of the Cherokee Nation who graduated from the Cherokee
Male Seminary before attending Barnes Medical College in St. Louis. He
practiced medicine for five years in the Nation, but gave up that profession
to take up his monumental work on Cherokee genealogy and history.</p>
<p>After serving in the Confederate Creek Regiment during the Civil War, Porter
reorganized the Creek school system and was a delegate to Washington. He
served his people in various ways before becoming Principal Chief in 1899, a
post he held until his death in 1907.</p>
</div2>
<div2 type="work" id="d5" n="1">
<head>Correspondence</head>
<div3 type="part" id="d6" n="1">
<head>Inola, Indian Territory - August 29, 1898</head>
<p>
<hi rend="bold">August 29, 1898</hi>
</p>
<p>
<hi rend="bold">Doctor Emmett Starr</hi>
</p>
<p>
<hi rend="bold">Cherokee Historian</hi>
</p>
<p>
<hi rend="bold">Claremore, Cherokee Nation</hi>
</p>
<p>
<hi rend="bold">Indian Territory</hi>
</p>
<p>
<hi rend="bold">Sir:</hi>
</p>
<p>I am informed by Doctor W. R. Harper of Inola that you are engaged in
writing A History of the Cherokee Tribe. I was employed by Chief
Isparhechar of this Nation (Creek) to translate from the Muskogee
Language to English for the purpose of giving an account of the first
treaty of peace between the Cherokees and Muskogees, which is contained
in the tradition of "The Small Circle of Beads or (Ko-nau-wau) and the
Northern Cloud." Chief Isparhechar had this translation made, as I
understood, to present to Daniel Red Bird, and David Muskrat, of the
"Ketowah" Society for the Cherokee Indians who had forgotten the
tradition but still held the emblems. It is a graphic picture of the
ancient customs and modes, yet it is so enshrined with the old Indian
superstitions as to prevent me from attempting an outline sketch of same
for the Old Chief was strict in having every word to correspond exactly
to the original story as he claimed any omissions or additions would
portent an evil omen. It is full of old history including Customs and
modes of Council, Honor of Official rank, etc. peculiar to the ancient
Cherokee. You can obtain this story, I think, from Honorable Daniel Red
Bird of the Cherokee Council.</p>
<p>The Cherokees were members of the Great International Councils by the
Great Lakes with the Mingoes, Miamies, Wyandottes, Shawnees , Ottowas,
etc. And it was on the occasion of meeting a delegation of Cherokees
proceeding to one of these Grand Councils that Logan, the Mingoe Orator
of History, was killed. He was intoxicated and rushed at the Cherokee
Band of Councilors with uplifted tomahawk. When he refused to be
restrained, He was shot by his own nephew and killed. He was aroused by
the memory of a Great War that had been fought between the Huron
Iroquois aided by their Algonquin allies. And the Cherokees who had the
assist once of the Creeks as allies. The Creeks also aided the Cherokees
in their wars with the white settlers of East Tennessee when they fought
Col. Sevier and his mountaineer, wild, white hunters.</p>
<p>An Indian Union existed once a long time ago. Some kind of Intertribal
Union under the prestige of the Yamasees of South Carolina which
included the Cherokees, Catawbas, and the Creeks, who assisted the
Carolina Colonists to defeat and expel the Tuscororas. And after this
occurrence by object lessons therefrom, the Yamasees organized a war
upon the Colonists with a great war party of Yamasees, Cherokees,
Catawbas, and Creeks. Upon their defeat on account of lacking firearms
and ammunition, occurred the greatest suicide of all the world's
History. Unknown to the white-people, the Yamasee Nation claiming to
foresee the final extinction of the American Indians, they deliberately
committed suicide, at a Great Dance dressed in their best personal
ornaments, and singing their happiest songs. Men, women, and children
danced out into the deep waters with weights attached to their bodies
and were all drowned by their own will. (I will refer you to Chief
Isparhechar, Ya-teh-Kah-Hacho, and other old Creeks for this
tradition.). With the exception of a few families of the Clan of the
Beaver, who were not responsible for the war. These went to the
Applachees of Florida, who in turn were afterwards defeated in a war
with the Seminoles with Great Slaughter. And if any Yamasees (or
Yo-mau-sou) escaped this slaughter they are in the Seminole nation with
the small remnant of Appalachees that were adopted by the Seminoles as
prisoners of war. With the death of the Yamasees, ended this Union of
tribes which included the Cherokees at one time.</p>
<p>A Remarkable Cherokee by the name of Jess Chisholm lived on the Canadian
River near an old Cherokee town where Captain Dutch lived before the
Cherokee Nation occupied their present country. Jess Chisholm roamed the
great plains among the Hostile wild tribes then inhabiting that region
during the 30's, 40's, 50's, and 60's of the present century. He was
well known to the frontier traders from the Rocky Mountains to St. Louis
. He spoke all the Indian languages of this region and was the only man
on the plains that did not fear to meet a Comanchee war party alone for
he knew all their secret signals and they never molested him.</p>
<p>He was instrumental in liberating many Mexican captives held by the
Comanchees. The Chisholm Cattle Trail was named for him, for it followed
one of his old trading trails from the Southwest to Kansas City .</p>
<p>During the War of 1812-14, a band of 800 Creeks and 32 Cherokees
commenced hostilities against the Americans by capturing Fort Mims which
held seven murderers of Wetherford's wife and four children. Who Major
Beasley commandant refused to surrender to Civil Law. This being right
on the heels of Tecumsehs visit to the Creeks but which Major Hawkins,
Creek Agent, reported as being quieted down. Started a war which failed
to draw out the entire Nation into hostilities.</p>
<p>The Cherokee Nation and the Creek Nation furnished a Battalion of Brave
warriors each, who done effective service for the American troops.
Timpochee Barnett, Cowacochee-Matha, and Chowe-matha, of the Creek
portion of the Battalions were awarded Medals of Honor by Congress on
recommendations of General Andy Jackson for Great Bravery in Battle and
read "The Bravest of the Brave." Those of the Cherokees were also
awarded. I do not remember the names. The Red Stick Hostilities were
finally very near exterminated before they would surrender. My mother's
uncles (Creeks) were with Jackson for which Mother, during the 50's drew
two land warrants as bounty pay to her uncles.</p>
<p>If you desire I can tell you more. For History must corroborate the facts.</p>
<p/>
<p>
<hi rend="bold">Respectfully,</hi>
</p>
<p>
<hi rend="bold">J. R. Gregory</hi>
</p>
<p>Document found in J. R. Gregory's, personal file, Creek Archives,
Oklahoma Historical Society Library, Oklahoma City . Transcribed by
Barbara Cox.</p>
<lb/>
<lb/>
</div3>
<div3 type="part" id="d7" n="2">
<head>Inola, Indian Territory - December 30, 1899</head>
<p>December 30, 1899</p>
<p>Mr. Emmett Starr</p>
<p>Claremore, Cherokee Nation</p>
<p>Indian Territory </p>
<p>My Dear Sir and Friend:</p>
<p>I am going to be at home for some time. I have brought home three books
that I had loaned to the Dawes Commission at Muskogee when you were here
before. These books contain Very authentic Indian History. They contain
Cherokee history that may be of value to your work on Cherokee History.
The book I sent you entitled "The Creek War" I consider rather limited
information, while it seems to be fair and impartial, by evidence I have
before me, the Editors wished to be correct, but their source of
information in many instances were Very incorrect.</p>
<p>I also would like to see you in regard to the future of the Indian
Interests. I am convinced that there is no political Salvation in
prospect anywhere on the lines we had all hoped for as late as one month
ago. I would like to compare the philology of the Creek and Cherokee
languages with you. I am convinced much good can be accomplished by an
Indian Union to create a prestige to be respected in whatever condition.
Some half-breeds think they can shield themselves behind their white
blood. Of course they will generate a contempt all around against them,
that they will be welcome to all the gratification they will gain. Our
proper course is to be Indians. In fact, whatsoever may be the results.
And the more power we can demonstrate, the greater our respect will
stand. It is in our power to preserve ourselves. And it is in our power
to destroy ourselves. The outside world are mere spectators to these issues.</p>
<p>I wish you come and spend a few days with me as I am home. Rheumatic, and
occupying my old arm chair, wishing to talk on these subjects above
mentioned. I would be very glad to see you.</p>
<p>
<hi rend="bold">Respectfully,</hi>
</p>
<p>
<hi rend="bold">"Your Friend,"</hi>
</p>
<p>
<hi rend="bold">J. R. Gregory</hi>
</p>
<p>(Document found in J. R. Gregory, personal file, Creek Indian Archives,
Oklahoma Historical Society Library, Oklahoma City. Transcribed by
Barbara Cox)</p>
<lb/>
<lb/>
</div3>
<div3 type="part" id="d8" n="4">
<head>Inola, Indian Territory - February 16, 1900</head>
<p>
<hi rend="bold">February 16, 1900</hi>
</p>
<p>
<hi rend="bold">Mr. Emmett Starr</hi>
</p>
<p>
<hi rend="bold">My Dear Sir and Friend:</hi>
</p>
<p>After the proper efforts due to my people has failed on all sides to be
understood as I had wished, I do not give any to despair. I am ready
always to meet Emergencies. Just as I find them.</p>
<p>I have for years foreseen the present conditions of our common interests,
but I had totally failed to appreciate the mesmeric toils that have
developed against our common Brotherhood. The true facts of cause and
affect of these conditions have been clearly explained time and again.
So that even the lisping babes of all these nations know them as the
first words they ever learned. Yet, here comes over three hundred full
blood Creeks in Convention assembled last summer and nominates that foul
monster, L. C. Perryman, for Chief. Endorsed by Chief Isparhechar and
the well wishes of some of the Cherokee Ke-toa-wah (Ca-toh-wau-Ko-ne).
Extended to this foul monster whose former Chieftaincy laid the
disrupting Schemes that has finally destroyed the Creek Nation.</p>
<p>I have Wyandotte , Cherokee, Choctaw Indian blood in my veins, as well as
Creek. It would be beneath my duty to wish Evil against the Creek
people. I have been with them all my life. There is not a song, word, or
tradition of the Mus-ko-kee that I do not Know. It is also true, the
only Enemies I have on all God's Green Earth are some of these Creek
Indians. I am not the man to punish my best friends. Along with person
that choose to Challenge my eminence. I will save an enemy before I will
destroy a friend, why may be embrace or implicating the two.</p>
<p>When L. C. Perryman succeeded to the Chieftaincy, efforts were made
towards my injury. I compelled them to resist their attempts. I
compelled them to acknowledge my right and Supreme Manhood Among Men. I
compelled Chief L. C. Perryman to acknowledge to the Secretary of the
Interior my right here and his acknowledgment of my vindication. And I
have drank deep the Cup of Vengence and breathed deep the Joy of
Victory. I am vastly Superior to them and time will prove it too.</p>
<p>Isparhechar tried to reform the government, which was commendable as far
as his time permitted. At the end of his administration, the Ensuing
Campaign, the people were torn into fractions. They really did not know
what to do. They are not going to accomplish even what Isparhechar had
prepared for their possibilities to do. His treaty with the Dawes
Commission was a good treaty. It will be amended by Congress into a
death warrant because they know how the political trend is with us
today. Unless we will have relief gained by our own efforts.</p>
<p>I do not expect anything better of the Cherokee treaty short of another
Death Warrant. The Great Masses of non-land holders (white and negro
State Comers) are organized into Secret Societies for the purpose of
taxing, by governmental authority, The Indian land holders out of their
lands. To Tax Excessive taxes, and compel Sheriff Sales of real estate
for taxes until their desighns are accomplished and then relieve
themselves of that tax. The Negro Citizens are organixes into Similar
Secret Societies with the non-citiizen organizations of Negroes. Who
intend to cash all their interests and emigrate to Africa . The Indians
are the blindfolded tools to their own disfranchisement and
disinheritance. Now is the time to Secure Proper legislation towards
protecting them. The United States government is willing to do right but
we have failed to present, a proper defense, while our worst enemies,
"Boomer," have had everything their own way and gained lots. Against us.</p>
<p>Among us are fractions who expect to obviate these Evils by emigrating to
Mexico . This scheme has failed to defend our Interests here to complete
efforts when the people are so divided on questions of proper methods.
(I am) Not begging for office, but striving to have that done for the
public good. Time will show what I mean. I have tried for Years to keep
a clear record for the Indian before the U. S. Government, in order to
give us the advantage of un-convicted right to plead our own cause and
then dictate the conditions of allotments and percentage of State
Taxation and other necessary laws for the assured Existence of the
future. Voiceless Existence of a minority of landholders governed by the majority.</p>
<p>The books I referred to in my former letter are Egglestons, "Life of Red
Eagle," G. B. Grinell's "Story of the Indian," F.A. Ober, "In the
Everglades." "Quotations of an Old Sailor Named Romans," written over
one hundred years ago of the Creeks, Seminoles, Choctaws, and Cherokees.
Come down any time and read them. I told Mr. Yancy about my letting you
have the book, "Creek War." He said he was glad I had done so. The book
is yours now. You are to keep it.</p>
<p>I saw a funny letter of old Ko-wes-Kowi John Ross to Seminoles 1837 about
elder brothers, etc. The Creeks call the white men their Youngest
brother because he came here last. They call the Cherokees Elder
brothers because the Cherokees lived on the lower Chattahoochee River
before the Creeks did.</p>
<p>
<hi rend="bold">Ko-naw-la</hi>
</p>
<p>
<hi rend="bold">J. R. Gregory</hi>
</p>
<p>(Document found in the personal file of J. R. Gregory, Creek Indian
Archives, Oklahoma Historical Society Library, Oklahoma City.
Transcribed by Barbara Cox.)</p>
<lb/>
<lb/>
</div3>
<div3 type="part" id="d9" n="5">
<head>Inola, Indian Territory - May 21, 1900</head>
<p>
<hi rend="bold">May 21, 1900</hi>
</p>
<p>
<hi rend="bold">Emmett Starr, M.D.</hi>
</p>
<p>
<hi rend="bold">My Sir and Friend:</hi>
</p>
<p>I enclose a rough sketch of a map of the traditional route traveled by
the Creeks in their Emigration from the South West to the old nation in
the East. You will see by the circle marked " Tallahassee " which was
the first capitol Council Ground of the Creeks in the East and now
Capital of the State of Florida , was the Center from which the old
Creek Empire expanded from. While in the East, Tallahassee means in
Creek "The oldest town that has been worn out and passed its glory," is
expressed in it.</p>
<p>From aboriginal names, we can easily find the older countries these
people came from. That their traditions mentions, "Jalisco" (10 fires)
is evidently where the Cherokees came from, on the Pacific coast in
Mexico . Both traditions agree that the Cherokees came to the East land
before the Creeks came there. The Creeks evidently came from the region
marked Colina in Mexico . It (Colina) being a Creek word. That is south
east of where the Cherokees came from. The Creeks have an oracle that
when the Great Spirit deems proper, they are to return to the old
Country of "Colina" is why the notion of going to Mexico obliterates all
other means of meeting the present crisis.</p>
<p>My purpose in the sketch is to try to show you that it is -- was possible
for (Cherokees) then to come by a North East route from South west by
dry land from Jalisco, Mexico to Chota on the little Tennessee River.
Easy enough, While the Creeks coming from Colina , Mexico to Tallahassee
in Florida by dry land, would have had to go north first and deflect to
the south east. Or would have had to cross the Gulf of Mexico .</p>
<p>Get a Good Map and you will understand me better. Creek tradition says in
going north they came to the black grass land and there they became
involved in war with an enemy and they left the old folks, children, and
people that did not care to follow the enemy any distance; leaving them
at the black grass land. The best warriors and the flower of the young
people followed this enemy in the pleasure of war until they came a long
ways to the old nation at Tullahassee. And that they have never seen or
heard of the people left at the black grass land ever since. We do not
know where this black grass land is. (Probably here where we are now.)
There are people in British Columbia on the headwaters of Fraser River
and on west to the sea coast that evidently speaks the Creek Language.
They may be the same people who have gone there from the black grass or
the Creeks may have gone there before turning East.</p>
<p>
<hi rend="bold">J. R. Gregory</hi>
</p>
<p/>
<p>(Document found in J. R. Gregory, personal file, Creek Indian Archives,
Oklahoma Historical Society Library, Oklahoma City. Transcribed by
Barbara Cox.</p>
<lb/>
<lb/>
</div3>
<div3 type="part" id="d10" n="6">
<head>Inola, Indian Territory - August 20, 1900</head>
<p>
<hi rend="bold">August 20, 1900</hi>
</p>
<p>
<hi rend="bold">Doctor Emmett Starr</hi>
</p>
<p>
<hi rend="bold">My Dear Sir and Friend:</hi>
</p>
<p>You presented me a copy of "Magazine of American History,: date May 1884;
which contains an article by Cyrus Thomas, Ph.D. who attempts to prove
that the Cherokees are the ancient mound builders, etc. The Cherokees
did build towns and town houses. Just the Same as the other Southern
tribes did. A thing peculiar with the Cherokees was that they used a
deal of Shells in ornamenting their town houses with which the other
towns of Southern Indians did not; except the Coweta town of the Creek
Nation. The Shells of the Coweta town mentioned above was held by them
as trophies of war. They having captured them from a Cherokee town house.</p>
<p>Another thing peculiar to both the Cherokees and Creeks was that they
renewed the Furniture of the town houses once every year (excepting
trophies of war). A thing more peculiar to the Cherokees was that all of
this town house furniture such as seats, mats, dance rattles, drums and
sticks, medicine blow-canes, etc, were burned with the old fire in use
and this old fire thrown away and extinguished. And a new fire kindled
by friction and new furniture provided in place of the old furniture
destroyed by fire by the fire priests, known as the a-cha-la-tagheh
(medicine men). The Shells, earthen vessels, and clay floor were broken
and swept to outer verge of the Sacred Limits of the town house yard
once a year. (Just before the Green Corn dance). Thus accumulating a
narrow ridge of two Semi-circles above the yard of the town house never
exceeding 4-5 feet high and most generally 2-3 feet high. In these
semi-circle ridges can be found the Shells and broken crockery mentioned
and wherever found are known as Cherokee shell mounds. They extend from
the Kanawha River, Virginia down to Cape Florida . This Custom of
destroying public utensils once a year by fire, prevailing among these
Ke-to-waa-Kee band (Since known as Cherokees) gave them the name of
Au-Cha-land-Kee, or Fire Towns . Hence the name Cherokee.</p>
<p>The Creeks built the same kind of Semi-ridges by sweeping the town house
each year with broken Earthenware, the remains of medicine vessels,
hence the name Muskogee (named after their medicine). They did not burn
any furniture. They threw away the old fire, and renewed a new fire annually.</p>
<p>Thus the Creek Semi-circle ridges contained no Shells or Clay flooring
and were not quite as high as the Cherokee Shell Mounds. And in either
case, after the lapse of a few Score years would become very near
obliterated by the Elements; excepting the larger ones.</p>
<p>Beyond the above mentioned Shell Mounds, I am thoroughly Convinced that
the Cherokees are not the Mound builders Cyrus Thomas refers to. Those
large Mounds Mr. Thomas speaks of extend down to remote antiquity by
Creek and Cherokee Traditions with Corroborating evidence within the
Structure of these mounds themselves. That Mr. Thomas' theory is but a
lost speck in an ocean of facts. First: these large mounds are so vast
in Extent, with all possible conditions considered, is positive proof of
Slave labor fully as much as does the Pyramids of Egupt prove Slave
labor. They used Copper metal, quarried mica, wove cloth, cultivated
great quantities of Corn. The Skulls of the Skeletons buried in these
mounds indicate a race vastly inferior in energetic manhood to the North
American Indian. They were the Antochthonous race of the American
Continent. The Indian was an intrusive race vastly superior to the Mound
Builders. The skulls of the mound builders indicate a low type of
humanity who could hardly have been capable of deep passions, good or
bad, and were fit Subjects of tyranny and Slavery who could have been
easily imposed upon and destroyed by a more turbulent cruel, treacherous people.</p>
<p>The Skull of the North American Indian is a total reverse being of a very
high order of persistent manhood. They are totally above and beyond
being made Slaves of. The Wild North American Indian has developed
mental powers far superior to the semi-civilized Toltecs of Mexico and
Central America, Far Superior to the Peruvian Incas of South America;
The Equal of the Free and Great Romans.</p>
<p>The Indian skull is typic of Scipio, of Julius Caesar, of the British
Veteran. Square skulled with the Corners rounded. Known in Science as
the Brachycephali skull. Some of the best types are found among the
Algonquin, Iroquois, Cherokees, Aztecs, Natchez , Creeks, Seminoles,
Osages, and Northern Dacotah tribes. None of them would entertain for
one moment, digging and carrying wet clay by thousands of tons by hand
and building firm clay mounds a hundred feet high, 400 feet long by
sixty feet wide, time and again in different styles and types to be
found all over the United States, British America, down into South
America. The Evident use of which was funeral sepulcher for their best
and ruling types at which they offered human sacrifices. No Sir! No
North American tribe has done these things. Creek traditions tell that
they Slew an Evil People whose practices and presence was abominable.
Who were witches, with whom no man could have pleasure, who had heads
like frogs, and were called the frog people, who covered the Earth in
multitudes and delighted to build.</p>
<lb/>
<lb/>
</div3>
<div3 type="part" id="d11" n="7">
<head>Muskogee Nation - September 14, 1901</head>
<p>
<hi rend="bold">September 14, 1901</hi>
</p>
<p>
<hi rend="bold">Honorable P. Porter,</hi>
</p>
<p>
<hi rend="bold">Principal Chief, Muskogee Nation</hi>
</p>
<p>I submit this as my annual report of the conditions of the Creek Schools
during my term of office as Superintendent of Public Instruction for the
Muskogee Nation.</p>
<p>Financial reports of the expenditures of school expenses have been
rendered to your office quarterly during the year; you have them.</p>
<p>The condition of the schools during my incumbency of office has been
fairly well with the exception of the prevalence of small pox which has
been severe at Coweta, Wealaka, and Euchee National Boarding Schools .
Also at a number of the Creek neighborhood schools. Pneumonia and
malarial fever have been prevalent at the Eufaula High School ,
seemingly on account of the bad water supply and also to the limited
spaces of the bed rooms of the pupils causing a too crowded condition in
those sleeping apartments, antagonistic to the good health of the
school. The same condition exists at the Euchee National Boarding School
, although the Euchee school has been more exempt from the fevers
mentioned. The Creek Orphan Home with the comfortable and commodious
design of the building, under the charge of the most excellent fatherly
superintendent of that institution, an institution budding from the
deepest fountains of the hearts of every Muskogee Indian, an institution
baptized with the tears and dying prayers of loving parents of youths of
misfortune, an institution not of charity, but that of the inheritance
of the Muskogee Indian children residing there; demands every comfort we
would extend to our own children at home. Shady groves should surround
the building where the wild birds would blend heaven endowed songs of
comfort to them that have sorrowed. Tributes of flowery beauty should
adorn the paths that would lead them onward to happier days than the
bitter hours they have passed through. It should be a home in every
sense of the term from the cold drink of pure water to the pillow where
pleasant dreams should linger with them during their darkest hours. Many
minor necessities of this home require attention to be perfect. The
available water supply is unreliable being cisterns which fail during
dry season. I am informed that the well water possibilities are not
good. The land is fertile and capable of producing excellent
agricultural supplies for the home. There is no timber or shade trees on
the grounds of this orphan home. The usual appropriations are too
limited, too inadequate to do this in one season.</p>
<p>Industrial training of the pupils may largely accomplish these necessary
results if the prairie sod was broken and fenced for them. This
proposition will apply to all the other national boarding schools more
or less. Broad acres then would yield much to the support of these
schools that is being purchased with cash out of the school funds.
Fruit, vegetables and other luxuries may even be produced over and
beyond the needs of the schools which could be sold and the proceeds
placed to the credit of the school producing same. I would recommend
that consideration be made to this end by the Creek Council. I would
further recommend that a kit of blacksmith's tools and one of
carpenter's tools with necessary agricultural implements be allowed each
one of the nation boarding schools and one text book on the use of the
mechanic's tools be furnished with each kit of tools, and an act of
Council direction the instruction of the school boys in the use of these
tools be enacted. This would result in the saving of much expenditure
for the cruder portions of such work and would better advance the pupils
of these schools to better meet the world after attaining majority than
they would without such industrial training. I would further recommend
that a system of teaching the Indian children the English language by
direct tuition be adopted for the classes of the Creek schools. The
intense patriotism of the Euchees of this Nation causes them to still
cling to the language of their fore-fathers, their language seems to
them to be a part of their very lives. Unfortunately there has never
been an English and Euchee pronouncing dictionary constructed. The
lesson in their case would have to be oral. A majority of the Euchees do
not speak the Muskogee language. The Alabamas , Natchez , Quasadas, and
Hitchitas, tribes originally of different languages from the Muskogee ,
now all speak the Muskogee language fluently, and are really more of an
English speaking people than the Muskogees and the Euchees are. Rev. R.
M. Loughridge who was long a missionary among the Creeks and is yet
remembered by the oldest of the present generation of Creeks, compiled
an excellent dictionary, pronouncing in the English and Muskogee
Languages. That work reveals the fact of the immense volume of the
variations of the verb in the Muskogee language. Vastly more than any
known language found. Its descriptive powers renders it an open and
overflowing revelation of mind thought on the tip of the Muskogee Indian
tongue. It is the reason why the Muskogees are so persistent in speaking
their own native language. There are a few volumes of Mr. Loughridge's
dictionaries in existence yet, but I believe them to be out of print. In
such case it may be necessary under such conditions to teach such
lessons orally unless a volume of Mr. Loughridge's dictionary can be
furnished to each Creek Indian School .</p>
<p>I am indebted to Mr. Charles Gibson for many valuable suggestions in the
direction of teaching Indian children the English language. He shows to
the public by his recent sarticles in the public press his observations
of the Indian student being taught words by sound without comprehending
the meaning of the word rendering it a burden without any realized
benefit. In that language alone will our opportunities depend. It is
most important that a special study of the language be devised for the
use of our schools. It has been deemed advisable by the United States
Supervisor of Schools for the Creek people that the advanced students of
the Indian schools be assigned to higher grade classes at the Eufaula
High School and primary grades to the other national Creek schools for
Indians. I have concurred with such advice for I am impressed that such
was the intention at the original institution of the Eufaula High School
and would prove an advantage of more rapid progress to the advanced
students of our schools.</p>
<p>Some repairing has been done on buildings of the National Boarding
Schools during vacation months on roofs that were leaky and flues,
furnaces, and other apparatus that endangered the buildings to fire and
for protection from the weather. This work has been done at Tullahassee
and Pecan Creek National Boarding Schools by the superintendents who had
saved a large surplus of the appropriations by last Council for said
schools. I would recommend that Council by act make such surplus
appropriations available or that portion of them that may be needed for
such special repairs mentioned above. Repairs are badly needed at
Eufaula High School , the southwest porch being now a veritable death
trap and all the other three porches are dangerous to the occupants.
Much repairing is needed on doors and windows to make the building
comfortable during cold weather. The surplus of the appropriations were
too small to attempt any repairs and the superintendency of the school
having been a matter of contention for some time. Nothing had been done
towards the repairs needed. The boys dormitory buildings at the Colored
Orphan Home was burned last spring and no appropriation being in sight
to have the dormitory rebuilt by the new regulations and modifications
as per treaty by the Secretary of the Interior received at Mr. J. D.
Benedict's office September 3, 1901; Architects will have to be sent to
estimate specifications, plans, and costs before the contracts for
repairing and building can be let. Therefore I would recommend that a
proper amount should be appropriated by act of the Council to defray the
expenses of architect's fees as above mentioned, including repairs on
the Nuyaka National Boarding School, as Mr. Robe the superintendent
there states repairs are needed there too as the building will have to
be repaired or the school suspended on account of the condition of the
buildings there. If an arrangement could be made to have a sufficient
amount appropriated to do the repairing and building after the
architect's estimates were made, such work could be proceeded with,
without delay. The lives of the occupants of some of these school
buildings are at dangerous risk until the buildings are rendered secure
requires prompt action.</p>
<p>The barn at the Orphan Home was burned last summer. Mr. J. E. Tiger had
over $900.00 saved out of the appropriation last year. He obtained
permission of the School Board to rebuild the barn right away as the
Orphan Home stock and hay required a barn badly. Therefore I would
recommend that Council by act allow the settlement of the repairs done
on Tullahassee National Boarding School and the rebuilding of the barn
at the Creek Orphan Home which has been done before the Secretary of the
Interior forwards his rules and regulations as per treaty. I further
recommend that Council by act make available by appropriation necessary
for architect's fees on specifications, plans and estimates, and for
repairs on the Nuyaka National Boarding School building and for
rebuilding the boy's dormitory building that was burned last spring at
the Colored Orphan Home. The repairs above mentioned at Tullahassee,
Pecan Creek and Orphan Home national boarding schools will cost less
than the surplus the superintendents have saved over and bills, if
approved will be due settlement at the end of the first scholastic
quarter, Nov. 16th next, the bills to be presented by the
superintendents with their reports of school expenditures at that date.
Inspection of the work is to be made prior to the settlement of the
accounts by the Supervision and the office before settlement and pay is
allowed. If necessary an architect will be employed to assist in the inspection.</p>
<p>You are aware that our school system as now instituted is yet new, being
but a few years ago when the present extensive up-building of the
extraordinary fine system of schools were build with the newly acquired
school fund by the Oklahoma sale a few years ago. Before that time the
school fund of the Nation was insufficient to accomplish much with.
Those that received advanced education in those small schools are now
mostly in other employment. Therefore we have very few of our educated
people in the school work; a host of new students of this new system
preparing to teach and aid in the schools of their fellow men.</p>
<p>Arguments have been used against the Creek people that their vast school
system has failed to develop graduated students not accounting for the
short period of the existence of these schools. This accusation amounts
to a very galic belch from professors who are most profoundly interested
in saying that very thing without noting records. I must say that I am
highly encouraged with the prospective good results of the great
interest the Creek people are taking in their schools. The pupils of
Indian blood excel in penmanship, spelling, and reading. They are apt
and quick mathematicians, they are fond of history and geography. They
have superlative strong nerve and steady hand for the finer arts. They
have strong passions and supreme resisting wills that they are not
easily discouraged with their tasks.</p>
<p>Full classes of the primary rudiments of music should receive more
attention than is being done. As I said before, the English language
should be specially taught to all Indian pupils who do not understand
that language or speak it imperfectly. Industrial training in the trades
should be taught the boys. Housekeeping and cooking might prove a merry
romp each day for the future housekeepers among the Creek people if the
school girls could only be given a chance to show the folks what they
could do in that time.</p>
<p>I would recommend that the superintendents of each of the national
boarding schools be authorized by act of the National Council to take
measures to take allotments of forty acres each for their respective
schools as provided by the recent treaty. These school superintendents
each being the business head of their respective schools, they alone
have the information of evidence required at the land office as to the
occupation of the lands describing the bounds and location and the
previous holding of their own personal knowledge during the term of
their service and transfers from preceding superintendents. These
questions will have to be answered of their own personal knowledge and
not by hearsay evidence renders these superintendents the only competent
qualified officers to comply with the rules of filing for the national
schools as such school lands. A sufficient fund should be appropriated
by act of the National Council to aid in defending these school
allotments from persons who have or may presume to file on or contest
these filings as in the case at the Eufaula High School where filings
have been made on the school farm and show inclination to contest the
allotment on the cultivated land of the school farm. The certificates of
these school lands, deeds, and etc., should be help by the
superintendents of these schools for each school.</p>
<p>Upon my entrance to this office I found that a good supply of school
books had been secured for the schools with the exception of a few
editions which were short. On the 6th instant an order was on Mr. J. B.
Bleser of Wichita , Kansas for:</p>
<p>
<hi rend="bold">250 Baldwin 's Primers</hi>
</p>
<p>
<hi rend="bold">100 Baldwin 's First Readers</hi>
</p>
<p>
<hi rend="bold">300 Baldwin 's Second Readers</hi>
</p>
<p>
<hi rend="bold">100 Baldwin 's Third Readers</hi>
</p>
<p>
<hi rend="bold">200 Milne's Elementary Arithmetics</hi>
</p>
<p>
<hi rend="bold">150 Redway &amp; Hinman Natural Elementary Geography</hi>
</p>
<p>
<hi rend="bold">250 Small Slates</hi>
</p>
<p>
<hi rend="bold">250 Medium Slates</hi>
</p>
<p>
<hi rend="bold">2500 Slate Pencils</hi>
</p>
<p>
<hi rend="bold">10 Gross Steel pens for copy book use</hi>
</p>
<p>
<hi rend="bold">500 Lead Pencils</hi>
</p>
<p>
<hi rend="bold">50 Black Board Erasers</hi>
</p>
<p>Up to this writing, nothing has been heard from them yet.</p>
<p>Find appended as Exhibit copies of the statistics of the Creek schools
furnished this Office by Miss Alice Robertson, Supervisor of Schools in
the Creek Nation.</p>
<p>Near all the teachers' reports have been made to that Office. The
original records are deposited in Miss Robertson's charge and through
her kindness, I obtained of that office the appended statistic sheets.</p>
<p>The costs of the National Board Schools are more correctly $50,470.40,
the appropriations are $57,500.00. The expenditures for the neighborhood
schools are $12,366.92. The Nuyaka Boarding School contract $5,600.00. I
would recommend that $9,000 each be appropriated for Eufaula High School
, Wetumka National Boarding School and Tullahassee Colored Boarding
School . That $7,200 be appropriated for the Euchee Naitonal Boarding
School . That $6,666.66 be appropriated for the Creek Orphan Home. I
would recommend that the sum of $5,600.00 be appropriated on the
contract for the Nuyaka Boarding School . I would recommend the sums of
$4,500 for the Wealaka, Coweta, and Pecan Creek (Colored) National
Boarding Schools each. I would recommend that the sum of $3,333.33 be
appropriated for the Colored Orphan Home and $12,500 for neighborhood
schools of the Creek Nation.</p>
<p>I respectfully ask that you submit the several recommendations herein
stated to the National Council of the Muskogee Nation for the above
specified considerations and appropriations.</p>
<p>
<hi rend="bold">Respectfully</hi>
</p>
<p>
<hi rend="bold">Your Humble Servant,</hi>
</p>
<p>
<hi rend="bold">James R. Gregory</hi>
</p>
<p>
<hi rend="bold">Superintendent of Public Instruction for the Muskogee Nation</hi>
</p>
<p>(Document # 38800, J. R. Gregory file, Creek Indian Files, Indian
Archives of the Oklahoma Historical Society Library, Oklahoma City .
Transcribed by Barbara Cox.)</p>
<lb/>
<lb/>
</div3>
<div3 type="part" id="d12" n="8">
<head>Inola, Indian Territory - August 23, 1902</head>
<p>
<hi rend="bold">August 23, 1902</hi>
</p>
<p>
<hi rend="bold">Doctor Emmett Starr</hi>
</p>
<p>
<hi rend="bold">Claremore, Creek Nation</hi>
</p>
<p>
<hi rend="bold">Indian Territory</hi>
</p>
<p>
<hi rend="bold">Sir:</hi>
</p>
<p>I have been trying to write the Emigration Story of the Creeks for you
for some time. I find I cannot do so Without betraying the confidence of
the persons that told me the Story, as they regard the methods of
transmission with Superstition.</p>
<p>If You can come to my place to get the Subject matter properly, or if You
can go out to Okmulgee with me next October, we can possibly get it from
Chief Isparhechar as has proper authority to transmit same and You, as a
Cherokee Indian have the Privilege of learning this Sacred tradition.
But the trouble is, that if You should publish the Story, the proper
Custodians would have to attest that the Subject was rendered word for
word strictly accurate, and what puzzles me is that your authority to
publish the tradition should be conceded by the Elders who are deemed
authorized Custodians of Same under the laws of our Old Customs. And
that no works were added or taken away from the Story anymore that the
days of life can be Justly Changed.</p>
<p>
<hi rend="bold">Respectfully,</hi>
</p>
<p>
<hi rend="bold">James R. Gregory</hi>
</p>
<p>(Document found in J. R. Gregory, personal file, Creek Archives, Oklahoma
Historical Society Library, Oklahoma City . Transcribed by Barbara Cox.)</p>
<p>Being for Verbal Transmission Only, The Author's name is unsigned and
unknown on these pages and can be found by a friend only.</p>
<p>In the days and time before men became evil, The Earth was White, Sacred
and Clean. There was received from the author of life an admonishment to
not Spill human blood on the Earth, for the ground was Created Holy and
Clean. There were more people on Earth then Than there has ever been
Since men became Evil. In that day the language of the people was
musical, polite, and graceful. All Speech was filled with Exclamations
of adoration with Compliments of truth and trust. Temples were built of
Stone and Cedar timbers, where the Wise Men taught the people a System
of Civil perpetuation of this innocent life. The ground upon which these
temples Stood were termed Holy Grounds. These Holy Grounds were devoted
to religious exercises and festivals of peace and goodwill.</p>
<p>On an Evil day, two twin brothers were born; they were both noble and
beautiful, but one excelled the other in merit. This caused a Jealousy
in the heart of the least favored one and he slew his most favored
brother. It was then that the ground was first fouled with innocent
blood and became dark and trembled with horror.</p>
<p>The Sky became dark and cold. The hearts of men became distrustful of
their brothers. Before this, all men were known as Ustee (people). After
this first murder, different groups of men were designated by different
names. There, old graceful speech became Silent. Their Speech became
evasive and filled with the Strategy of mistrust. Three wise men still
held fast to the good life of former days and still spoke the good old
language of truth and trust filled with exclamations of adoration.</p>
<p>The people and the Earth became very evil. There was only one object in
the universe that retained its Holy, bright purity, and that was the
Sun. These three wise men reasoned that as the Sun daily came from the
East, there might possibly be a country as holy and clean in the distant
East where they might possibly regain their former innocent and Holy
life. These three wise men resolved to take their kindred to the East
and endeavor to find the Holy place whence the Sun came from.</p>
<p>Each one collected their respective kindred into three groups and
prepared to Emigrate to the East. These three groups were camped in a
triangle and were to Start at Sunrise the next day. Poles were set to
get the true course to the Sunrise by which they were to travel by the
route indicated by these poles in line with distant mountains to the
true Sunrise .</p>
<p>When the morning came, the Groups to the left front of the triangle,
being on higher ground, exclaimed in the manner of their good old
Speech: Chee-Ki-Hus-Su (See the Sun). And the group became known as the
Chickasaw group. The group to the right front of the groups, inquired by
the manner of their good old Speech: Ko-hus-se-ta (Where is the sun).
This group became known as the Coh-Seeh-ta group by that inquiry. They
were also installed as the great peace group for their inquiries was in
the interest of peace and goodwill to all men. As the two front groups
started off on their Journey, the group to the rear of the Triangle also
followed the two front groups. They were designated as the Ko-ow-e-ta
Group (They that follow us). This expression was also in the manner of
their former good old Speech. As they Journeyed on, these three groups
became Separated by Several days Journey from each other. The advance of
the Coh-Seeh-ta group came to a large River which they crossed over to
the East side of this great river. On the East bank of this River, they
built a great temple of Earth in the manner of a mound with a door way
in the top by which they could enter the great chamber of the Temple
which was built, thus for the purpose of sacred rites and also for
defense against enemies that began to appear in this Strange country.
The main body of the warriors of this Coh-Seeh-ta group went out to
subdue these strange people in order to clear a way for their
non-combatants to pass Safely through the country. They left their
non-combatants at this fortress mound. While the Coh-Seeh-ta warriors
were absent, the rear group which hand now became known as the Co-we-ta
group came up on the west bank of this Great River, opposite the Temple
mound built by the Coh-Seeh-ta group. The Coh-Seeh-ta non-combatants, at
their newly improvised mound, seemed strange to the Co-we-ta people and
as they had fought several battles with the Strange people of the
Country, they supposed the people of the Temple mound to be of the
Strange people of the Country. They made hostile demonstrations against
the Coh-Seeh-ta people. The army of the Coh-Seeh-ta warriors were
informed of this, upon which they returned to the defense of their
Temple Mound . When they came to the Co-we-ta group, they whipped them
with switches cut from the forest, but did not strike any of them with a
weapon of war. The Coh-Seeh-ta warriors then rebuked the Co-we-tas for
their conduct and then placed them in charge of the Mound Temple as they
took their non-combatants along with them and proceeded on their Journey
to the Sunrise . By the whipping with Switches, the Coh-Seeh-ta and
Co-we-ta groups have been antagonists in the great national game of ball games.</p>
<p>While the Co-we-tas remained in charge of the Temple mound and one day
while the great mass of the Co-we-tas warriors were in the Great
Champber of the Mound, purifying their bodies by Scared rites, the
Encampment of the Co-we-ta non-combatants was attacked by the Cherokees
who were the true descendants of the twin brother that had killed his
brother. The Cherokees did not know that the Temple Mound was occupied
by a Strong force of warriors. The Co-we-ta warriors came up out of the
door in the top of the Mound Temple and fought the Cherokees and
defeated them with great slaughter. As the Cherokees had been deemed
strong and expert fighters, this valorous deed of the Co-we-tas gave
them the title of the Great War town. After the Chickasaw group had
crossed the great River, Several days Journey above where the two other
groups had crossed the Great River, they proceeded no further, but
stopped and built towns in the Center of Small prairies that were there
and upon which grew an abundance of Strawberries, and there was an
abundance of good water which could be had by digging an elbow's length
beneath the surface of these prairies. The Coh-Seeh-ta group continued
on towards the Sunrise , followed by the Co-we-tas. They proceeded
onwards until they came to a country where lived a people who were naked
and wore no clothes and were very wild. These naked wild people held no
intercourse with them but fled and hid in a great fog or mist that lay
to the East.</p>
<p>These two groups of Coh-Seeh-tas and Co-we-tas followed these naked
people into this Great mist. On passing through the mist, they found
that the mist was cast up from a great Sea of water that was white with
foam crested waves. And that the Sun arose up out of this white-water
was the reason why the Sun remained pure and bright. They furthermore
became convinced that all Earth had become dark and unholy and that only
the Sea and the Sun remained pure in the Sight of the Great Author of Life.</p>
<p>They then resolved to occupy the country from the Sea coast back the way
they had came as far as the country extended to the boundaries of the
country occupied by the Chickasaws, which is the land from Mobile Bay
and around by the Sea Coast to the mouth of the Savannah River. They
built holy mounds and wrote upon the rocks of the Chat-ta-hoo-chee River
in Commemoration of these events.</p>
<p>The Coh-Seeh-ta and Co-we-ta names are the oldest band names of the
Muskogee Nation and they are the two principal towns of the Creek Nation
to this day. With the Chickasaws are the oldest designation of names in
the Muskogee language to distinguish groups of people in the old and
beloved language when the perfection and purity was lost to mankind by
the Spilling of blood.</p>
<p>(Document found in J.R. Gregory file, Creek Archives, Oklahoma Historical
Society Library, Oklahoma City . Transcribed by Barbara Cox.)</p>
<lb/>
<lb/>
</div3>
<div3 type="part" id="d13" n="9">
<head>Inola, Indian Territory - January 31, 1910</head>
<p>
<hi rend="bold">January 31, 1910</hi>
</p>
<p>
<hi rend="bold">Doctor Emmett Starr</hi>
</p>
<p>
<hi rend="bold">Claremore</hi>
<hi rend="bold">, Oklahoma </hi>
</p>
<p/>
<p>
<hi rend="bold">My Dear Sir and Friend:</hi>
</p>
<p>Yours of recent date noted and in reply will say that the Osage band that
occupied Claremore Mound as a resident village were known to the white
traders as Big Hill Town of the Great Osage Nation. The Little Osage
Nation resided on the Osage River, now in the State of Missouri . The
Indian name of the Town was Pah-Sug-Gee (Town on the Big Hill). The
Osage Village Pah-Sug-Gee contained a large family of Very Large people.
Many of the men being near seven feet tall, were well formed and of
great physical endurance and were great warriors, being invincible in
hand-to-hand conflicts with enemies of their Surroundings in those days
of the long ago.</p>
<p>The family name of this Great family was Pah-Son-na, a name then feared
and respected from the Missouri River of the north to the Red River of
the South. Wherever they went, they always proclaimed themselves
Pah-Son-na in preference to Pah-Sug-Gee or Wa-sa-see because they were
deemed to be Greater than all other Osages. Thus it became a habit to
term the Village on the Big Hill to be the home of the Pah-Son-na men.
Although there were members of the Pah-Sug-Gee Village that were not
blood relatives of the Pah-Son-na family and who remained Silent when
their Village was termed Pah-Son-na; but whenever their village was
termed Pah-Sug-Gee, they then responded "How How."</p>
<p>Chief Cleremont, who was killed by the Cherokees at the Battle of
Claremore Mound, belonged to the Pah-Son-na family and was then the
first and foremost man of that family because his Indian name was
Pah-Son-na. The French of St. Louis gave him the name of Cleremont,
pronounced Klam-mo, as the name is peculiar French spelling that carries
Silent letters.</p>
<p>
<hi rend="bold">Respectfully,</hi>
</p>
<p>
<hi rend="bold">Your Obedient Servant,</hi>
</p>
<p>
<hi rend="bold">James R. Gregory</hi>
</p>
<p>(Document found in J. R. Gregory personal file, Creek Indian Archives,
Oklahoma Historical Society Library, Oklahoma City. Transcribed by
Barbara Cox.)</p>
<lb/>
<lb/>
</div3>
</div2>
<div2 type="work" id="d14" n="2">
<head>Histories</head>
<div3 type="introduction" id="d15">
<head>General History of James Roane Gregory</head>
<p>Barbara Cox is a descendent of James Roane Gregory. These texts are of
two types, histories and correspondence. The histories follow the
pattern of those published above.</p>
<p>The correspondence includes letters Gregory sent to two prominent Indian
Territory figures, Emmet Starr and Pleasant Porter. It is included
because of the light it sheds on Gregory's concepts of American Indian
history and culture.</p>
<p>Starr was a native of the Cherokee Nation who graduated from the Cherokee
Male Seminary before attending Barnes Medical College in St. Louis . He
practiced medicine for five years in the Nation, but gave up that
profession to take up his monumental work on Cherokee genealogy and history.</p>
<p>After serving in the Confederate Creek Regiment during the Civil War,
Porter reorganized the Creek school system and was a delegate to
Washington . He served his people in various ways before becoming
Principal Chief in 1899, a post he held until his death in 1907.</p>
<lb/>
<lb/>
</div3>
<div3 type="part" id="d16" n="1">
<head>Euchees of the Creeks</head>
<p>
<hi rend="bold"/>The Euchee tribe of the Creek Indian is a distinct
family of Indians from all the other eastern tribes. They differ in
habits, language and appearance from all their surrounding neighbors,
with a possible slight exception in the manner of saying "no," "none,"
and the single guttural sound of "eauh" for "yes." All evidence point to
the Pacific coast to locate the cousins and tribal families of the
Euchees, among the Tin-nay nations, who are composed of the Apache,
Navajo, and Hupi tribes of the southwest part of the United States .
Extending northward on the Pacific coast and mountains are the Kotenay,
Nehane, Sekane and Tututenay tribes, who, with some other tribes, are
classified as the Athabascan tribes. Mr. Mooney, and also Grinnell,
describes these western tribes so well in their histories that anyone
acquainted with the Euchees can recognize the western origination of
these people, as they themselves prove by distinguishing individuals as
the Te-nay in common with the Athabascan tribes of the west.</p>
<p>The Euchees are a brave, war-like tribe. Physically they are moderately
well developed being more of a lank sinewy structure than any of their
neighbors, excepting possibly the mountain Cherokees. We have been told
by the old folks who knew the Euchees when they were wild, savage
Indians, that it was a common thing for a Euchee to start in the morning
on the track of a deer, his only weapon being a knife, and would run
down the deer and kill it with his knife before evening. The tribe was
once strong and a powerful nation on the Savanna, Chattahoochee ,
Tennessee and Suwannee rivers of the southeast. They had no allies. They
fought every tribe within reach of them, and braver men than they never
lived. They were unconquerable. They are the only tribe that ever got
the best of the Chickasaws in battle. They were the warriors that drove
the Sioux from their eastern home. Then finally the semi-civilized
Muskogees (or Creeks, as they were afterwards called), came from the
west along the Gulf coast, fighting all opposition to their progress,
when the greatest war the Euchees ever engaged in ensued. After a
protracted struggle for several years' duration the Euchees lost so
heavily they retired from before these new enemies. Yet for four
generations they continued desultory warfare, until at a great council
of the Muskogee or Creek tribe the question of exterminating the entire
Euchee tribe was considered by the council and recommended by two of the
three Espokokee towns of the Creek nation. The third Espokokee town,
known as the Cussehtah town, interceded for the lives of the remnant of
the Euchees. This being done in regular order and according to the laws
and customs of the Creek nation, it was granted by the council, as the
Cussehtah town was the Espokokee peace town of the nation. This town had
legal authority to command the peace, even with the enemy.</p>
<p>The Euchees were formally notified of this action by the Creek council
and were taken by the hand of peace and friendship and led to the
entrance of the boundary mounds of the Cussehtah sacred ground of the
town square, thus becoming full-fledged citizens of the Great Cussehtah
Town of the Creek nation. They were requested in common with all other
members of the town, by poll tax labor to keep the Cussehtan Temple of
the Sacred Fire in repair. This tax was required of all young male
members of the town, including those of other bands who were
intermarried, unless exempted by special privileges known only to the
town Tus-ke-he-ne-ha. Hence, thus was the story started by ignoramuses
about the Euchees once having been the slaves of the Creeks. This labor
meant, at most, only about two days in the year, with plenty to eat and
entertainment, dances, and ball plays, a plug of chewing tobacco, with a
black junk bottle of whisky and with a ki-yi-whoop, homeward he would
go, the little pessel-tail pony carrying the drunk and happy rider, with
an extra haversack full of bear steak and big bean dumplings, home to
the little shaved head Euchee, who, that morning, made faces and
grimaces at the great Cussehtah king who rode by the split log cabin.
Yes, and they shot blunt arrows at the lazy sofky dog that was following
the pony heels of his majestic master. The boys whooped "kella
hun-no-wah, ko see-ya" as the king rode on, paying no attention to
trifles below the dignity of a king and his sofky dog.</p>
<p>It is a pity every Indian, white man and Negro in the Territory are not
as free and happy today as those people were in that day. No, the
Euchees were never slaves of the Creeks. They never asked quarter of the
Creeks and probably would have gone down fighting to the last, if the
Creek council had decided to exterminate them. Among them we find some
of the able men of the Creek nation of today. It was a Euchee chief by
the name of Timpoochee Bairnard [sic] that received the gold medal from
the Congress of the United States , through recommendation of General
Jackson being the "bravest of the brave" during the British war of 1812-14.</p>
<p>There were 590 Euchees in the Creek nation at the last Creek census, they
having in the last few years decreased rapidly. This decrease seems to
be largely due to a new habit they have learned of drinking Jamaica
ginger, which is prepared principally of wood alcohol, and which is
destroying a great many lives in this Territory.</p>
<p>The Euchees, like the Osages, strongly adhere to their old customs. They
are like wild quails, hard to domesticate. The Euchee is by nature a
hunter and a great lover of the wild mountains and forests. Their
language is very limited. The Euchee is not a man of words but a man of deeds.</p>
<p>Published in the Indian Journal, Eufaula, I.T., April 26, 1901</p>
<lb/>
<lb/>
</div3>
<div3 type="part" id="d17" n="2">
<head>Creek Indian Migration Record</head>
<p>Ispahihtca,<ref target="n1">[*]</ref> a former chief of the Creek Nation, of the Kasihta town,
told the following version of the Creek Indian Migration Legend to James
Roane Gregory. Mr. Gregory repeated the legend to John R. Swanton in May
of 1912. Mr. Swanton included the legend in his "42nd Annual Report" to
the Secretary of the Smithsonian Institute, entitled "Social
Organization and Social Usages of Creek Indians," pages 53-55,
1924-1925. A copy was found in the "Bureau of American Ethnology,
Bulletin 73" in the Oklahoma Historical Library, Oklahoma City .</p>
<p>Some people anciently lived together in the West. In course of time they
became so evil that they could find nothing pure in the world except the
sun, and they determined to travel eastward to find the place from
whence it came. On the way they became separated into three bodies. The
first of these were called Chickasaw because on the morning when they
were to set out they were the first to see the sun rise and said Tcika
ha'sa (hitcika hasa), "See the sun!" The second body said to the first
Kohasita, ("Ko" is not the usual word meaning "where?" but is probably
an exclamatory particle.) 'Where is the sun?' from which circumstance
they received the name Kasihta. The Chickasaw moved first, the Kashihta
following them, but the third body of people had some difficulty in
passing around a brier thicket and were left a long distance behind, so
that the parties in advance began to call them Ko-aoita, 'Those that are
following us,' whence the Coweta.</p>
<p>During their travels these tribes came to a great river which they
crossed, and presently the Chickasaw entered upon a beautiful country
whre ther were small prairies abundantly supplied with strawberries and
other wild fruits and having deep pools of water. Then the Chickasaw did
not want to go any farther and said that they did not care where the sun
came from So they settled in that country, while the remaining bands
held on their course. By and by the Kasihta, who were still in advance,
crossed a river smaller than the first. On the other side they raised a
mound, leaving a great chamber in the center in which to fast and purify
their bodies. They left their women, children, and other noncombatants
there and went on toward the east.</p>
<p>Afterward, the Coweta arrived on the opposite side of the river and sent
word over that they intended to cross and kill everyone in the place
because the Kasihta warriors had not waited to have them join in the
expedition. But among the Kasihta women was one who had a magic white
stone or pebble, the mate to which was in the keeping of her husband
among the warriors. By means of this stone she informed him of the
serious state of affairs, and the Kasihta warriors immediately retraced
their steps, cut switches, and, passing over to the Coweta warriors,
whipped them severely. But they did not strike them with a weapon of
war. They then told the Coweta to take charge of the mound, and,
gathering together their own noncombatants, they went eastward once more.</p>
<p>After the Kasihta had left, the Coweta made medicine and went inside of
the great mound in order to purify them selves, but while they were
there a Cherokee war party attacked the camp. Great was their surprise,
however, when the Coweta warriors poured up from the bowels of the
earth, and the Cherokees were defeated with great slaughter. From this
circumstance the Coweta town became the Great War town of the Creek
Nation. Then the Kasihta sent back for the Coweta but, without waiting
for them to catch up, continued in the same direction as before.
Presently they reached a country populated by naked people who would
attack them and then run off. The naked people did this repeatedly until
they at length ran into a dense fog. The Kasihta followed them, and
emerging on the other side, found them selves on the shore of the ocean
from which the fog had arisen. Unable to go farther they camped where
they were, and in the morning saw the sun rise out of the sea. They
concluded that was why it was bright and pure. By and by the Coweta came
up, and the two peoples agreed that the country from which they had
started was so far off that they would not return to it. So they
remained where they were, fought with the inhabitants of the land, and
brought them under their own system of laws.</p>
<p>In curse of time no people were left willing to resist them, and they
longed for someone with whom to fight. Hereupon Coweta challenged
Kasihta to a game of ball in order to obtain revenge for having been
beaten with switches by the latter. The custom of having ball contests
originated at this time and in this manner and has continued to the
present day. Now arose the division between the war towns and the peace
towns. The war towns have separated from the Coweta and the peace towns
from the Kasihta, except in the cases of towns which have been brought
in from outside. These have usually been brought in by the peace towns,
and hence are generally white.</p>
<note id="n1"><seg type="note-symbol">*</seg> <p>Ispahihtca, the name spelled in the Swanton report, is more typically
found spelled Isparhechar.</p></note>
<p>(Transcribed by Barbara Cox.)</p>
<lb/>
<lb/>
</div3>
<div3 type="part" id="d18" n="3">
<head>Early Creek History</head>
<p>The meaning of the name Is-te-cm-us-suk-c-kee, abbreviated to Mus-ko-kee,
or Muskogee, means the "People of the Holly Leaf Confederacy," referring
to a shrub found in the Southern States near the Gulf coast known as the
"Gulf Holly." The old-time Creeks had considerable knowledge of the
medicinal virtues of the various plants and herbs of the "Old Nation" in
the East -- Georgia, Alabama , and Florida . This medicinal science
covered the entire scope of their existence for healing the sick, for
counteracting evil omens and for purifying their bodies during their
council deliberations, on their hunting expeditions and war campaigns of
invasion within an enemy's territory. The holly leaf was a medicine used
by them to purify their bodies during religious ceremonies of the
feasts, fasts, and festivals of the first fruits, sometimes called "The
Green Corn Dance." "Usseh" is what they termed this medicine, hence it
is said Osceola derived his name by being a great drinker of this "Usseh."</p>
<p>"Em-us-suk-c-kee" is of the same character of construction as the name
Uh-chay-la-o-kee, which, abbreviated is rendered Cha-lo-kee, hence is
derived the name of "Cherokee" -- the people of the five confederacies
being of two distinct national names of one linguistic construction.</p>
<p>A great many names have been lost to the Mus-ko-gee language by their
emigration to a colder climate than is that of their former homes east
of the Mississippi . Many changes were made in their customs and
old-time usages after their removal west. Very few Muskogess live who
know that If-too-mic-coo was their name for the magnolia tree, which
means "king of trees." Very few remember the legends of the Su-wa-nee
fairires, who, with shouts of derisive laughter, mocked the lost and
bewildered victims of their rude sports, whom they had led astray by the
Su-wa-nee River to the trembling morasses of the great O-kee-fin-o-kee
wilderness. Hence, the name of the Su-wa-nee ("Echo') River, and the
Okefinokee ('shaking water") Swamp.</p>
<p>It is a long time since we old Creeks, as small children, watched the
snow-white locks of the octogenarian as he placed his right hand behind
his ear so as to enable him to listen to the Eolian harps away off to
the Eastern twilight shades, as evening's dark mantle was gently thrown
over Earth. We listened in childish awe while he told the story of the
"Tul-lee-has-see" over again -- the story of the Deserted Village . And
then the wild songs and moans told him of the suicide of the whole
Ya-mo-see Nation in the Pasguella bay. They had exhausted every means in
their power to save their nation from an unhappy extinction until at
last all hopes vanished and they knew that they were powerless. 'Twas
then that they determined to die bravely, and together. Arrayed in their
brightest -- hued dance costumes, and singing their happiest songs, they
danced out into the deep waters, surrendering the free liberty of their
lives to the Great Spirit, and were every one drowned. It is said after
darkness comes each evening, for all time, the messenger of the Great
Spirit sing in response to the songs of the Ya-ma-sees- the sweetest,
strangest music ever heard by mortal man. This is heard on Pasguella
bay, any evening, for a short while just at dusk.</p>
<p>When the Mus-ko-gees, or Creek Indians were first found by the European
explorers and historians they were the most powerful Nation of Indians
in the Southeast of the main continent of America, and were among the
most advanced tribes in civilization. This high state of civilization
can be accounted for by their having had an excellent code of moral laws
which protected their social conditions. They had laws of marriage and
divorce. Any infringement upon these laws was punished by cutting off
the ears of the first offense, cutting off the nose for the second and
death for the third offense. A grown man who did not do his share of
work in the corn field was denied the right to family relations.</p>
<p>The Creeks' art in engraving wood was remarkable. They understood the art
of weaving cloth, for which they used a species of silk-weed bark fiber.
They kept historic and religious records by strands of beads which by
their variety were arranged so as to convey information. This art was
not generally taught, but was entrusted to a class of professors who
were bound by the laws of the Nation to reveal the truth, for if they
should add to or take away any part of the subject of this bead history
they would suffer the penalty of death.</p>
<p>Yet, alas, they failed to understand the true extent of their power and
civilization. They were fleet of foot and as strong as the old Roman
warriors. Their arrows pierced the armor of the Spanish invaders. Yet,
with all this, their ancient glory is gone forever, and a new world has
opened up for them. Kind reader, will you bear with us the faith that
the Creek Indians will meet the present and the future with that
glorious courage that is their inheritance from the Past which they have survived.</p>
<p>(Published in Sturm's Statehood Magazine, pages 86-87, 1905; Oklahoma
Historical Society. Transcribed by Barbara Cox)</p>
<lb/>
<lb/>
</div3>
</div2>
</div1>
</body>
</text>
</TEI.2>
