<?xml version="1.0"?>

<?dlps id="HadElme"?>
<?dlps page-images="none" figure-images="no"?>
<?dlps transcription="other"?>

<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/tei-p4/tei2.dtd" [
<!ENTITY % POSTKB "INCLUDE">
<!ENTITY % TEI.extensions.ent SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.ent">
<!ENTITY % TEI.extensions.dtd SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.dtd">
<!ENTITY % ISOnum SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/charent/iso-num.ent"> %ISOnum;

]>
<TEI.2 id="HadElme">
<teiHeader type="migrated" creator="Etext">
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title type="main" n="240">Elmer Gantry:  Exemplar of American Televangelism</title>
<title type="sort">elmer gantry exemplar of american televangelism</title>
<author>Hadden, Jeffrey; Shupe, Anson</author>
<respStmt>
<resp>Creation of machine-readable version:</resp>
<name>Jeffrey Hadden, http://religiousbroadcasting.lib.virginia.edu/pubs</name>
<resp>Conversion to TEI.2-conformant markup:</resp>
<name>University of Virginia Library Electronic Text Center.</name>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt>
<extent>ca. <num type="kilobytes">33</num> kilobytes</extent>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>University of Virginia Library</publisher>
<pubPlace>Charlottesville, Virginia</pubPlace>
<idno type="ETC">HadElme</idno>
<date value="2002">2002</date>
<availability status="public">
<p n="copyright">Copyright &copy; 2002 by the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia</p>
<p n="access">Publicly accessible</p>
</availability>
<idno type="uva-pid">uva-lib:476015</idno>
</publicationStmt>
<seriesStmt>
<title>University of Virginia Library, Text collection</title>
<idno type="uva-set">UVA-LIB-Text</idno>
</seriesStmt>
<sourceDesc>
<biblFull>
<titleStmt>
<title type="main">Elmer Gantry:  Exemplar of American Televangelism</title>
<title type="sort">elmer gantry exemplar of american televangelism</title>
<author>Jeffrey Hadden; Anson Shupe</author>
<editor>[first name then last name]</editor>
</titleStmt>
<extent>10 pp</extent>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>Ablex Publishing</publisher>
<pubPlace>Norwood, NJ</pubPlace>
<date value="1990">1990</date>
<idno type="callNo">Source copy consulted: Private copy</idno>
</publicationStmt>
<notesStmt>
<note>
<p>Appeared in Robert Abelman and Stuart M. Hoover, Eds.  Religious Television:  Controversies and Conclusions</p>
</note>
</notesStmt>
</biblFull>
</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc>
<encodingDesc>
<projectDesc>
<p>Prepared for the University of Virginia Library Electronic Text Center.</p>
</projectDesc>
<editorialDecl>
<p>All unambiguous end-of-line hyphens have been removed, and the  trailing part of a word has been joined to the preceding line.</p>
<p id="ETC">Some keywords in the header are a local Electronic Text Center scheme  to aid in establishing analytical groupings.</p>
</editorialDecl>
</encodingDesc>
<profileDesc>
<creation>
<date value="1990">1990</date>
</creation>
<langUsage>
<language id="eng" usage="main">English</language>
</langUsage>
<textClass>
<keywords>
<term>CORD</term>
<term>religion</term>
<term>sociology</term>
</keywords>
<keywords>
<term>nonfiction</term>
<term>prose</term>
<term>masculine</term>
</keywords>
<keywords>
<term>LCSH, democracy, religion</term>
</keywords>
</textClass>
</profileDesc>
<revisionDesc>
<change>
<date value="2002-02">12/02</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>corrector</resp>
<name>Irene Oh, Electronic Text Center</name>
</respStmt>
<item/>
</change>
<change>
<date value="2005-07">July 2005</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>Corrector</resp>
<name>John Ivor Carlson</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Converted SGML to XML. Fixed tagging.</item>
</change>
<change>
<date value="2007-09">September 2007</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>Migration</resp>
<name>Ethan Gruber, University of Virginia Library</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Converted XML markup from TEI Lite to uva-dl-tei (TEI P4 with local customizations).</item>
</change>
<change>
<date value="2008-01">January 2008</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>Migration</resp>
<name>Greg Murray, University of Virginia Library</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Programmatically updated TEI header markup (but not header content) for minimal compliance with current QA requirements.</item>
</change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>
<text id="d1">
<body id="d2">
<div1 type="essay" id="d3">
<head>
Elmer Gantry: Exemplar of American Televangelism<lb/>
Jeffrey K. Hadden and Anson Shupe
</head>
<div2 type="section" id="d4">

<p>The first news of the televangelism scandals at
Heritage USA had scarcely gone out over the wire services before
an old name in the lore of evangelism found its way back into
America's consciousness: Elmer Gantry. He was also a hypocrite and
a slick-talking scoundrel. Gantry consumed great quantities of
whiskey, seduced church secretaries, and removed the choir robes
of countless virgins, all without the slightest qualm of
conscience. He stole from little old ladies and lined his pockets
with offerings from the collection plate.</p>

<p>Elmer Gantry was as loathsome a character as
has ever been born in the mind of an American writer. Few
Americans have actually read Sinclair Lewis's (1927) novel about
the barn-storming tent evangelist. Still, millions know <hi rend="italic">Elmer
Gantry</hi> is a story about a preacher who personified all that
is wrong with fundamentalist religion.</p>

<p>So magnificently and seductively does Lewis
develop his conniving and lecherous evangelist that it is too
easily forgotten that Elmer Gantry never existed. He is a
composite caricature of all the worst features of evangelists,
without the slightest hint that there were any redeeming features
in any of them. The thought that some evangelists might have been
honest men and women, doing the best they could by the means
available to them to preach the gospel and do good, never emerges
for even an instant.</p>

<p>Elmer Gantry cannot be understood outside the
context of the man who created him. Sinclair Lewis was a social
critic and satirist who not only rejected, but repudiated, his
small-town Minnesota roots. Lewis hated everything that smacked
of provincialism, conformity, or hypocrisy. He also hated lawyers
and physicians, but most of all, Lewis hated religion. Lewis's
life embodies the cultural struggle between the sophisticated
secular urban world and the simpler life in the hinterland, a
life which urban sophisticates presumed was rapidly dying out.
Lewis was not content to merely walk away from his Midwestern
roots; he spent his life attempting to hasten their
passing.</p>

<pb n="14"/>

<p>Sinclair Lewis's caricature of an evangelist
has survived. When the televangelism scandals broke in 1988, the
mass media wasted little time in invoking the name Elmer Gantry.
But newspaper writers didn't have to pull the novel from a shelf
or locate a videotape of the 1950s movie starring Burt Lancaster
to become acquainted with Gantry. Lewis's character had long
since left the tents with sawdust trails and taken up residence
in plush television studios.</p>

<p>For most of this decade, made-for-television
movies and dramatic series featuring a television preacher have
been straight out of Elmer Gantry. An ABC television movie
entitled "Pray TV" left viewers with little doubt that the
message was about preying and not praying. Portrayals of
televangelists in such series as Murder, <hi rend="italic">She Wrote</hi>,
<hi rend="italic">Mike Hammer</hi>, and <hi rend="italic">Spencer for Hire</hi>,
among others, are vintage Gantryesque portraits.</p>

<p>Like Elmer Gantry, these fictionalized
televangelists are obsessed with money and power. To protect
their turf and hide their lecherous lifestyles, the characters
portrayed have no qualms about living on the edge, even outside
the law. Lying is not a defensive measure to save one's hide. It
is, along with sweetness and slick talk, a means to whatever ends
are desired. And, it is assumed, every high-rolling television
preacher must have a carefully concealed Swiss bank account as
insurance against the possible future discovery of his fraudulent
religious racketeering. The legacy of Elmer Gantry which Sinclair
Lewis bequeathed to American culture is a stereotype so mean and
nasty that had he been portraying a black man we most certainly
would have witnessed an outcry of protest demanding copies of the
book be removed from libraries and that the movie version of the
novel not be run on late night television.</p>

<p>Part of the success of any stereotype rests
with a viewer's or reader's unfamiliarity with the person or
group being portrayed. The negative image of contemporary
televangelists is so powerful because it "fits" the legacy of the
evangelist our culture has inherited from Sinclair Lewis.
Millions of Americans who have never switched the dial on their
television sets to a religious program are convinced, beyond any
reasonable doubt, that the caricature they carry around in their
head is quite literally true to life.</p>

<p>Occasionally academic scholars have published
papers which, at least by inference, suggest that it might be
inappropriate to tar and feather all religious broadcasters with
the Gantryesque stereotype. But then came the dreadful
televangelism scandals of 1987 and 1988. Oral Roberts, Jim
Bakker, Jimmy Swaggart, and a lesser cast of luminaries,
contributed to reinforcing the Elmer Gantry
stereotype.</p>

<p>The stormy month of March 1987 was a watershed
in the history of religious broadcasting. It began when the press
discovered that Oral Roberts was claiming to be held hostage by
God Almighty. If Oral didn't raise $8 million in "ransom money"
by the end of the month, God would</p>

<pb n="15"/>

<p>surely call him home. The press descended upon
Tulsa, Oklahoma for the bizarre countdown to April Fools Day, a
donnybrook of extraordinary proportions. Would Oral emerge
triumphant, cash in hand, from his Prayer Tower on the campus of
Oral Roberts University? Or would he be snatched home by his
Heavenly Father?</p>

<p>The media were having so much fun with the
Roberts story that they missed the announcement that Tammy Faye
Bakker, star of the PTL Network's <hi rend="italic">Jim and Tammy Show,</hi> had
entered the Betty Ford Center for drug rehabilitation. Then came
the fateful announcement on March 19 that Pentacostal Jim Bakker
was stepping down as head of PTL and Heritage USA, and that he
would be replaced by fundamentalist Jerry Falwell. The
precipitating event was the eminent disclosure of a sexual
encounter Bakker had with a former church secretary seven years
earlier. Bakker didn't deny that the tryst had happened, but he
didn't go quietly or in shame. In his resignation statement,
broadcast on the PTL Network, he claimed that he "was wickedly
manipulated by treacherous former friends . . . who victimized me
with the aid of a female confederate" (Bakker, 1987, p. A1). God
and Tammy Faye had forgiven Jim for his brief sexual encounter
with Jessica Hahn. He seemed perplexed that others could not
forgive him as well. He was ready to get on with the business of
building Heritage USA, Jim and Tammy Faye's own fantasy world,
which they dreamed would one day be a veritable spiritual
Disneyland.</p>

<p>Jim could only explain his unfortunate position
in the context of years of "constant harassment and pressures by
various groups and forces whose objective has been to undermine
and to destroy us" (Bakker, 1987, p. A1). He admitted that paying
blackmail was "poor judgment" but he only did it to "to protect
and spare the ministry and my family."</p>

<p>With attention focused on the sordid details of
the live soap opera unfolding at Heritage USA, Oral Roberts'
give-or-I-die fund raising shenanigans might have been completely
overlooked had it not been for his shameless acceptance of a $1.3
check from a Florida racetrack owner. The donor said he thought
Oral ought to check in with a psychiatrist. But neither the
putdown nor the thought that this might be Satan's money bothered
Roberts in the slightest.</p>

<p>Even as America was learning the details of the
blackmail paid for Bakker's brief encounter in a Florida motel,
and trying to comprehend why a fundamentalist might encounter
resistance to taking over a Pentecostal ministry, there came
additional charges which drew yet another major televangelist
into the conflict. From Norman Roy Grutman, attorney for PTL,
came the accusation of "unmistakable evidence. . . that Jimmy
Swaggart was attempting to orchestrate the ouster of Jim
Bakker" (Frank &amp; Grove, 1987, p. A14).</p>

<p>"I'm ashamed, I'm embarrassed," retorted Jimmy
Swaggart, the thunderous pulpit pounder from Baton Rouge,
Louisiana. Continued Swaggart:</p>

<pb n="16"/>

<p><q>
The gospel of Jesus Christ has never sunk to such a level as it
has today. We've got a dear brother in Tulsa, Oklahoma, perched up in a
tower telling
people that if they don't send money that God's going to kill
him, then we got
this soap opera being carried out live down in South Carolina all
in the name
of God. (Frank &amp; Grove, 1987, p. A14)</q></p>

<p>But those who preached the gospel on the
airwaves would sink lower still. There was a lot more
embarrassment and shame to come: the sex, the bad taste, the
details of the robbing of the PTL treasury, the rumors of an
imminent return of the Bakkers.</p>

<p>Then there was the presidential candidacy of
M.G. "Pat" Robertson, only months earlier the host of the <hi rend="italic">700
Club, </hi>the most frequently watched religious broadcast in
America (Clark &amp; Virts, 1985). Robertson's campaign itself
had some bizarre moments, but in April of 1988, just as it
appeared that a former televangelist might be a serious player in
the Republican presidential nomination sweepstakes, yet another
scandal unfolded.</p>

<p>Jimmy Swaggart, the biggest and toughest and
holiest of them all, tearfully confessed before television
cameras that he too had fallen to the sins of the flesh. Unlike
the indiscretion that Jim Bakker's former friends has lured him
into, Jimmy Swaggart had, of his own volition, been hanging out
with lowly prostitutes, in a New Orleans neighborhood. Marvin
Gorman, once a rising televangelist whose career was wrecked when
Jimmy Swaggart blew the whistle on his sexual misconduct, had
trailed Swaggart to a seedy motel in New Orleans and photographed
him with a prostitute.</p>

<p>While the fate of the Swaggart religious empire
hung in doubt, Robertson's political aspirations did not.
Robertson's claim that the timing of the disclosure of Swaggart's
misconduct was a dirty trick staged by the Bush campaign helped
seal his fate as an uncreditable candidate. He didn't drop out of
the campaign immediately, but the enthusiasm of his "invisible
army" was gone. And a financially troubled Christian Broadcasting
Network brought him back to a co-host role on the <hi rend="italic">700 Club
</hi>in May, something he said would never ever happen.</p>

<p>Also in May, Rufus Reynolds, the judge
presiding over the Chapter 11 bankruptcy reorganization of PTL,
concluded that liquidation was inevitable. Jim Bakker returned to
Charlotte claiming that "God has given us a plan how to pay for
it and how to restore it" (Associated Press, 1988, p. A2). But
arrangements fell through.</p>

<p>By midyear of 1988 it seemed that the saga of
lurid revelations of sleaze and corruption in televangelism land
would never end. And all of this was not Burt Lancaster
portraying Elmer Gantry. It was life imitating art!</p>

<p>There have been scandals in American religion
before. For more than 200 years, America's great evangelists have
been colorful and controversial. And a few of them have been real
rascals. So it should have come as no</p>

<pb n="17"/>

<p>surprise that the development of radio and then
television would only enhance the visibility of the controversial
few. And indeed they did.</p>

<p>The scandals of 1987 and 1988 were not the
first in broadcasting. Back in the 1920s, Aimee Semple McPherson,
the beautiful and flamboyant radio evangelist, titillated
America's prurient interests with her alleged love affairs.
Father Charles E. Coughlin's bombastic demagoguery from his
radical pulpit far exceeded any mixing of religion and politics
that we have seen in more recent times. And in 1976, Billy James
Hargis, whose program was carried on 140 television stations,
became the first major televangelist to fall when he was accused
of both homosexual and heterosexual affairs. Lesser figures of
radio and television evangelism have fallen victims to booze,
sex, and at least one was imprisoned for swindling his
followers.</p>

<p>Nothing like the 1987-88 scandals had ever
befallen religious broadcasting before. The scandals were a
disaster to the broadcasting industry and a devastating blow to
millions of listeners whose faith was shaken. To the secular mass
media, it was "show time." "An irresistible spectacle,"
<hi rend="italic">Newsweek</hi>called it on June 8, 1987 in its second cover
story of the scandal in as many months (Watson, 1987).
Cartoonists and satirists had a field day. Doug Marlette's
nationally syndicated cartoon strip "Kudzu," for example,
features in iconoclastic character named The Reverend Will B.
Dunn. Transformed into a televangelist, Will's ministry was
ruined when he got entangled with Tammy Faye in the
"Mascarascam." But this did not destroy Marlette's
ability to get Reverend Will entangled in every scrape faced by
the whole world of televangelism. Perhaps no piece of videotape
has been copied more times than the <hi rend="italic">Saturday Night </hi>Live
interview of the "Church Lady" with comedy troupe actors playing
Jim and Tammy Faye Bakker discussing the infamous encounter with
the church secretary at a Florida resort.</p>

<p>By any standard of soap opera sleaze, the
televangelist scandals were spectacular first-class drama. For
sheer entertainment, the unfolding sagas were better and juicier
than any episode of <hi rend="italic">Dallas </hi>or <hi rend="italic">Dynasty. </hi>The mass
media were accused, with some justification, of perpetuating a
circus-like atmosphere. But if the mass media explicated the
opportunity, and did not always exercise the best taste, it was
the televangelists themselves who wrote the script.</p>

<p>Not all of the commentary was in fun. There was
plenty of serious, sardonic satire, as a secular press discovered
new heights of piety. "[B]eneath the little-girl sweetness
and outrageous wigs and false eyelashes," wrote Jean Seligman in
<hi rend="italic">Newsweek, "Tammy </hi>Faye Bakker is as shrewd as Imelda
Marcos and probably just as unrepentant about her excesses"
(1987, p. 69). And, wrote Tom Shales, <hi rend="italic">Washington Post
</hi>television critic, "The thrill of watching aJim and Tammy
Show is something compara-</p>

<pb n="18"/>

<p>ble to the thrill of a Judy Garland show late
in Garland's career, when some members of the audience showed up
just to see if she'd make it through the night" (1987, p.B1).</p>

<p>With ratings soaring, ABC's <hi rend="italic">Nightline</hi>
devoted more than a dozen programs to the scandals. There was
big money in the scandals, and no one made out better than the
publishers of skin magazines. Hugh Hefner twice enticed Jessica
Hahn to pose and tell all about her encounter with Bakker for the
pages of <hi rend="italic">Playboy.</hi>Later, <hi rend="italic">Penthouse</hi> publisher Bob
Guccione won the bidding rights to show all and send Debra
Murphree, the prostitute that Jimmy Swaggart frequented on
Airline Highway in New Orleans, on a promotion tour that included
an appearance on the <hi rend="italic">Phil Donabue Show </hi>to bolster sales of
the July, 1988 issue of <hi rend="italic">Penthouse. </hi>Seldom in the history
of radio and television has there been such a blatant
exploitation of a pathetic person for profit.</p>

<p>Before the scandals broke in 1987, large
proportions of Americans were scarcely aware of the thriving
religious broadcasting industry. But of those who were aware of
the televangelists, large proportions of them held unfavorable
opinions. In a national poll conducted for the <hi rend="italic">Los Angeles
Times</hi> in July, 1986, 59 percent of the public reported that
they were "not aware" of Jim Bakker; 47 percent and 41 percent
respectively said they were not aware of Pat Robertson and Jimmy
Swaggart (Los Angeles Times, 1986). Only Billy Graham (by a
margin of 3: 1) and Robert Schuller (by a margin of 2:1) had net
positive ratings. The scandals greatly increased name recognition
and, predictably, negative ratings soared as well. The <hi rend="italic">LA
Times</hi> replicated their survey after the scandals broke and
found that favorable ratings fell for everyone except Billy
Graham (Los Angeles Times, 1987).</p>

<p>Had the scandals been limited to the Bakkers,
America's heightened awareness of the religious broadcasters
might have led to some sorting out of the cast of video vicarage.
That is, Americans might have made discriminating judgments,
sorting out the "good guys" from the "bad guys" as it were. But
bombarded by the seemingly endless revelations of misconduct, it
was inevitable that the negative imagery would spill over and
taint the entire industry. How could America not come to the
conclusion that the televangelists are scoundrels, all real-life
Elmer Gantrys?</p>

<p>The high mass media visibility of religious
broadcasters will pass. And most of them will consider that a
blessing. The high visibility they received in 1987 and 1988 did
not lead to a better understanding of who they are and why they
are attractive to a rather substantial minority of Americans.
Rather, it tended to reinforce the stereotypes that were already
prevalent in our culture. These stereotypes, we have argued, are
the legacy of an era of tension between religion and the emerging
secular culture during the early part of this century. Sinclair
Lewis' caricature of an unscrupulous evangelist is the conduit or
carrier of that legacy. The unscrupulous televangelists have
played their part in giving credence to the
stereotype.</p>

<pb n="19"/>

<p>The myth of Elmer Gantry as exemplar of
American televangelism will persist for a long time. It is a kind
of variant on Gresham's Law: The dishonorable televangelists will
not drive the honest ones from the airwaves, but the bad name
they so deserve will tarnish the honest broadcasters as well and
make it more difficult for the latter to do their work. And, in
all likelihood, the myths enumerated by Stewart Hoover in the
next chapter in this volume will also be with us.</p>

<p>An examination of information flow about
religious broadcasters can readily provide an explanation of why
the stereotypes and myths will persist. Production and
distribution of information about religious broadcasting come
from 4 groups: (a) the religious broadcasters themselves, (b)
their adversaries, (c) scholars, and (d) the mass
media.</p>

<p><hi rend="bold">Religious broadcasters.</hi></p>
<p>From the perspective of their
adversaries, scholars, and the press, information that comes from
broadcasters themselves is likely to be treated as propaganda.
All organizations, of course, engage in some public relations
efforts to create the best possible image of themselves. And only
rarely have we witnessed examples of organizations voluntarily
hanging their dirty linen out for public inspection. The press
knows this and they expect organizations to hide information and
put the best spin possible on that which they release. And given
the legacy of highly negative images, televangelists and their
spokespersons will be especially suspect of slick talk and hiding
the truth.</p>

<p>Religious broadcasters have never had a very
felicitous relationship with the secular media. They tend to view
the media as unsympathetic, even hostile toward them. Most of
them have aufficient anecdotal evidence to sustain continued
suspicion and distrust of the media. And most of them have not
brought in public relations specialists to deal with the mass
media. For the immediate future, at least, broadcasters are
likely to continue to view their audiences, and known sympathetic
supporters, as the primary outlets for communications about their
ministries. A few may develop more sophistication in dealing with
the media, but most will continue to flounder, ducking
communication as often as possible, and living in constant fear
that reporters are really only present to "do a job" on
them.</p>

<p>Religious broadcasters, thus, are essentially
locked into a closed communications loop, maintaining positive
images. As long as this remains the case, they are unlikely to
have much input into what the mass media write about
them.</p>

<p><hi rend="bold">Adversaries.</hi></p>

<p>Adversaries of religious broadcasting fall into 4
frequently
overlapping groups: (a) theological, (b) competitors, (c)
ideological, and (d) political.
Theological diversity is at the heart of the religious vitality
of American culture, and
this diversity guarantees a large opposition. An overlapping, but
distinct adversarial group
are those who stand in competition for access to the airwaves.
Liberal Protestants, who once
had a virtual monopoly to the airwaves, are the principle but not
the only group in direct</p>

<pb n="20"/>

<p>
competition. Ideological adversaries are committed to a secular
world
and many in this group are opposed to any religious group having
access to
the airwaves (see, for example, Chapter 12). Finally, there are
many who
view the conservative political messages of the televangelists as
a threat
perception of "the American way." Norman Lear's People for the
American
Way, for example, was created for the explicit purpose of doing
battle with
the televangelists. In varying degrees, each of these 4 groups is
engaged in
the production and distribution of negative information about
religious
broadcasters.
</p>

<p><hi rend="bold">Scholars. </hi></p>
<p>
Scholars are the smallest group engaged in the
production of consumable information about religious
broadcasters. Indeed, a fair proportion of the scholarly
community interested in religious broadcasting is represented in
this volume. As often typifies scholarly groups, they are prone
to communicate obtusely, elucidate ad infinitum alternative
interpretations of the meaning of data, quarrel among themselves
about matters that are imperceptible to the consumer public, and
qualify conclusions to the point that consumers can't understand
or don't care what they are saying.</p>

<p>To this should be added the simple observation
that financial resources to conduct empirical studies of religion
have long been scarce and this is unlikely to change. In the
absence of large data bases, scholars are compelled to conduct
small surveys and secondary analyses of resources like the
Arbitron and Nielsen audience ratings, and to engage in creative
speculation (see Chapter 3 for more information).</p>

<p>Scholars do play an important role as resource
persons for print and broadcast journalists assigned to cover
religious broadcasting. But given the diversity of
interpretations among this group, and the absence of much
authoritative data, scholars are not very significant players in
the arena where the images, myths, and symbols about religious
broadcasting are created.</p>

<p><hi rend="bold">Mass media. </hi> </p>
<p>
Most of what the general public knows about religious
broadcasting is communicated through newspapers, radio and
television news and documentaries, and radio talk shows. The
messages from religious broadcasters, adversaries, and scholars
are all filtered through the mass media.</p>

<p>The mass media collectively are not simply a
conduit for communication of news and analysis. This was
especially evident during the televangelism scandals of 1987 and
1988. Television personalities themselves became central players
in the unholy wars. The guests they selected for their programs,
the questions they asked and which answers they chose to probe,
and analyses they offered made Ted Koppel, Larry King, and others
as much a part of the spectacle as Jim and Tammy Faye Bakker,
Jerry Falwell, Jessica Hahn, Oral Roberts, and Jimmy
Swaggart.</p>

<p>The mass media were simultaneously makers,
packagers, participants,</p>

<pb n="21"/>

<p>and interpreters of the news. The images,
analyses, and conclusions America received about the scandals and
the broader world of religious broadcasting were essentially
created by the mass media. The mass media shouldn't be criticized
too severely for their role in keeping the story alive. But it is
significant to note that during the 15-month period or so when
the scandals were a regular part of the national news, not a
single major news source devoted any time or space to
investigative reporting about those televangelists who were not
scandal-ridden. During the same time period, considerable
investigative reporting resources were devoted to trying to
uncover more dirt in other ministries.</p>

<p>It does seem curious that for
all the attention devoted to the scandals editorial curiosity
never brought forth any effort to learn and write about those
ministries and personalities that were not scandal-ridden. One
might assert that the mass media are biased against the
televangelists, and there is some evidence to indicate that this
is true. But the accusation of bias does not get to the heart of
the problem. Rather than crying "bias," we can better understand
the nature of the mass media coverage if we ask a simple and
fundamental question: What are the presuppositions of those who
decide what is newsworthy with respect to the subject they are
investigating? If one assumes a priori that religion and the
modern world don't mix, that religions belong properly in the
private sphere, then it is highly likely that something as
clamorous as televangelism will arouse suspicion from the onset.
Nothing carries so well on visual-driven television as conflict.
It follows that among the sources offering information about
religious broadcasting, the adversaries of religious broadcasting
are likely to gain a disproportionate amount of attention. That
the critics share value presuppositions which are compatible with
the presuppositions of the mass media is likely to result in
their being viewed as "creditable" sources.</p>

<p>If the mass media had dug beneath the grotesque
Gantryesque stereotype of the religious broadcasters, they would
have discovered that most of the radio and television ministries
are operated by men and women of good will and integrity. And
they would have found that many of the broadcasters would readily
admit that the scandals helped them to see themselves in a new
light and forced them to reassess their own activities and
accountability to supporters. Many now understand more clearly
than they were earlier able to see how competition, the desire to
grow, and, in some instances, how the sheer struggle to survive
had drawn them into the use of fund-raising tactics that were
questionable.</p>

<p>More importantly, in the past, religious
broadcasters have jealously guarded their organizational
autonomy. Scandals in someone else's ministry were not their
problem. But the fraud, deception, and hypocrisy that became
evident as details of the PTL scandal unfolded, and the hoax of a
wrathful God holding his televangelist servant hostage to pay
broadcasting bills were simply too much to ignore. The
credibility of all broadcasters was</p>

<pb n="22"/>

<p>profoundly challenged. Perhaps not so much out
of an altruistic desire to be their brothers' keeper as a desire
to protect their own hides, the National Religious Broadcasters
created a regulatory agency (Ethics and Financial Integrity
Commission) with real teeth to enforce standards of ethical
conduct. Membership in EFICOM is not optional for NRB members.
When Swaggart confessed his sexual misconduct, NRB Executive
Committee wasted no time in recommending expulsion even before
the machinery of EFICOM was in place.</p>

<p>However reluctantly, the broadcasters have come
to the conclusion that they cannot escape the negative
stereotypes that a few of their brethren have helped create and
sustain. If they don't become complacent once the storms of the
scandals have blown over, the broadcasters would become a model
of integrity for voluntary organizations in America. But this
will not come easily. Even if there are no further scandals among
NRB members for a sustained time, the most unscrupulous will
remain outside of the organization's watchdog organization. And
their excesses and misdeeds will continue to cast a shroud of
doubt regarding the integrity of all broadcasters.</p>

<p>In the final analysis, the market test for
those broadcasters who operate with integrity will be
whether they are reaching an audience that finds inspiration in
their message. And if they do, they will survive. But in the
minds of the millions who are neither turned onto their programs
nor attuned to their theology and world view, Elmer Gantry will
remain alive and well as exemplar of American
televangelism.</p>
</div2>

<div2 type="bibliography" id="d5">

<head>REFERENCES</head>

<p>Associated Press. (1988, June 9). Bakker
says God has given him plan. <hi rend="italic">Charlottesville Daily Progress,
</hi> p. A2.</p>

<p>Bakker, J. (1987, March 20). Transcript of
resignation statement. <hi rend="italic">Charlotte Observer,
</hi>p. A1.</p>

<p>Ctark, D.W., &amp; Virts, P.H. (1985, October25).
<hi rend="italic">Religious television audience: A new development
in measuring audience size.</hi> Paper presented at The Society
for the Scientific Study of Religion Conference, Savanna,
GA.</p>

<p>Frank, J.A., &amp; Grove, L. (1987, March 24).
The raging battles of the evangelicals. <hi rend="italic">Washington Post,</hi>
pp. A1, A14.</p>

<p>Lewis, S. (1927). <hi rend="italic">Elmer Gantry.</hi> New
York: Harcourt, Brace.</p>

<p>Los Angeles Times. (1986). Los Angeles Times
poll: Religion and politics, LAT 108. Los Angeles, CA:
Author.</p>

<p>Los Angeles Times. (1987). Los Angeles Times
poll: Religion and politics, LAT 108C/Panelback. Los Angeles, CA:
Author.</p>

<p>Seligman, J. (1987, June 8). The inimitable
Tammy Faye; Newsweek, p. 69.</p>

<p>Shales, T. (1987, May 29). The "Nightline"
coup. <hi rend="italic">Washington Post,</hi>p. B1.</p>

<p>Watson, R. (1987, June 3). Heaven can wait.
<hi rend="italic">Newsweek, </hi>pp. 58-62, 65.</p>

<p>Appeared in: Robert Abelman and Stuart M. Hoover, Eds.

<hi rend="italic">Religious Television: Controversies and Conclusions</hi>

Norwood, NJ: Ablex Publishing. 1990. 13-22.</p>

</div2>
</div1>
</body>
</text>
</TEI.2>
