<?xml version="1.0"?>

<?dlps id="HadPoli"?>
<?dlps page-images="none" figure-images="no"?>
<?dlps transcription="other"?>

<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/tei-p4/tei2.dtd" [
<!ENTITY % POSTKB "INCLUDE">
<!ENTITY % TEI.extensions.ent SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.ent">
<!ENTITY % TEI.extensions.dtd SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.dtd">
<!ENTITY % ISOnum SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/charent/iso-num.ent"> %ISOnum;

]>
<TEI.2 id="HadPoli">
<teiHeader type="migrated" creator="Etext">
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title type="main">Policing the Religious Airwaves:  A Case of Market Place Regulation</title>
<title type="sort">policing the religious airwaves a case of market place regulation</title>
<author>Hadden, Jeffrey K.</author>
<respStmt>
<resp>Creation of machine-readable version:</resp>
<name>religiousbroadcasting.lib.virginia.edu/pubs</name>
<resp>Conversion to TEI.2-conformant markup:</resp>
<name>University of Virginia Library Electronic Text Center.</name>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt>
<extent>ca. <num type="kilobytes">73</num> kilobytes</extent>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>University of Virginia Library</publisher>
<pubPlace>Charlottesville, Virginia</pubPlace>
<idno type="ETC">HadPoli</idno>
<date value="2001">2001</date>
<availability status="public">
<p n="copyright">Copyright &copy; 2001 by the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia</p>
<p n="access">Publicly accessible</p>
</availability>
<idno type="uva-pid">uva-lib:476017</idno>
</publicationStmt>
<seriesStmt>
<title>University of Virginia Library, Text collection</title>
<idno type="uva-set">UVA-LIB-Text</idno>
</seriesStmt>
<seriesStmt>
<p>BYU Journal of Public Law</p>
</seriesStmt>
<sourceDesc>
<biblFull>
<titleStmt>
<title type="main">Policing the Religious Airwaves:  A Case of Market Place Regulation</title>
<title type="sort">policing the religious airwaves a case of market place regulation</title>
<author>Jeffrey Hadden</author>
<editor>[first name then last name]</editor>
</titleStmt>
<extent>21 pp.</extent>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>J. Reuben Clark Law School</publisher>
<pubPlace>Provo, Utah</pubPlace>
<date value="1994-09">Fall 1994</date>
<idno type="callNo">Source copy consulted:    University of Virginia Library, P.B106, Volume 8, Number 2</idno>
</publicationStmt>
<notesStmt>
<note>
<p>Volume 8, Number 2, p. 393-416</p>
</note>
</notesStmt>
</biblFull>
</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc>
<encodingDesc>
<projectDesc>
<p>Prepared for the University of Virginia Library Electronic Text Center.</p>
</projectDesc>
<editorialDecl>
<p>All unambiguous end-of-line hyphens have been removed, and the  trailing part of a word has been joined to the preceding line.</p>
<p id="ETC">Some keywords in the header are a local Electronic Text Center scheme  to aid in establishing analytical groupings.</p>
</editorialDecl>
</encodingDesc>
<profileDesc>
<creation>
<date value="1994">1994</date>
</creation>
<langUsage>
<language id="eng" usage="main">English</language>
<language id="lat">Latin</language>
</langUsage>
<textClass>
<keywords>
<term>nonfiction</term>
<term>prose</term>
<term>masculine</term>
<term>LCSH, RELIGION, DEMOCRACY, SOCIOLOGY</term>
</keywords>
</textClass>
</profileDesc>
<revisionDesc>
<change>
<date value="2003-04">April 2003</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>corrector</resp>
<name>Jason Smick</name>
</respStmt>
<item/>
</change>
<change>
<date value="2005-07">July 2005</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>Corrector</resp>
<name>John Ivor Carlson</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Converted SGML to XML. Fixed tagging.</item>
</change>
<change>
<date value="2007-09">September 2007</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>Migration</resp>
<name>Ethan Gruber, University of Virginia Library</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Converted XML markup from TEI Lite to uva-dl-tei (TEI P4 with local customizations).</item>
</change>
<change>
<date value="2008-01">January 2008</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>Migration</resp>
<name>Greg Murray, University of Virginia Library</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Programmatically updated TEI header markup (but not header content) for minimal compliance with current QA requirements.</item>
</change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>
<text id="d1">
<body id="d2">

<div1 type="article" id="d3">
<head>Policing the Religious Airwaves:  A Case of<lb/>
Market Place Regulation<lb/>
<lb/>
<lb/>
Jeffrey K. Hadden
<ref target="n1.0">*</ref>
</head>
<div2 type="section" n="1" id="d4">
<head>
<hi rend="bold">I. INTRODUCTION: OF TELEVANGELISTS, SCANDAL, MARKET<lb/>
PRESSURES AND GOVERNMENT</hi></head>


<p>The movement of a few television preachers into politics during the
early 1980s led to the widely held perception that the televangelists
had trespassed the serpentine wall that has traditionally separated
religion and politics.
<ref target="n1.1">[1]</ref>
As tormented money and sex scandals unfolded--not in the supermarket
tabloids but on the evening television news and on ABC's <hi rend="italic">Nightline,</hi>
millions of Americans concluded that the televangelists were living
beyond accountability.
<ref target="n1.2">[2]</ref>
</p>
<pb n="394"/>
<p>If ever the time was ripe for the government to step in and regulate
religious broadcasters, it was in the late 1980s. But religious
broadcasters had not taken orders from worldly authorities in the past,
and the misdeeds of some of their broadcast colleagues were not enough
to temper their fierce independence. When called before the oversight
committee of the House Ways and Means Committee in October 1987, several
of the nation's leading religious broadcasters told Congressman J. J.
Pickle (D-Tex.) and his colleagues that they were quite capable of
regulating themselves. While religious broadcasters spoke softly, if
sternly, the executive director of their trade association, the National
Religious Broadcasters (NRB), went on the attack. Ben Armstrong labeled
the Pickle hearings an "insidious" attack and "the
beginning of a new 'inquisition,'" against religious broadcasters.
<ref target="n1.3">[3]</ref>
</p>
<p>The new inquisition never materialized. Congressman Pickle's
subcommittee has kept a watchful eye on religious broadcasters, as
has the Internal Revenue Service. But the pattern of federal
government agency monitoring has been one of quietly seeking
information and, where questions of compliance with government
regulations arose, of privately seeking compliance.
<ref target="n1.4">[4]</ref>
</p>
<p>Critics of religious broadcasters complained that the cozy
political alliance between the televangelists and conservative White
House incumbents effectively squelched inquiries by federal
regulatory agencies. While this proposition would seem</p>
<pb n="395"/>
<p>to have some <foreign lang="lat"><hi rend="italic">prima facie</hi></foreign> merit, the argument advanced in this
article is that market forces should be the primary instrument for
the regulation of religious broadcasting. The conclusion reached is
that notwithstanding the encroachments of some religious
broadcasters into the arena of politics, and the scandals and shame
that befell some broadcast ministries, governmental and market
structures for policing religious broadcasters appear to be in place
and working well. The future, however, may be more problematic. This
uncertain future stems from underlying structural developments in
the communications industry and in the changing legal character of
the culture, not from the scandals that rocked religious
broadcasting in the late 1980s.</p>
<p>To date, policing of the religious airwaves has taken place at
two levels. First, religious broadcasters have been subjected to
essentially the same regulatory principles that govern all
broadcasting in America.
<ref target="n1.5">[5]</ref>
If the radio and television preachers sometimes appear to be
operating in a relatively unfettered manner, it is because
broadcasting in the United States operates with greater latitude and
freedom from government interference than broadcasting in any other
nation. Although not the subject of this piece, it is interesting to
note that religious broadcasting is, in many ways, a macrocosm of
the broadcast industry itself.</p>
<p>The second level of regulation of religious broadcasters is a
complex web of informal social controls. These informal social
controls operate most effectively on the level of the broadcast
networks, the level of local radio and television station managers
and owners, and the level of the viewing and listening audiences
which support the access of religious broadcasters to the airwaves.
This Article takes on the task of exploring the history of how these
informal social controls evolved and worked.</p>
<p>Notwithstanding the general effectiveness of informal social
controls, the trend of the modern welfare state is toward the
involvement of government in virtually every aspect of public and
private life. This portends a similar fate for religion in general
and religious broadcasting specifically. In the concluding section,
this paper will explore the implications of this development.</p>
</div2>
<pb n="396"/>
<div2 type="notes" id="d5">
<head>Footnotes</head>
	<note id="n1.0"><seg type="note-symbol">[*]</seg> <p>Professor of Sociology at the University of Virginia.  Published works on
religious broadcasting include <hi rend="bold">Prime Time Preachers (1981)</hi>
and <hi rend="bold">Televangelisms:  Power and Politics On God's Frontier (1988)</hi></p></note>
<note id="n1.1"><seg type="note-symbol">[1]</seg> <p>This was not the first time religious broadcasters stepped
over the preaching-politicking line. The most celebrated case was
that of Father Charles E. Coughin, a Roman Catholic parish priest
from a Detroit suburb, who began radio broadcasting in 1926.
Gradually, his sermons became highly politicized. In 1932, he
actively supported the presidential candidacy of Franklin D.
Roosevelt and then later became Roosevelt's bitter enemy. So
daunting were Coughlin's attacks that Roosevelt had Coughlin's
mailing privileges revoked under the Espionage Act of 1917, and
considered having him indicted for sedition before choosing to
persuade the priest's archbishop to silence him.</p></note>
	<note id="n1.2"><seg type="note-symbol">[2]</seg> <p>The televangelism scandals commenced in early 1987, when
Oral Roberts sent out a direct-mail fundraising appeal in which he
claimed that God would "call him home" if he failed to
raise $8 million by the first of April. The secular press picked up
the story and treated it as something between a tragic scam and high
comedy. The count down to April Fools Day was preempted, however, on
March 19, when Jim Bakker, then head of the <hi rend="italic">Praise The Lord</hi> (PTL)
religious broadcasting empire, resigned in disgrace after
allegations of sexual and other misconduct. Bakker, with his wife
and broadcast partner Tammy Faye at his side, tearfully described
the cause for his resignation. By his account, a long past and
forgiven sexual encounter with a former church secretary was now
being used against him by former friends. But there was more. The
sordid details unfolded for months revealing high salaries and high
living built on a pyramid-like scheme of "life time
partnerships" guaranteeing free accommodations at Heritage USA,
a Christian theme park created by the Bakkers. Bakker eventually
turned the empire over to Jerry Falwell, a Virginia-based
fundamentalist broadcaster who had gained international visibility
in 1980 as the head of a political organization called the Moral
Majority. But before all of the details of the PTL scandal were
revealed Louisiana-based televangelist Jimmy Swaggart was caught in
the presence of a prostitute by a rival small-time television
preacher. Some months later Swaggart was again caught in the
presence of a prostitute, this time by police officers that had
stopped him for a moving violation. These scandals destroyed the
television empires of Bakker and Swaggart. Perhaps more importantly,
they cast a shroud of doubt on the integrity of all religious
broadcasters.</p></note>
	<note id="n1.3"><seg type="note-symbol">[3]</seg> <p>Michael Isikoff, <hi rend="italic">Evangelists Defend Funding Tactics,</hi> THE
WASHINGTON POST. October 7, 1987, at C4.</p></note>
	<note id="n1.4"><seg type="note-symbol">[4]</seg> <p>While federal agencies have chosen a quiet, almost private
path to monitoring religious broadcasters, this has not always been
the case at the state level of government. For example, Texas
Attorney General Dan Morales publicly pursued litigation against
televangelist Robert G. Tilton following an expose by ABC's <hi rend="italic">Prime
Time Live</hi> in late 1991. U.S. District Judge Sam Sparks of Austin
threw out the suit against Tilton and admonished Morales, noting
that the attorney general's investigation was "neither
professional nor responsible, bordering on unethical, and
constitutes bad faith." Nancy St. Pierre, <hi rend="italic">U.S. Court Judge
Criticizes Morales in Tilton Inquiry,</hi> DALLAS MORNING NEWS. March
19, 1992, at 13A.</p></note>
	<note id="n1.5"><seg type="note-symbol">[5]</seg> <p>The primary regulatory agency of the government, of course,
is the Federal Communications Commission (FCC).</p></note>
</div2>

<div2 type="section" n="2" id="d6">
<head>
<hi rend="bold">II. FORMAL REGULATORY STRUCTURES AND ACCOUNTABILITY<lb/>
IN RELIGIOUS BROADCASTING</hi></head>
<p>The Radio Act of 1912, which actually preceded regular broadcasting, did not
adequately anticipate the problems of this new communications medium. Indeed,
these early days of radio broadcasting were characterized by few regulations. A talented
engineer could build a station for a few hundred dollars, and anyone
could obtain a license. These have been characterized as the
"wild and wooly days of radio"
<ref target="n2.6">[6]</ref>
and as a "frenzied frequency free-for-all."
<ref target="n2.7">[7]</ref>
Ben Armstrong, former Executive Director of the National Religious
Broadcasters, described what happened: "Stations competed for
the airwaves all across the frequency band, drowning one another in
bedlam of squeaks, whistles, and disjointed words."
<ref target="n2.8">[8]</ref>
</p>
<p>One of the most celebrated renegades of this early era was Aimee
Semple McPherson, an early superstar of radio evangelism.
McPherson's shifting of power and frequency was sufficiently
annoying that Secretary of Commerce Herbert Hoover ordered her
station in Los Angeles closed. Enraged by this action, McPherson
fired an angry telegram to Hoover saying, "Please order your
minions of Satan to leave my station alone. You cannot expect the
Almighty to abide by your wave length nonsense. When I offer my
prayers to Him I must fit into His wave reception. Open this station
at once."
<ref target="n2.9">[9]</ref>
In the end, Hoover didn't have the authority to shut down
McPherson's station. It took the Radio Act of 1927, which created a
federal agency with the power to license and regulate radio
broadcasting; to bring it under some semblance of control.
<ref target="n2.10">[10]</ref>
This episode teaches at least three enduring lessons
<pb n="397"/>
concerning the relationship between religious broadcasters and
public policy.</p>
<p>First, some regulation of broadcasting, religious and otherwise,
would be necessary to safeguard stations from technical interference
by other stations, to insure that the limited spectrum of
frequencies available to broadcasters would be utilized efficiently
and fairly, and to prevent misuse by those who would influence
society in ways judged harmful.
<ref target="n2.11">[11]</ref>
These considerations, taken together, virtually assured that
government would play some role, probably a critical one, in
regulating radio and television broadcasting.
<ref target="n2.12">[12]</ref>
Government could not and would not, after all, stand by while
renegade broadcasters transmitted their signals in whatever
direction caught their fancy, or while high-power stations drowned
out lower-power stations.</p>
<p>Second, while the incident of a flamboyant and highly visible
female preacher, such as Aimee Semple McPherson, may lend credence
to the perception that religious broadcasters are the principal
abusers of the airwaves, in reality abuse of the airwaves is by no
means restricted to religious broadcasters. Aimee Semple McPherson
was not and would not be the only broadcaster to violate simple
norms of civility, such as, avoiding interference with other
broadcasters.
<ref target="n2.13">[13]</ref>
Quite deservedly, the behavior of religious broadcasters has been
the</p>
<pb n="398"/>
<p>subject of intense public scrutiny in recent years. But a
fair-minded assessment of that behavior will recognize that every
misdeed of religious broadcasters can be matched by parallel
misdeeds by secular broadcasters. 'It might well be asserted, in
fact, that non-religious broadcasters are responsible for the lion's
share of questionable behavior broadcast over the airwaves.</p>
<p>Third, notwithstanding the inevitability of government
regulation, religious broadcasters have tended to see their mission
as special and, therefore, have believed that they should not be
subject to regulation by any worldly or secular authority. For many
broadcasters, this view is grounded in the belief that the airwaves
are quite literally an instrument given by God to facilitate the
mission of preaching the Gospel to all the nations. They take
seriously Christ's commandment to go into all the world and preach
the gospel to every creature.
<ref target="n2.14">[14]</ref>
The ability to transmit the voice and the visual image of the
preacher has, for the first time in history, made it possible to
reach all humankind with the Gospel message.
<ref target="n2.15">[15]</ref>
When this perspective is taken seriously, it is understandable why
some evangelicals view God's command to spread the Gospel as loftier
and more worthy of obedience than any mortal decree. It is important
to note here that this perspective focuses attention on the biblical
commandment to preach the Gospel, rather than on any constitutional
right to do so. From a secular perspective, however, the real issue
is not a divine commandment so much as it is one of
arrogance--arrogance stemming from the belief that religious
broadcasters are accountable to God alone and,</p>
<pb n="399"/>
<p>hence, that any other accountability would be superfluous. At a
press conference following Jerry Falwell's assumption of Praise The
Lord (PTL) leadership in April, 1987, he confessed this to be the
case albeit in an underwhelming way: "[we] have had a little
sense of arrogance out there in the [televangelistic] church that it
is none of [the Government's] business or anybody else's what we do
or how we do it."
<ref target="n2.16">[16]</ref>
Falwell promised that "the arrogance is over,"
<ref target="n2.17">[17]</ref>
but six years after the televangelism scandals came to public light,
a large proportion of America's religious broadcasters still
stubbornly refuse to open their books to outsiders or to subject
themselves to formal self-regulation.</p>
</div2>
<div2 type="notes" id="d7">
<head>Footnotes</head>
<note id="n2.6"><seg type="note-symbol">[6]</seg> <p> Kimberly A. Neuendorf, <hi rend="italic">The Public Trust Versus the Almighty
Dollar,</hi> in <hi rend="bold">Religious Television: Controversies and Conclusions</hi> 73
(Robert Abelman and Steward M. Hoover eds., 1990).</p></note>
<note id="n2.7"><seg type="note-symbol">[7]</seg> <p> Dennis N. Voskuil, <hi rend="italic">The Power of the Air: Evangelicals and
the Rise of Religious Broadcasting,</hi> in <hi rend="bold">American Evangelicals and
the Mass Media</hi> 72 (Quentin J. Schultze ed., 1990).</p></note>
<note id="n2.8"><seg type="note-symbol">[8]</seg> <p> Ben Armstrong, <hi rend="bold">The Electric Church</hi> 24 (1979).</p></note>
<note id="n2.9"><seg type="note-symbol">[9]</seg> <p> Jeffrey K. Hadden &amp; Charles E. Swann, <hi rend="bold">Prime Time
Preachers</hi> pp. 188-89 (1981). Whether Aimee Semple McPherson
believed the Department of Commerce agents literally to be
"minions of satin" or merely intrusive bureaucrats, it is
clear that she believed they had no legitimate basis for interfering
with her broadcasting. There remain today a significant number of
religious broadcasters who share that view.</p></note>
<note id="n2.10"><seg type="note-symbol">[10]</seg> <p> This was one of the classic confrontations in the politics
of American broadcasting. McPherson was a self-made evangelist
without professional credentials, yet she was one of the most gifted
radio evangelists of the 20th Century. In her indomitable resistance
she succeeded in facing down a powerful Washington politician who
just three years later would become the President of the United
States.</p></note>
<note id="n2.11"><seg type="note-symbol">[11]</seg> <p> For a more detailed discussion of the rationale for
broadcast regulation, see Sydney W. Head, <hi rend="bold">World Broadcasting
Systems</hi>. 129-61 (1985).</p></note>
<note id="n2.12"><seg type="note-symbol">[12]</seg> <p> Clearly, preventing technical interference and protecting a
scarce resource are more readily defined and executed than
determining "the public interest" and "misuse"
of the airwaves. The first two objectives have been managed
relatively easy by the regulatory agency, while the latter two have
periodically engaged executive, judicial and legislative branches of
government.</p></note>
<note id="n2.13"><seg type="note-symbol">[13]</seg> <p> As to Aimee Semple McPherson being singled out for punitive
attention, the historical record as to whether her practice was more
egregious than that of others is not clear. My informed speculation
is that it was not. I suspect McPherson was singled out because of
the content and style of her broadcasts. An important lesson of the
McPherson case is that we ought to examine the behavior of religious
broadcasters in the light of broadcasting industry standards rather
than from the perspective of externally imposed standards. To demand
that regulatory agencies hold religious broadcasters to higher
standards than other broadcasters is to introduce prejudice that, if
acted upon, would likely result in violation of the Free Exercise
Clause of the First Amendment.</p></note>
<note id="n2.14"><seg type="note-symbol">[14]</seg> <p> <hi rend="italic">Mark</hi> 16:15.</p></note>
<note id="n2.15"><seg type="note-symbol">[15]</seg> <p> The history of electronic communication is intertwined with
religious significance and symbolism which serves to affirm these
evangelical Christians' belief that this medium has providential
purpose. In 1844 when Samuel F. B. Morse completed the installation
of the first telegraphic line he seemed to have experienced a sense
of awe, even sacredness, in what he was doing as is evidenced by the
choice of his first transmission: "What hath God wrought."
Head; supra note 11, at 108. Radio dates back to 1896 with Guglielmo
Marconi's discovery of wireless communication, but the first
successful voice transmission occurred a decade later when a
Canadian engineer, Reginal Fessenden, beamed a signal from the coast
of Massachusetts to ships at sea on Christmas Eve, 1906. The content
of this first transmission was a religious service. Hadden &amp;
Swann, <hi rend="italic">supra</hi> note 9, at 8-9. Marconi provided technical assistance
in the construction of Vatican Radio and introduced the Holy Father
to the world in the inauguration of the first global network. <hi rend="bold">Donald
R. Browne, International Radio Broadcasting.</hi> 306 (1982).
These and other early developments in radio and television provide
the rationale evangelicals express for the providential character of
broadcasting.</p></note>
<note id="n2.16"><seg type="note-symbol">[16]</seg> <p> <hi rend="italic">Excerpts from the Rev. Jerry Falwell's News Conference.</hi>
<hi rend="bold">The Charlotte Observer.</hi> April 2D, 1987, at llA (emphasis added).</p></note>
<note id="n2.17"><seg type="note-symbol">[17]</seg> <p> <hi rend="italic">Ibid.</hi></p></note>
</div2>

<div2 type="section" n="3" id="d8">
<head>
<hi rend="bold">III. Informal Social Controls and Accountability in<lb/>
Religious Broadcasting</hi></head>

<div3 type="subsection" id="d9">


<p>Radio and television broadcasting in the United States have
passed through four stages of development. Each stage corresponds
roughly to the formal regulatory environment,
<ref target="n3.18">[18]</ref>
but formal regulatory structures are themselves determined by
technological, organizational, and social developments.
<ref target="n3.19">[19]</ref>
</p>

<div4 type="notes" id="d10">
<head>Footnotes</head>
<note id="n3.18"><seg type="note-symbol">[18]</seg> <p> Neuendorf, <hi rend="italic">supra</hi> note 6, at 72.</p></note>
<note id="n3.19"><seg type="note-symbol">[19]</seg> <p>The dates attached to each stage are only rough
approximations. Beginning dates correspond to specific developments,
although the real impact of that development may not be felt for
some years. Similarly, the denotation of a new phase does not
usually represent a sharp departure from the previous stage.</p></note>
</div4>
</div3>

<div3 type="subsection" id="d11">


<head><hi rend="italic">A. Stage One: Unregulated Broadcast Experimentatiation<lb/>
(1906-1927)</hi></head>

<p>Reginal Fessenden's offshore airwaves transmission on Christmas
Eve of 1906 inaugurated broadcasting and the ensuing stage of
experimentation.
<ref target="n3.1.20">[20]</ref>
The technology was quickly grasped and widely explored around the
globe. The first regularly scheduled radio broadcast in the United
States commenced in November 1920, in Pittsburgh. Owned by
Westinghouse Electric, radio station KDKA was created to stimulate
the sale of radios. Many other radio stations quickly commenced
regular broadcasting. In less than two years, there were 382
stations in operation. In just over four years, there</p>
<pb n="400"/>
<p>were over 600 stations on the air. By 1927, just seven years
since the establishment of the KDKA, the number of radio stations
had escalated to 732.
<ref target="n3.1.21">[21]</ref>
And religious organizations were into broadcasting from the
beginning. For, of the 600 stations identified by <hi rend="italic">Popular Radio</hi>
magazine in January 1925, sixty-three were owned by churches and
pare-church organizations.
<ref target="n3.1.22">[22]</ref>
</p>
<p>By 1924, station owners discovered that they could sell time to
business organizations to promote their products, and the rush to
develop privately owned commercial radio was underway. Religious
stations did not fare well under the stiff competition of a market
that quickly turned commercial. In fairly short order, many of these
radio pulpit preachers turned out to be short on the capital needed
to keep up with the rapidly rising costs and technology of
broadcasting, to say nothing of the political capital needed to
protect themselves from the assaults of those who, for commercial
reasons, coveted their broadcast licenses. While some religious
broadcasters were blasted off the air by stations with greater
power, others faced license challenges by commercial stations. Some
were squeezed out by heavy-handed deals, others sold their licenses,
and others still simply ceased to broadcast. Those who remained
would face even stiffer challenges during the second stage of
broadcasting.</p>


<div4 type="notes" id="d12">
<head>Footnotes</head>

<note id="n3.1.20"><seg type="note-symbol">[20]</seg> <p> <hi rend="italic">See supra</hi> note 12.</p></note>
<note id="n3.1.21"><seg type="note-symbol">[21]</seg> <p> Voskuil, <hi rend="italic">supra</hi> note 7.</p></note>
<note id="n3.1.22"><seg type="note-symbol">[22]</seg> <p> HADDEN &amp; SWANN, <hi rend="italic">supra</hi> note 9, at 73-74.</p></note>
</div4>
</div3>

<div3 type="subsection" id="d13">


<div4 type="subsection" n="3.2" id="d14">
<head><hi rend="italic">B. Stage Two: Sustaining-Time and the Politics of Exclusion<lb/>
(1927-1956)</hi></head>

<p>During the first stage of experimental radio, commercial
broadcasters had ample opportunity to observe that religious
broadcasters tended to be noisy, often intolerant, and otherwise
controversial. What was more, they came in large numbers seeking
access to the airwaves. Dealing with them posed no small problem.</p>
<p>Most station owners preferred having liberal Protestants on the
air to having Fundamentalists or Pentecostals, groups who were
clamoring for the opportunity. But from the beginning, the liberal
Protestant traditions were very much underrepresented. Part of the
problem was that liberal Protestants were ambivalent about
broadcasting. They saw the possibility</p>
<pb n="401"/>
<p>of some positive benefits, but they could also see potential
negative consequences, and some were vociferous in their
condemnation of evangelical broadcasters.
<ref target="n3.2.23">[23]</ref>
Their attacks provided legitimacy for the exclusive policies of the
broadcast networks and the Federal Radio Commission,
<ref target="n3.2.24">[24]</ref>
(FRC) policies which would remain in effect for nearly three
decades.</p>
<p>The formal and informal mechanisms that restricted evangelical
access to the airwaves first became evident in the late 1920s with
the creation of FRC and the formation of radio networks.
<ref target="n3.2.25">[25]</ref>
In its early years of operation, FRC used its broad authority in a
rather heavy-handed way. During the late 1920s, FRC reassigned some
religious stations to low-powered frequencies, determined not to
grant new licenses to new religious stations, and used its broad
regulatory powers to examine complaints that existing religious
stations were not operating in the "public interest."
<ref target="n3.2.26">[26]</ref>
</p>
<p>At this time, the broadcast networks combined their informal
efforts to control evangelical broadcasting. NBC, the first radio
network, was founded in 1926. At the onset, NBC determined not to
accept paid religious broadcasting. Time allocated for religious
broadcasting would be offered at no cost (or as <hi rend="italic">sustaining-time,</hi>
as it is called in the industry), but would be offered "only [to]
the central national agencies of great religious faiths."
<ref target="n3.2.27">[27]</ref>
The Federal Council of Churches, an affiliation of liberal
Protestant groups were solicited for counsel and manpower for
religious broadcasts. This policy explicitly excluded
"individual churches or small group movements where the
<pb n="402"/>
national membership is comparatively small."
<ref target="n3.2.28">[28]</ref>
Small denominations and independent evangelical broadcasters were
thus caught in a double bind; for, on the one hand, they were
excluded by network radio, and, on the other they were squeezed out
by the FRC. But for the free enterprise character of broadcasting,
evangelicals might have been excluded from the airwaves altogether.</p>
<p>When CBS radio network was formed in 1927, they needed cash and,
thus, determined they would sell air-time for religious
broadcasting, but in 1931 they shifted to a policy of
sustaining-time religious broadcasts only.
<ref target="n3.2.29">[29]</ref>
For the next four years, the only access to the airwaves for
evangelicals was on local stations, but this was often difficult.
Many local stations adopted the networks' policy of sustaining-time
only and, further, accommodated only "mainline" religious
groups.
<ref target="n3.2.30">[30]</ref>
</p>
<p>A major breakthrough for evangelicals came in 1935 with the
formation of the Mutual Broadcasting Network (Mutual). Mutual
accepted paid religious broadcasts, and Charles E. Fuller's
"The Old-Fashioned Revival Hour" quickly became Mutual's
largest account. By 1940, paid religious broadcasting accounted for
more than one-quarter of Mutual's revenues. In 1943, Mutual seemed
ready to join NBC and CBS in a policy of sustaining-time only for
religious programming, but then reversed its decision and announced,
instead, restrictive policies. Most important among the restrictions
was the banning of on air solicitation of money from listening
audiences. The prohibition against asking audiences to help pay for
the programs made it impossible for some broadcasters to continue.</p>
<p>It is widely believed that Mutual's decision to restrict access
was the result of pressure from liberal church groups.
<ref target="n3.2.31">[31]</ref>
</p>
<pb n="403"/>
<p>Whether or not there was a conspiracy to exclude religious
broadcasters from the air, evangelicals were having a difficult time
gaining access to the airwaves. In 1942, they created the National
Association of Evangelicals, and one of the first official acts of
that organization was to create a radio committee to explore the
problem of discrimination in access to the airwaves. Furthermore, in
April, 1944, just a month after Mutual announced its policy changes,
150 evangelical broadcasters met in Columbus, Ohio, and formed NRB,
<ref target="n3.2.32">[32]</ref>
whose first official act was to retain a Washington-based
communications attorney.
<ref target="n3.2.33">[33]</ref>
NRB claimed some early successes, including gaining access to some
sustaining time on Mutual and NBC's newly created Blue Network (a
forerunner to ABC), but then lost some of its initial zeal and
vitality.
<ref target="n3.2.34">[34]</ref>
</p>
<p>The rapid expansion of television in the 1950s, like the initial
expansion of network radio, caught evangelicals off guard. NBC
turned again to the Federal Council of Churches and representatives
of Catholicism and Judaism and moved swiftly to put in place a
policy that would exclude evangelicals. CBS, leery of earlier
conflict with evangelicals, added the Southern Baptists to its
consortium of liberal Protestants,</p>
<pb n="404"/>
<p>Catholics, and Jews. The Southern Baptists were evangelical, but
not members of NRB. Thus, the large body of small evangelical
denominations and independent broadcasters were effectively cut out
of access to national television at the same time they were
struggling to keep a foothold in national radio.</p>
<p>In summary, the late 1920s through the mid-1950s saw the rapid
expansion of television and the formation of networks.
<ref target="n3.2.35">[35]</ref>
This period also saw evangelical broadcasters excluded from the
communications marketplace.
<ref target="n3.2.36">[36]</ref>
One can pose questions of prejudice and First Amendment rights of
access, but these questions are moot today. If evangelical preachers
perceived their problem in constitutional terms of free access, they
did not take their fight to the courts. Most important, however, is
the fact that, at the time, evangelical religious broadcasters were
not well organized enough to challenge those who did not want them
on the airwaves.</p>
</div4>

<div4 type="notes" id="d15">
<head>Footnotes</head>

<note id="n3.2.23"><seg type="note-symbol">[23]</seg> <p> For a treatise that personifies the ambivalence of liberal
church leaders toward radio and television broadcasting from the
onset, see JOHN W. BUCKMAN, THE CHURCH IN THE WORLD OF RADIO AND
TELEVISION. (1960). Their response was not totally negative.
"As early as 1923 the Federal Council of Churches [the
forerunner of the National Council of Churches] officially
encouraged local church federations to develop cooperative radio
ministries." Voskuil, <hi rend="italic">supra</hi> note 5, at 76. This counsel was to
some measure followed, but liberal church leaders never became as
excited about the possibilities of broadcasting as did the
evangelical traditions.</p></note>
<note id="n3.2.24"><seg type="note-symbol">[24]</seg> <p> Forerunner to the FCC.</p></note>
<note id="n3.2.25"><seg type="note-symbol">[25]</seg> <p> FRC was created by the Radio Act of 1927, which empowered an
independent agency to assign frequencies, license stations, review
the performance of those licensed, and otherwise exercise broad
authority in the regulation of broadcast communications.</p></note>
<note id="n3.2.26"><seg type="note-symbol">[26]</seg> <p> In 1931 the license of a powerful and controversial Los
Angeles religious broadcaster, "Fighting Bob" Shuller, was
withdrawn.</p></note>
<note id="n3.2.27"><seg type="note-symbol">[27]</seg> <p> <hi rend="italic">Policy Statement of the NBC Advisory Committee on Religious
Activities,</hi> in JEFFREY K. HADDEN &amp; CHARLES E. SWANN. PRIME
TIME PREACHERS at 77.</p></note>
<note id="n3.2.28"><seg type="note-symbol">[28]</seg> <p> <hi rend="italic">Ibid.</hi></p></note>
<note id="n3.2.29"><seg type="note-symbol">[29]</seg> <p> Ostensibly, this policy shift was to bring CBS into
conformity with the other network. In reality, it was a means of
getting rid of Father Charles Coughlin, whose sermons were
considered too controversial. CBS, like NBC, called upon the Federal
Council for assistance in programming.</p></note>
<note id="n3.2.30"><seg type="note-symbol">[30] </seg> <p>When evangelicals did get on local stations, they were twice
as likely to be charged for the airtime, as were Roman Catholics and
mainline Protestants. Voskuil, <hi rend="italic">supra</hi> note 7, at 76.</p></note>
<note id="n3.2.31"><seg type="note-symbol">[31]</seg> <p> Federal Council officials denied this and investigators of
the controversy have failed to find a smoking gun. It is also likely
that both networks and local stations were pressured by prospective
advertisers for these choice time slots. William Martin, <hi rend="italic">Giving the
Winds a Mighty Voice, in</hi> AMERICAN EVANGELICALS AND THE MASS MEDIA.
63 (Quentin J. Schultze ed., 1990). Lowell Saunders, in perhaps the
most comprehensive investigation of the controversy, concluded that
the charges against the Federal Council could only be considered
hearsay, and that there exist there existed a high correlation
between the economic health of the broadcasting industry and their
willingness to sell time to evangelicals. When local stations or
networks needed money, they sold time to evangelicals. Lowell
Saunders, The National Religious Broadcasters and the Availability
of Commercial Radio Time (1968) (unpublished Ph.D. Dissertation
University of Illinois).

<lb/>
While there may have been no overt conspiratorial activities to
exclude evangelicals, there can be no question that the Federal
Council preferred to have its own members represented on the network
airwaves rather than nonmember churches. Furthermore, it is clear
that many liberal church leaders were openly hostile toward the
evangelical broadcasters as is evidenced in the editorial policy of
<hi rend="italic">The Christian Century,</hi> long the most prominent independent
publication of liberal Protestantism. When Mutual announced its
decision to restrict access, <hi rend="italic">The Christian Century</hi> published an
article bitterly complaining that they had not gone far enough:

<lb/>
The network religious radio program racket, capitalized by
independent super-fundamentalist revivalists, will not be eliminated
nationally until Mutual goes the whole way and bans paid religious
programs altogether, as the other networks have done. Charles W.
Crowe, <hi rend="italic">Religion on the Air,</hi> THE CHRISTIAN CENTURY 973-74
(1944).
</p></note>
<note id="n3.2.32"><seg type="note-symbol">[32] </seg> <p>Ralph M. Jennings, Policies and Practices in Selected
National Religious Bodies as Related to Broadcasting in the Public
Interest, 1920-1950, 317 (1968) (unpublished Ph.D. dissertation, New
York University).</p></note>
<note id="n3.2.33"><seg type="note-symbol">[33]</seg> <p> JAMES DEFOREST MURCH, ADVENTURES FOR CHRIST IN CHANGING
TIMES. 173 (1973).</p></note>
<note id="n3.2.34"><seg type="note-symbol">[34]</seg> <p> JEFFREY K. HADDEN &amp; AANSON SHUPE. TELEVANGELISM: POWER
AND POLITICS ON GOD'S FRONTIER. 48 (1988). Personal interview, May
17, 1991. I did not sense that the former commissioner meant this
literally but, rather, intended to emphasize the fact that religious
broadcasters are sophisticated lobbyists.</p></note>
<note id="n3.2.35"><seg type="note-symbol">[35]</seg> <p> A few radio broadcasters, like Charles E. Fuller and Walter
E. Maier, gained network access and, thus, large national audiences.
But on the whole, evangelicals found themselves struggling for
access in local markets. The combination of a competitive free
market and an unsympathetic Federal Radio Commission made it
difficult for them to own radio stations. The policies of NBC and
CBS offered access only through sustaining-time, and the cozy
relationships the networks formed with the Federal Council of
Churches alliance substantially blocked access to outlets for
reaching a national audience.</p></note>
<note id="n3.2.36"><seg type="note-symbol">[36]</seg> <p> <hi rend="italic">Ibid.</hi></p></note>
</div4>
</div3>

<div3 type="subsection" id="d16">


<div4 type="subsection" n="3.3" id="d17">
<head><hi rend="italic">C. Stage Three: Free Market Access (1956-1977)</hi>
</head>

<p>From the Radio Act of 1927, it has always been understood that an
important criterion for retaining a broadcasting license is
"public service" broadcasting. Just how much public
service time is necessary has never been explicitly defined, but it
has always been clear that religious programming constitutes public
service. In 1960, the Federal Communications Commission (FCC) ruled
that there was no intrinsic relationship between sustaining-time and
public service. The implications of this ruling were monumental, for
both religious broadcasters and local stations. Under the ruling,
local stations could sell airtime for religious programs and still
get FCC "public interest credit." Under the ruling,
evangelical broadcasters found cause to renew their commitment to
buying religious airtime. Their faith was buoyed. Market forces
explain the rest of the story. The ensuing competition between
religious broadcasters for religious airtime became fierce. Fierce
competition greatly</p>
<pb n="405"/>
<p>enhanced the value of the air-time, which fact, in its turn,
prompted many local stations, which had previously abstained from
selling air-time to religious broadcasters, to cash in on the new
demand.
<ref target="n3.3.37">[37]</ref>
</p>
<p>In the course of the next two decades, the landscape of religious
broadcasting was transformed from the rule of sustaining-time to the
dominance of free market access. By 1977, ninety-two percent of all
religious broadcasting in the U.S. was paid-time programming
<ref target="n3.3.38">[38]</ref>
the overwhelming majority of which was being purchased by
evangelicals.
<ref target="n3.3.39">[39]</ref>
</p>
<p>The 1960 ruling of the FCC was a watershed in the long struggle
of evangelicals to gain access to the airways. I have identified
1956 rather than 1960 as the beginning of this free market stage of
religious broadcasting, because that was the year that James
DeForest Murch became the executive director of the National
Religious Broadcasters. Murch took several important initiatives
that quickly made NRB a big player in the communications business.
The most important step was to take the annual meetings of the NRB
to Washington, D.C. In his autobiography, Murch explained his
reasoning:</p>
<q>I felt that our position would be immensely strengthened
if we could take our national convention to the Nation's
Capital. This was the seat of the Federal Communications
Commission and the lawmakers who could assure our constitutional
rights to freedom of religion and freedom of speech on the
airwaves. It was also the seat of the industry's National
Association of Broadcasters and the leading trade journal of the
industry, <hi rend="italic">Broadcasting</hi> Magazine.
<ref target="n3.3.40">[40]</ref>
</q>
<p>One of Murch's early and most important moves was to call on Sol
Taishoff, editor and publisher of <hi rend="italic">Broadcasting.</hi> Murch persuaded
Taishoff that evangelicals had a legitimate complaint and created in
Taishoff a champion of NRB's campaign to purchase airtime. Murch and
other NRB leaders also found their way to the offices of the FCC and
pleaded their case for
<pb n="406"/>
fair treatment.</p>
<p>Soon enough, evangelical broadcasters moved beyond gaining mere
parity with religious broadcasters of the "mainline"
religious traditions. Eventually, evangelical broadcasters acquired
absolute dominance of the religious airwaves, a dominance, which
they have maintained until the present. Just how have they
maintained this absolute dominance? NRB continues to hold its
influential annual meetings in Washington, D.C., meetings which
perennially feature an appearance by the President of the United
States and which attract the faithful attendance of the
Commissioners of the FCC. One former FCC Commissioner recently
commented that the religious broadcasters "have a lobbying
capability that makes the National Rifle Association seem like a
bunch of rank amateurs."
<ref target="n3.3.41">[41]</ref>
</p>
<p>Liberal Protestants and Catholics have attempted to check the
dominance of evangelical broadcasters along two lines.
<ref target="n3.3.42">[42]</ref>
First, liberal Protestants and Catholics have argued that a license
to broadcast is a public trust, that those who hold this trust are
obliged to offer sustaining-time for religious programming, and,
further, that mainline religious traditions ought to be the
recipients of such gratis air-time. Second, liberal Protestants and
Catholics have assailed the worthiness not only of evangelical
broadcasters, but also of television as a medium. The argument runs
roughly like this: televangelists are scoundrels using a medium that
is inherently corrupting.
<ref target="n3.3.43">[43]</ref>
In short, liberal Protestants and Catholics find difficulty in
arguing for entitlement to gratuitous access to a medium that they
barely trust. But this ambivalence towards the broadcast media is
one they have lived with for the better part of the century.</p>
<p>The growth of syndicated religious broadcasting occurred during
the 1970s as individual televangelists purchased airtime
station-by-station. During the 1980s the marketplace of syndicated
religious broadcasters became saturated. This led to increased
competition that drove the cost of air-time beyond the</p>
<pb n="407"/>
<p>means of the broadcasters to pay, i.e., beyond their capability
to raise money from the small proportion of the viewers who were
willing to send in a donation. One theory advanced regarding the
underlying conditions precipitating the scandals was that the market
had become saturated and some broadcasters were covertly seeking
reduced competition.
<ref target="n3.3.44">[44]</ref>
</p>
</div4>

<div4 type="notes" id="d18">
<head>Footnotes</head>
<note id="n3.3.37"><seg type="note-symbol">[37]</seg> <p> HADDEN &amp; SHUPE, <hi rend="italic">supra</hi> note 34, at 51.
</p></note>
<note id="n3.3.38"><seg type="note-symbol">[38]</seg> <p> <hi rend="italic">Report by the Communications Committee of the U.S. Catholic
Conference,</hi> in PETER G. HORSFIELD, RELIGIOUS TELEVISION: THE
AMERICAN EXPERIENCE 89 (1984).</p></note>
<note id="n3.3.39"><seg type="note-symbol">[39]</seg> <p>
The Networks produced their sustaining-time religious
programs for more than a decade, but with the lure of big bucks from
the syndicated televangelists, local affiliates elected not to run
the network productions.</p></note>
<note id="n3.3.40"><seg type="note-symbol">[40] </seg> <p>MURCH, <hi rend="italic">supra</hi> note 33, at 179.</p></note>
<note id="n3.3.41"><seg type="note-symbol">[41]</seg> <p> Personal interview, May 17, 1991. I did not sense the former
commissioner meant this literally, but, rather, intended to emphasize the fact
that religious broadcasters are sophisticated lobbyists.</p></note>
<note id="n3.3.42"><seg type="note-symbol">[42]</seg> <p> The office of the Assistant General Secretary for
Communications of the Nation Council of Churches has been the focal
point of the counterattack.</p></note>
<note id="n3.3.43"><seg type="note-symbol">[43] </seg> <p>William F. Fore, until recently the assistant general
secretary for communications of the National Council of Churches, is
the most important spokesperson for this argument. For an
introduction to this perspective, see WILLIAM F. FORE. TELEVISION
AND RELIGION. (1987).</p></note>
<note id="n3.3.44"><seg type="note-symbol">[44]</seg> <p> This thesis can be pursued in many possible directions. For
example, when Marvin Gorman, an Assemblies of God minister, began to
develop a significant television ministry in Louisiana, Jimmy
Swaggart brought charges of sexual misconduct before the Assemblies
of God. Gorman was defrocked and subsequently lost his New Orleans
church and television ministry. Swaggart subsequently threatened to
bring Jim Bakker's sexual improprieties before the Assembly of God.
When this became public knowledge, Swaggart denied that he had his
eye on the PTL Network. Jerry Falwell similarly denied that his
motivation for taking over PTL had anything to do with acquiring a
network for his own broadcasting ambitions. The truth of the
"economic motivation" thesis will probably never be
proven. For some of the best investigative research on this thesis
see Charles E. Shepard. Forgiven (1989); LARRY MARTZ, MINISTRY
OF GREED. (1988).</p></note>
</div4>
</div3>

<div3 type="subsection" id="d19">


<div4 type="subsection" n="3.4" id="d20">
<head><hi rend="italic">D. Stage Four: Techno-legal Regulation (1977-present)</hi>
</head>

<p>As important as the televangelism scandals seemed at the time,
they were relatively unimportant in terms of the overall regulatory
picture. As noted at the beginning of this inquiry, the scandals did
not escape the attention of various government regulatory agencies,
but there was no zealous crusade to legislate or find existing
regulatory structures that could be used to put the pinch on
broadcasters. This was true for at least three reasons.</p>
<p>First, religious broadcasters succeeded in creating the
impression that they had taken bold initiatives toward
self-regulation. Several months before the PTL scandal broke, NRB
approved in principle a plan to create an Ethics and Financial
Integrity Commission (EFICOM). In the wake of the PTL scandal, NRB
contracted with the Evangelical Council for Financial Accountability
(ECFA) to independently manage EFICOM. In the end, NRB rhetoric was
stronger than self-regulatory reality.
<ref target="n3.4.45">[45]</ref>
Impressions, nonetheless, counted for much.</p>
<p>Second, legislators who might have been inclined to craft
legislation designed to reign in religious broadcasters quickly
became aware of the difficulty of doing so without tackling much
broader issues of broadcast regulation. The 1970s and 1980s
witnessed ever-broadening acceptance of what could</p>
<pb n="408"/>
<p>appear in print, cinema, and on the airwaves under the "free
speech" protection of the First Amendment. To regulate even the
most outrageous televangelists would necessarily pose the question
of the limits of First Amendment protection for the bizarre antics
of the likes of Howard Stern and Morton Downey Jr. If the First
Amendment doesn't protect broadcasters like Stern, then perhaps
censorship of "Geraldo" and "Donahue" would be
around the corner. Even the thought of a slippery slope towards
greater regulation of commercial broadcasting serves as a powerful
antidote against proposals to regulate radio and television
preachers.</p>
<p>The third, and perhaps most important factor mitigating against
the rush to regulate the televangelists, was the fact that the
marketplace itself responded swiftly and effectively. Upon learning
of the televangelism scandals of 1987-88, tens of thousands of
formerly loyal viewers closed their checkbooks with devastating
consequences. Virtually every television ministry in America was
negatively impacted by the scandals. Six years after the scandals
first broke; the religious broadcasting industry remains shrouded
with public doubt as to its integrity. Of course, formerly loyal
viewers had time to sort things out. And, on the whole,
non-scandalized ministries eventually recovered both viewers and
revenues.</p>
<p>In sharp contrast, scandalized ministries suffered serious and
ostensibly permanent losses. Jim and Tammy Faye Bakker were forced
to leave the air when the PTL scandal broke. Their network went
bankrupt within a week, heroic fund-raising efforts of Jerry Falwell
notwithstanding. The scandalized ministries of Jimmy Swaggart, Oral
Roberts and Robert Tilton have all paid a heavy price as well. Even
though all three remain on the air, each has been reduced to but a
shadow of bygone glory. And there is no credible evidence to suggest
that any of them will be able to rebuild to the point where they
approach past financial and audience achievements.</p>
<p>The marketplace, then, has constituted a key force in both formal
and informal regulation of religious broadcasters. Ultimately, a
free press, not government regulatory intervention, brought the
crimes and moral misdeeds of these televangelists to the attention
of the public. The viewing public, in turn, played an important
regulatory role by switching channels and closing their checkbooks.
It may not be a perfect regulatory system, but it worked efficiently
throughout the late 1980s.</p>
<p>As I read the history of religious broadcast regulation, the</p>
<pb n="409"/>
<p>fourth stage had been in progress fully a decade, when the
scandals of the late 1980s broke. A defining feature of the fourth
stage has been the rapid development of expensive, highly
sophisticated delivery technology. Another defining feature of the
fourth stage has been the expanding role litigation has come to play
in the affairs of religious broadcasters. This latter feature is an
inevitable consequence of rapid, technologically driven growth and
of the expanding role litigation has played generally in promoting
individual and collective advancement.</p>


<div5 type="notes" id="d21">
<head>Footnotes</head>
<note id="n3.4.45"><seg type="note-symbol">[45]</seg> <p> <hi rend="italic">See NRB Moves Slowly to Enforce Ethics Code,</hi>
CHRISTIANITY TODAY. March 9, 1992, 59.</p></note>
</div5>


<div5 type="subsection" n="3.4.1" id="d22">
<head>
<hi rend="italic">1. Technology</hi>
</head>

<p>In a strict sense, technology does not regulate religious
broadcasting. But technology is a powerful factor in defining the
parameters wherein broadcasting operates. The growth of
communication technologies permitted rapid expansion of syndicated
programming, satellite transmission, personalized direct mail and
telemarketing, among other things. These innovations in
communications technology were the driving force behind the
phenomenal growth of televangelism during the 1970s and 1980s.
Television ministries became big precisely because all of these
technologies made rapid growth of parachurch organizations
possible.</p>
<p>The technological advances that spawned dozens of syndicated
religious television programs seems now to be working toward the
concentration of economic power in religious broadcasting. This
process can be dated to April 29, 1977, when the Christian
Broadcasting Network transmitted its first satellite broadcast. In
rapid succession, Trinity Broadcasting Network was founded in
southern California, followed by the PTL Network in North
Carolina. All three networks had state-of-the-art technology
poised to deliver religious programming via cable even before the
wiring of the nation for cable began in earnest. That cabling
process was substantially achieved in the 1980s and continues
towards saturation in the 1990s.</p>
<p>While the cabling of the nation has resulted in a significant
loss of market share for the three major television networks, the
religious networks have been among the beneficiaries of this
redistribution of viewers. The costs for broadcasting on major
networks have always been prohibitive for religious telecasters.
This option will become even more prohibitive in the future. Loss
of market share by major networks has not driven down the cost of
air-time, but merely reduced the trajec-
<pb n="410"/>
tory of soaring costs. Similarly, local network-affiliated
stations will continue to command top dollar for the purchase of
airtime.</p>
<p>This portends a decline in syndicated religious
broadcasting on local network stations. Religious broadcasters
simply will not be able to raise adequate revenues to pay the high
cost of being on the several hundred local network stations. Thus,
it is increasingly clear that the future of religious broadcasting
is in satellite delivery via cable television. The only
economically viable long-term alternative for syndicated
broadcasters is to turn to religious networks and a growing number
of low power religious stations. Those who have satellite delivery
capability, and have established an extensive network of cable
systems, to which they can deliver their programs, are in a
position to dominate the future market.</p>
<p>At the present time there are four religious networks with
significant cable access: Christian Broadcasting Network (CBN),
Trinity Broadcasting Network (TBN), Vision Interfaith Satellite
Network/American Christian Television System (VISN/ACTS), and
Eternal Word Network (EWN). Pat Robertson's CBN now operates under
the umbrella of the Family Channel which ranks among the largest
cable systems in the nation. In late 1991 the Family Channel
reached 92 percent of all cable households and 59 percent of all
households in America.
<ref target="n3.3.1.46">[46]</ref>
</p>
<p>Of the three networks devoted exclusively to religious
programming, TBN is the most viable. Founder and owner Paul Crouch
has aggressively bought up small powered television stations in
addition to expanding cable system coverage. While Crouch is
Pentecostal, and this is emphasized in programming, he is well
positioned to sell airtime to non-Pentecostal Evangelicals.</p>
<p>VISN is a collaborative effort of 28 main line Protestant,
Jewish, Roman Catholic and Eastern Orthodox groups. ACTS was
founded by the Radio and Television Commission of the Southern
Baptist Church. Neither network allows on-air solici-
<pb n="411"/>
tation of funds. Both organizations have experienced financial
difficulties and in 1992 began sharing a single cable channel. EWN
was founded by Sister Angelica, a Roman Catholic nun from Alabama.
While both VISN/ACTS and EWN currently have significant cable
outlets across the nation, these operations do not appear to have
adequate capitalization or management resources to be competitive
in the long run competition for cable outlets. Even now, they are
dependent on free access to cable systems. This gratuitous
relationship with cable owners is unlikely to persist unless
mandated by the Federal Communications Commission, which appears
unlikely. The unknown quotient is the potential of technology to
produce unforeseen and unanticipated options for production of
delivery of television.</p>
</div5>

<div5 type="notes" id="d23">
<head>Footnotes</head>
<note id="n3.3.1.46"><seg type="note-symbol">[46]</seg> <p> The Family Channel broadcasts <hi rend="italic">The 700 Club,</hi> the flagship
telecast of CBN, daily, and offers other related religious programs
plus a substantial outlet for religious programming on Sunday. While
Robertson found "family oriented programming" to be more
profitable than a full diet of religious programming, the program
schedule of the Family Channel is potentially elastic and could
return to more religious broadcasting should that become profitable.</p></note>
</div5>

<div5 type="subsection" n="3.4.2" id="d24">
<head>
<hi rend="italic">2. Litigation</hi>
</head>
<p>The second half of the Twentieth Century has experienced a
significant growth in the social welfare state. Social movements
and lobbying have identified ever expanding domains where the
benevolent social welfare state "ought" to protect or
serve its citizens. Litigation has increasingly become the
instrument whereby individuals and organizations press their
claims for access to resources. Religious organizations generally,
and religious broadcasters in particular, have not escaped this
trend. Over the past decade-and-a-half, major ministries have
devoted increasing resources to legal matters. Some of the
increased legal work reflects a need among religious broadcasters
for legal counsel in contractual matters as well as in matters
respecting regulatory compliance. But religious broadcasters have
been increasingly involved in litigation, both as defendants and
as plaintiffs. Legal proceedings involving religious broadcasters
have occurred on a wide range of issues. I can here offer only
illustrations.</p>
<p>One of the major struggles religious broadcasters have faced is
the issue of their tax-exempt status. In 1983 the State Board of
Equalization of California revoked the tax-exempt status of Robert
Schuller's Crystal Cathedral in response to the use of the
cathedral for admission charging events. The Board of Equalization
subsequently agreed to a compromise in which taxes would be paid
on part of the Crystal Cathedral's "facilities used for such
non-exempt commercial purposes as concerts</p>
<pb n="412"/>
<p>and community group meetings."
<ref target="n3.4.2.47">[47]</ref>
A ministry spokesperson characterized the taxation issue as
"the beginning of a new kind of harassment [of] religious
institutions."
<ref target="n3.4.2.48">[48]</ref>
</p>
<p>Religious broadcasters as defendants: California was also the
scene of <hi rend="italic">Swaggart v. Board of Equalization</hi>
<ref target="n3.4.2.49">[49]</ref>
which has not received great attention, but which nonetheless has
had tax exemption implications for religious broadcasters
specifically and for religious institutions more generally. This
case involved the authority of the state of California to collect
taxes on various items, including religious records, tapes, and
books sold by the Swaggart ministry to Californians. The Supreme
Court upheld a decision by the California appeals court permitting
the state to tax items sold by the Swaggart ministry. The decision
leaves open the question of whether any religious organization has
a constitutional right to tax exemption.</p>
<p>Religion-based tax exemption challenges have also been brought
against the ministries of television preachers by individuals. In
Virginia, two Lynchburg residents appealed a Circuit Court ruling
granting Jerry Falwell's Liberty University the right to issue $61
million in tax-free government bonds on the grounds that this
violated the Separation Clause.
<ref target="n3.4.2.50">[50]</ref>
Ultimately, the Virginia Supreme Court blocked the issuance of the
tax-free bonds. Falwell, electing not to appeal to the Supreme
Court, turned to Kemper Securities for assistance with a private
bond sale. Kemper, finding no market interest in the bonds,
withdrew from the underwriting agreement. Falwell, in turn, sued
Kemper for default.
<ref target="n3.4.2.51">[51]</ref>
The parties agreed to submit the dispute to arbitration.
Arbitrators subsequently found the case &quot;without merit.&quot;
<ref target="n3.4.2.52">[52]</ref>
</p>
<p>Religious broadcasters as plaintiffs: Jerry Falwell sued
<hi rend="italic">Hustler</hi> magazine for "intentional infliction of emotional
distress" resulting from a satirical parody.
<ref target="n3.4.2.53">[53]</ref>
In anticipation of his bid for the Republican nomination for the
presidency in 1988,</p>
<pb n="413"/>
<p>Pat Robertson sued former California Congressman Paul
"Pete" McCloskey and Indiana Congressman Andrew Jacobs
for making statements about his Korean War military record that
were alleged to be "wanton and reckless."
<ref target="n3.4.2.54">[54]</ref>
Neither Falwell nor Robertson's suits were ultimately successful,
but they illustrate a perceived need to protect the good name and
reputation of religious broadcasters. Interestingly, both Falwell
and Robertson publicly interpreted the litigation outcome as
vindicating their positions.</p>
<p>Apart from the need to litigate, legal departments have become
a part of virtually every television ministry for other reasons.
They seek to develop endowments and trust funds for long term
support of their ministries. In addition to developing trusts and
endowments, the legal departments of television ministries, more
often than other nonprofit organizations, face challenges to wills
by heirs of those who have made significant bequests.</p>
<p>More recently, radio and television ministries have found
themselves embroiled in controversy and litigation with former
employees. In the wake of the PTL scandals, CBN placed <hi rend="italic">The 700
Club</hi> co-host Danuta Soderman on "temporary leave of
absence" after the publication of her autobiography that
included a discussion of a love affair outside of marriage. CBN,
sensing that this could be grist for media that was on a feeding
frenzy with the PTL scandal, concluded that they could not risk
having Soderman, who had been called the, "Barbara Walters of
Christian television," on the air. Ms. Soderman quietly
disappeared from the scene.
<ref target="n3.4.2.55">[55]</ref>
</p>
<p>Religious broadcasters also need good legal counsel to keep
abreast of developments in constitutional law affect free
exercise. Take for example, <hi rend="italic">Employment Division v. Smith</hi>
<ref target="n3.4.2.56">[56]</ref>
a Supreme Court case potentially with significant implications for
the regulation of religious broadcasting. If <hi rend="italic">Smith</hi> effectively
establishes the precedent that religious organizations are
entitled to no substantive protection under the Free Exercise
Clause of the First Amendment, then religious broadcasters--along
with other religious organizations--stand to be entangled in a
much broader web of government regulation.</p>
<pb n="414"/>
<p>Or, take the recent passage of the Religious Freedom
Restoration Act
<ref target="n3.4.2.57">[57]</ref>
(RFRA),
an act intended to lessen, if not altogether to defeat, the impact
of <hi rend="italic">Smith.</hi> Will RFRA substantially alter the fact that religious
broadcasters have become deeply and increasingly involved in all
kinds of litigation? Probably not. But, as a general proposition,
we can postulate that religious broadcasters can expect to
continue to spend precious resources on legal matters. It follows
that, whereas larger ministries can more easily allocate resources
to deal with legal costs, small ministries can be easily
overwhelmed by such costs.</p>
<p>In the years since the PTL scandal, other religious broadcast
employees have declined passively to accept what they perceive to
be mistreatment by their employers. James Dobson's radio program
<hi rend="italic">Focus on the Family</hi> is broadcast daily on 1,350 outlets, second
only to Paul Harvey. When co-host Gil Moegerle's marriage ended in
divorce in 1987, Dobson reassigned Moegerle to the film
department. Some months later, Moegerle married an employee of the
ministry. Subsequently, both resigned claiming they were forced
out. Moegerle sued claiming, among other things, "invasion of
privacy, interference with business activities, and wrongful
termination."
<ref target="n3.4.2.58">[58]</ref>
More recently, Bob Larson Ministries, which broadcasts a radio and
television talk-show, has been a hotbed of employee grievances,
including wrongful dismissal, sexual harassment, nonpayment of
accrued overtime, and the like.
<ref target="n3.4.2.59">[59]</ref>
The day of religious broadcast
employees passively accepting managerial decisions that affect
their lives appears now to be a thing of the past.</p>
<p> This discussion of the impact of technology and the increasing
propensity for problems to be resolved by litigation draws attention
to the fact that the religious broadcasting industry no longer lives
in a world apart. They have entered the mainstream of society. They
have utilized technology to great advantage, even as technology has
shaped the character of their ministry. An increasingly litigious
society is similarly impacting religious broadcasting in ways that
are only now beginning to be understood.</p>
</div5>

<div5 type="notes" id="d25">
<head>Footnotes</head>

<note id="n3.4.2.47"><seg type="note-symbol">[47]</seg> <p> <hi rend="italic">Crystal Cathedral to Pay Back Taxes on Concert Receipts,</hi>
NEW YORK TIMES. August 31, 1983. A18.</p></note>

<note id="n3.4.2.48"><seg type="note-symbol">[48] </seg> <p><hi rend="italic">Ibid.</hi></p></note>

<note id="n3.4.2.49"><seg type="note-symbol">[49]</seg> <p> 493 U.S. 378 (1990).</p></note>

<note id="n3.4.2.50"><seg type="note-symbol">[50]</seg> <p> U.S. CONST., amend.</p></note>

<note id="n3.4.2.51"><seg type="note-symbol">[51]</seg> <p> Liberty University v. Kemper Securities Group, Civil
Action No. 90-0075-L (W.D. Va.).</p></note>

<note id="n3.4.2.52"><seg type="note-symbol">[52] </seg> <p>Liberty University v. Kemper Securities Group, AAA
Arbitration No. 11136-00194-91.</p></note>

<note id="n3.4.2.53"><seg type="note-symbol">[53]</seg> <p> Hustler Magazine v. Falwell, 485 U.S. 46 (1988).</p></note>

<note id="n3.4.2.54"><seg type="note-symbol">[54]</seg> <p> Charles R. Babcock &amp; T.R. Reid, <hi rend="italic">Robertson's Libel
Suit Dismissed,</hi> THE WASHINGTON POST. March 8, 1988, A6.</p></note>

<note id="n3.4.2.55"><seg type="note-symbol">[55]</seg> <p> <hi rend="italic">CBN Co-Host Is Reassigned,</hi> THE DAILY
PROGRESS. June 26, 1987.</p></note>

<note id="n3.4.2.56"><seg type="note-symbol">[56]</seg> <p> Employment Div. V. Smith, 494 U.S. 872 (1990).</p></note>

<note id="n3.4.2.57"><seg type="note-symbol">[57] </seg> <p>Religious Freedom Restoration Act of 1993, Pub. L. NO.
103-141, 107 Stat. 1488 (1993).</p></note>

<note id="n3.4.2.58"><seg type="note-symbol">[58]</seg> <p> NATIONAL AND INTERNATIONAL RELIGION REPORT. No. 3.
January 16, 1989, at 6.</p></note>

<note id="n3.4.2.59"><seg type="note-symbol">[59]</seg> <p> Timothy C. Morgan, <hi rend="italic">Personnel Woes Persist at Larson
Ministries,</hi> CHRISTIANITY TODAY. 62 (1993).</p></note>
</div5>
</div4>
</div3>
</div2>

<pb n="415"/>

<div2 type="section" n="4" id="d26">
<head>
IV. Conclusions: Toward Accountability in Televangelism
</head>
<p>We have come a long way since a leading religious broadcaster
sent signals of varying strength in directions of her own choosing,
and then sassed the Secretary of Commerce telling him, in effect,
that where she sent her broadcast signals was a matter of concern
only between her and the Almighty. That Aimee Semple McPherson did
this, much less that she got away with it, seems today almost
incomprehensible. Even Jerry Falwell's 1987 confession, on behalf of
religious broadcasters, of "a little sense of arrogance"
in believing that they were answerable only to God, seems archaic.</p>
<p>From the very beginning, it was inevitable that broadcasting and
its related technologies would have to be regulated. What may be
amazing is that we have not had much more regulation. The full
implications of technological and legal developments on religious
broadcasting cannot be fully understood at this point. It is
possible, however, to offer at least limited speculation about how
technology and legal process will affect the future of religious
broadcasting.</p>
<p>First, the informal mechanisms of regulation discussed in this
paper will continue to impact religious broadcasting. Networks,
audiences, the press, and market competition will continue to play a
significant role in shaping religious broadcasting.</p>
<p>Second, technology is a double-edged sword. On the one hand, the
spread of technology tends to lower per unit cost to religious
broadcasters and, thus, invites more players to enter the
competition. The cost of a television studio and equipment once made
participation in competition prohibitive. Today, local public access
channels provide the opportunity for virtually everyone with an
interest to try their hand at producing television programming.
Nearly two decades ago the National Religious Broadcasters were
offering regional workshops to would-be religious broadcasters. The
novice could not then, and still cannot compete head on with
broadcasters owning state of the art equipment. But skillful use of
video equipment can still put one in business. In the past, the best
of the local religious broadcasters were soon entering multiple
markets, syndicating, and becoming contenders for national markets.
Rising costs are rapidly closing off this option.</p>
<p>At the same time that technology was making it possible
<pb n="416"/>
for more players to get in the game, the expansion of satillite
transmission and cable redirected delivery into the hands of a few
who controlled access to satellites and cables. The result has
diminished the role of syndicated programming except for those that
have the resources to contract with networks. This trend is almost
certain to continue. Programming that cannot deliver large markets,
e.g. religious broadcasting, will become increasingly hard to
sustain by syndicated selling to individual stations. While
individual broadcasters will be able to buy time on satellite
networks, their opportunities for developing large audiences will be
significantly restricted.</p>
<p>In short, while technological innovations of the 1970s and 1980s
made it possible for more broadcasters to syndicate, the technology
of the 1990s is shifting delivery to cable via satellite. This
development concentrates power in the hands of those who control the
delivery technology. They will reserve prime viewing time for their
own programming and cut hard bargains with independent newcomers.</p>
<p>Third, the second half of the Twentieth Century has seen an
enormous expansion in the role of litigation in resolving competing
claims for resources and demands for justice. Federal and state
government agencies play an increasing role in the pursuit of
claims, acting as enforcers of legislatively mandated regulations,
interpreters of regulations, and investigators of claims brought by
individuals. Even though most religious broadcasters are organized
as tax-exempt organizations and, as such, are not subject to many
state and federal rules that govern corporations, litigation and the
need to comply with government regulations still impact religious
broadcasters in many ways. As the religion-based tax exemption cases
suggest, such regulations will continue to be a serious issue.</p>
<p>Finally, the future shape of broadcasting will be determined in
part, at least, by technological developments that are yet to be
discovered or invented. Since we don't know what these developments
may be, we cannot anticipate their impact. But on the basis of
everything we know about the first nine decades of technological
development in broadcasting, we can anticipate that religious
broadcasting is unlikely to be affected in ways very different from
commercial broadcasting. Although both experienced a long history of
only minimal regulation, that era seems likely to be coming to a
close.</p>
</div2>
</div1>
</body>
</text>
</TEI.2>
