<?xml version="1.0"?>

<?dlps id="HalWood"?>
<?dlps page-images="none" figure-images="no"?>
<?dlps transcription="other"?>

<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/tei-p4/tei2.dtd" [
<!ENTITY % POSTKB "INCLUDE">
<!ENTITY % TEI.extensions.ent SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.ent">
<!ENTITY % TEI.extensions.dtd SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.dtd">
<!ENTITY % ISOnum SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/charent/iso-num.ent"> %ISOnum;
<!ENTITY % ISOlat1 SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/charent/iso-lat1.ent"> %ISOlat1;
<!ENTITY % ISOpub SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/charent/iso-pub.ent"> %ISOpub;

]>
<TEI.2 id="HalWood">
<teiHeader type="migrated" creator="Etext">
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title type="main">Woodbine Cottage</title>
<title type="sort">woodbine cottage</title>
<author>Hale, Sarah Josepha</author>
<respStmt>
<resp>Creation of machine-readable version:</resp>
<name>Judy Boss</name>
<resp>Creation of digital images:</resp>
<name/>
<resp>Conversion to TEI.2-conformant markup:</resp>
<name>University of Virginia Library Electronic Text Center.</name>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt>
<extent>ca. <num type="kilobytes">21</num> kilobytes</extent>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>University of Virginia Library</publisher>
<pubPlace>Charlottesville, Virginia</pubPlace>
<idno type="ETC">HalWood</idno>
<date value="1998">1998</date>
<availability status="public">
<p n="copyright">Copyright &copy; 1998 by the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia</p>
<p n="access">Publicly accessible</p>
</availability>
<idno type="uva-pid">uva-lib:476023</idno>
</publicationStmt>
<seriesStmt>
<title>University of Virginia Library, Text collection</title>
<idno type="uva-set">UVA-LIB-Text</idno>
</seriesStmt>
<notesStmt>
<note>
<p>We were unable to check this electronic version against its print source.</p>
</note>
</notesStmt>
<sourceDesc>
<biblFull>
<titleStmt>
<title type="main">Woodbine Cottage</title>
<title level="j">The Christian Keepsake, and Missionary Annual, for MDCCCXLIX</title>
<title type="sort">woodbine cottage</title>
<author>Sarah Josepha Hale</author>
</titleStmt>
<extent>pp. 30-42</extent>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>Brower, Hayes &amp; Co.</publisher>
<pubPlace>Philadelphia</pubPlace>
<date value="1849">1849</date>
<idno type="callNo">Print copy consulted:</idno>
</publicationStmt>
</biblFull>
</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc>
<encodingDesc>
<projectDesc>
<p>Prepared for the University of Virginia Library Electronic Text Center.</p>
</projectDesc>
<editorialDecl>
<p>All unambiguous end-of-line hyphens have been removed, and the trailing part of a word has been joined to the preceding line.</p>
<p>Some keywords in the header are a local Electronic Text Center scheme to aid in establishing analytical groupings.</p>
</editorialDecl>
</encodingDesc>
<profileDesc>
<creation>
<date value="1849">1849</date>
</creation>
<langUsage>
<language id="eng" usage="main">English</language>
</langUsage>
<textClass>
<keywords>
<term>fiction</term>
<term>prose</term>
<term>feminine</term>
<term>Women Writers</term>
</keywords>
</textClass>
</profileDesc>
<revisionDesc>
<change>
<date value="1998-06">June 1998</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>corrector</resp>
<name>Anne Stinehart, Electronic Text Center</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Added TEI header and tags. Closed up end-of-line hyphenation.</item>
</change>
<change>
<date value="2005-07">July 2005</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>Corrector</resp>
<name>John Ivor Carlson</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Converted SGML to XML. Fixed tagging.</item>
</change>
<change>
<date value="2007-09">September 2007</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>Migration</resp>
<name>Ethan Gruber, University of Virginia Library</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Converted XML markup from TEI Lite to uva-dl-tei (TEI P4 with local customizations).</item>
</change>
<change>
<date value="2008-01">January 2008</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>Migration</resp>
<name>Greg Murray, University of Virginia Library</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Programmatically updated TEI header markup (but not header content) for minimal compliance with current QA requirements.</item>
</change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>


<text id="d1">

<body id="d2">



<div1 type="story" id="d3"> <pb n="30"/>
<head>
WOODBINE COTTAGE.<lb/>
BY MRS. SARAH J. HALE.
</head>

<epigraph>
<q>"Love, and love only, is the loan for love." &mdash; <hi rend="italic">Young</hi>.</q>
</epigraph>

<p>
     "PRAY, can you tell me who owns yonder pretty
cottage?  I am sure it must have a history," said Mrs.
Conant to her landlady.
</p><p>"Ah, yes &mdash; is it not a love of a place, with its pillars
and porticoes all around?" said Mrs. Bell, advancing
towards the window.  "It is called a cottage orn&eacute;, you
know, and belongs to Mr. &mdash;"
</p><p>"No, no!  I don't mean that flaunting pagoda, which
is just such a vulgar, expensive-looking thing as any
body who has money may buy or build," said Mrs.
Conant.  "I mean that dear little cot on the hill-side
there, nestled in among the green vines and shrubbery
and peeping forth from among the leaves and flowers
like a timid bride from beneath her veil.  Who lives
there?"
   <pb n="31"/>
</p><p>"O! that is Woodbine Cottage, you know," replied
Mrs. Bell; "and the Waltons live there, you know."
</p><p>"Yes, I know it now you have told me," said Mrs.
Conant, smiling at the repetition of <hi rend="italic">you know</hi>, which
better educated people than Mrs. Bell are sometimes
in the habit of using.
</p><p>"It is a charming place!" exclaimed Emily Conant;
"and good old Izaak himself, with his refined taste
for the beauties of nature, never described a more delightful spot.
I hope Mr. Walton loves fishing."
</p><p>"Mrs. Walton is a widow," said Mrs. Bell; and
she added, compassionately, "her son, poor fellow,
could not be persuaded to hurt a fly, much less to pull
a struggling fish out of the water."
</p><p>"Why, he must be romantic, indeed," said Emily,*
Conant.  "What is he &mdash; a poet?"
</p><p>The landlady shook her head.  "You have never
heard then of Mrs. Walton's idiot son?"
</p><p>Mrs. Conant assured her she had not.
</p><p>"Well, then" &mdash; said Mrs. Bell, in her rambling way
&mdash; "Clara Walton is very beautiful and very bright,
and that makes it more strange poor Henry should be
so ill-shapen and dull.  But then he is a kind, loving,
harmless creature, and his mother and sister think all
the world of him, you know.  Some say it was a judgment
on Mrs. Walton for her pride, when she was so
rich in her first husband's day; but that is over now,
   <pb n="32"/>
and she is poor enough, you know.  But I must say,
that she has borne all sorrows like a Christian, as she
is, you know."
</p><p>"Indeed, I know nothing of Mrs. Walton or her
affairs, except what you have now communicated,"
replied Mrs. Conant.  "I feel an interest in her from
these circumstances; a widow, poor, with an idiot son
clinging to her for the protection which, from such a
relation, it would seem natural he should give, makes a
touching appeal to my feelings."
</p><p>"And she has a lovely daughter," said Emily
Conant.  "I wish, mother, we could make their acquaintance."
</p><p>"That would be easy enough if you were sick or in
distress," said the landlady.  "Mrs. Walton is famous
for her broths and possets; and as for Clara, why, she
thinks nothing of going miles to carry something nice
to the sick, or to watch with the poor, while she would
not spare an afternoon from her work or her books to
visit a neighbor socially!"
</p><p>"O, what a eulogy!" exclaimed Mrs. Conant, turning
to her daughter.  "How glad I am to find that the
moral beauty of the dwellers in that lovely cottage is
in unison with the charms of nature around them!
What a Paradise we might make of this earth if all
were good and kind!"
</p><p>"Clara and her mother are good and kind," chimed
   <pb n="33"/>
in the landlady; "that every body allows; but people
say they are over proud, though certainly, as Mrs.
Walton is not able to go out much &mdash; she has the asthma
terribly at times &mdash; except to church, it is not strange
that Clara stays at home with her, and to take care of
poor Henry.  But then, she never seems to care about
going, and that is strange; and now, as she has managed
to catch the richest match in the state of Vermont,
I suppose she will hold her head higher than ever."
</p><p>"Then I presume Miss Walton is soon to be
married," remarked Emily Conant.
</p><p>"I hope so," replied Mrs. Bell; "for they say her
mother is urging on the match.  But indeed, poor lady,
who can blame her? when Mr. Palmer is so rich and
they have nothing."
</p><p>"But the cottage  " said Mrs. Conant.
</p><p>"O! that is not their own; they live there on
sufferance," replied the other.  "The place is owned by the
Rev. Mr. Forester."
</p><p>"What, Charles Forester?" inquired Emily Conant.
</p><p>"Yes, I believe his name is Charles &mdash; at any rate he
is a southern gentleman, and came here with his invalid
mother, who had been ordered to try our bracing
climate," said the loquacious Mrs. Bell.  "He fitted up
the cottage, which he bought, and ornamented the
grounds, and lived there two years or more, and became
very intimate with the Waltons.  I told you they always
   <pb n="34"/>
visited the sick; so Mrs. Forester had Clara with her
nearly half the time, and Mr. Forester gave her lessons
&mdash; she was a mere child when they came, not more
than fifteen, you know &mdash; so he gave her lessons in
music and drawing, and all sorts of languages; some
say he taught her Hebrew; and when they went away,
they put the Waltons into the cottage to take care
of it."
</p><p>"The Foresters have been absent near three years, I
believe," observed Mrs. Conant.
</p><p>"Thereabouts," said Mrs. Bell.  "But news has
just come that the old lady is dead, and Mr. Forester is
coming back soon.  So I suppose Mrs. Walton will
hurry Clara's marriage; otherwise they would have to
go into cheap lodgings, which would terribly mortify
her, after living so long in such a lovely place &mdash; so
people say."
</p><p>And thus, under the shelter of that convenient oracle,
the sayings of the thoughtless, the idle, or the envious,
did Mrs. Bell virtually bear false witness against her
neighbor &mdash; and yet they both knelt at the same altar,
and took the symbols of their Saviour's dying love from
the same Pastor's hand.  Nay, more than this, Mrs.
Bell, in her own soul, believed Mrs. Walton to be a
pious, humble Christian.  Truly, evil-speaking is the
sin which, in social life, requires our most constant
watchfulness.  Let us pray each morning not to be led
   <pb n="35"/>
into this temptation, but that we may have our hearts
filled with that clarity which suffereth long and is
kind, which believeth no evil, and giveth tongue to no
slanderous report.
</p><p>At the very time when this conversation between
the Conants and Mrs. Bell occurred, a scene was passing
at the cottage, which, could they have known, would
have read them a lesson never to have been forgotten.
</p><p>Mrs. Walton was sitting by her work-table, which
stood not far from an open window that over-looked the
river, called in poetic lore, the "soft-flowing Connecticut;"
(but which here, compressed in its channel, was
deep and rapid) &mdash; and the green hills beyond.  It was
a soft June evening; the sun had disappeared behind
the western mountains, but his beams yet rested on the
heads of the tall cliffs that bordered the river, and
brightened the old evergreens that clothed the broken
hills on the eastern shore.  The flowers, that surrounded
the cottage, were filled with fresh fragrance as the
evening drew on; and the birds, that thronged, unmolested,
in this sanctuary of peace, were pouring forth
their sweetest songs of thankfulness and love.
</p><p>But all these beauties and perfections of nature were
lost on Mrs. Walton.  Her thoughts were busy with
the past, while her heart yearned towards her daughter.
She felt the time had come when the deep lessons,
which errors and sufferings had engraved in her own
   <pb n="36"/>
heart, must be told to Clara.  The sweet girl was leaning
beside the open window.  The pale roses that
drooped over her head not so white as her cheek.  Yet
she shed no tear, breathed no sigh; her eyes were, in
truth, bright, as though she had nerved her soul for
some deep sacrifice of self at the shrine of duty.
</p><p>She had, that day, received the reiterated and urgent
offer of marriage from Mr. Palmer, with a pledge that
if she would become his wife, her mother and brother
should be amply provided for &mdash; should have Woodbine
Cottage, if it could be obtained, or one equally as good,
and a yearly allowance besides of a thousand dollars.
</p><p>"Clara, my darling child, come here to me; I want
to see you smile once more.  You have not smiled of
late.  Come and sit here close beside me," said Mrs.
Walton.
</p><p>Clara obeyed, and seated herself on a cushion at her
mother's feet &mdash; but she did not look up.
</p><p>Her mother took her hand &mdash; it was cold and trem-bling.  "Clara," said Mrs. Walton, impressively, "you
must not accept this offer."
</p><p>"Mother!
</p><p>"No, you must not.  You do not love Mr. Palmer,
and unless you can give him your heart, you must not
become his wife."
</p><p>"But what will you do?  What will become of you
and poor Henry?  You have no longer strength to
   <pb n="37"/>
work &mdash; nay, hear me, dear mother &mdash; we must leave this
cottage immediately.  Mr. Forester will come soon, and
I would not for the world he should fine me here."
She spoke this hurriedly, for there was a rustling
among the shrubbery near the window, which opened
to the ground, and she thought some one was coming
in.  They listened.  "It is only Henry gathering his
evening offering of flowers," said Mrs. Walton, and
Clara resumed.
</p><p>"I have thought of every plan, but I do not find
anything I can do will support you in comfort.  And
then poor Henry &mdash; he so loves these trees and flowers
that he will droop and die if we take him into a close
room, as we must do, should we go back to boarding
again.  But do not fear that I shall deceive Mr. Palmer.
I have told him that I do not love him; that if I
accepted him, it would be for the sake of my mother and
brother.  To-morrow I shall tell him &mdash;"
</p><p>"That you love another," said Mrs. Walton, in a
low sad tone.
</p><p>"No &mdash; but that I have loved.  I think," continued
this heroic girl, "I hope, I have overcome the weakness
I ought never to have indulged!"
</p><p>"O! it was my fault; I ought never to have permitted
you to pass so much time with the Foresters.
The excellencies of that young man's character seemed
to me, then, a guarantee that he would not abuse my
   <pb n="38"/>
confidence &mdash; would not seek to win the heart of my
child, and then cast it away like a worthless weed!"
said Mrs. Walton, in a tone of deep anguish.
</p><p>"He did not &mdash; he did not.  O! mother, you wrong
him," said Clara, weeping for the first time.  "He
never attempted to win my affections.  He never paid
me a compliment, or said a word which a good brother
might not have said to a young sister, whom he wished
to guide in the way of everything pure and holy.  I
gave him my love unsought, unknown by him &mdash; un-known even to myself.  Till Mr. Palmer addressed me,
to whom, except that he is not a religious man, I could
have no reasonable objection, I knew not that I had no
heart to give.  But I must not be thus weak," she
added, wiping the tears from her eyes.  "My resolution is taken."
</p><p>"To marry Mr. Palmer?"
</p><p>"Yes &mdash; if he continues to desire it after I have told
him all."  Here the rose-tree by the window was again
agitated.
</p><p>"Clara," said Mrs. Walton, solemnly, "listen to me.
I dare not allow you to make this sacrifice on my account,
neither would it be for good.  All mere worldly
prosperity is unstable; even while it lasts, it is hollow
and unsatisfying.  I married Colonel Meredith, because
he was rich and my parents insisted on the connection
&mdash; while I loved only Edward Walton, your father.
   <pb n="39"/>
The consequences were most unhappy.  I lived in
splendor, it is true, and became so absorbed in the
dissipations of fashionable life, into which I plunged to
avoid reflection, that I left my dear little Henry, one of
the most beautiful children I ever looked upon, when
he was only three years old, at home, to the care of
hired servants, and made the tour of Europe, not for
health, but amusement.  When, at the end of two
years, I returned, I found him a poor cripple and idiotic.
A fall he received, which was neglected, because his
<hi rend="italic">mother</hi> was not near to watch over him, was the cause
of this!  My husband knew that I did not love him,
and after our return, and he found his hopes in his
son thus destroyed, he grew morose and unkind.  His
affairs, too, were deranged, and the failure of a large
banking-house in England, where he had placed most
of his money, completed our ruin.  He lived but a few
weeks after this loss; and thus, in less than seven
years from the time I married one of the richest men
in New York, I was left a poor widow, with a sickly,
deformed child to provide for &mdash; and, Clara, during these
seven years, I was never happy &mdash; for my heart was
not in my duties, and God was not with me."
</p><p>"But then you married my father, and he was good
and kind to you, my dear mother," said Clara, sobbing.
"He had always loved you."
</p><p>"He had always remembered me," replied Mrs.
   <pb n="40"/>
Walton, "and my sorrows revived his affection.  But
he had lost his health, and was not able to take orders,
as he had intended.  His lungs were so weak that he
could not preach.  When we married, his income,
gained by his writings and giving lessons in the
languages, was only sufficient to furnish us with the mere
necessaries of life.  But then we loved each other, and
had faith in God.  I had learned that earth was a
broken reed &mdash; Edward taught me to look to heaven and
trust in the Saviour.  Our humble home was the temple
of prayer and praise; and then we had you to crown
our happiness.  There was still one bitter drop in my
cup &mdash; poor Henry's state, and the thought that it was
my fault.  But your father was so kind to him, and
Henry always seemed so happy himself, that though I
mourned I did not repine.  O! Clara &mdash; I can bear witness
from my own experience, that better is a dinner
of herbs where love is &mdash; I mean love to God and to
each other &mdash; than a house full of sacrifices with strife."
</p><p>"But when my father died  " said Clara, hesitatingly.
</p><p>"O! that was a sorrow which God inflicted, and he
alone could comfort," said Mrs. Walton, looking upwards.
"I bowed to His will, I trusted that he would
sustain me, and He has never forsaken us.  We have
been poor, but God has raised up friends to help us
when we have done what we could.  We will trust Him
   <pb n="41"/>
still.  Let us only do right, and then we shall all have
faith to pray for His blessing.  But if, from motives of
expediency, of selfish, or indeed, of generous feeling,
we violate His law, how can we expect to prosper?  And
the law of God bears witness, in every human heart, that
those who marry together should love each other.  I
dare not allow you, on my account, to violate this law.
You must send a decided refusal to Mr. Palmer."
</p><p>"But will you, mother, leave this place directly?"
</p><p>"As soon as possible, my love."
</p><p>"O, let us go to-morrow, dear mother.  I so fear
Mr. Forester will come while we are here," said Clara.
</p><p>"I don't think he would turn us out of the cottage,"
replied Mrs. Walton, half-smiling; "though, to be
sure, he has been very negligent about writing."
</p><p>"O, he has quite forgotten us, mother, and  "
</p><p>"Clara, <hi rend="italic">dear</hi> Clara!" said a deep manly voice, but
in a tone of the softest tenderness, and Charles Forester
stood before them!
</p><p>"O, Clara!" said Mr. Forester, as he pressed her
hand to his bosom, after she had become tranquilized &mdash;
"O Clara, you little know how severe was the trial of
my soul, how painful the sacrifice, when I left you
without declaring my love, and attempting to secure
yours in return.  But I was going to attend on my
dear, feeble mother, who required all my time and
means; I knew not how long this filial duty would
   <pb n="42"/>
be upon me.  Young, lovely, and attractive as you
are, should I, ought I, to have bound you in a long
engagement, which might, as you saw more of the
world, be irksome to you, and prevent you from
choosing among others, the rich and distinguished, who, I
foresaw, would bow before you?  I thank God that He
strengthened me to do what I felt to be right &mdash; to leave
you free.  But, dear Clara, I have prayed night and
morning, on my knees, that, if it could be, I might find
you thus; and I bless God he has granted my prayer.
He has brought your heart to love him supremely,
while its tenderest earthly affections have been kept
constant and pure.  Forget you, Clara!  I can truly say

</p>

<lg type="verse">
<l>"I've wandered east, I've wandered west,
</l><l>I've borne a weary lot;
</l><l>But in my wanderings, far or near,
</l><l>You never were forgot."
</l>
</lg>

<p>And they were married, &mdash; Mr. Forester and Clara
Walton, &mdash; united in that true affection and sympathy
of heart, soul, and mind, which constitute the holiness
of the relation, and make it a fit type of the union
between Christ and his Church.
</p><p>Mrs. Conant and her daughter, who were distant
connections of Mr. Forester, remained in Windsor till
after the wedding; and Mrs. Bell acknowledged she
had wronged Mrs. Walton, and never would again
make an evil report of her neighbor on the mere <hi rend="italic">"they
say"</hi> of the world.
</p>

</div1>

</body>
</text>
</TEI.2>

