<?xml version="1.0"?>

<?dlps id="HapCoun"?>
<?dlps page-images="none" figure-images="no"?>
<?dlps transcription="other"?>

<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/tei-p4/tei2.dtd" [
<!ENTITY % POSTKB "INCLUDE">
<!ENTITY % TEI.extensions.ent SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.ent">
<!ENTITY % TEI.extensions.dtd SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.dtd">
<!ENTITY % ISOnum SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/charent/iso-num.ent"> %ISOnum;
<!ENTITY % ISOpub SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/charent/iso-pub.ent"> %ISOpub;

]>

<TEI.2 id="HapCoun">
<teiHeader type="migrated" creator="Etext">
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title type="main">Count Tolstoi and the Public Censor</title>
<title type="sort">count tolstoi and the public censor</title>
<author>Hapgood, Isabel F.</author>
<respStmt>
<resp>Creation of machine-readable version:</resp>
<name>Judy Boss</name>
<resp>Conversion to TEI.2-conformant markup:</resp>
<name>University of Virginia Library Electronic Text Center</name>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt>
<extent>ca. <num type="kilobytes">45</num> kilobytes</extent>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>University of Virginia Library</publisher>
<pubPlace>Charlottesville, Virginia</pubPlace>
<idno type="ETC">HapCoun</idno>
<date value="1995">1995</date>
<availability status="public">
<p n="copyright">Copyright &copy; 1995 by the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia</p>
<p n="access">Publicly accessible</p>
</availability>
<idno type="uva-pid">uva-lib:476024</idno>
</publicationStmt>
<seriesStmt>
<title>University of Virginia Library, Text collection</title>
<idno type="uva-set">UVA-LIB-Text</idno>
</seriesStmt>
<sourceDesc>
<biblFull>
<titleStmt>
<title type="main">Count Tolstoi and the Public Censor</title>
<title type="sort">count tolstoi and the public censor</title>
<author>Isabel F. Hapgood</author>
</titleStmt>
<editionStmt>
<p>1st Edition</p>
</editionStmt>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>Atlantic Monthly</publisher>
<pubPlace>Boston</pubPlace>
<date value="1887">1887</date>
</publicationStmt>
<seriesStmt>
<p>
<hi rend="italic">Atlantic Monthly</hi> 60 (July 1887)</p>
</seriesStmt>
</biblFull>
</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc>
<encodingDesc>
<projectDesc>
<p>Prepared for the University of Virginia Library Electronic Text Center</p>
</projectDesc>
<editorialDecl>
<p>All quotation marks retained as data</p>
<p>All unambiguous end-of-line hyphens have been removed, and the
trailing part of a word has been joined to the preceding line.</p>
<p id="ETC">Keywords in the header are a local Electronic Text Center scheme
to aid in establishing analytical groupings</p>
</editorialDecl>
<refsDecl>
<p>ID elements are given for each page element and are composed of the text's
unique cryptogram and the given page number, as in AusEmma1 for page one of
Jane Austen's Emma.</p>
</refsDecl>
</encodingDesc>
<profileDesc>
<creation>
<date value="1887">1887</date>
</creation>
<langUsage>
<language id="eng" usage="main">English</language>
</langUsage>
<textClass>
<keywords>
<term>non-fiction; prose</term>
<term>Women Writers</term>
</keywords>
</textClass>
</profileDesc>
<revisionDesc>
<change>
<date value="1995-08">August 1995</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>corrector</resp>
<name>Deirdre Johnson, Electronic Text Center, University of Virginia</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Header added, basic TEI markup added</item>
</change>
<change>
<date value="2005-07">July 2005</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>Corrector</resp>
<name>John Ivor Carlson</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Converted SGML to XML. Fixed tagging.</item>
</change>
<change>
<date value="2007-09">September 2007</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>Migration</resp>
<name>Ethan Gruber, University of Virginia Library</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Converted XML markup from TEI Lite to uva-dl-tei (TEI P4 with local customizations).</item>
</change>
<change>
<date value="2008-01">January 2008</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>Migration</resp>
<name>Greg Murray, University of Virginia Library</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Programmatically updated TEI header markup (but not header content) for minimal compliance with current QA requirements.</item>
</change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text id="d1">
<body id="d2">

<div1 type="article" id="d3"><pb n="57"/>
<head>COUNT TOLSTOI AND THE PUBLIC CENSOR</head>

<p>     IT is a well-known fact that the sympathy between Count Lyof
Tolstoi and the censor of the Russian press is the reverse of
profound.  Nevertheless, the manner in which the two men are
working together, unwittingly, for the confusion of the count's
future literary executors and editors, furnishes a subject of
interest, not unmixed with amusement, to spectators in a land which
is not burdened with an official censor.  The extent of the
censorship exercised over the first eleven volumes of his works
will probably never be known.  But the twelfth volume is a literary
curiosity, which can be appreciated only after a comparison of its
contents as printed there with the manuscript copies of works
prohibited in Russia, or with copies of such works printed out of
Russia.</p>
<p>     The contents of the volume are of a very miscellaneous
character, and consist of sixteen short moral tales for popular
reading, some of which are cast in the form of legends, folk-tales,
and explanatory texts to accompany cheap chap-book pictures: a
fragment entitled In What Happiness Consists; an article on the
Census of Moscow, written in 1882; one written two years later,
called Thoughts Evoked by the Moscow Census; a psychological study
of death,&mdash;The Death of Ivan Ilitch; and an article on Popular
Education, which was originally printed in a journal in 1875, and
accidentally omitted from the fourth volume of the collected works,
where it properly belongs, in company with a large number of the
stories for popular reading.  This last article serves, in some
measure, to explain why so highly talented an author has devoted
himself, of late years, to the production of the peculiar stories
begun in his pedagogical journal, entitled Yasnaya Polyana, after
the name of his estate, and continued to the present time in
various publications.  As he has added no qualifying notes, the
article may be taken as still presenting his views.  They may be
summed up as follows: that the German method of elementary
instruction (evidently the Kindergarten) may be suited to the
capacities of "Hottentots, negroes, and small German children," but
that it certainly is not to the little Russian <hi rend="italic">muzhik</hi>, who
knows more at the age of two years than all the elaborate
puerilities of the two chief Russian authorities on the subject can
teach him from their books.  He believes that the peasant himself
is the best judge of what he should be taught, even though the
latter does hold the Dogberrian theory that schools need not be
permanent institutions, since, if the parents once learn, the
following generations will inherit their wisdom.  Count Tolstoi's
personal experience in the peasant schools has shown him that
Russian, Slavonic (the language of the church), and mathematics,
"and <hi rend="italic">nothing</hi> else" should constitute the course of study in
schools for the people, since these branches of learning are at the
foundation of all others.  In order that the people may have proper
reading matter for due progress, he has prepared the simple stories
contained in the present volume, as well as those referred to as
preceding them.  They are written in the simplest, most concise
peasant language, and in accordance with his theory that the people
always speak good Russian, while the educated classes do not.  They
are all ingenious, though, at times, the moral truth which he seeks
to convey is rendered difficult of perception by the involved
allegories by which it is obscured.  "Love one another, resist not
evil, despise money:" such is the burden of his exhortation, and as
a rule, it is beautifully and touchingly<pb n="58"/>  expressed.  If the
peasants are observing, however, they will not fail to note some
discrepancies in his arguments on the subject of money.  In one of
the tales, for instance, he represents the subjects of Ivan the
Fool&mdash;who are fools like their ruler, yet the only wise in truth&mdash;
as refusing money altogether except for the purpose of necklaces
for the women and playthings for the children, since it is nothing
but an invention of "the real gentleman, the old Devil," to lead
men astray.  In another, a man who finds a heap of gold by the
wayside, and devotes the whole of it to the founding of asylums for
orphans and old people, and other works of charity, is rebuked by
an angel of the Lord for having even touched the accursed thing.
In still another, a poor peasant, who has with difficulty scraped
together enough money to make a pilgrimage to Jerusalem for the
salvation of his soul, spends nearly the whole of it in restoring
a starving family to prosperity, and is obliged to return home.
Yet he or his wraith is seen at the Holy Sepulchre by his friend
and traveling-companion, as a heavenly reward for the good
accomplished with gold, that lure of the Evil One.  The giving of
money in alms is directly commended in other tales.  The author's
opinions on this question, elsewhere expressed, show that he
entertains strong doubts as to whether money is not an unmixed
evil, and the old-fashioned system of barter the only true solution
of the difficulty.  These stories, as printed in this volume, do
not correspond, in all respects, with the versions furnished the
people in the separate penny copies, but it can hardly be a
question of the censor, in this case.</p>
<p>     The fragment entitled In What Happiness Consists represents
all of the work popularly known as My Religion which is allowed in
a printed form, in Russia.  It corresponds with a portion of
chapter x., beginning with the sentence, "Christ preaches the
truth."  (My Religion, Crowell, page 179; What I Believe,
Gottsberger, page 171.)  Throughout, the "doctrine of the church"&mdash;
where the phrase is permitted at all,&mdash;is replaced by the words,
"the teaching of the world."  The references to asceticism,
voluntary torture in this life, and the scriptural quotation on
which monasticism is founded are expunged.  The remark that the
circle of friends which emperors and kings can have is very
restricted also strikes the censor as objectionable.  The outspoken
passage on pages 191, 182 (respectively, as above), beginning with
the comments on the servant in a bath-house, including observations
on cabinet ministers perpetually engaged in signing documents of no
importance, and men following a gaudy uniform to the wars, like a
herd of cattle, and so on, is the next omission.  The wickedness of
oaths to authorities and the results of a refusal to perform
military service follow, as well as the phrase about torture in
Sevastopol and Plevna.  (What I Believe, page 184.)  The quotation
and reference to poverty as one of the indispensable conditions of
following Christ's doctrine is also omitted, possibly out of
consideration for the feelings of wealthy ecclesiastics.  The
passage concerning the millions of men in Russia who do not
practice the doctrine of Christ, and yet do not starve, the miracle
of the loaves and fishes (pages 203-207; 191-194, as above), and
one or two lesser omissions complete the list of the censor's
cancellations.  The cuts are significant and leave very little of
even that one chapter to stand as the authorized version.</p>
<p>     The Death of Ivan Ilitch is the most important thing, in the
line of strictly literary work, which Count Tolstoi has written
since Anna Karenina, and consists mainly of a subtle psychological
study of the cultivated man in general, during the hopeless illness
preceding his death.  There is enough ordinary description
connected with this to admit us <pb n="59"/>  into the circumstances of
Ivan Ilitch's life, before and during his illness, and the
unfeeling conduct of his family, which leaves him dependent for
sympathy, in his sufferings, on the cheerful, simple-minded peasant
who waits upon him.  It is through the unconscious influence of
this peasant that Ivan Ilitch is at last brought into a state of
mind where he no longer fears death, but dies with the calm
composure of the muzhik.  As is natural, this portion of the
narrative outweighs the rest in the reader's interest, but there is
some equally fine analytical work in the opening chapter, where
Petr Ivanovitch, Ivan Ilitch's old friend, calls upon the widow.</p>
<p>     The most important article in this volume, however, is that
devoted to the Census of Moscow.  In general character, it is a
continuation of My Religion, many of the same subjects being
considered in the light of his personal experience as one of the
census-takers in one of the poorest quarters of the city, to which
he had been appointed at his own request.  It was not to be
expected that such a social study would be allowed to pass the
censor unmutilated.  The omissions are numerous and noteworthy.  A
hint of this state of things is sometimes conveyed by a line of
dots, but in other cases no indication whatever is vouchsafed.
Copies of the article, printed abroad, and under a different title,
supply the suppressed passages, which are generally the most
interesting of all.  Count Tolstoi's idea of a census is to combine
works of mercy with the technical labor: if a starving woman should
come under the notice of one of the agents, she should be attended
to, even if the census proper should go to destruction in
consequence, the succor of the suffering being the most important
task of our lives.  In short, the census should be simply a means
to that end.</p>
<p>     In 1882, Count Tolstoi went to live in Moscow, where he was
speedily struck with the numerous beggars, by whom he was cheated,
in accordance with methods universally prevalent, when he offered
them work, or gave them money for specific objects.  He found that
old inhabitants of the city spoke with considerable satisfaction
and pride of the 50,000 beggars, just as people in London had
boasted to him of poverty in London.  Prompted by a desire to
inspect this wretchedness in person, he finally went to a certain
square, which was a sort of headquarters for an army of beggars,
after having made several attempts and beaten a retreat, overcome
by his feelings.  Thence he followed the crowd to the Lyapinsky
free lodging-house for the night.  While waiting with the throng
for the doors to open, at five P. M., he conversed with various
poor people, treated them to hot <hi rend="italic">sbiten</hi> (poor man's tea, made
of water, honey, and laurel or salvia leaves), and gave them all
the money he had about him, amounting to twenty rubles.  He was
conducted over the house, as soon as it was opened, by some of his
new friends, and got his first sight of the double row of bunks and
their wretched occupants, as the latter prayed, cursed, and jested.
The passage which follows is omitted from the version authorized by
the censor.  It describes his sensations of personal guilt, on
returning to his own house, with its carpeted stairs and anterooms,
where, after removing his fur cloak, he sat down to a dinner of
five courses, served by two lackeys, in dress-coats, white ties,
and white gloves.  He also describes an execution which he had
witnessed thirty years before, in Paris, and announces his
conviction that he was guilty of murder, because he bestowed his
tacit approval on it by being present without offering a
remonstrance.  He compares his sensations on that occasion to those
experienced on the present one, when he might have given, not only
the small change in his pocket, but the coat from his back and the
entire contents of his house, and declares that he shall always
hold <pb n="60"/>  himself to be an accomplice in crime so long as he
possesses two garments, while there is any one who has none at all.
In the evening he discussed the question with a friend, and
unconsciously shouted at the latter, as he says, with tears in his
voice, "I can't live so; it is impossible to live so,&mdash;impossible!"
until his wife rushed in from an adjoining room to inquire the
cause of his excitement.  He was then made to feel ashamed of his
heat in argument, was told that he never could talk quietly, that
he became unpleasantly excited, and it was proved to him that the
existence of such unfortunate wretches could not possibly afford
him any excuse for embittering the lives of those about him.  "I
felt that this was perfectly just," he adds, "and held my tongue;
but at the bottom of my heart I knew that I was right, and I could
not calm myself."</p>
<p>     The luxury of his city life became intolerable to him, but his
friends assured him that it was only because he was very good and
tender-hearted, which he gladly believed.  He then set about
devising a plan of philanthropic activity, which would exhibit all
his benevolence, although secretly persuaded that this was not what
he wanted.  This plan was the one above referred to in connection
with the census, after exercising the exhaustive benevolence of
which, the rich would be able to enjoy their luxuries without any
compunction.  All the friends to whom he wrote or spoke about
banishing poverty from Moscow treated him with consideration, but
appeared sorry to hear him utter nonsense which they could not
qualify as such to his face.  They allowed him to put down their
names for various sums, but not one of them gave him ready money,
as they would have done for a box at the theatre to see Sarah
Bernhardt.  At one elegant house, he found a large circle of ladies
engaged in dressing dolls, which were to be raffled for the benefit
of the poor, but lack of means prevented their giving him anything.
He returned home with a mortified sense of having been engaged in
something very shameful, but shame itself forbade the
relinquishment of the scheme.  He wrote his article on the census,
containing an outline of his plan (it is given in this twelfth
volume), and then read it to the city council, "blushing almost to
tears" with embarrassment as he did so.  No official action was
taken; they all seemed to regret his folly; so did the students
appointed to take the census; so did his wife, his son, and various
other persons.  He was still conscious that he was not on the right
track, but his article was printed, and he entered on the duties
connected with the census.  He was assigned to a quarter of the
city in which was situated a stronghold of the direst poverty,
popularly known under the name of the "Rzhanoff house," or the
"fortress."  On the appointed day, the students who were to assist
him made their appearance at that house early in the morning, but,
as he did not rise until ten o'clock, and had to drink his coffee
and smoke for his digestion, he, the benefactor, did not reach the
fortress until twelve o'clock.  His description of the sights which
he witnessed there is graphic and terrible, as was to be expected;
but at the end, he was ashamed to confess that he felt rather
disappointed to discover that these people were not in the least
peculiar, but exactly like his ordinary associates.  He had gone
there with the idea that he should find people in need of immediate
assistance, and he saw petty artisans of various sorts, all
cheerful and busily working.  Where help was required, it had
already been given by the poor people themselves.  What these
people needed, like people in the higher ranks, was to have their
false views of life corrected.  A comparison between the miserable
women whom he found in this house and ladies of the higher classes
has been suppressed by the censor.  Among the children, he
<pb n="61"/>
was particularly struck with a lad of twelve, named Serozha.  He
took Serozha to his own house, and installed him in the kitchen,
being unwilling to introduce to his own children a boy fresh from
the haunts of vice.  Having thus, as he expresses it, shifted the
feeding of the boy upon the cook, and presented him with some old
clothes, he felt himself to be extremely good and benevolent.  The
child remained there one week, in the course of which Tolstoi
addressed a few words to him on two occasions, and spoke to a
shoemaker about taking the lad as an apprentice, as the latter had
refused an offer to go to the country.  At the end of the week, the
boy ran away, and hired out for thirty kopeks a day, as one of a
band of savages in costume, who led an elephant in a procession,
and he appeared utterly ungrateful for Tolstoi's kindness.
Thereupon the latter blames himself for having brought the boy into
demoralizing contact with his own children, thereby imbuing him
with the notion that enjoyment without labor was permissible to him
also, since he saw the little Tolstois soiling and spoiling
everything about them, breaking the dishes, eating dainties, and
flinging to their dogs food which would have seemed a delicacy to
this beggar lad.  His criticism of his own course is very frank.
His experience of giving assistance with money was a bitter
disappointment; genteel beggars were voracious in their demands,
and the really poor lied and deceived him, until his faith in his
scheme was destroyed.  Not one of the people who had offered their
help or had promised money (he had reckoned their subscriptions at
3000 rubles) ever gave him a single kopek; but the students who
were under his charge contributed what they received for their work
on the census,&mdash;about twelve rubles.  To this was added twenty-five
rubles sent to him by the city authorities, in compensation for his
own work.  "And I positively did not know," he adds, "to whom to
give them."  Before he went to the country for the summer, he made
a special trip to the Rzhanoff fortress, for the purpose of
"getting rid of those thirty-seven rubles."  He found one poor old
man to whom he gave five rubles.  He gave the rest to a trustworthy
man, for distribution in the neighborhood, as he could find no
proper subjects for charity himself, and as those who begged of him
were too well known to him, and in a roistering carnival state.
Thus ended his scheme of benevolence, and he went off to the
country, irritated with others because he had done a stupid and
unprofitable deed.  But though his experimental philanthropy was at
an end, the thoughts evoked by it and the sentiments with which it
had inspired him did not cease, and the inward conflict proceeded
with redoubled vigor.</p>
<p>     In the country, he says, he had done very little for the poor,
but the demands upon him were so moderate that this little created
an atmosphere of love and union with the people, which enabled him
to believe what he had always heard, namely, that wealth is the
gift of God, and that one can help the poor while continuing a life
of luxury.  A short personal investigation of city poverty
convinced him that these wretched working classes could not be
helped, because the very fact of their toil attached them to life
more closely than he was himself attached, and because their chief
misfortune lay in their being exactly the same as himself.  For a
long time, a false shame, and a liking for the self-satisfaction of
feeling himself to be a benefactor, prevented his abandoning his
attempts to render material aid.  His mistake, which it took him
three years longer to discover, lay in thinking that in order to
live a good life it was necessary to amend the lives of others, not
his own.  The result of his reflections has been suppressed by the
censor.  It is, that the first cause of the peculiar poverty of the
city, which he was unable to <pb n="62"/>  alleviate, lies in the fact
that he deprives the country people of their necessaries, and
carries them off to town with him.  The second cause is, that he
employs the goods which he has collected in the village in
senseless luxury, thereby demoralizing those country people who
follow him thither, in the hope of in some way recovering a portion
of their property.  One day, as he was talking to his sympathizing
sister, and to a peasant named Siutaeff, the latter gave him the
first real gleam of light on the subject of true charity, and as to
the reason why Tolstoi had been unsuccessful with his gifts of
money.  "True charity," said Siutaeff, "consists in teaching the
poor.  Take your proportion of the poor, work beside them in the
fields, and they will learn; eat at the same table with them, and
let them hear your words."  At this point the censor intervenes,
and cuts out over a thousand words containing reflections on this
theme.  Every effort in the life of the wealthy, says Tolstoi, from
their food, clothing, and dwellings, down to their cleanliness and
their culture, is directed towards keeping the poor at a distance,
and nine tenths of their money is spent in attaining this object
alone.  His socialistic utterances upon this subject are
delightfully unconventional, but those on cleanliness, which is
regarded as a moral virtue, though in reality only valued as a mark
of class distinction, are of the most radical sort.  "White hands
love other people's work," is the proverb which he takes for his
motto.  The popular idea of the grades among the upper classes is
thus defined: Culture signifies fashionable clothing, political
conversation, and clean hands.  In the circle next above, a
knowledge of French, the ability to play the piano and to write a
letter in Russian free from orthographical errors, and a "still
greater degree of outward cleanliness" are the requisites.  The
next step in the social scale brings a knowledge of English, a
diploma from one of the higher institutes of learning, and still
greater personal cleanliness.  "I am convinced," he says, "that
between the poor and the rich there rises this wall of cleanliness
and culture, and that in order to assist the poor we must break
down this wall, first of all, adopt the plan of Siutaeff, and
receive the poor among ourselves."</p>
<p>     Another of Count Tolstoi's experiences puzzled him not a
little.  If he gave a beggar a few kopeks, when requested, without
stopping to speak to him, the beggar looked grateful, and the Count
was conscious of an agreeable sense of benevolence himself.  But if
he conversed with the man he felt obliged to give more, and the
more he gave the more displeased the beggar appeared.  The gift of
ten rubles caused the beggar to look as though he had been
insulted, and to walk off without saying so much as "Thank you,"
leaving Tolstoi feeling conscience-stricken and guilty.  He
concludes that this is the result of deliberately abandoning the
<hi rend="italic">role</hi> of a good-natured passer-by, and assuming that of a kind-hearted man.  The solution of this puzzle was furnished him by a
little scene at his country place, which the censor has seen fit to
omit.  He wanted twenty kopeks to give to a tramp, and sent his son
to the house to borrow it of some one.  It was lent by the cook.
Shortly afterwards Tolstoi wanted another twenty kopeks for a
tramp, and went to the kitchen to see if the cook could change a
ruble for him.  The cook called to his wife to take the money, and
she, supposing that it was a gift, kissed Tolstoi's hand, whereupon
the latter fled from the kitchen, groaning with shame, and did not
undeceive her.  The conclusion which he comes to is, that if any
man asks three kopeks, or twenty, or even several rubles, one must
give them, if one has them, this being merely a "matter of
politeness, and not charity," with which view the censor,
evidently, does not agree. <pb n="63"/> </p>
<p>     When Tolstoi first went to Moscow to live, he took up the
habit of going to the Sparrow Hills to saw wood with a couple of
peasants, for the sake of the exercise.  One night he walked into
town with them, and gave twenty kopeks to an old man who begged of
them, thinking what a good impression such charity would make on
Semyon, one of the peasants.  Semyon pulled out his purse, gave the
man a three-kopek piece, and asked for two kopeks in change.  The
man had but one, and after a momentary hesitation Semyon took off
his cap, crossed himself, and went on, leaving the man the money.
This set Tolstoi to thinking.  Semyon had a wife and two children,
and no reserve fund; Tolstoi had about 600,000 rubles saved up.  In
order to proportion his alms to Semyon's, Tolstoi reckoned that he
should have given 3000 rubles, have asked 2000 in change, and then,
leaving it all, have crossed himself, and proceeded quietly with
his conversation.  His deductions do not meet with the favor of the
censor, who has cut out some reflections on the source of Tolstoi's
fortune.  "A part," says the author, "I inherited from my father.
The peasant sold his last sheep to furnish me with it.  Another
part has come from the sale of my books.  If my books are
injurious, then I only lead people astray with them by selling
them, and the money which I receive for them is ill-gained; but if
they are helpful to people, my case is even worse.  I do not give
them to people, but I say, 'Give me seventeen rubles, and then I
will give them to you.'  And as the peasant sells his last sheep in
the country, so here the poor student, the teacher, every poor man,
deprives himself of necessaries in order to give me this money.
And then I take this money to the city, and only give it to poor
men when they comply with my whims, and come to town to clean my
sidewalks, my lamps, my boots, and to toil in factories for my
benefit.  And I get as much as I can out of them, and give them as
little as possible.  I have erred so far that I have regarded this
grasping of thousands with one hand, and this squandering of kopeks
with the other, on any one who might strike my fancy, as good.  It
is no wonder that I was ashamed of myself."  Very little of the
following chapter meets with the approval of the censor.  It
contains comparisons of the ways of the rich&mdash;the Demidoffs and
other families being mentioned by name, the bankers, merchants, and
the land-owners, to which latter class the writer himself belongs&mdash;
with those of the poor.  "I go to help the poor," he says.  "Who is
poorer than I?  No one. . . .  I am a weak, good-for-nothing
parasite, who can exist only when thousands of people toil for the
support of this life, which is useful to no one. . . .  I know how
to do nothing but eat, and talk, and listen, and write, and sleep.
. . .  The only wonder is that I should ever have had so stupid a
thought as helping people who are good for something," is his
conclusion.  "I have never done anything in my life.  I do nothing,
and never shall do anything except cut off coupons, and yet I
firmly believe that money represents labor.  This is amazing!  Talk
of lunatics after that!" he exclaims, at the conclusion of an
earnest argument that money is only a new form of slavery.  The
root of all slavery is the use of the labor of others; and having
once perceived the "immorality" of his position, Count Tolstoi
resolved to use no more of his money to compel slavery, to do
everything for himself, or to do without it.  "This simple and
inevitable deduction enters into all the details of my life," he
says.  "It alters it completely, at once frees me from those moral
sufferings which I experienced at the sight of the sufferings and
vice of men, and instantly annihilates all those causes of my
inability to help the poor which I discovered while seeking the
reason of <pb n="69"/>  my failure."  These causes are, the herding
together of the poor in towns, the isolation of the rich from the
poor, and the shame consequent on the consciousness of being
wrongfully in possession of the money with which he tried to assist
the poor; money, being in itself an evil thing, cannot be used as
an instrument of good.  The sum of the matter is contained in the
words of John the Baptist: "Let him that hath two garments give to
him that hath none, and let him that hath food do likewise."  As
Tolstoi puts it, it means "to give away everything superfluous, and
never more take what is superfluous from men. . . .  For him who is
sincerely pained by the sufferings of those about him, there is the
easiest, simplest, and most evident remedy, the only possible one
for the alleviation of the evil which environs us, and for
conferring on us a consciousness of the legitimacy of our life, the
same which John the Baptist gave and which Christ confirmed,&mdash;to
have but one garment, and no money.  Having no money signifies
making no use of the labors of others, and therefore doing with our
own hands all that it is possible for us to do."</p>
<p>     The next thing to which the censor takes exception is the
description of a ball in fashionable society (in which Tolstoi
expresses himself in the plainest language, with regard to the
dresses and conduct of both men and women), which is introduced as
a companion picture to a sketch of the factory girls who work in
the vicinity of his Moscow house.</p>
<p>     Tolstoi's argument on behalf of wearing one shirt a week,
instead of paying a laundress to provide him with two clean ones
each day, and of making his own cigarettes, is, that the money thus
saved can be given to the laundress for less work, or to some
superannuated working people.  To this he suggests the retort, that
"if one goes in dirty linen, and does not smoke, but gives the
money to the poor, the latter will be deprived of the money all the
same, and an individual drop in the sea will do no good."  It is a
shame to reply to such a commonplace objection, he says, yet he
does make a reply, to the effect that he would not eat savory
cutlets made from a prisoner, among cannibals, even if his refusal
did the prisoner no good; but the censor disapproved of this,
possibly the author himself thought better of it, for it is
replaced in his collected works with an Indian fable about dipping
the sea dry with a bucket, to find a lost pearl, which the spirit
of the sea restored in affright on the seventh day.  In a brief
section he sketches life in the country, and shows the selfish
proprietors during their short summer residence, and the hardships
of the peasants.  This is followed by a lengthy consideration of
the merits of science and art.  His chief objection to these latter
lies in the fact that they are the outcome of the division of
labor, and cannot exist on any other conditions than those of
rendering many people slaves, for the production of the necessaries
of life for those engaged in them.  "Science has now become a
distributor of premiums on idleness. . . .  With frightful
struggles and conflicts men have freed themselves from many
delusions.  And now a new and still worse delusion has sprung up in
their path,&mdash;the delusion of science. . . .  The theory of
evolution, to speak in ordinary language, merely asserts that by
accident, in an endlessly long space of time, out of anything you
please any other thing you please may issue."  He denies that art
and science have given a great deal to mankind, as is usually
affirmed.  They have not devoted themselves to the interests of the
people, and those who exercise them simply live on the necks of the
laboring classes.  "We have become so accustomed," he says, "to our
weakly and tenderly cared for representatives of mental labor that
it seems barbarous to us that a learned man or an artist should
till the soil or cart manure.  It <pb n="65"/>  seems to us that all his
wisdom will be ruined and shaken out of him on the cart, and that
the grand artistic conceptions which he bears about in his bosom
will get soiled in the manure."  He thinks that art and science
should not be exempted from serving themselves and others, simply
because they are such very beautiful things.</p>
<p>     Tolstoi admits that telegraph, telephone, spectroscope,
chloroform, and many other inventions and discoveries are
wonderful, but he maintains that the condition of the majority&mdash;of
the working people that is&mdash;has been rendered worse by them, since
the railways, factories, and so on have only served to make poor
men the slaves of capitalists.  According to his views, the
province of science is to teach the poor man what axe is the best
to cut with, what is the swiftest saw, the best way to mix bread
and the proper flour to use, how to set and bake it, and how to
build an oven, also the right sort of food and the best utensils.
He complains that instead of doing this, science has enumerated two
million beetles.  He frequently returns to this complaint.  Not a
single plant has been added to the list of foods since the days of
ancient Egypt, when wheat and the lentil were already known, except
the potato, which was not the contribution of science.  He goes
into this question with a good deal of detail, pointing the moral
at doctors, artists, teachers, musicians, and so forth, in turn.
The poet and author should, for example, throw aside their poems
and romances, and write songs, histories, and tales which the
people can understand; and Tolstoi considers the so-called division
of labor, which has formed in our days the indispensable condition
of activity on the part of artists and scientists, to be the chief
reason for the slow progress of mankind.  Science, in the true
meaning of the term, he says, has existed as long as man himself
has existed, and consists in the knowledge of those things which it
most imports men to know.  Such was the science of Confucius,
Buddha, Socrates, Mahomet, and others,&mdash;a science which is within
the comprehension of every one.  This has degenerated, and art
also, which has descended from its true sphere of activity in the
church; so that those who exercise chorographic, culinary,
cosmetic, and wig-making arts are now as much entitled to the name
of artists as poets, painters, and musicians.</p>
<p>     Tolstoi declares that if he in any way differs from the
average man, on this question of the misapplication of art and
science, it is because he, more than the average man, has served
and forwarded this false conception of science which is held by the
world, has received more applause from the people who belong to the
reigning scientific circle, and has therefore sinned more than
others and wandered further from the true path.  For this reason,
he thinks that the solution of the question which he has found for
himself will fit the case of all sincere people, who have put the
same question to themselves, namely, "What is to be done?"  First
of all, he has resolved not to lie, either to others or to himself,
not to fear the truth, no matter whither it may lead him; since he
firmly believes that in whatever position truth and conscience may
land him, however terrible it may be, it cannot be worse than one
that is founded on a lie.  He has been rewarded for his boldness in
doing this; all the incoherent, complicated, senseless phenomena of
life have grown clear to him, and his own attitude among these
conditions, formerly strange and oppressive, has become natural and
easy.  Too high an opinion of himself and his position led him to
the second answer to the question, "What is to be done?"  Thorough
repentance, a just estimate of himself, a confession that he is
ignorant and unlearned instead of cultured, harsh and immoral
instead of kind and moral, lowly, instead of exalted, are what is
<pb n="66"/>  required.  "How am I, so fine a writer, a man who has
acquired so much learning and talents, to use them for the benefit
of the people?" is the erroneous form in which he put the question
to himself.  It should have run: "How am I, who have wasted the
best years of my life in useless occupations which are ruinous to
the soul" (this includes the French language, playing on the piano,
grammar, geography, verses, novels, romances, and so forth), "to
repay the people who fed and clothed me during all that time, and
who still feed and clothe me?"  The answer to this is: "I must
learn not to live on others, and, having learned this, I must
devote to the service of the people hands, and feet, and heart, and
brain, and everything that the people may require; for the first
and indubitable duty of man is to share in the struggle with
nature, for his life and the lives of others."  Count Tolstoi
regards it as his and every man's first duty to provide his own
food, clothing, fuel, and shelter, and thus help others; and
departure from this law entails the inevitable penalty of the
annihilation of the bodily or mental life of man.  "At first," he
says, "I thought that in order to carry out this plan some
establishment was necessary, some institution, a company of men
entertaining the same ideas, the consent of my family, life in the
country; then I felt rather ashamed to show myself thus before
people, to undertake a thing so unusual in our society as manual
labor, and I did not know how to set about it."  This false shame
was expelled, however, by the real shame which he felt at not
undertaking it, and he came to the conclusion that the strangeness
would last only a week (in which calculation he appears to have
been mistaken), and that no society or institution was required.
He had also thought that this manual labor would absorb all his
time, and deprive him of all possibility of pursuing intellectual
occupations, "which I love," he says, "and which, in moments of
self-sufficiency I have thought not unprofitable to my fellow-men."
He found, however, that when he had given up the eight hours,
during which he had formerly battled with <hi rend="italic">ennui</hi>, to physical
toil, he still had the five hours necessary for mental exertion;
and he enters on a curious computation, which proves that, if he
had pursued the same plan, reading and studying during those five
hours every day, and writing only a couple of pages on holidays, he
would have accomplished as much in fourteen years as he has
actually accomplished in forty.  Physical exertion spurs up his
mental faculties, and the nearer it approaches rude agriculture,
the closer and more affectionate is his communion with men, his
enjoyment of art and learning, and the true happiness of life.  The
writer also finds that many of his former requirements, in the way
of dainty food, bed, clothing, "conventional cleanliness," all of
which interfere with work, have disappeared without any effort on
his part, and that he prefers the simplest food: cabbage soup,
groats, black bread, and tea <hi rend="italic">v prikusky</hi> (that is, tea which is
not sweetened, but accompanied by bites at a lump of sugar).  Thus,
he sees that "the most costly needs of his life, vanity and relief
from ennui," have vanished, and that his health is improved, in
spite of his age.  He decides that our arts and sciences and
improvements of the pleasures of life are mere attempts to deceive
the moral demands of man, and he refers to a peasant of his
district who lost his wits through beholding the luxury of official
life, and who now declares that he "lives to pass the time."
Tolstoi declares that he gazes on this crazy muzhik as in a mirror.
He has, accordingly, divided his days into four portions.  The
first is to be occupied with some heavy labor, of a nature to
produce perspiration; the second, with labor of hands and wrists,
some sort of artisan toil; the third, with exercise of the mind
<pb n="67"/>  and imagination; and the fourth, in communion with others,
since no one has a right to devote himself to a specialty, unless
he feels within himself an irresistible impulse, and a demand is
made by others, when he is justified in making this sacrifice to
his brethren.</p>
<p>     Count Tolstoi's hope is that if a number of his "caste" engage
in a similar life, young people will be induced to follow their
example.  He argues that as it is now the fashion to do many things
for one's self which no gentleman thought of doing when he was a
boy, so it is a mere question of fashion when gentlemen will feed
their own cows and hens, dig, plant potatoes, clean their boots,
and wash their shirts; and he defines property as that which cannot
be taken from a man,&mdash;in other words, his own person alone.  It is
worth noting that he permits the use of scientific improvements,
and his perfect man will use a steam plough, if obtainable, or will
scratch the soil with a hoe, if nothing better be within his reach;
and people, perceiving his efforts, will strive to render his work
as profitable as possible.  Others, observing a handful of
"lunatics tilling the soil and making shoes, instead of smoking
cigarettes and playing cards," will comprehend what it behooves
them to do, will cease to ruin each other, and will find happiness.
He predicts that before long people of his class will consider it
not disgraceful to make calls in boots made with the outside of the
leather in, but disgraceful to wear overshoes in the presence of
people who have no shoes at all; that it is not disgraceful to be
ignorant of French, but disgraceful to eat bread, and not to know
how it is made; that it is not disgraceful not to have starched
shirts and clean clothes, but disgraceful to go about in clean
clothes, thereby demonstrating one's idleness; that it is not
disgraceful to have dirty hands, but disgraceful not to have
callouses on the hands.  And all this will come about when public
opinion demands it, like the emancipation of serfs and the
destruction of other errors which concealed the truth.  This
section of the book closes with the author's views on the duties of
women, which are expressed in the plainest of language.  Their duty
is to their family solely, and he concludes, "Yes, ye mothers, in
your hands, more than in those of all others, rests the salvation
of the world."  There is much more that is worth quoting, in this
volume, since it is pervaded with the strong personality of the
great author, who has endeared himself to thousands of hearts
outside of his own country, in spite of the disadvantages under
which they have learned to know him, and who is revered by other
thousands at home; but nothing less than a full translation would
convey a complete idea of its contents, especially of the striking
Moscow article.</p>
                          <signed><hi rend="italic">Isabel F. Hapgood</hi></signed>


</div1>
</body>
</text>
</TEI.2>
