<?xml version="1.0"?>

<?dlps id="HarLast"?>
<?dlps page-images="none" figure-images="no"?>
<?dlps transcription="other"?>

<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/tei-p4/tei2.dtd" [
<!ENTITY % POSTKB "INCLUDE">
<!ENTITY % TEI.extensions.ent SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.ent">
<!ENTITY % TEI.extensions.dtd SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.dtd">
<!ENTITY % ISOnum SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/charent/iso-num.ent"> %ISOnum;
<!ENTITY % ISOpub SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/charent/iso-pub.ent"> %ISOpub;
]>

<TEI.2 id="HarLast">
<teiHeader type="migrated" creator="Etext">
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title type="main">The Red Man's Last Roll-Call</title>
<title type="sort">red mans last roll call</title>
<author>Harvey, Charles M.</author>
<respStmt>
<resp>Creation of machine-readable version:</resp>
<name>Judy Boss</name>
<resp>Conversion to TEI.2-conformant markup:</resp>
<name>University of Virginia Library Electronic Text Center.</name>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt>
<extent>ca. <num type="kilobytes">32</num> kilobytes</extent>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>University of Virginia Library</publisher>
<pubPlace>Charlottesville, Virginia</pubPlace>
<idno type="ETC">HarLast</idno>
<date value="1994">1994</date>
<availability status="public">
<p n="copyright">Copyright &copy; 1994 by the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia</p>
<p n="access">Publicly accessible</p>
</availability>
<idno type="uva-pid">uva-lib:476029</idno>
</publicationStmt>
<seriesStmt>
<title>University of Virginia Library, Text collection</title>
<idno type="uva-set">UVA-LIB-Text</idno>
</seriesStmt>
<sourceDesc>
<biblFull>
<titleStmt>
<title type="main">The Red Man's Last Roll-Call</title>
<title level="j">Atlantic Monthly</title>
<title type="sort">red mans last roll call</title>
<author>Charles M. Harvey</author>
</titleStmt>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>Atlantic Monthly</publisher>
<pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
<date value="1906">1906</date>
</publicationStmt>
<seriesStmt>
<p>Volume 97; pp. 323-330</p>
</seriesStmt>
</biblFull>
</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc>
<encodingDesc>
<projectDesc>
<p>Prepared for the University of Virginia Library Electronic Text Center.</p>
</projectDesc>
<editorialDecl>
<p>Spell-check and verification made against printed text</p>
<p>All unambiguous end-of-line hyphens have been removed, and the
trailing part of a word has been joined to the preceding line.</p>
<p id="ETC">Keywords in the header are a local Electronic Text Center scheme
to aid in establishing analytical groupings.</p>
</editorialDecl>
<refsDecl>
<p>ID elements are given for each page element and are composed of the
text's unique cryptogram and the given page number, as in AusEmma1 for page one of
Jane Austen's Emma.</p>
</refsDecl>
</encodingDesc>
<profileDesc>
<creation>
<date value="1906">1906</date>
</creation>
<langUsage>
<language id="eng" usage="main">English</language>
</langUsage>
<textClass>
<keywords>
<term>non-fiction; prose</term>
<term>Native American</term>
</keywords>
</textClass>
</profileDesc>
<revisionDesc>
<change>
<date value="1994-08">August 1994</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>corrector</resp>
<name>Kelly Tetterton, University of Virginia Library Electronic Text Center.</name>
</respStmt>
<item>TEI tagging</item>
</change>
<change>
<date value="2005-07">July 2005</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>Corrector</resp>
<name>John Ivor Carlson</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Converted SGML to XML. Fixed tagging.</item>
</change>
<change>
<date value="2007-09">September 2007</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>Migration</resp>
<name>Ethan Gruber, University of Virginia Library</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Converted XML markup from TEI Lite to uva-dl-tei (TEI P4 with local customizations).</item>
</change>
<change>
<date value="2008-01">January 2008</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>Migration</resp>
<name>Greg Murray, University of Virginia Library</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Programmatically updated TEI header markup (but not header content) for minimal compliance with current QA requirements.</item>
</change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text id="d1">
<body id="d2">

<div1 type="article" id="d3"><pb n="323"/>
<head>Harvey, Charles M.  "The Red Man's Last Roll-Call."
<hi rend="italic">Atlantic Monthly</hi> 97 (1906): 323-330.</head>

<p>WHEN, on March 4, 1906, the tribal organization of the
Cherokees, Choctaws, Creeks, Chickasaws, and Seminoles is
dissolved, and their members diffused in the mass of the country's
citizenship, the final chapter in the Indian's annals as a distinct
race will have been written.  These are very far from comprising
all the red men in the country.  They number a little over 86,000,
while the total Indian population of the United States, exclusive
of Alaska, is about 270,000.  They do not even include the entire
Indian population of their own locality, the Indian Territory.  In
the territory's northeast corner there are fragments of the
Peorias, Shawnees, Quapaws, Wyandottes, Senecas, Modocs, and
Ottawas, numbering in all about 1500.
</p><p>Numerically, however, the Five Civilized Tribes are more
important than any other aggregation of red men.  They are of
immeasurably greater consequence socially than all the rest of the
Indians in the United States put together.  The middle term of the
designation here given to them means just what it says.  They are
civilized Indians.  In each tribe for itself, for two generations,
they have been conducting their own affairs in their own way.  They
have their own legislatures, executives, and courts; also their own
churches and school system.  Subject to the requirement that they
must keep within the limitations of the Constitution of the United
States and must recognize the United States government's paramount
authority, they have been supreme in their own domain.
</p><p>This ascendency ends with the dissolution of the tribal
governments on March 4, 1906.  United States laws will then be
immediately extended over the Indian Territory, the terms Seminole,
Cherokee, Choctaw, and the rest of them will vanish, and their
bearers will gain the same privileges and be subject to the same
responsibilities as their white neighbors in Oklahoma and the other
territories.  Very soon after that date they will probably, jointly
with Oklahoma, enter on the larger privileges and penalties of
statehood.
</p><p>To most persons east of the Mississippi, and to many of those
west of that stream, the names Five Tribes and Indian Territory
give wrong impressions.  Many of the Indians are such in but a
constructive sense.  Of the 86,000 who are classed as Indians only
25,000 are full bloods; 41,500 are of various shades of mixture,
most of whom would pass anywhere as pure whites; 1500 are whites
who have been adopted into the tribes through intermarriage; and
18,000 are of negro or of mixed negro blood, the slaves of the
period prior to 1865, and their descendants.  Nor are the Indians,
actual and constructive, in the majority in the Territory.  Its
white residents &mdash; immigrants from Kansas, Missouri, Texas, Illinois,
and the rest of the country &mdash; out-number the Indians, actual and
theoretical, of the Indian Territory more than five to one.
</p><p>The Five Tribes' idyllic seclusion was doomed by the entrance
of the railways on their lands.  They tried to keep the roads out,
but the pressure on the Territory's barriers on all sides was too
strong for them, and they were forced to consent to the invasion.
The first toot of the whistle of the Missouri, Kansas, and Texas
Railroad's first locomotive, speeding through the Indian Territory
in 1875 on its short-cut from the East and the world to Texas and
the Southwest, pronounced sentence of death on the red
<pb n="324"/>
man's isolation.  Like Horace's rustic on the banks of the river in
Italy, waiting for the water to roll by, the Indian watched the
stream of settlers flowing into Texas and New Mexico, but saw no
chance that it would end.  And then, wiser than the rustic, who may
be waiting yet, for all we know, the Indian bowed to manifest
destiny, and agreed to lease some of his lands.  It was
civilization marching on.
</p><p>The towns built along that railway and on the roads which
afterward entered the territory &mdash; the St. Louis and San Francisco,
the Chicago and Rock Island, the Oklahoma, Choctaw and Gulf, and
the rest of them &mdash; compelled the government at Washington to prepare
for the new necessities, and constrained the red man to accept the
inevitable.  By agreements with the Indians, supplemented by acts
of Congress, most of the obstructions to land purchases by the
whites were removed; Oklahoma in 1889, enlarged by subsequent
accretions from the same source, was set off from the Indian
Territory's westerly end; allotments of land have been made to the
Indians as individuals; the federal authority has been extended
over the territory in an elementary way; United States citizenship
has been conferred on the members of the Five Tribes; and all the
preliminaries leading to the dissolution of the tribal governments
on March 4, 1906, have been arranged.
</p><p>Necessarily the Indians have had a profound influence on the
history and the development of the American continent.  They were
never anything like as numerous as the earlier explorers and
chroniclers supposed them to be.  Within the territory comprised in
the mainland of the present United States they probably did not
number more than 600,000 or 800,000 when Columbus landed.  But they
outnumbered the whites hundreds of times in the generation
immediately after the establishment of the Jamestown and Plymouth
colonies.  Notwithstanding a few sporadic outbreaks, for which the
blame often belonged to the whites, the red man with the giant's
strength refused at the outset to use it like a giant.
</p><p>But he was a far more formidable warrior than any of the other
"inferior races" ever encountered by the empire builders of Spain,
France, England, Holland, or America.  From King Philip the
Wampanoag, down to Sitting Bull the Sioux, Chief Joseph the Nez
Perce, and Geronimo the Apache, the Indians of the United States
have produced a race of warriors unequaled by the aborigines of any
other land.  The Indian of the United States surpassed all the
other members of his race on the American continent in fighting
qualities.  Neither did the Spaniards in South America, nor the
French or the British in Canada, encounter as fierce warriors as
were met by these races and by the Americans between the Great
Lakes and the Gulf of Mexico; as fought the Spaniards in Texas, New
Mexico, and Arizona, and as blocked the way of the Americans for
many decades on the great plains and the mountains between the
Missouri and the Columbia.
</p><p>The Gentleman of Elvas and other members of the expedition
tell us of the adventures of the "Adelantado Hernando De Soto,
Governor and Captain General of the Kingdom of Florida," in his
attempt to conquer that realm for himself and for Charles V.  When
De Soto, with his men picked from the best fighting element of
Spain and Portugal, landed in what we call Tampa Bay in 1539, he
had a far larger and far better equipped army than was with Cortez
when he made the conquest of Mexico, and it was also greatly
superior in numbers, armament, and enthusiasm to the force under
Pizarro and De Soto when they overran Peru.  Experience, cupidity,
and cash, in ample measure were on the great conquistadore's side.
Nearly everything "out of doors," with all the gold that it held,
was offered to him as a lure, for the "kingdom of Florida" of
Charles V's patent to De Soto comprised all the territory between
the Gulf of Mexico and the North Pole.  The advent of the French
<pb n="325"/>
and the English in those days was far in the future.
</p><p>Yet De Soto was harried and baffled from the outset by the
ancestors, then residing in the Gulf states, of the Chickasaws,
Creeks, and the rest of the Five Tribes of the Indian Territory of
to-day.  As told in the Anabasis of the Gentleman of Elvas, the
flight of De Soto's followers in their canoes down the Great River,
after the midnight burial of their commander in its waters near the
present Memphis, pursued, ambushed, and attacked on all sides all
the way by their fierce foes, is as thrilling a tale as the retreat
of Xenophon's Ten Thousand through the Persian empire.  Many of the
elemental passions &mdash; greed, cruelty, hatred, revenge &mdash; were there.
it does not need much historical imagination on the reader's part
to tell him that the cry, "The sea!  The sea!" of that far-away
day, by the crushed remnants of the dead Adelantado's proud army of
Spanish and Portuguese hidalgos at the sight of the Gulf of Mexico,
must have been as joyful as that uttered by the Greeks nineteen
centuries earlier, when they got their first glimpse of the Euxine.
</p><p>All this would probably have been widely different had De
Soto, instead of encountering the warlike Chickasaws, Cherokees,
and their neighbors when he made his foray into the Mississippi
Valley, met the feeble followers of Montezuma or of the Incas.  In
that event Charles V might have erected another Mexico between the
Gulf and the Great Lakes; Gosnold, Newport, and Captain John Smith
would have been shut out when they approached the Chesapeake; and
Carver, Bradford, and Miles Standish would very likely have struck
a Spanish "No thoroughfare" barring the entrance to the Bay of Cape
Cod.
</p><p>When Champlain, as an ally of the Ottawas and Hurons of
Canada, fought the Mohawks at Ticonderoga in 1609, he aroused the
wrath of the "Romans of the West," the powerful confederation of
the Iroquois, or the Five Nations, as the British and Americans
called them, whose easternmost member was the Mohawk tribe.
Champlain's act put the confederation on the side of the successive
owners of New York, prevented the French in Canada, with their
feudal military system, and their long line of warlike governors,
from cutting the scattered and discordant British colonies on the
Atlantic coast in two, and saved the United States for the English-speaking peoples.
</p><p>"By the arm of St. James!" exclaimed Simon of Montfort,
proudly, when he beheld Edward and his army, all pupils of his,
advancing to crush him at the battle of Evesham, "they are coming
in a wise fashion.  They learned this from me."  "They learned this
from me!" could Tecumseh the Shawnee, the most skillful and
intrepid commander on the British side in the Canadian campaign in
the war of 1812, speaking for himself, for Little Turtle, for
Pontiac, and for other red warriors, stretching back in a long
procession to King Philip, have exultantly and truthfully
exclaimed, as "Old Tippecanoe" Harrison's Kentuckians, Virginians,
Pennsylvanians, and Ohioans were enveloping and overwhelming him at
the battle of the Thames.  With Tecumseh's death at that battle and
the killing or the scattering of his braves, British fighting in
western Canada, even for defensive purposes, collapsed.
</p><p>Long before the cant phrase "modern style of fighting" &mdash; the
open formation, individual initiative, and the use of natural
objects for cover in advancing or retreating &mdash; had been invented,
the American red man taught the American white man how to fight in
the modern way.  The real military genius of Lord Dunmore's war of
1774, which ended with the battle of Point Pleasant, was not Lewis,
Morgan, Christian, or George Rogers Clark, all famous fighters then
or later, who were on Dunmore's and the colonists' side, but
Cornstalk, the Shawnee commander, against whom they battled.  In
New Mexico and Arizona, before President Roosevelt's grandfather
<pb n="326"/>
was born, the Apache Rough Riders hit the Spaniards oftener
and harder than Roosevelt and his Tenth Legion did in Cuba.  What
the British learned in a provisional and partial way from a long
series of humiliating beatings by smaller bodies of Boers in 1899-1902, and what the Hereros' repeated defeats of the German troops
in Germany's section of Africa show that the Kaiser's soldiers have
not learned yet, the Americans had learned by Boone's day.
</p><p>In peace, too, the American Indian gained victories which
ought to be as renowned as those he won in war.  Hiawatha the
Onondaga, and Dagonoseda the Mohawk, evolved a confederation for
the Iroquois under which the affairs common to the Mohawks,
Cayugas, Oneidas, Onondagas, and Senecas were regulated, and this
went into operation over three centuries before Washington,
Hamilton, Madison, and their associates met in Philadelphia to
devise the federal scheme under which we live.  While at work in
the convention Morris, Wilson, Madison, and the rest of the
constitution framers, said much about the Amphictyonic, the Lycian,
the Achaean, the Dutch, the Swiss, and other confederacies of
ancient, medieval, and modern days, but they overlooked one that
was nearer at hand than any of them.  The League of the Iroquois,
as Jefferson wisely intimated, could have given valuable points to
the Philadelphia convention of 1787.
</p><p>While leaving their local capitals at home, their national
capital &mdash; their Philadelphia or Washington &mdash; was at Onondaga, near
the middle of the confederation's territory, where the chiefs and
other representative men of the confederation met at stated times
and managed the general concerns of the league.  This gave them
peace at home and allowed them to make effective war abroad.  They
drove out Champlain's old allies, the Hurons and Ottawas,
exterminated the Eries, brought the Algonquins into subjection, and
carried their victorious sway from New England to the Mississippi,
and from the Ottawa and the Saguenay to the Tennessee and the
Savannah.  Their power in war was due almost as much to the wisdom
of their governmental organization as it was to their activity,
intelligence, and intrepidity as fighters.  It is possible that, if
the discovery of the continent had been postponed two or three
centuries, the Kinsmen of the Long House would have dominated all
the tribes from the Great Lakes to the Gulf of Mexico, and the work
of white colonization would have been harder, or would have had to
proceed on different lines.
</p><p>The Indian has incited a distinctive and many-sided
literature, &mdash; scientific, sociological, and adventurous, &mdash; which
fills libraries in Europe and America.  More than a century ago
Charles Brockden Brown, in his <hi rend="italic">Edgar Huntley</hi>, declared that in
that book he was the first to utilize for literary purposes, the
"incidents of Indian hostility and the perils of the Western
wilderness."  He has had a long line of followers &mdash; Cooper,
Paulding, Robert Montgomery Bird, William Gilmore Simms, Captain
Mayne Reid, Emerson Bennett, and scores of others, down to Edward
S. Ellis, whose heroes in 1906 chase long-extinct buffaloes over
abolished prairies, and across whose pages scurry Indian hunters
who are as dead as the men who built the Pyramids.
</p><p>Gail Hamilton said if there never were to be any railroads it
would have been an impertinence in Columbus to have discovered
America.  The Indian's knowledge of the location and direction of
the rivers and lakes and of the positions of the portages, and his
readiness, under the right sort of persuasion, to put this
knowledge at the service of explorers, missionaries, and settlers,
"stood off" this stigma from Columbus before the railways came.
Indians guided Captain John Smith, Champlain, and La Salle through
the wilderness.  Indian trails blazed pathways for the pioneers
through forests and over mountains.  Sometimes these trails were
utilized by the railway builders.  At the Louisiana Purchase Exposition
<pb n="327"/>
at St. Louis, and at the Lewis and Clark fair at
Portland were monuments to the heroic Shoshone girl, Saccajawea,
who piloted Lewis and Clark across the Rocky Mountains and through
the wilderness on each side of that range, in their exploration to
the Pacific a century ago.
</p><p>What have been the relations of the races since the
establishment of the United States government?  One writer has said
specifically &mdash; and many have said virtually &mdash; that our treatment of
the Indians has made our record a "Century of Dishonor."  Despite
the evident sincerity of its author, this book was extravagant and
misleading.  So far as it obtained credence, its influence, on the
whole, was mischievous.  Said Jefferson, at the outset of his
service as President: "I am myself alive to the obtaining lands
from the Indians by all honest and peaceable means, and I believe
that the honest and peaceable means adopted by us will obtain them
as fast as the expansion of our settlements, with due regard to
compactness, will require."
</p><p>This has been the spirit displayed and the policy pursued by
the heads of the government, from Washington onward.  The purpose
has been to win the continent for civilization with the least
possible embarrassment to its barbaric original occupants.  In
carrying out this policy presidents and congresses have sometimes
made mistakes.  More than once they have selected incompetent or
corrupt instruments.  Blunders and crimes have occasionally been
perpetrated by these agents.  But the crimes and the blunders have
assailed the spirit and the letter of their instructions.
Moreover, these have been fewer than is popularly supposed, and all
were rectified by changes in agents and methods, while the
government's practice of the past quarter of a century has
sometimes been characterized by a generosity which has been
quixotic in its extravagance.  Through land accumulations and
investments the Osages are the richest people on the globe.  If all
of Uncle Sam's white children had as much money per capita as these
Oklahoma red men, the $112,000,000,000 which represents the wealth
of the United States in 1906 would be advanced to at least
$200,000,000,000.
</p><p>With Jefferson, just after the purchase of Louisiana,
originated the idea of transferring the Indians to the west of the
Mississippi, by an equitable exchange of the lands occupied by them
for lands in the new province, and this purpose was carried out in
1834, in Jackson's day, by the creation of the Indian Territory.
To that region were removed the Cherokees and the rest of the Five
Tribes, and there they have remained ever since.  Through
modification and expansion the Indian Territory idea generated the
reservation system for the Indians outside of the Five Tribes, and
this, though in a rapidly diminishing area, exists to-day.  The
reservation system, which was conceived in a spirit of benevolence
toward the Indian, was at length, through its free rations, its
annuities, and its idleness, found to pauperize and emasculate him;
and then began the change of policy by which he is being prepared
for citizenship.
</p><p>In the latter part of his service as President, after pointing
out that the Indians are "our brethren, our neighbors," and that
they may be valuable friends and troublesome enemies, Jefferson
said: "Both duty and interest enjoin that we should extend to them
the blessings of civilized life, and prepare their minds for
becoming useful members of the American family."
</p><p>In this, as in some other things, the third President was
ahead of his generation, but we have caught up with him.  As a
preliminary step in advance, we abolished, in 1871, the practice of
dealing with the Indians as independent nations, of sending out
embassies to negotiate with them as we would with England or
Germany, and since then Congress has had direct control of all
intercourse with the red men.  The formal treaties prior to that
day have given place to agreements, but the 370 treaties from the
founding of the government to 1871 remain as valid as
<pb n="328"/>
the eighty or ninety agreements which have been entered into between
1871 and 1906.
</p><p>To tempt the Indian into individual ownership Congress in 1862
passed an act to protect him in the enjoyment of his property if he
would abandon his tribe and live the white man's life.  As a
further incentive Congress in 1875 passed a law to give him a share
of his tribe's property if he would give up the tribe and settle on
a quarter section of land under the free homes law signed by
Lincoln in 1862.  In 1877 an act was passed making appropriations
to educate Indians for citizenship, and in 1887 one granting
citizenship to all Indians who, separated from their tribes,
accepted lands in severalty, and adopted civilized life.  This act
was extended to the Five Tribes of the Indian Territory in 1901,
and thus covered all the red men in the United States.
</p><p>From 1789 to the end of the current fiscal year on June 30,
1906, the government will have expended $420,000,000 for the
Indians, and, in greater part, this means for those outside of the
Five Tribes, who have been practically self-supporting in all their
activities for two generations, except that in recent years
Congress has been making small appropriations for them for
educational and other purposes.  The Indian appropriation bill for
1906 carried an outlay of $8,000,000, of which $3,777,000 was for
the support of schools, and all this was for the Indians outside of
the Five Tribes, of those in New York (whose schools are controlled
by that state), and of Alaska.  Congress's appropriation for
education in 1877, when this policy started was $20,000.
</p><p>What use is the Indian making of his opportunities?  Let these
facts answer.  Outside of those in the Five Tribes, in New York,
and in Alaska, 30,000 Indians are attending school, or one out of
every six of the population.  Of these, 26,000 are in the
government's 257 schools, and 4000 are in schools supported by
churches or by contracts with the government.  Civilized clothes
are worn wholly by 116,000 Indians, and are worn partly by 44,000;
nearly all of these reside in dwelling-houses; 70,000 talk English
enough for ordinary purposes, and most of them can read it; and
40,000 are members of churches.
</p><p>In the Five Tribes, of course, and among the Indians of New
York, all wear the garb of civilization, all have good school
facilities, all dwell in the same sort of habitations as white men,
and most of them, either actually or theoretically, belong to some
Christian denomination.  Only 26,000 blanket Indians are left in
the United States.  Since 1877 the Indians, under the common-sense
tutelage given to them, have made more progress than the whites
ever did in any equal time.  Under the improved sanitary
conditions, too, and in the absence of wars, they are steadily
increasing in numbers.
</p><p>Both out of and in the Indian Territory the Indian has at
least ceased to be
<lb/>
<q><lg type="section"><l>An infant crying in the night;</l>
<l>An infant crying for the light,</l>
<l>And with no language but a cry.</l></lg></q>
</p><p>In the division of the turkey and the buzzard the white man,
in his deals with his red brother, can no longer shove off the
buzzard on all of the red men all of the time.  There are
politicians among the Five Tribes who, in the tricks of the trade,
have nothing valuable to learn from Murphy, Platt, Gorman, or any
other boss.  Lobbies are set up by them at Washington.  They pack
caucuses at Tahlequah, South McAlester and Chickasha.  Coming to
politics of a higher order, they frame constitutions, as they did
in the latter part of 1905, under the leadership of Pleasant
Porter, the chief of the Creeks, &mdash; who is a more astute personage
than was his famous Machiavellian precursor.  McGillivray, of the
Creek nation of a century ago, &mdash; for the proposed state of Sequoyah,
comprising the Indian Territory.
</p><p>Nobody in or out of the Indian Territory is saying that Green
McCurtain, chief of the Choctaws, or Douglas H. Johnston, governor
of the Chickasaws
<pb n="329"/>
(alone among the Five Tribes the Chickasaws call their head man
governor), is as picturesque a personage as were their forerunners who
fought De Soto and who blocked the path of Bienville and his French
successors; nor will John Brown, the Seminole chief of to-day, hold such a
large place in story as that filled by Osceola; while Edward VII is not likely
to invite William C. Rogers, of the Cherokees, to England to talk
great matters of state, as George III did Rogers's illustrious
precursor, Oganasdoda.  All these dignitaries, however, are meeting
the demands of the situation better probably than could their
predecessors, if they were here.
</p><p>Warlike deeds make a more seductive appeal to the popular
fancy than the exploits of peace, and no great Indian wars have
taken place since Geronimo and Natchez, the Apache chiefs, led
Crook, Miles, and other fighters through Arizona's deserts and
hills in the campaigns of 1882-86, which resulted in Geronimo's
overthrow; except the rising of the Sioux at Pine Ridge, South
Dakota, in 1889-90, on the report of the approach of a conquering
Indian Messiah; and that conflict, in which Sitting Bull was
killed, lasted only a few weeks.  And, of course, nothing like this
can take place again.
</p><p>The visitor to the Indian Territory in 1906 has more exercise
in dodging automobiles and electric cars than he has in getting out
of the way of arrows, bullets, or lassos.  The only feathered
headdresses which he sees are in women's hats on shopping tours or
on the way to balls or theatres.  The Territory has 1500 miles of
railway, and 1000 miles more are projected.  It has churches,
schools, banks, newspapers (one of them in the Cherokee language),
and all the other accompaniments of the highest order of
civilization.  Ardmore, Muscogee, South McAlester, Tahlequah,
Coalgate, Chickasha, and other towns of the Territory, are as
modern in their ideas and their appointments as are places of the
same size in Massachusetts or New York.
</p><p>Tibet and Korea lagged behind, and were removed from the map.
In the world's economy of to-day there is no room for hermit
nations.  The Seminoles, Cherokees, and their neighbors of the
Indian Territory have bowed to this decree of destiny.  If the
Indian, out of as well as in the Indian Territory, is capable, he
will keep his place in the procession, but with him or over him the
procession will move on.
</p><p>There is a fair prospect that the Indian will keep his place
in the procession.  The Carlisle school's football players have
recently beaten West Point, and they have often defeated other
white colleges.  A basket-ball team of full-blooded Indian girls
from the Fort Shaw (Montana) reservation school have, in playing
that game, taken a long string of feminine scalps from the girls of
white universities in the West.  The educated red men are
displaying a camaraderie and an adaptability to the new conditions
which promise success to them in civilization's struggle.  One or
more of them will represent their end of the coming state of
Oklahoma in Congress.  This is right.  They are to the manner born.
The real F. F. A.'s are the Indians.  Some of them, in the coming
time, will sit in Roosevelt's chair.
</p><p>Three quarters of a century ago, at the time that the
Cherokees moved from Georgia to their present locality, the region
west of the Missouri was about as blank as that referred to by
Swift, when
<lb/>
<q><lg type="section"><l>Geographers, in Afric maps,</l>
<l>With savage pictures fill their gaps,</l>
<l>And o'er unhabitable downs</l>
<l>Place elephants for want of towns.</l></lg></q>
</p>
<p>On the maps of that day the whole expanse from the westerly border
of Arkansas, Missouri, and the present states of Iowa and
Minnesota, to the Rocky Mountains, the boundary of the United
States in that quarter, was designated "The Indian Country."  All
that wilderness has since then been organized into states, except
Oklahoma and the Indian Territory, and they are about to join the
roll.
</p>
<pb n="330"/>

<p>Down in the foothills of the Wichita Mountains of Oklahoma the
Comanches' Epictetus, the aged Quanah Parker, discourses philosophy
and stoically awaits the end.  Like the Moorish king Abu Abdallah,
looking mournfully backward at his lost Granada, Geronimo, from
Fort Sill, gazes westward across prairies and hills to the Arizona
of his great days, which he will not see again.  Up at Pine Ridge
agency the Sioux nonogenarian Red Cloud, the most famous of living
Indian warriors, who could tell as many marvels as AEneas told to
Dido, refuses to accept the government's offer of an allotment of
land, and goes down, like Dickens's Steerforth in the storm at
Yarmouth, waving his hand defiantly in the face of destiny.
</p><p>Most of Hercules's labors looked light compared with the task
which the late Henry L. Dawes undertook when he and the commission
created under the law of 1893 started out to induce the Choctaws,
the Creeks, and their neighbors to allot their lands to their
members as individuals, to abolish their tribal government, and to
merge themselves in the mass of the country's citizenship.  That
work has been grandly finished.  The last councils of the Five
Tribes have been held.  The epic of the American Indian has closed.
</p>

</div1>
</body>
</text>
</TEI.2>
