<?xml version="1.0"?>

<?dlps id="HarVirg"?>
<?dlps page-images="none" figure-images="no"?>
<?dlps transcription="other"?>

<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/tei-p4/tei2.dtd" [
<!ENTITY % POSTKB "INCLUDE">
<!ENTITY % TEI.extensions.ent SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.ent">
<!ENTITY % TEI.extensions.dtd SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.dtd">
<!ENTITY % ISOnum SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/charent/iso-num.ent"> %ISOnum;
<!ENTITY % ISOpub SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/charent/iso-pub.ent"> %ISOpub;
]>

<TEI.2 id="HarVirg">
<teiHeader type="migrated" creator="Etext">
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title type="main">A Virginia Girl in the First Year of the War.</title>
<title type="sort">virginia girl in the first year of the war</title>
<author>Harrison, C. C.</author>
<respStmt>
<resp>Creation of machine-readable version:</resp>
<name>Judy Boss</name>
<resp>Creation of digital images:</resp>
<name>creator of image(s)</name>
<resp>Conversion to TEI.2-conformant markup:</resp>
<name>University of Virginia Library Electronic Text Center</name>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt>
<extent>ca. <num type="kilobytes">47</num> kilobytes</extent>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>University of Virginia Library</publisher>
<pubPlace>Charlottesville, Virginia</pubPlace>
<idno type="ETC">HarVirg</idno>
<date value="1996">1996</date>
<availability status="public">
<p n="copyright">Copyright &copy; 1996 by the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia</p>
<p n="access">Publicly accessible</p>
</availability>
<idno type="uva-pid">uva-lib:476030</idno>
</publicationStmt>
<seriesStmt>
<title>University of Virginia Library, Text collection</title>
<idno type="uva-set">UVA-LIB-Text</idno>
</seriesStmt>
<sourceDesc>
<biblFull>
<titleStmt>
<title type="main">"A Virginia Girl in the First Year of the War.</title>
<title type="sort">a virginia girl in the first year of the war</title>
<author>Harrison, C. C.</author>
</titleStmt>
<publicationStmt>
<date value="1885">1885</date>
</publicationStmt>
<seriesStmt>
<p>Century Magazine 30 (Aug. 1885): 606-614.</p>
</seriesStmt>
<notesStmt>
<note>
<p>Some dialect present, e.g. "coase" for course, "rig'ment" for regiment,
"kivered tharselves" for covered themselves, "sorter yarnin' arter" for sort of yearning after,
etc.</p>
</note>
</notesStmt>
</biblFull>
</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc>
<encodingDesc>
<projectDesc>
<p>Prepared for the University of Virginia Library Electronic Text Center</p>
</projectDesc>
<editorialDecl>
<p>All quotation marks retained as data</p>
<p>All unambiguous end-of-line hyphens have been removed, and the
trailing part of a word has been joined to the preceding line.</p>
<p id="ETC">Keywords in the header are a local Electronic Text Center scheme
to aid in establishing analytical groupings</p>
</editorialDecl>
<refsDecl>
<p>ID elements are given for each page element and are composed of the text's
unique cryptogram and the given page number, as in AusEmma1 for page one of
Jane Austen's Emma.</p>
</refsDecl>
</encodingDesc>
<profileDesc>
<creation>
<date value="1885">1885</date>
</creation>
<langUsage>
<language id="eng" usage="main">English</language>
</langUsage>
<textClass>
<keywords>
<term>non-fiction; prose</term>
<term>American Civil War</term>
<term>Women Writers</term>
</keywords>
</textClass>
</profileDesc>
<revisionDesc>
<change>
<date value="1996-03">Mar. 1996</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>corrector</resp>
<name>Jan Horner</name>
</respStmt>
<item>TEI header &amp; footer added. Page coding corrected.</item>
</change>
<change>
<date value="2005-07">July 2005</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>Corrector</resp>
<name>John Ivor Carlson</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Converted SGML to XML. Fixed tagging.</item>
</change>
<change>
<date value="2007-09">September 2007</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>Migration</resp>
<name>Ethan Gruber, University of Virginia Library</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Converted XML markup from TEI Lite to uva-dl-tei (TEI P4 with local customizations).</item>
</change>
<change>
<date value="2008-01">January 2008</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>Migration</resp>
<name>Greg Murray, University of Virginia Library</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Programmatically updated TEI header markup (but not header content) for minimal compliance with current QA requirements.</item>
</change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text id="d1">
<body id="d2">


<div1 type="essay" id="d3"><pb n="606"/>
<head>A VIRGINIA GIRL IN THE FIRST YEAR OF THE WAR.</head>

<p>THE only association I have with my old home in Virginia that is
not one of unmixed happiness relates to the time immediately
succeeding the execution of John Brown at Harper's Ferry.  Our
homestead was in Fairfax, at a considerable distance from the
theater of that tragic episode; and, belonging as we did to a
family among the first in the State to manumit slaves&mdash;our
grandfather having set free those which came to him by inheritance,
and the people who served us being hired from their owners and
remaining in our employ through years of kindliest relations&mdash;there
seemed to be no especial reason for us to share in the apprehension
of an uprising by the blacks.  But there was the fear&mdash;unspoken, or
pooh-poohed at by the men who served as mouth-pieces for our
community&mdash;dark, boding, oppressive, and altogether hateful.  I can
remember taking it to bed with me at night, and awaking suddenly
oftentimes to confront it through a vigil of nervous terror of
which it never occurred to me to speak to any one.  The notes of
whip-poor-wills in the sweet-gum swamp near the stable, the
mutterings of a distant thunder-storm, even the rustle of the night
wind in the oaks that shaded my window, filled me with nameless
dread.  In the day-time it seemed impossible to associate suspicion
with those familiar tawny or sable faces that surrounded us.  We
had seen them for so many years smiling or saddening with the
family joys or sorrows; they were so guileless, so patient, so
satisfied.  What subtle influence was at work that should transform
them into tigers thirsting for our blood?  The idea was
preposterous.  But when evening came again, and with it the hour
when the colored people (who in summer and autumn weather kept
astir half the night) assembled themselves together for dance or
prayer-meeting, the ghost that refused to be laid was again at
one's elbow.  Rusty bolts were drawn and rusty fire-arms loaded.
A watch was set where never before had eye or ear been lent to such
a service.  Peace, in short, had flown from the borders of
Virginia.
</p><p>I cannot remember that, as late as Christmas-time of the year
1860, although the newspapers were full of secession talk and the
matter was eagerly discussed at our tables, coming events had cast
any positive shadow on our homes.  The people in our neighborhood,
of one opinion with their dear and honored friend, Colonel Robert
E. Lee, of Arlington, were slow to accept the startling suggestion
of disruption of the Union.  At any rate, we enjoyed the usual
holiday gathering of kinsfolk in the usual fashion.
</p>

<pb n="607"/>
<p>
The old Vaucluse house, known for many years past as the center of
cheerful hospitality in the county, threw wide open its doors to
receive all the members who could be gathered there of a large
family circle.  The woods around were despoiled of holly and
spruce, pine and cedar, to deck the walls and wreathe the picture-frames.  On Christmas Eve we had a grand rally of youths and boys
belonging to the "clan," as they loved to call it, to roll in a
yule log, which was deposited upon a glowing bed of coals in the
big "red parlor" fire-place, and sit around it afterwards,
welcoming the Christmas in with goblets of egg-nog and apple-toddy.
</p><p>"Where shall we be a year hence?" some one asked at a pause in
the merry chat; and, in the brief silence that followed, arose a
sudden spectral thought of war.  All felt its presence; no one
cared to speak first of the grim possibilities it projected on the
canvas of the future.
</p><p>On Christmas Eve of the following year the old house lay in
ruins, a sacrifice to military necessity; the forest giants that
kept watch around her walls had been cut down and made to serve as
breastworks for a fort erected on the Vaucluse property, but
afterwards abandoned.  Of the young men and boys who took part in
that holiday festivity, all were in active service of the South,&mdash;
one of them, alas! soon to fall under a rain of shot and shell
beside his gun at Fredericksburg; the youngest of the number had
left his mother's knee to fight in the battles of Manassas, and
found himself, before the year was out, a midshipman aboard the
Confederate steamer <hi rend="italic">Nashville</hi>, on her cruise in distant
seas!
</p><p>My first vivid impression of war-days was during a ramble in
the woods around our place one Sunday afternoon in spring, when the
young people in a happy band set out in search of wild flowers.
Pink honeysuckles, blue lupine, beds of fairy flax, anemones, and
ferns in abundance sprung under the canopy of young leaves on the
forest boughs, and the air was full of the song of birds and the
music of running waters.  We knew every mossy path far and near in
these woods, every tree had been watched and cherished by those who
went before us, and dearer than any other spot on earth was our
tranquil, sweet Vaucluse.  Suddenly the shrill whistle of a
locomotive struck the ear, an unwonted sound on Sunday.  "Do you
know what that means?" said one of the older cousins who
accompanied the party.  "It is the special train carrying
Alexandria volunteers to Manassas, and to-morrow I shall follow
with my company."  An awe-struck silence fell upon our little band.
A cloud seemed to come between us and the sun.  It was the
beginning of the end too soon to come.
</p><p>The story of one broken circle is the story of another at the
outset of such a war.  Before the week was over, the scattering of
our household, which no one then believed to be more than
temporary, had begun.  Living as we did upon ground likely to be in
the track of armies gathering to confront each other, it was deemed
advisable to send the children and young girls into a place more
remote from chances of danger.  Some weeks later the heads of the
household, two widowed sisters, whose sons were at Manassas, drove
in their carriage at early morning, away from their home, having
spent the previous night in company with a half-grown lad digging
in the cellar hasty graves for the interment of two boxes of old
English silver-ware, heirlooms in the family, for which there was
no time to provide otherwise.  Although troops were long encamped
immediately above it after the house was burnt the following year,
this silver was found when the war had ended, lying loose in the
earth, the boxes having rotted from around it.
</p><p>The point at which our family reunited within Confederate
lines was Bristoe, the station next beyond Manassas, a cheerless
railway inn; a part of the premises was used as a country grocery;
and there quarters were secured for us with a view to being near
the army, a few miles distant.  By this time all our kith and kin
of fighting age had joined the volunteers.  One cannot picture
accommodations more forlorn than these eagerly taken for us and for
other families attracted to Bristoe by the same powerful magnet.
The summer sun poured its burning rays upon whitewashed walls
unshaded by a tree.  Our bedrooms were almost uninhabitable by day
or night, our fare the plainest.  From the windows we beheld only
a flat, uncultivated country, crossed by red-clay roads, then knee-deep in dust.  We learned to look for all excitement to the
glittering lines of railway track, along which continually
thundered trains bound to and from the front.  It was impossible to
allow such a train to pass without running out upon the platform to
salute it, for in this way we greeted many an old friend or
relative buttoned up in the smart gray uniform, speeding with high
hope to the scene of coming conflict.  Such shouts as went up from
sturdy throats when the locomotive moved on after the last stop
before Manassas, while we stood waving hands, handkerchiefs, or the
rough woolen garments we were at work upon!  Then fairly awoke the
spirit that made of Southern women the inspiration of Southern

<pb n="608"/>

men for the war.  Most of the young fellows we were
cheering onward wore the uniform of privates, and for the right to
wear it had left homes of ease and luxury.  To such we gave our
best homage; and from that time forth, during the four years
succeeding, the youth who was lukewarm in the cause or unambitious
of military glory fared uncomfortably in the presence of the
average Confederate maiden.
</p><p>Thanks to our own carriage, we were able during those rallying
days of June to drive frequently to visit our boys in camp, timing
the expeditions to include battalion drill and dress parade, and
taking tea afterwards in the different tents.  Then were the gala
days of war, and our proud hosts hastened to produce home dainties
dispatched from the far-away plantations&mdash;tears and blessings
interspersed amid the packing, we were sure; though I have seen a
pretty girl persist in declining other fare, to make her meal upon
raw biscuit and huckleberry pie compounded by the bright-eyed
amateur cook of a well-beloved mess.  Feminine heroism could no
farther go.
</p><p>And so the days wore on until the 17th of July, when a rumor
from the front sent an electric shock through our circle.  The
enemy were moving forward!  On the morning of the 18th those who
had been able to sleep at all awoke early to listen for the first
guns of the engagement of Blackburn's Ford.  Abandoned as the women
at Bristoe were by every masculine creature old enough to gather
news, there was, for them, no way of knowing the progress of events
during the long, long day of waiting, of watching, of weeping, of
praying, of rushing out upon the railway track to walk as far as
they dared in the direction whence came that intolerable booming of
artillery.  The cloud of dun smoke arising over Manassas became
heavier in volume as the day progressed.  Still, not a word of
tidings, till towards afternoon there came limping up a single,
very dirty soldier with his arm in a sling.  What a heaven-send he
was, if only as an escape-valve for our pent-up sympathies!  We
seized him, we washed him, we cried over him, we glorified him
until the man was fairly bewildered.  Our best endeavors could only
develop a pin-scratch of a wound on his right hand; but when our
hero had laid in a substantial meal of bread and meat, we plied him
with trembling questions, each asking news of some staff or
regiment or company.  It has since occurred to me that this first
arrival from the field was a humorist in disguise.  His invariable
reply, as he looked from one to the other of his satellites, was:
"The&mdash;Virginia, marm?  Why, of coase.  They warn't no two ways o'
thinkin' 'bout that ar rig'ment.  They just <hi rend="italic">kivered</hi>
tharselves with glory!"
</p><p>A little later two wagon-loads of slightly wounded claimed our
care, and with them came authentic news of the day.  Most of us
received notes on paper torn from a soldier's pocket-book and
grimed with gunpowder, containing assurance of the safety of our
own.  At nightfall a train carrying more wounded to the hospitals
at Culpeper made a halt at Bristoe; and, preceded by men holding
lanterns, we went in among the stretchers with milk, food, and
water to the sufferers.  One of the first discoveries I made,
bending over in that fitful light, was a young officer I knew to be
a special object of solicitude with one of my fair comrades in the
search; but he was badly hurt, and neither he nor she knew the
other was near until the train had moved on.  The next day, and the
next, were full of burning excitement over the impending general
engagement, which people then said would decide the fate of the
young Confederacy.  Fresh troops came by with every train, and we
lived only to turn from one scene to another of welcome and
farewell.  On Saturday evening arrived a message from General
Beauregard, saying that early on Sunday an engine and car would be
put at our disposal, to take us to some point more remote from
danger.  We looked at one another, and, tacitly agreeing that the
gallant general had sent not an order, but a suggestion, declined
his kind proposal.
</p><p>Another unspeakably long day, full of the straining anguish of
suspense.  Dawning bright and fair, it closed under a sky darkened
by cannon-smoke.  The roar of guns seemed never to cease.  First,
a long sullen boom; then a sharper rattling fire, painfully
distinct; then stragglers from the field, with varying rumors.  At
last, the news of victory; and, as before, the wounded, to force
our numbed faculties into service.  One of our group, the mother of
an only son barely fifteen years of age, heard that her boy, after
being in action all the early part of the day, had through sheer
fatigue fallen asleep upon the ground, where his officers had found
him, resting peacefully amidst the roar of the guns, and whence
they had brought him off, unharmed.  A few days later we rode on
horseback over the field of the momentous fight.  The trampled
grass had begun to spring again, and wild flowers were blooming
around carelessly made graves.  From one of these imperfect mounds
of clay I saw a hand extended; and when, years afterwards, I
visited the tomb of Rousseau beneath the Pantheon in Paris, where
a sculptured hand bearing a torch protrudes from the sarcophagus,
I thought of that mournful

<pb n="609"/>
spectacle upon the field of
Manassas.  Fences were everywhere thrown down; the undergrowth of
the woods was riddled with shot; here and there we came upon spiked
guns, disabled gun-carriages, cannon-balls, blood-stained blankets,
and dead horses.  We were glad enough to turn away and gallop
homeward.
</p><p>With August heats and lack of water, Bristoe was forsaken for
quarters near Culpeper, where my mother went into the soldiers'
barracks, sharing soldiers' accommodations, to nurse the wounded.
In September quite a party of us, upon invitation, visited the
different headquarters.  We stopped overnight at Manassas, five
ladies, sleeping in a tent guarded by a faithful sentry, upon a
couch made of rolls of cartridge-flannel.  I remember the comical
effect of the five bird-cages (an article without which no self-respecting female of that day would present herself in public)
suspended upon a line running across the upper part of our tent,
after we had reluctantly removed them in order to adjust ourselves
for repose.  Our progress during that memorable visit was royal; an
ambulance with a picked troop of cavalrymen had been placed at our
service, and the convoy was "personally conducted" by a pleasing
variety of distinguished officers.  It was at this time, after a
supper at the headquarters of the "Maryland line" at Fairfax, that
the afterwards universal war-song, "My Maryland," was set afloat
upon the tide of army favor.  We were sitting outside a tent in the
warm starlight of an early autumn night, when music was proposed.
At once we struck up Randall's verses to the tune of the old
college song, "Lauriger Horatius,"&mdash;a young lady of the party from
Maryland, a cousin of ours, having recently set them to this music
before leaving home to share the fortunes of the Confederacy.  All
joined in the ringing chorus, and when we finished a burst of
applause came from some soldiers listening in the darkness behind
a belt of trees.  Next day the melody was hummed far and near
through the camps, and in due time it had gained and held the place
of favorite song in the army.  No doubt the hand-organs would have
gotten hold of it; but, from first to last during the continuance
of the Confederacy, those cheerful instruments of torture were
missing.  (I hesitate to mention this fact, lest it prove an
incentive to other nations to go to war.)  Other songs sung that
evening, which afterwards had a great vogue, were one beginning "By
blue Patapsco's billowy dash," arranged by us to an air from
"Puritani," and shouted lustily, and "The years glide slowly by,
Lorena," a ditty having a queer little quavering triplet in the
heroine's name that served as a pitfall to the unwary singer.
"Stonewall Jackson's Way" came on the scene afterwards, later in
the war.  Another incident of note, in personal experience during
the autumn of '61, was that to two of my cousins and to me was
intrusted the making of the first three battle-flags of the
Confederacy, directly after Congress had decided upon a design for
them.  They were jaunty squares of scarlet crossed with dark blue,
the cross bearing stars to indicate the number of the seceding
States.  We set our best stitches upon them, edged them with golden
fringes, and when they were finished dispatched one to Johnston,
another to Beauregard, and the third to Earl Van Dorn,&mdash;the latter
afterwards a dashing cavalry leader, but then commanding infantry
at Manassas.  The banners were received with all the enthusiasm we
could have hoped for; were toasted, feted, cheered abundantly.
After two years, when Van Dorn had been killed in Tennessee, mine
came back to me, tattered and smoke-stained from long and honorable
service in the field.  But it was only a little while after it had
been bestowed that there arrived one day at our lodgings in
Culpeper a huge, bashful Mississippi scout,&mdash;one of the most daring
in the army,&mdash;with the frame of a Hercules and the face of a child.
He was bidden to come there by his general, he said, to ask if I
would not give him an order to fetch some cherished object from my
dear old home&mdash;something that would prove to me "how much they
thought of the maker of that flag!"  After some hesitation I
acquiesced, although thinking it a jest.  A week later I was the
astonished recipient of a lamented bit of finery left "within the
lines," a wrap of white and azure, brought to us by Dillon himself,
with a beaming face.  He had gone through the Union pickets mounted
on a load of fire-wood, and while peddling poultry had presented
himself at our town house, whence he carried off his prize in
triumph, with a letter in its folds telling us how relatives left
behind longed to be sharing the joys and sorrows of those at large
in the Confederacy.
</p><p>The first winter of the war was spent by our family in
Richmond, where we found lodgings in a dismal rookery familiarly
dubbed by its new occupants "The Castle of Otranto."  It was the
old-time Clifton Hotel, honeycombed by subterranean passages, and
crowded to its limits by refugees like ourselves from country homes
within or near the enemy's lines&mdash;or "'fugees," as we were all
called.  For want of any common sitting-room, we took possession of
what had been a doctor's office, a few steps distant down the hilly
street, fitting it up to the best of our ability; and there we
received

<pb n="610"/>
our friends, passing many merry hours.  In rainy
weather we reached it by an underground passageway from the hotel,
an alley through the catacombs; and many a dignitary of camp or
state will recall those "Clifton" evenings.  Already the pinch of
war was felt in the commissariat; and we had recourse occasionally
to a contribution supper, or "Dutch treat," when the guests brought
brandied peaches, boxes of sardines, French prunes, and bags of
biscuit, while the hosts contributed only a roast turkey or a ham,
with knives and forks.  Democratic feasts those were, where major-generals and "high privates" met on an equal footing.  The
hospitable old town was crowded with the families of officers and
members of the Government.  One house was made to do the work of
several, many of the wealthy citizens generously giving up their
superfluous space to receive the new-comers.  The only public event
of note was the inauguration of Mr. Davis as President of the
"Permanent Government" of the Confederate States, which we viewed,
by the courtesy of Mr. John R. Thompson, the State Librarian, from
one of the windows of the Capitol, where, while waiting for the
exercises to begin, we read "Harper's Weekly" and other Northern
papers, the latest per underground express.  That 22d of February
was a day of pouring rain, and the concourse of umbrellas in the
square beneath us had the effect of an immense mushroom-bed.  As
the bishop and the President-elect came upon the stand, there was
an almost painful hush in the crowd.  All seemed to feel the
gravity of the trust our chosen leader was assuming.  When he
kissed the Book a shout went up; but there was no elation visible
as the people slowly dispersed.  And it was thought ominous
afterwards, when the story was repeated, that, as Mrs. Davis, who
had a Virginia negro for coachman, was driven to the inauguration,
she observed the carriage went at a snail's pace and was escorted
by four negro men in black clothes, wearing white cotton gloves and
walking solemnly, two on either side of the equipage; she asked the
coachman what such a spectacle could mean, and was answered, "Well,
ma'am, you tole me to arrange everything as it should be; and this
is the way we do in Richmon' at funerals and sich-like."  Mrs.
Davis promptly ordered the outwalkers away, and with them departed
all the pomp and circumstance the occasion admitted of.  In the
mind of a negro, everything of dignified ceremonial is always
associated with a funeral!
</p><p>About March 1st martial law was proclaimed in Richmond, and a
fresh influx of refugees from Norfolk claimed shelter there.  When
the spring opened, as the spring does open in Richmond, with a
sudden glory of green leaves, magnolia blooms, and flowers among
the grass, our spirits rose after the depression of the latter
months.  If only to shake off the atmosphere of doubts and fears
engendered by the long winter of disaster and uncertainty, the
coming activity of arms was welcome!  Personally speaking, there
was vast improvement in our situation, since we had been fortunate
enough to find a real home in a pleasant brown-walled house on
Franklin street, divided from the pavement by a garden full of
bounteous greenery, where it was easy to forget the discomforts of
our previous mode of life.  I shall not attempt to describe the
rapidity with which thrilling excitements succeeded each other in
our experiences in this house.  The gathering of many troops around
the town filled the streets with a continually moving panorama of
war, and we spent our time in greeting, cheering, choking with
sudden emotion, and quivering in anticipation of what was yet to
follow.  We had now finished other battle-flags begun by way of
patriotic handiwork, and one of them was bestowed upon the
"Washington Artillery" of New Orleans, a body of admirable soldiers
who had wakened to enthusiasm the daughters of Virginia in
proportion, I dare say, to the woe they had created among the
daughters of Louisiana in bidding them good-bye.  One morning an
orderly arrived to request that the ladies would be out upon the
veranda at a given hour; and, punctual to the time fixed, the
travel-stained battalion filed past our house.  These were no
holiday soldiers.  Their gold was tarnished and their scarlet faded
by sun and wind and gallant service&mdash;they were veterans now on
their way to the front, where the call of duty never failed to find
the flower of Louisiana.  As they came in line with us, the
officers saluted with their swords, the band struck up "My
Maryland," the tired soldiers sitting upon the caissons that
dragged heavily through the muddy street set up a rousing cheer.
And there in the midst of them, taking the April wind with daring
color, was our flag, dipping low until it passed us.
</p><p>Well! one must grow old and cold indeed before such things are
forgotten.
</p><p>A few days later, on coming out of church&mdash;it is a curious
fact that most of our exciting news spread over Richmond on Sunday,
and just at that hour&mdash;we heard of the crushing blow of the fall of
New Orleans and the destruction of our ironclads; my brother had
just reported aboard one of those splendid ships, as yet
unfinished.  As the news came directly from our kinsman, General
Randolph, the Secretary of War, there was no

<pb n="611"/>
doubting it;
and while the rest of us broke into lamentation, Mr. Jules de St.
Martin, the brother-in-law of Mr. Benjamin, merely shrugged his
shoulders, with a thoroughly characteristic gesture, making no
remark.
</p><p>"This must affect your interests," some one said to him
inquiringly.
</p><p>"I am ruined, <hi rend="italic">voila tout!"</hi> was the rejoinder&mdash;a fact
too soon confirmed.
</p><p>This debonair little gentleman was one of the greatest
favorites of our war society in Richmond.  His cheerfulness, his
wit, his exquisite courtesy, made him friends everywhere; and
although his nicety of dress, after the pattern of the
<hi rend="italic">boulevardier fini</hi> of Paris, was the subject of much
wonderment to the populace when he first appeared upon the streets,
it did not prevent him from going promptly to join the volunteers
before Richmond when occasion called, and roughing it in the
trenches like a veteran.  His cheerful endurance of hardship during
a freezing winter of camp life became a proverb in the army later
in the siege.
</p><p>For a time nothing was talked of but the capture of New
Orleans.  Of the midshipman brother we heard that on the day
previous to the taking of the forts, after several days'
bombardment, by the United States fleet under Flag-Officer
Farragut, he had been sent in charge of ordnance and deserters to
a Confederate vessel in the river; that Lieutenant R&mdash;, a friend
of his, on the way to report at Fort Jackson during the hot
shelling, had invited the lad to accompany him by way of a pleasure
trip; that while they were crossing the moat around Fort Jackson,
in a canoe, and under heavy fire, a thirteen-inch mortar-shell had
struck the water near, half filling their craft; and that, after
watching the fire from this point for an hour, C&mdash; had pulled
back again alone, against the Mississippi current, under fire for
a mile and a half of the way&mdash;passing an astonished alligator who
had been hit on the head by a piece of shell and was dying under
protest.  Thus ended a trip alluded to by C&mdash; twenty years later
as an example of juvenile foolhardiness, soundly deserving
punishment.
</p><p>Aboard the steamship <hi rend="italic">Star of the West</hi>, next day, he and
other midshipmen in charge of millions of gold and silver coin from
the mint and banks of New Orleans, and millions more of paper
money, over which they were ordered to keep guard with drawn
swords, hurried away from the doomed city, where the enemy's
arrival was momentarily expected, and where the burning ships and
steamers and bales of cotton along the levee made a huge crescent
of fire.  Keeping just ahead of the enemy's fleet, they reached
Vicksburg, and thence went overland to Mobile, where their charge
was given up in safety.
</p><p>And now we come to the 31st of May, 1862, when the eyes of the
whole continent turned to Richmond.  On that day Johnston assaulted
the portion of McClellan's troops which had been advanced to the
south side of the Chickahominy, and had there been cut off from the
main body of the army by the sudden rise of the river, occasioned
by a tremendous thunder-storm.  In face of recent reverses, we in
Richmond had begun to feel like the prisoner of the Inquisition in
Poe's story, cast into a dungeon with slowly contracting walls.
With the sound of guns, therefore, in the direction of Seven Pines,
every heart leaped as if deliverance were at hand.  And yet there
was no joy in the wild pulsation, since those to whom we looked for
succor were our own flesh and blood, standing shoulder to shoulder
to bar the way to a foe of superior numbers, abundantly provided as
we were not with all the equipments of modern warfare, and backed
by a mighty nation as determined as ourselves to win.  Hardly a
family in the town whose father, son, or brother was not part and
parcel of the defending army.
</p><p>When on the afternoon of the 31st it became known that the
engagement had begun, the women of Richmond were still going about
their daily vocations quietly, giving no sign of the inward anguish
of apprehension.  There was enough to do now in preparation for the
wounded; yet, as events proved, all that was done was not enough by
half.  Night brought a lull in the cannonading.  People lay down
dressed upon their beds, but not to sleep, while their weary
soldiers slept upon their arms.  Early next morning the whole town
was on the street.  Ambulances, litters, carts, every vehicle that
the city could produce, went and came with a ghastly burden; those
who could walk limped painfully home, in some cases so black with
gunpowder they passed unrecognized.  Women with pallid faces
flitted bareheaded through the streets, searching for their dead or
wounded.  The churches were thrown open, many people visiting them
for a sad communion-service or brief time of prayer; the lecture-rooms of various places of worship were crowded with ladies
volunteering to sew, as fast as fingers and machines could fly, the
rough beds called for by the surgeons.  Men too old or infirm to
fight went on horseback or afoot to meet the returning ambulances,
and in some cases served as escort to their own dying sons.  By
afternoon of the day following the battle, the streets were one
vast hospital.  To find shelter for the sufferers a number of
unused buildings were thrown open.  I remember, especially,

<pb n="612"/>
the St. Charles Hotel, a gloomy place, where two young girls went
to look for a member of their family, reported wounded.  We had
tramped in vain over pavements burning with the intensity of the
sun, from one scene of horror to another, until our feet and brains
alike seemed about to serve us no further.  The cool of those vast
dreary rooms of the St. Charles was refreshing; but such a
spectacle!  Men in every stage of mutilation lying on the bare
boards with perhaps a haversack or an army blanket beneath their
heads,&mdash;some dying, all suffering keenly, while waiting their turn
to be attended to.  To be there empty-handed and impotent nearly
broke our hearts.  We passed from one to the other, making such
slight additions to their comfort as were possible, while looking
in every upturned face in dread to find the object of our search.
This sorrow, I may add, was spared, the youth arriving at home
later with a slight flesh-wound.  The condition of things at this
and other improvised hospitals was improved next day by the
offerings from many churches of pew-cushions, which, sewn together,
served as comfortable beds; and for the remainder of the war their
owners thanked God upon bare benches for every "misery missed" that
was "mercy gained."  To supply food for the hospitals the contents
of larders all over town were emptied into baskets; while cellars
long sealed and cobwebbed, belonging to the old Virginia gentry who
knew good Port and Madeira, were opened by the Ithuriel's spear of
universal sympathy.  There was not much going to bed that night,
either; and I remember spending the greater part of it leaning from
my window to seek the cool night air, while wondering as to the
fate of those near to me.  There was a summons to my mother about
midnight.  Two soldiers came to tell her of the wounding of one
close of kin; but she was already on duty elsewhere, tireless and
watchful as ever.  Up to that time the younger girls had been
regarded as superfluities in hospital service; but on Monday two of
us found a couple of rooms where fifteen wounded men lay upon
pallets around the floor, and, on offering our services to the
surgeons in charge, were proud to have them accepted and to be
installed as responsible nurses, under direction of an older and
more experienced woman.  The constant activity our work entailed
was a relief from the strained excitement of life after the battle
of Seven Pines.  When the first flurry of distress was over, the
residents of those pretty houses standing back in gardens full of
roses set their cooks to work, or better still, went themselves
into the kitchen, to compound delicious messes for the wounded,
after the appetizing old Virginia recipes.  Flitting about the
streets in the direction of the hospitals were smiling white-jacketed negroes, carrying silver trays with dishes of fine
porcelain under napkins of thick white damask, containing soups,
creams, jellies, thin biscuit, eggs a la creme, broiled chicken,
etc., surmounted by clusters of freshly gathered flowers.  A year
later we had cause to pine after these culinary glories, when it
came to measuring out, with sinking hearts, the meager portions of
milk and food we could afford to give our charges.
</p><p>As an instance, however, that quality in food was not always
appreciated by the patients, my mother urged upon one of her
sufferers (a gaunt and soft-voiced Carolinian from the "piney-woods
district") a delicately served trifle from some neighboring
kitchen.
</p><p>"Jes ez you say, old miss," was the weary answer, "I ain't a-contradictin' you.  It mout be good for me, but my stomick's kinder
sot agin it.  There ain't but one thing I'm sorter yarnin' arter,
an' that's a dish o' greens en bacon fat, with a few molarses
poured onto it."
</p><p>From our patients, when they could syllable the tale, we had
accounts of the fury of the fight, which were made none the less
horrible by such assistance as imagination could give to the facts.
I remember that they told us of shot thrown from the enemy's
batteries into the advancing ranks of the Confederates, that plowed
their way through lines of flesh and blood before exploding in
showers of musket-balls to do still further havoc.  Before these
awful missiles, it was said, our men had fallen in swaths, the
living closing over them to press forward in the charge.
</p><p>It was at the end of one of these narrations that a piping
voice came from a pallet in the corner: "They fit right smart, them
Yanks did, I tell <hi rend="italic">you!"</hi> and not to laugh was as much of an
effort as it had just been not to cry.
</p><p>From one scene of death and suffering to another we passed
during those days of June.  Under a withering heat that made the
hours preceding dawn the only ones of the twenty-four endurable in
point of temperature, and a shower-bath the only form of diversion
we had time or thought to indulge in, to go out-of-doors was
sometimes worse than remaining in our wards.  But one night, after
several of us had been walking about town in a state of panting
exhaustion, palm-leaf fans in hand, a friend persuaded us to ascend
to the small platform on the summit of the Capitol, in search of
fresher air.  To reach it was like going through a vapor-bath, but
an hour amid the cool breezes above the tree-tops of the square was
a thing of joy unspeakable.

<pb n="613"/>
</p><p>Day by day we were called to our windows by the wailing dirge
of a military band preceding a soldier's funeral.  One could not
number those sad pageants: the coffin crowned with cap and sword
and gloves, the riderless horse following with empty boots fixed in
the stirrups of an army saddle; such soldiers as could be spared
from the front marching after with arms reversed and crape-enfolded
banners; the passers-by standing with bare, bent heads.  Funerals
less honored outwardly were continually occurring.  Then and
thereafter the green hillsides of lovely Hollywood were frequently
upturned to find resting-places for the heroic dead.  So much taxed
for time and attendants were the funeral officials, it was not
unusual to perform the last rites for the departed at night.  A
solemn scene was that in the July moonlight, when, with the few who
valued him most gathered around the grave, we laid to rest one of
my own nearest kinsmen, about whom in the old service of the United
States, as in that of the Confederacy, it was said, "He was a
spotless knight."
</p><p>Spite of its melancholy uses, there was no more favorite walk
in Richmond than Hollywood, a picturesquely beautiful spot, where
high hills sink into velvet undulations, profusely shaded with
holly, pine, and cedar, as well as by trees of deciduous foliage.
In spring the banks of the stream that runs through the valley were
enameled with wild flowers, and the thickets were full of May-blossom and dogwood.  Mounting to the summit of the bluff, one may
sit under the shade of some ample oak, to view the spires and roofs
of the town, with the white colonnade of the distant Capitol.
Richmond, thus seen beneath her verdant foliage "upon hills,
girdled by hills," confirms what an old writer felt called to
exclaim about it, "Verily, this city hath a pleasant seat."  On the
right, below this point, flows the rushing yellow river, making
ceaseless turmoil around islets of rock whose rifts are full of
birch and willow, or leaping impetuously over the bowlders of
granite that strew its bed.  Old-time Richmond folk used to say
that the sound of their favorite James (or "Jeems," to be exact)
went with them into foreign countries, during no matter how many
years of absence, haunting them like a strain of sweetest music;
nor would they permit a suggestion of superiority in the flavor of
any other fluid to that of a draught of its amber waters.  So blent
with my own memories of war is the voice of that tireless river,
that I seem to hear it yet, over the tramp of rusty battalions, the
short imperious stroke of the alarm-bell, the clash of passing
bands, the gallop of eager horsemen, the roar of battle or of
flames leaping to devour their prey, the moan of hospitals, the
stifled note of sorrow!
</p><p>During all this time President Davis was a familiar and
picturesque figure on the streets, walking through the Capitol
square from his residence to the executive office in the morning,
not to return until late in the afternoon, or riding just before
nightfall to visit one or another of the encampments near the city.
He was tall, erect, slender, and of a dignified and soldierly
bearing, with clear-cut and high-bred features, and of a demeanor
of stately courtesy to all.  He was clad always in Confederate gray
cloth, and wore a soft felt hat with wide brim.  Afoot, his step
was brisk and firm; in the saddle he rode admirably and with a
martial aspect.  His early life had been spent in the Military
Academy at West Point and upon the then north-western frontier in
the Black Hawk War, and he afterwards greatly distinguished himself
at Monterey and Buena Vista in Mexico; at the time when we knew
him, everything in his appearance and manner was suggestive of such
a training.  He was reported to feel quite out of place in the
office of President, with executive and administrative duties, in
the midst of such a war; General Lee always spoke of him as the
best of military advisers; his own inclination was to be with the
army, and at the first tidings of sound of a gun, anywhere within
reach of Richmond, he was in the saddle and off for the spot&mdash;to
the dismay of his staff-officers, who were expected to act as an
escort on such occasions, and who never knew at what hour of the
night or of the next day they should get back to a bed or a meal.
The stories we were told of his adventures on such excursions were
many, and sometimes amusing.  For instance, when General Lee had
crossed the Chickahominy, to commence the Seven Days' battles,
President Davis, with several staff-officers, overtook the column,
and, accompanied by the Secretary of War and a few other non-combatants, forded the river just as the battle in the peach
orchard at Mechanicsville began.  General Lee, surrounded by
members of his own staff and other officers, was found a few
hundred yards north of the bridge, in the middle of the broad road,
mounted and busily engaged in directing the attack then about to be
made by a brigade sweeping in line over the fields to the east of
the road and towards Ellerson's Mill, where in a few minutes a hot
engagement commenced.  Shot, from the enemy's guns out of sight,
went whizzing overhead in quick succession, striking every moment
nearer the group of horsemen in the road, as the gunners improved
their range.  General Lee observed the President's approach, and
was evidently annoyed at what
<pb n="614"/>
he considered a fool-hardy
expedition of needless exposure of the head of the Government,
whose duties were elsewhere.  He turned his back for a moment,
until Col. Chilton had been dispatched at a gallop with the last
direction to the commander of the attacking brigade; then, facing
the cavalcade and looking like the god of war indignant, he
exchanged with the President a salute, with the most frigid reserve
of anything like welcome or cordiality.  In an instant, and without
allowance of opportunity for a word from the President, the
general, looking not at him but at the assemblage at large, asked
in a tone of irritation:
</p><p>"Who are all this army of people, and what are they doing
here?"
</p><p>No one moved or spoke, but all eyes were upon the President&mdash;
everybody perfectly understanding that this was only an order for
him to retire to a place of safety; and the roar of the guns, the
rattling fire of musketry, and the bustle of a battle in progress,
with troops continually arriving across the bridge to go into
action, went on.  The President twisted in his saddle, quite taken
aback at such a greeting&mdash;the general regarding him now with
glances of growing severity.  After a painful pause the President
said, with a voice of deprecation:
</p><p>"It is not my army, general."
</p><p>"It certainly is not <hi rend="italic">my</hi> army, Mr. President," was the
prompt reply, "and this is no place for it"&mdash;in an accent of
command unmistakable.  Such a rebuff was a stunner to the recipient
of it, who soon regained his own serenity, however, and answered:
</p><p>"Well, general, if I withdraw, perhaps they will follow," and
raising his hat in another cold salute, he turned his horse's head
to ride slowly towards the bridge&mdash;seeing, as he turned, a man
killed immediately before him by a shot from a gun which at that
moment got the range of the road.  The President's own staff-officers followed him, as did various others; but he presently drew
rein in the stream, where the high bank and the bushes concealed
him from General Lee's repelling observation, and there remained
while the battle raged.  The Secretary of War had also made a show
of withdrawing, but improved the opportunity afforded by rather a
deep ditch on the roadside to attempt to conceal himself and his
horse there for a time from General Lee, who at that moment was
more to be dreaded than the enemy's guns.
</p><p>When on the 27th of June the Seven Days' strife began, there
was none of the excitement attending the battle of Seven Pines.
People had shaken themselves down, as it were, to the grim reality
of a fight that must be fought.  "Let the war bleed, and let the
mighty fall," was the spirit of their cry.
</p><p>It is not my purpose to deal with the history of those awful
Seven Days.  Mine only to speak of the rear side of the canvas
where heroes of two armies passed and repassed as if upon some huge
Homeric frieze, in the manoeuvres of a strife that hung our land in
mourning.  The scars of war are healed when this is written, and
the vast "pity of it" fills the heart that wakes the retrospect.
</p><p>What I have said of Richmond before these battles will suffice
for a picture of the summer's experience.  When the tide of battle
receded, what wrecked hopes it left to tell the tale of the Battle
Summer!  Victory was ours, but in how many homes was heard the
voice of lamentation to drown the shouts of triumph!  Many
families, rich and poor alike, were bereaved of their dearest; and
for many of the dead there was mourning by all the town.  No
incident of the war, for instance, made a deeper impression than
the fall in battle of Colonel Munford's beautiful and brave young
son Ellis, whose body, laid across his own caisson, was carried
that summer to his father's house at nightfall, where the family,
unconscious of their loss, were sitting in cheerful talk around the
portal.  Another son of Richmond whose death was keenly felt by
everybody received his mortal wound while leading the first charge
to break the enemy's line at Gaines's Mill.  This was Lieutenant-Colonel Bradfute Warwick, a young hero who had won his spurs in
service with Garibaldi.  Losses like these are irreparable in any
community; and so, with lamentations in nearly every household,
while the spirit along the lines continued unabated, it was a
chastened "Thank God" that went up from among us when Jackson's
victory over Pope had raised the siege of Richmond.

</p><signed>                              <hi rend="italic">C. C. Harrison.</hi>
</signed>

</div1>
</body>
</text>
</TEI.2>
