<?xml version="1.0"?>

<?dlps id="HawDevi"?>
<?dlps page-images="none" figure-images="no"?>
<?dlps transcription="other"?>

<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/tei-p4/tei2.dtd" [
<!ENTITY % POSTKB "INCLUDE">
<!ENTITY % TEI.extensions.ent SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.ent">
<!ENTITY % TEI.extensions.dtd SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.dtd">
<!ENTITY % ISOnum SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/charent/iso-num.ent"> %ISOnum;
<!ENTITY % ISOpub SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/charent/iso-pub.ent"> %ISOpub;

]>
<TEI.2 id="HawDevi">
<teiHeader type="migrated" creator="Etext">
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title type="main">The Devil in Manuscript</title>
<title type="sort">devil in manuscript</title>
<author>Hawthorne, Nathaniel, 1804-1864</author>
<respStmt>
<resp>Creation of machine-readable version:</resp>
<name>Charles Keller</name>
<resp>Conversion to TEI.2-conformant markup:</resp>
<name>University of Virginia Library Electronic Text Center.</name>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt>
<extent>ca. <num type="kilobytes">20</num> kilobytes</extent>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>University of Virginia Library</publisher>
<pubPlace>Charlottesville, Virginia</pubPlace>
<idno type="ETC">HawDevi</idno>
<date value="1996">1996</date>
<availability status="public">
<p n="copyright">Copyright &copy; 1996 by the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia</p>
<p n="access">Publicly accessible</p>
</availability>
<idno type="uva-pid">uva-lib:476039</idno>
</publicationStmt>
<seriesStmt>
<title>University of Virginia Library, Text collection</title>
<idno type="uva-set">UVA-LIB-Text</idno>
</seriesStmt>
<sourceDesc>
<biblFull>
<titleStmt>
<title type="main">The Devil in Manuscript</title>
<title level="m">The Complete Novels and Selected Tales of Nathaniel Hawthorne</title>
<title type="sort">devil in manuscript</title>
<author>Nathaniel Hawthorne</author>
<respStmt>
<resp>Editor</resp>
<name>Norman Holmes Pearson</name>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt>
<editionStmt>
<p>Modern Library Edition</p>
</editionStmt>
<extent>pp 1203-1209.</extent>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>Random House, Inc.</publisher>
<pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
<date value="1937">1937</date>
<idno type="callNo">Print copy consulted: UVa Library call number PS 1850 1937</idno>
</publicationStmt>
</biblFull>
</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc>
<encodingDesc>
<projectDesc>
<p>Prepared for the University of Virginia Library Electronic Text Center.</p>
</projectDesc>
<editorialDecl>
<p>All quotation marks retained as data.</p>
<p>All unambiguous end-of-line hyphens have been removed, and the trailing part of a word has been joined to the preceding line.</p>
<p>The images exist as archived TIFF images, one or more JPEG versions for general use, and thumbnail GIFs.</p>
<p>Keywords in the header are a local Electronic Text Center scheme to aid in establishing analytical groupings.</p>
</editorialDecl>
</encodingDesc>
<profileDesc>
<creation>
<date value="1851">1851</date>
</creation>
<langUsage>
<language id="eng" usage="main">English</language>
</langUsage>
</profileDesc>
<revisionDesc>
<change>
<date value="1996-09">September 1996</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>corrector</resp>
<name>Catherine Tousignant, Electronic Text Center, University of Virginia</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Added TEI header and tags. Corrected an error in print source:
page 1205, para. 5:  or not] or not.</item>
</change>
<change>
<date value="2005-07">July 2005</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>Corrector</resp>
<name>John Ivor Carlson</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Converted SGML to XML. Fixed tagging.</item>
</change>
<change>
<date value="2007-09">September 2007</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>Migration</resp>
<name>Ethan Gruber, University of Virginia Library</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Converted XML markup from TEI Lite to uva-dl-tei (TEI P4 with local customizations).</item>
</change>
<change>
<date value="2008-01">January 2008</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>Migration</resp>
<name>Greg Murray, University of Virginia Library</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Programmatically updated TEI header markup (but not header content) for minimal compliance with current QA requirements.</item>
</change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>


<text id="d1">
<body id="d2">


<div1 type="story" id="d3"> <pb n="1203"/>
<head>THE DEVIL IN MANUSCRIPT</head>

<p>ON a bitter evening of December, I arrived by mail in a large town,
which was then the residence of an intimate friend, one of those
gifted
youths who cultivate poetry and the belles-lettres, and call
themselves
students at law. My first business, after supper, was to visit him
at the
office of his distinguished instructor. As I have said, it was a
bitter night,
clear starlight, but cold as Nova Zembla,&mdash;the shop-windows along
the
street being frosted, so as almost to hide the lights, while the
wheels of
   <pb n="1204"/>
coaches thundered equally loud over frozen earth and pavements of
stone. There was no snow, either on the ground or the roofs of the
houses. The wind blew so violently, that I had but to spread my
cloak
like a main-sail, and scud along the street at the rate of ten
knots,
greatly envied by other navigators, who were beating slowly up,
with
the gale right in their teeth. One of these I capsized, but was
gone on
the wings of the wind before he could even vociferate an oath.
</p><p>After this picture of an inclement night, behold us seated
by a great
blazing fire, which looked so comfortable and delicious that I felt
inclined to lie down and roll among the hot coals. The usual
furniture of
a lawyer's office was around us,&mdash;rows of volumes in sheepskin, and
a
multitude of writs, summonses, and other legal papers, scattered
over
the desks and tables. But there were certain objects which seemed
to intimate that we had little dread of the intrusion of clients,
or of
the
learned counsellor himself, who, indeed, was attending court in a
distant town. A tall, decanter-shaped bottle stood on the table,
between
two tumblers, and beside a pile of blotted manuscripts, altogether
dissimilar to any law documents recognized in our courts. My
friend,
whom
I shall call Oberon,&mdash;it was a name of fancy and friendship between
him
and me,&mdash;my friend Oberon looked at these papers with a peculiar
expression of disquietude.
</p><p>``I do believe,'' said he, soberly, ``or, at least, I could
believe, if I
chose, that there is a devil in this pile of blotted papers. You
have read
them, and know what I mean,&mdash;that conception in which I endeavored
to embody the character of a fiend, as represented in our
traditions and
the written records of witchcraft. Oh, I have a horror of what was
created in my own brain, and shudder at the manuscripts in which I
gave
that dark idea a sort of material existence! Would they were out of
my
sight!''
</p><p>``And of mine, too,'' thought I.
</p><p>``You remember,'' continued Oberon, ``how the hellish thing
used to
suck away the happiness of those who, by a simple concession that
seemed almost innocent, subjected themselves to his power. Just so
my
peace is gone, and all by these accursed manuscripts. Have you felt
nothing of the same influence?''
</p><p>``Nothing,'' replied I, ``unless the spell be hid in a
desire to turn novelist, after reading your delightful tales.''
</p><p>``Novelist!'' exclaimed Oberon, half seriously. ``Then,
indeed, my
devil has his claw on you! You are gone! You cannot even pray for
deliverance! But we will be the last and only victims; for this
night
I
mean to burn the manuscripts, and commit the fiend to his
retribution in
the flames.''
</p><p>``Burn your tales!'' repeated I, startled at the desperation
of the idea.
</p><p>``Even so,'' said the author, despondingly. ``You cannot
conceive what
an effect the composition of these tales has had on me. I have
become
ambitious of a bubble, and careless of solid reputation. I am
surrounding myself with shadows, which bewilder me, by aping the
realities
of
   <pb n="1205"/>
life. They have drawn me aside from the beaten path of the world,
and
led me into a strange sort of solitude,&mdash;a solitude in the midst of
men,&mdash;where nobody wishes for what I do, nor thinks nor feels as I
do.
The
tales have done all this. When they are ashes, perhaps I shall be
as I
was before they had existence. Moreover, the sacrifice is less than
you
may suppose, since nobody will publish them.''
</p><p>``That does make a difference, indeed,'' said I.
</p><p>``They have been offered, by letter,'' continued Oberon,
reddening
with vexation, ``to some seventeen booksellers. It would make you
stare
to read their answers; and read them you should, only that I burnt
them
as fast as they arrived. One man publishes nothing but
school-books;
another has five novels already under examination.''
</p><p>``What a voluminous mass the unpublished literature of
America must
be!'' cried I.
</p><p>``Oh, the Alexandrian manuscripts were nothing to it!'' said
my
friend. ``Well, another gentleman is just giving up business, on
purpose,
I verily believe, to escape publishing my book. Several, however,
would
not absolutely decline the agency, on my advancing half the cost of
an
edition, and giving bonds for the remainder, besides a high
percentage
to themselves, whether the book sells or not. Another advises a
subscription.''
</p><p>``The villain!'' exclaimed I.
</p><p>``A fact!'' said Oberon. ``In short, of all the seventeen
booksellers,
only one has vouchsafed even to read my tales; and he&mdash;a literary
dabbler himself, I should judge&mdash;has the impertinence to criticise
them,
proposing what he calls vast improvements, and concluding, after a
general sentence of condemnation, with the definitive assurance
that
he will
not be concerned on any terms.''
</p><p>``It might not be amiss to pull that fellow's nose,''
remarked I.
</p><p>``If the whole `trade' had one common nose, there would be
some satisfaction in pulling it,'' answered the author. ``But,
there does
seem to
be one honest man among these seventeen unrighteous ones; and he
tells
me fairly, that no American publisher will meddle with an American
work,&mdash;seldom if by a known writer, and never if by a new
one,&mdash;unless
at the writer's risk.''
</p><p>``The paltry rogues!'' cried I. ``Will they live by
literature, and yet
risk nothing for its sake? But, after all, you might publish on
your own
account.''
</p><p>``And so I might,'' replied Oberon. ``But the devil of the
business is
this. These people have put me so out of conceit with the tales,
that I
loathe the very thought of them, and actually experience a physical
sickness of the stomach, whenever I glance at them on the table. I
tell
you there is a demon in them! I anticipate a wild enjoyment in
seeing
them in the blaze; such as I should feel in taking vengeance on an
enemy, or destroying something noxious.''
</p><p>I did not very strenuously oppose this determination, being
privately
of opinion, in spite of my partiality for the author, that his
tales would
   <pb n="1206"/>
make a more brilliant appearance in the fire than anywhere else.
Before
proceeding to execution, we broached the bottle of champagne, which
Oberon had provided for keeping up his spirits in this doleful
business.
We swallowed each a tumblerful, in sparkling commotion; it went
bubbling down our throats, and brightened my eyes at once, but left
my
friend sad and heavy as before. He drew the tales towards him, with
a
mixture of natural affection and natural disgust, like a father
taking a
deformed infant into his arms.
</p><p>``Pooh! Pish! Pshaw!'' exclaimed he, holding them at
arm's-length.
``It was Gray's idea of heaven, to lounge on a sofa and read new
novels.
Now, what more appropriate torture would Dante himself have
contrived, for the sinner who perpetrates a bad book, than to be
continually
turning over the manuscript?''
</p><p>``It would fail of effect,'' said I, ``because a bad author
is always his
own great admirer.''
</p><p>``I lack that one characteristic of my tribe,&mdash;the only
desirable one,''
observed Oberon. ``But how many recollections throng upon me, as I
turn over these leaves! This scene came into my fancy as I walked
along a hilly road, on a starlight October evening; in the pure and
bracing air, I became all soul, and felt as if I could climb the
sky,
and run a
race along the Milky-Way. Here is another tale, in which I wrapt
myself during a dark and dreary night-ride in the month of March,
till the
rattling of the wheels and the voices of my companions seemed like
faint sounds of a dream, and my visions a bright reality. That
scribbled
page describes shadows which I summoned to my bedside at midnight:
they would not depart when I bade them; the gray dawn came, and
found me wide awake and feverish, the victim of my own
enchantments!''
</p><p>``There must have been a sort of happiness in all this,''
said I, smitten with a strange longing to make proof of it.
</p><p>``There may be happiness in a fever fit,'' replied the
author. ``And
then the various moods in which I wrote! Sometimes my ideas were
like
precious stones under the earth, requiring toil to dig them up, and
care
to polish and brighten them; but often a delicious stream of
thought
would gush out upon the page at once, like water sparkling up
suddenly
in the desert; and when it had passed, I gnawed my pen hopelessly,
or
blundered on with cold and miserable toil, as if there were a wall
of ice
between me and my subject.''
</p><p>``Do you now perceive a corresponding difference,'' inquired
I, ``between the passages which you wrote so coldly, and those
fervid
flashes
of the mind?''
</p><p>``No,'' said Oberon, tossing the manuscripts on the table.
``I find no
traces of the golden pen with which I wrote in characters of fire.
My
treasure of fairy coin is changed to worthless dross. My picture,
painted
in what seemed the loveliest hues, presents nothing but a faded and
indistinguishable surface. I have been eloquent and poetical and
humorous in a dream,&mdash;and behold! it is all nonsense, now that I am
awake.''
   <pb n="1207"/>
</p><p>My friend now threw sticks of wood and dry chips upon the
fire, and
seeing it blaze like Nebuchadnezzar's furnace, seized the
champagne-bottle, and drank two or three brimming bumpers,
successively. The
heady liquor combined with his agitation to throw him into a
species of
rage. He laid violent hands on the tales. In one instant more,
their faults
and beauties would alike have vanished in a glowing purgatory. But,
all
at once, I remembered passages of high imagination, deep pathos,
original thoughts, and points of such varied excellence, that the
vastness of
the sacrifice struck me most forcibly. I caught his arm.
</p><p>``Surely, you do not mean to burn them!'' I exclaimed.
</p><p>``Let me alone!'' cried Oberon, his eyes flashing fire. ``I
will burn
them! Not a scorched syllable shall escape! Would you have me a
damned author?&mdash;To undergo sneers, taunts, abuse, and cold neglect,
and faint praise, bestowed, for pity's sake, against the giver's
conscience! A hissing and a laughing-stock to my own traitorous
thoughts!
An outlaw from the protection of the grave,&mdash;one whose ashes every
careless foot might spurn, unhonored in life, and remembered
scornfully
in death! Am I to bear all this, when yonder fire will insure me
from
the whole? No! There go the tales! May my hand wither when it would
write another!''
</p><p>The deed was done. He had thrown the manuscripts into the
hottest
of the fire, which at first seemed to shrink away, but soon curled
around
them, and made them a part of its own fervent brightness. Oberon
stood
gazing at the conflagration, and shortly began to soliloquize, in
the wildest strain, as if Fancy resisted and became riotous, at the
moment
when
he would have compelled her to ascend that funeral pile. His words
described objects which he appeared to discern in the fire, fed by
his own
precious thoughts; perhaps the thousand visions which the writer's
magic had incorporated with these pages became visible to him in
the
dissolving heat, brightening forth ere they vanished forever; while
the
smoke, the vivid sheets of flame, the ruddy and whitening coals,
caught
the aspect of a varied scenery.
</p><p>``They blaze,'' said he, ``as if I had steeped them in the
intensest
spirit of genius. There I see my lovers clasped in each other's
arms. How
pure the flame that bursts from their glowing hearts! And yonder
the
features of a villain writhing in the fire that shall torment him
to eternity. My holy men, my pious and angelic women, stand like
martyrs
amid the flames, their mild eyes lifted heavenward. Ring out the
bells!
A city is on fire. See!&mdash;destruction roars through my dark forests,
while
the lakes boil up in steaming billows, and the mountains are
volcanoes,
and the sky kindles with a lurid brightness! All elements are but
one
pervading flame! Ha! The fiend!''
</p><p>I was somewhat startled by this latter exclamation. The
tales were
almost consumed, but just then threw forth a broad sheet of fire,
which
flickered as with laughter, making the whole room dance in its
brightness, and then roared portentously up the chimney.
</p><p>``You saw him? You must have seen him!'' cried Oberon. ``How
he
   <pb n="1208"/>
glared at me and laughed, in that last sheet of flame, with just
the features that I imagined for him! Well! The tales are gone.''
</p><p>The papers were indeed reduced to a heap of black cinders,
with a
multitude of sparks hurrying confusedly among them, the traces of
the
pen being now represented by white lines, and the whole mass
fluttering
to and fro in the draughts of air. The destroyer knelt down to look
at
them.
</p><p>``What is more potent than fire!'' said he, in his gloomiest
tone. ``Even
thought, invisible and incorporeal as it is, cannot escape it. In
this little
time, it has annihilated the creations of long nights and days,
which I
could no more reproduce, in their first glow and freshness, than
cause
ashes and whitened bones to rise up and live. There, too, I
sacrificed the
unborn children of my mind. All that I had accomplished&mdash;all that
I
planned for future years&mdash;has perished by one common ruin, and left
only this heap of embers! The deed has been my fate. And what
remains? A weary and aimless life,&mdash;a long repentance of this
hour,&mdash;and
It last an obscure grave, where they will bury and forget me!''
</p><p>As the author concluded his dolorous moan, the extinguished
embers
arose and settled down and arose again, and finally flew up the
chimney,
like a demon with sable wings. Just as they disappeared, there was
a
loud and solitary cry in the street below us. ``Fire!'' Fire! Other
voices
caught up that terrible word, and it speedily became the shout of
a multitude. Oberon started to his feet, in fresh excitement.
</p><p>``A fire on such a night!'' cried he. ``The wind blows a
gale, and wherever it whirls the flames, the roofs will flash up
like gunpowder.
Every
pump is frozen up, and boiling water would turn to ice the moment
it
was flung from the engine. In an hour, this wooden town will be one
great bonfire! What a glorious scene for my next&mdash;Pshaw!''
</p><p>The street was now all alive with footsteps, and the air
full of voices.
We heard one engine thundering round a corner, and another rattling
from a distance over the pavements. The bells of three steeples
clanged
out at once, spreading the alarm to many a neighboring town, and
expressing hurry, confusion, and terror, so inimitably that I could
almost
distinguish in their peal the burden of the universal cry,&mdash;``Fire!
Fire!
Fire!''
</p><p>``What is so eloquent as their iron tongues!'' exclaimed
Oberon. ``My
heart leaps and trembles, but not with fear. And that other sound,
too,
&mdash;deep and awful as a mighty organ,&mdash;the roar and thunder of the
multitude on the pavement below! Come! We are losing time. I will
cry
out in the loudest of the uproar, and mingle my spirit with the
wildest
of the confusion, and be a bubble on the top of the ferment!''
</p><p>From the first outcry, my forebodings had warned me of the
true object and centre of alarm. There was nothing now but uproar,
above,
beneath, and around us; footsteps stumbling pell-mell up the public
stair-case, eager shouts and heavy thumps at the door, the whiz and
dash
of
water from the engines, and the crash of furniture thrown upon the
pavement. At once, the truth flashed upon my friend. His frenzy
took
   <pb n="1209"/>
the hue of joy, and, with a wild gesture of exultation, he leaped
almost
to the ceiling of the chamber.
</p><p>``My tales!'' cried Oberon. ``The chimney! The roof! The
Fiend has
gone forth by night, and startled thousands in fear and wonder from
their beds! Here I stand,&mdash;a triumphant author! Huzza! Huzza! My
brain has set the town on fire! Huzza!''</p>
</div1>

</body>
</text>
</TEI.2>

