<?xml version="1.0"?>

<?dlps id="HawIngl"?>
<?dlps page-images="none" figure-images="no"?>
<?dlps transcription="other"?>

<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/tei-p4/tei2.dtd" [
<!ENTITY % POSTKB "INCLUDE">
<!ENTITY % TEI.extensions.ent SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.ent">
<!ENTITY % TEI.extensions.dtd SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.dtd">
<!ENTITY % ISOnum SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/charent/iso-num.ent"> %ISOnum;
<!ENTITY % ISOpub SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/charent/iso-pub.ent"> %ISOpub;

]>
<TEI.2 id="HawIngl">
<teiHeader type="migrated" creator="Etext">
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title type="main">John Inglefield's Thanksgiving</title>
<title type="sort">john inglefields thanksgiving</title>
<author>Hawthorne, Nathaniel, 1804-1864</author>
<respStmt>
<resp>Creation of machine-readable version:</resp>
<name/>
<resp>Conversion to TEI.2-conformant markup:</resp>
<name>University of Virginia Library Electronic Text Center.</name>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt>
<extent>ca. <num type="kilobytes">14</num> kilobytes</extent>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>University of Virginia Library</publisher>
<pubPlace>Charlottesville, Virginia</pubPlace>
<idno type="ETC">HawIngl</idno>
<date value="2000">2000</date>
<availability status="public">
<p n="copyright">Copyright &copy; 2000 by the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia</p>
<p n="access">Publicly accessible</p>
</availability>
<idno type="uva-pid">uva-lib:476050</idno>
</publicationStmt>
<seriesStmt>
<title>University of Virginia Library, Text collection</title>
<idno type="uva-set">UVA-LIB-Text</idno>
</seriesStmt>
<sourceDesc>
<biblFull>
<titleStmt>
<title type="main">John Inglefield's Thanksgiving</title>
<title level="m">The works of Nathaniel Hawthorne.</title>
<title type="sort">john inglefields thanksgiving</title>
<author>Nathaniel Hawthorne, 1804-1864</author>
</titleStmt>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>Houghton, Mifflin and Company</publisher>
<pubPlace>Boston</pubPlace>
<date value="1882">1882</date>
<idno type="callNo">Source copy consulted: PS 1850 1882</idno>
</publicationStmt>
</biblFull>
</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc>
<encodingDesc>
<projectDesc>
<p>Prepared for the University of Virginia Library Electronic Text Center.</p>
</projectDesc>
<editorialDecl>
<p id="ETC">Some keywords in the header are a local Electronic Text Center scheme to aid in establishing analytical groupings.</p>
</editorialDecl>
</encodingDesc>
<profileDesc>
<creation>
<date value="1853">1853</date>
</creation>
<langUsage>
<language id="eng" usage="main">English</language>
</langUsage>
<textClass>
<keywords>
<term>fiction</term>
<term>prose</term>
<term>masculine</term>
</keywords>
</textClass>
</profileDesc>
<revisionDesc>
<change>
<date value="2005-07">July 2005</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>Corrector</resp>
<name>John Ivor Carlson</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Converted SGML to XML. Fixed tagging.</item>
</change>
<change>
<date value="2007-09">September 2007</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>Migration</resp>
<name>Ethan Gruber, University of Virginia Library</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Converted XML markup from TEI Lite to uva-dl-tei (TEI P4 with local customizations).</item>
</change>
<change>
<date value="2008-01">January 2008</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>Migration</resp>
<name>Greg Murray, University of Virginia Library</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Programmatically updated TEI header markup (but not header content) for minimal compliance with current QA requirements.</item>
</change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text id="d1">
<body id="d2">

<div1 type="story" id="d3">
<head>John Inglefield's Thanksgiving
</head>


<p>On the evening of Thanksgiving Day, John Inglefield, the
blacksmith, sat in his elbow-chair, among those
who had been keeping festival at his board. Being
the central figure of the domestic circle, the
fire threw its strongest light on his massive and
sturdy frame, reddening his rough visage, so that
it looked like the head of an iron statue, all
aglow from his own forge, and with its features
rudely fashioned on his own anvil. At John
Inglefield's right hand was an empty chair. The
other places round the hearth were filled by the
members of the family, who all sat quietly, while,
with a semblance of fantastic merriment, their
shadows danced on the wall behind them. One of
the group was John Inglefield's son, who had been
bred at college, and was now a student of theology
at Andover. There was also a daughter of sixteen,
whom nobody could look at without thinking of a
rose-bud almost blossomed. The only other person
at the fireside was Robert Moore, formerly an
apprentice of the blacksmith, but now his
journeyman, and who seemed more like an own son of
John Inglefield than did the pale and slender
student.</p>

<p>Only these four had kept New England's festival beneath that roof. The vacant chair at John Inglefield's right
hand was in memory of his wife, whom death had
snatched from him since the previous Thanksgiving.
With a feeling that few would have looked for in
his rough nature, the bereaved husband had himself
set the chair in its place next his own; and often
did his eye glance thitherward, as if he deemed it
possible that the cold grave might send back its
tenant to the cheerful fireside, at least for that
one evening. Thus did he cherish the grief that
was dear to him. But there was another grief
which he would fain have torn from his heart; or,
since that could never be, have buried it too deep
for others to behold, or for his own remembrance.
Within the past year another member of his
household had gone from him, but not to the grave.
Yet they kept no vacant chair for her.</p>

<p>While John
Inglefield and his family were sitting round the
hearth with the shadows dancing behind them on the
wall, the outer door was opened, and a light
footstep came along the passage. The latch of the
inner door was lifted by some familiar hand, and a
young girl came in, wearing a cloak and hood,
which she took off, and laid on the table beneath
the looking-glass. Then, after gazing a moment
at the fireside circle, she approached, and took
the seat at John Inglefield's right hand, as if it
had been reserved on purpose for her.</p>

<p>"Here I
am, at last, father," said she. "You
ate your Thanksgiving dinner without me, but I
have come back to spend the evening with
you."</p>

<p>Yes, it
was Prudence Inglefield. She wore the same neat
and maidenly attire which she had been accustomed
to put on when the household work was over for the
day, and her hair was parted from her brow, in the
simple and modest fashion that became her best of
all. If her cheek might otherwise have been pale,
yet the glow of the fire suffused it with a
healthful bloom. If she had spent the many months
of her absence in guilt and infamy, yet they
seemed to have left no traces on her gentle
aspect. She could not have looked less altered,
had she merely stepped away from her father's
fireside for half an hour, and returned while the
blaze was quivering upwards from the same brands
that were burning at her departure. And to John
Inglefield she was the very image of his buried
wife, such as he remembered her on the first
Thanksgiving which they had passed under their own
roof. Therefore, though naturally a stern and
rugged man, he could not speak unkindly to his
sinful child, nor yet could he take her to his
bosom.</p>

<p>"You are
welcome home, Prudence," said he, glancing
sideways at her, and his voice faltered.
"Your mother would have rejoiced to see you,
but she has been gone from us these four
months."</p>

<p>"I know
it, father, I know it," replied Prudence,
quickly. "And yet, when I first came in, my
eyes were so dazzled by the firelight, that she
seemed to be sitting in this very chair!"</p>

<p>By this
time the other members of tine family had begun
to recover from their surprise, and became
sensible that it was no ghost from the grave, nor
vision of their vivid recollections, but Prudence,
her own self. Her brother was the next that
greeted her. He advanced and held out his hand
affectionately, as a brother should; yet not
entirely like a brother, for, with all his
kindness, he was still a clergyman, and speaking
to a child of sin.</p>

<p>"Sister Prudence,"
said he, earnestly, "I rejoice that a
merciful Providence hath turned your steps
homeward, in time for me to bid you a last
farewell. In a few weeks, sister, I am to sail as
a missionary to the far islands of the Pacific.
There is not one of these beloved faces that I
shall ever hope to behold again on this earth.
Oh, may I see all of them &mdash; yours and all &mdash; beyond
the grave!"</p>

<p>A shadow
flitted across the girl's countenance.</p>

<p>"The grave
is very dark, brother," answered she,
withdrawing her hand somewhat hastily from his
grasp. "You must look your last at me by the
light of this fire."</p>

<p>While this
was passing, the twin-girl &mdash; the rose-bud that had
grown on the same stem with the castaway &mdash; stood
gazing at her sister, longing to fling herself
upon her bosom, so that the tendrils of their
hearts might intertwine again. At first she was
restrained by mingled grief and shame, and by a
dread that Prudence was too much changed to
respond to her affection, or that her own purity
would be felt as a reproach by the lost one. But,
as she listened to the familiar voice, while the
face grew more and more familiar, she forgot
everything save that Prudence had come back.
Springing forward, she would have clasped her in a
close embrace. At that very instant, however,
Prudence started from her chair, and held out both
her hands, with a warning gesture.</p>

<p>"No, Mary, &mdash; no,
my sister," cried she, "do not you
touch me. Your bosom must not be pressed to
mine!"</p>

<p>Mary shuddered
and stood still, for she felt that something
darker than the grave was between Prudence and
herself, though they seemed so near each other in
the light of their father's hearth, where they had
grown up together. Meanwhile Prudence threw her
eyes around the room, in search of one who had not
yet bidden her welcome. He had withdrawn from his
seat by the fireside, and was standing near the
door, with his face averted, so that his features
could be discerned only by the flickering shadow
of the profile upon the wall. But Prudence called
to him, in a cheerful and kindly tone: &mdash; </p>

<p>"Come, Robert,"
she, "won't you shake hands with your old
friend?"</p>

<p>Robert Moore
held back for a moment, but affection struggled
powerfully, and overcame his pride and resentment;
he rushed towards Prudence, seized her hand, and
pressed it to his bosom.</p>

<p>"There, there,
Robert!" said she, smiling sadly, as she
withdrew her hand, "you must not give me too
warm a welcome."</p>

<p>And now,
having exchanged greetings with each member of
the family, Prudence again seated herself in the
chair at John Inglefield's right hand. She was
naturally a girl of quick and tender
sensibilities, gladsome in her general mood, but
with a bewitching pathos interfused among her
merriest words and deeds. It was remarked of her,
too, that she had a faculty, even from childhood,
of throwing her own feelings, like a spell, over
her companions. Such as she had been in her days
of innocence, so did she appear this evening. Her
friends, in the surprise and bewilderment of her
return, almost forgot that she had ever left them,
or that she had forfeited any of her claims to
their affection. In the morning, perhaps, they
might have looked at her with altered eyes, but by
the Thanksgiving fireside they felt only that
their own Prudence had come back to them, and were
thankful. John Inglefield's rough visage
brightened with the glow of his heart, as it grew
warm and merry within him; once or twice, even, he
laughed till the room rang again, yet seemed
startled by the echo of his own mirth. The grave
young minister became as frolicksome as a
school-boy. Mary, too, the rose-bud, forgot that
her twin-blossom had ever been torn from the stem,
and trampled in the dust. And as for Robert
Moore, he gazed at Prudence with the bashful
earnestness of love new-born, while she, with
sweet maiden coquetry, half smiled upon and half
discouraged him.</p>

<p>In short,
it was one of those intervals when sorrow
vanishes in its own depth of shadow, and joy
starts forth in transitory brightness. When the
clock struck eight, Prudence poured out her
father's customary draught of herb-tea, which had
been steeping by the fireside ever since
twilight.</p>

<p>"God bless
you, child!" said John Inglefield, as he
took the cup from her hand; "you have made
your old father happy again. But we miss your
mother sadly, Prudence, sadly. It seems as if she
ought to be here now."</p>

<p>"Now, father,
or never," replied Prudence.</p>

<p>It was
now the hour for domestic worship. But while the
family were making preparations for this duty,
they suddenly perceived that Prudence had put on
her cloak and hood, and was lifting the latch of
the door.</p>

<p>"Prudence, Prudence!
where are you going?" cried they all, with
one voice.</p>

<p>As Prudence
passed out of the door she turned towards them,
and flung back her hand with a gesture of
farewell. But her face was so changed that they
hardly recognized it. Sin and evil passions
glowed through its comeliness, and wrought a
horrible deformity; a smile gleamed in her eyes,
as of triumphant mockery, at their surprise and
grief.</p>

<p>"Daughter," cried
John Inglefield, between wrath and sorrow,
"stay and be your father's blessing, or take
his curse with you!"</p>

<p>For an
instant Prudence lingered and looked back into
the fire-lighted room, while her countenance wore
almost the expression as if sine were struggling
with a fiend, who had power to seize his victim
even within the hallowed precincts of her father's
hearth. The fiend prevailed; and Prudence
vanished into the outer darkness. When the family
rushed to the door, they could see nothing, hut
heard the sound of wheels rattling over the frozen
ground.</p>

<p>That same
night, among the painted beauties at the theatre
of a neighboring city, there was one whose
dissolute mirth seemed inconsistent with any
sympathy for pure affections, and for the joys and
griefs which are hallowed by them. Yet this was
Prudence Inglefield. Her visit to the
Thanksgiving fireside was the realization of one
of those waking dreams in which the guilty soul
will sometimes stray back to its innocence. But
Sin, alas! is careful of her bond-slaves; they
hear her voice, perhaps, at the holiest moment,
and are constrained to go whither she summons
them. The same dark power that drew Prudence
Inglefield from her father's hearth &mdash; the same in
its nature, though heightened then to a dread
necessity &mdash; would snatch a guilty soul from the
gate of heaven, and make its sin and its
punishment alike eternal.</p>
</div1>
</body>
</text>
</TEI.2>



