<?xml version="1.0"?>

<?dlps id="HawMrsb"?>
<?dlps page-images="none" figure-images="no"?>
<?dlps transcription="other"?>

<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/tei-p4/tei2.dtd" [
<!ENTITY % POSTKB "INCLUDE">
<!ENTITY % TEI.extensions.ent SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.ent">
<!ENTITY % TEI.extensions.dtd SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.dtd">
<!ENTITY % ISOnum SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/charent/iso-num.ent"> %ISOnum;
<!ENTITY % ISOpub SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/charent/iso-pub.ent"> %ISOpub;

]>
<TEI.2 id="HawMrsb">
<teiHeader type="migrated" creator="Etext">
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title type="main">Mrs. Bullfrog</title>
<title type="sort">mrs bullfrog</title>
<author>Hawthorne, Nathaniel, 1804-1864</author>
<respStmt>
<resp>Creation of machine-readable version:</resp>
<name>Charles Keller</name>
<resp>Conversion to TEI.2-conformant markup:</resp>
<name>University of Virginia Library Electronic Text Center.</name>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt>
<extent>ca. <num type="kilobytes">19</num> kilobytes</extent>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>University of Virginia Library</publisher>
<pubPlace>Charlottesville, Virginia</pubPlace>
<idno type="ETC">HawMrsb</idno>
<date value="1996">1996</date>
<availability status="public">
<p n="copyright">Copyright &copy; 1996 by the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia</p>
<p n="access">Publicly accessible</p>
</availability>
<idno type="uva-pid">uva-lib:476057</idno>
</publicationStmt>
<seriesStmt>
<title>University of Virginia Library, Text collection</title>
<idno type="uva-set">UVA-LIB-Text</idno>
</seriesStmt>
<sourceDesc>
<biblFull>
<titleStmt>
<title type="main">Mrs. Bullfrog</title>
<title level="m">The Complete Novels and Selected Tales of Nathaniel Hawthorne</title>
<title type="sort">mrs bullfrog</title>
<author>Nathaniel Hawthorne</author>
<respStmt>
<resp>Editor</resp>
<name>Norman Holmes Pearson</name>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt>
<editionStmt>
<p>Modern Library Edition</p>
</editionStmt>
<extent>pp 1065-1070.</extent>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>Random House, Inc.</publisher>
<pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
<date value="1937">1937</date>
<idno type="callNo">Print copy consulted: UVa Library call number PS 1850 1937</idno>
</publicationStmt>
</biblFull>
</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc>
<encodingDesc>
<projectDesc>
<p>Prepared for the University of Virginia Library Electronic Text Center.</p>
</projectDesc>
<editorialDecl>
<p>All quotation marks retained as data.</p>
<p>All unambiguous end-of-line hyphens have been removed, and the trailing part of a word has been joined to the preceding line.</p>
<p>The images exist as archived TIFF images, one or more JPEG versions for general use, and thumbnail GIFs.</p>
<p>Keywords in the header are a local Electronic Text Center scheme to aid in establishing analytical groupings.</p>
</editorialDecl>
</encodingDesc>
<profileDesc>
<creation>
<date value="1846">1846</date>
</creation>
<langUsage>
<language id="eng" usage="main">English</language>
</langUsage>
</profileDesc>
<revisionDesc>
<change>
<date value="1996-09">September 1996</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>corrector</resp>
<name>Catherine Tousignant, Electronic Text Center, University of Virginia</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Added TEI header and tags.</item>
</change>
<change>
<date value="2005-07">July 2005</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>Corrector</resp>
<name>John Ivor Carlson</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Converted SGML to XML. Fixed tagging.</item>
</change>
<change>
<date value="2007-09">September 2007</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>Migration</resp>
<name>Ethan Gruber, University of Virginia Library</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Converted XML markup from TEI Lite to uva-dl-tei (TEI P4 with local customizations).</item>
</change>
<change>
<date value="2008-01">January 2008</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>Migration</resp>
<name>Greg Murray, University of Virginia Library</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Programmatically updated TEI header markup (but not header content) for minimal compliance with current QA requirements.</item>
</change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>
<text id="d1">
<body id="d2">



<div1 type="story" id="d3"> <pb n="1065"/>
<head>MRS. BULLFROG</head>

<p>IT makes me melancholy to see how like fools some very sensible
people
act in the matter of choosing wives. They perplex their judgments
by a
most undue attention to little niceties of personal appearance,
habits,
disposition, and other trifles which concern nobody but the lady
herself.
An unhappy gentleman, resolving to wed nothing short of perfection,
keeps his heart and hand till both get so old and withered that no
tolerable woman will accept them. Now this is the very height of
absurdity.
A kind Providence has so skilfully adapted sex to sex and the mass
of individuals to each other, that, with certain obvious
exceptions, any
male
and female may be moderately happy in the married state. The true
rule
is to ascertain that the match is fundamentally a good one, and
then to
take it for granted that all minor objections, should there be
such, will
vanish, if you let them alone. Only put yourself beyond hazard as
to the
real basis of matrimonial bliss, and it is scarcely to be imagined
what
miracles, in the way of recognizing smaller incongruities,
connubial love
will effect.
</p><p>For my own part I freely confess that, in my bachelorship,
I was precisely such an over-curious simpleton as I now advise the
reader
not to
be. My early habits had gifted me with a feminine sensibility and
too
exquisite refinement. I was the accomplished graduate of a dry
goods
store, where, by dint of ministering to the whims of fine ladies,
and suiting silken hose to delicate limbs, and handling satins,
ribbons,
chintzes
calicoes, tapes, gauze, and cambric needles, I grew up a very
ladylike
sort of a gentleman. It is not assuming too much to affirm that the
ladies
themselves were hardly so ladylike as Thomas Bullfrog. So painfully
   <pb n="1066"/>
acute was my sense of female imperfection, and such varied
excellence
did I require in the woman whom I could love, that there was an
awful
risk of my getting no wife at all, or of being driven to perpetrate
matrimony with my own image in the looking-glass. Besides the
fundamental
principle already hinted at, I demanded the fresh bloom of youth,
pearly
teeth, glossy ringlets, and the whole list of lovely items, with
the utmost
delicacy of habits and sentiments, a silken texture of mind, and,
above
all, a virgin heart. In a word, if a young angel just from
paradise, yet
dressed in earthly fashion, had come and offered me her hand, it is
by no
means certain that I should have taken it. There was every chance
of my
becoming a most miserable old bachelor, when, by the best luck in
the
world, I made a journey into another state, and was smitten by, and
smote again, and wooed, won, and married, the present Mrs.
Bullfrog,
all in the space of a fortnight. Owing to these extempore measures,
I not
only gave my bride credit for certain perfections which have not as
yet
come to light, but also overlooked a few trifling defects, which,
however,
glimmered on my perception long before the close of the honeymoon.
Yet, as there was no mistake about the fundamental principle
aforesaid,.
I soon learned, as will be seen, to estimate Mrs. Bullfrog's
deficiencies
and superfluities at exactly their proper value.
</p><p>The same morning that Mrs. Bullfrog and I came together as
a unit,
we took two seats in the stage-coach and began our journey towards
my
place of business. There being no other passengers, we were as much
alone
and as free to give vent to our raptures as if I had hired a hack
for the
matrimonial jaunt. My bride looked charmingly in a green silk
calash
and riding habit of pelisse cloth; and whenever her red lips parted
with a
smile, each tooth appeared like an inestimable pearl. Such was my
passionate warmth that&mdash;we had rattled out of the village, gentle
reader,
and were lonely as Adam and Eve in paradise&mdash;I plead guilty to no
less
freedom than a kiss. The gentle eye of Mrs. Bullfrog scarcely
rebuked
me for the profanation. Emboldened by her indulgence, I threw back
the
calash from her polished brow, and suffered my fingers, white and
delicate as her own, to stray among those dark and glossy curls
which
realized my daydreams of rich hair
</p><p>``My love,'' said Mrs. Bullfrog tenderly, ``you will
disarrange my
curls.''
</p><p>``Oh, no, my sweet Laura!'' replied I, still playing with
the glossy ringlet. ``Even your fair hand could not manage a curl
more delicately
than
mine. I propose myself the pleasure of doing up your hair in papers
every
evening at the same time with my own.''
</p><p>``Mr. Bullfrog,'' repeated she, ``you must not disarrange my
curls.''
</p><p>This was spoken in a more decided tone than I had happened
to hear,
until then, from my gentlest of all gentle brides. At the same time
she
put up her hand and took mine prisoner; but merely drew it away
from
the forbidden ringlet, and then immediately released it. Now, I am
a
fidgety little man, and always love to have something in my
fingers; so
that, being debarred from my wife's curls, I looked about me for
any
   <pb n="1067"/>
other plaything. On the front seat of the coach there was one of
those
small baskets in which travelling ladies who are too delicate to
appear
at a public table generally carry a supply of gingerbread, biscuits
and
cheese, cold ham, and other light refreshments, merely to sustain
nature
to the journey's end. Such airy diet will sometimes keep them in
pretty
good flesh for a week together. Laying hold of this same little
basket, I
thrust my hand under the newspaper with which it was carefully
covered.
</p><p>``What's this, my dear?'' cried I; for the black neck of a
bottle had
popped out of the basket.
</p><p>``A bottle of Kalydor, Mr. Bullfrog,'' said my wife, coolly
taking the
basket from my hands and replacing it on the front seat.
</p><p>There was no possibility of doubting my wife's word; but I
never knew
genuine Kalydor, such as I use for my own complexion, to smell so
much
like cherry brandy. I was about to express my fears that the lotion
would
injure her skin, when an accident occurred which threatened more
than a
skin-deep injury. Our Jehu had carelessly driven over a heap of
gravel
and fairly capsized the coach, with the wheels in the air and our
heels
where our heads should have been. What became of my wits I cannot
imagine; they have always had a perverse trick of deserting me just
when they were most needed; but so it chanced, that in the
confusion of
our overthrow I quite forgot that there was a Mrs. Bullfrog in the
world.
Like many men's wives, the good lady served her husband as a
stepping-stone. I had scrambled out of the coach and was
instinctively
settling my
cravat, when somebody brushed roughly by me, and I heard a smart
thwack upon the coachman's ear.
</p><p>``Take that, you villain!'' cried a strange, hoarse voice.
``You have
ruined me, you blackguard! I shall never be the woman I have
been!''
</p><p>And then came a second thwack, aimed at the driver's other
ear; but
which missed it, and hit him on the nose, causing a terrible
effusion of
blood. Now, who or what fearful apparition was inflicting this
punishment on the poor fellow remained an impenetrable mystery to
me. The
blows were given by a person of grisly aspect, with a head almost
bald,
and sunken cheeks, apparently of the feminine gender, though hardly
to
be classed in the gentler sex. There being no teeth to modulate the
voice,
it had a mumbled fierceness, not passionate, but stern, which
absolutely
made me quiver like calf's-foot jelly. Who could the phantom be?
The
most awful circumstance of the affair is yet to be told: for this
ogre, or
whatever it was, had a riding habit like Mrs. Bullfrog's, and also
a green
silk calash dangling down her back by the strings. In my terror and
turmoil of mind I could imagine nothing less than that the Old
Nick,
at the
moment of our overturn, had annihilated my wife and jumped into her
petticoats. This idea seemed the most probable, since I could
nowhere
perceive Mrs. Bullfrog alive, nor, though I looked very sharply
about the
coach, could I detect any traces of that beloved woman's dead body.
There would have been a comfort in giving her Christian burial.
</p><p>``Come, sir, bestir yourself! Help this rascal to set up the
coach,'' said
   <pb n="1068"/>
the hobgoblin to me; then, with a terrific screech at three
countrymen at
a distance, ``Here, you fellows, ain't you ashamed to stand off
when a
poor woman is in distress?''
</p><p>The countrymen, instead of fleeing for their lives, came
running at
full speed, and laid hold of the topsy-turvy coach. I, also, though
a small-sized man, went to work like a son of Anak. The coachman,
too, with
the
blood still streaming from his nose, tugged and toiled most
manfully,
dreading, doubtless, that the next blow might break his head. And
yet,
bemauled as the poor fellow had been, he seemed to glance at me
with an
eye of pity, as if my case were more deplorable than his. But I
cherished
a hope that all would turn out a dream, and seized the opportunity,
as
we raised the coach, to jam two of my fingers under the wheel,
trusting
that the pain would awaken me.
</p><p>``Why, here we are, all to rights again!'' exclaimed a sweet
voice behind. ``Thank you for your assistance, gentlemen. My dear
Mr. Bullfrog, how you perspire! Do let me wipe your face. Don't
take this
little
accident too much to heart, good driver. We ought to be thankful
that
none of our necks are broken.''
</p><p>``We might have spared one neck out of the three,'' muttered
the driver, rubbing his ear and pulling his nose, to ascertain
whether he
had been
cuffed or not. ``Why, the woman's a witch!''
</p><p>I fear that the reader will not believe, yet it is
positively a fact, that
there stood Mrs. Bullfrog, with her glossy ringlets curling on her
brow,
and two rows of orient pearls gleaming between her parted lips,
which
wore a most angelic smile. She had regained her riding habit and
calash
from the grisly phantom, and was, in all respects, the lovely woman
who
had been sitting by my side at the instant of our overturn. How she
had
happened to disappear, and who had supplied her place, and whence
she
did now return, were problems too knotty for me to solve. There
stood
my wife. That was the one thing certain among a heap of mysteries.
Nothing remained but to help her into the coach, and plod on,
through
the journey of the day and the journey of life, as comfortably as
we
could. As the driver closed the door upon us, I heard him whisper
to the
three countrymen,&mdash;
</p><p>``How do you suppose a fellow feels shut up in the cage with
a she
tiger?''
</p><p>Of course this query could have no reference to my
situation. Yet, unreasonable as it may appear, I confess that my
feelings were not
altogether so ecstatic as when I first called Mrs. Bullfrog mine.
True,
she
was a sweet woman and an angel of a wife; but what if a Gorgon
should
return, amid the transports of our connubial bliss, and take the
angel's
place. I recollected the tale of a fairy, who half the time was a
beautiful
woman and half the time a hideous monster. Had I taken that very
fairy
to be the wife of my bosom? While such whims and chimeras were
flitting across my fancy I began to look askance at Mrs. Bullfrog,
almost
expecting that the transformation would be wrought before my eyes.
</p><p>To divert my mind, I took up the newspaper which had covered
the
   <pb n="1069"/>
little basket of refreshments, and which now lay at the bottom of
the
coach, blushing with a deep-red stain and emitting a potent
spirituous
fume from the contents of the broken bottle of Kalydor. The paper
was
two or three years old, but contained an article of several
columns, in
which I soon grew wonderfully interested. It was the report of a
trial for
breach of promise of marriage, giving the testimony in full, with
fervid
extracts from both the gentleman's and lady's amatory
correspondence.
The deserted damsel had personally appeared in court, and had borne
energetic evidence to her lover's perfidy and the strength of her
blighted
affections. On the defendant's part there had been an attempt,
though
insufficiently sustained, to blast the plaintiff's character, and
a plea, in
mitigation of damages, on account of her unamiable temper. A
horrible
idea was suggested by the lady's name.
</p><p>``Madam,'' said I, holding the newspaper before Mrs.
Bullfrog's eyes,
&mdash;and, though a small, delicate, and thin-visaged man, I feel
assured that
I looked very terrific,&mdash;``madam,'' repeated I, through my shut
teeth,
``were you the plaintiff in this cause?''
</p><p>``Oh, my dear Mr. Bullfrog,'' replied my wife, sweetly, ``I
thought all
the world knew that!''
</p><p>``Horror! horror!'' exclaimed I, sinking back on the seat.
</p><p>Covering my face with both hands, I emitted a deep and
deathlike
groan, as if my tormented soul were rending me asunder&mdash;I, the most
exquisitely fastidious of men, and whose wife was to have been the
most
delicate and refined of women, with all the fresh dew-drops
glittering on
her virgin rosebud of a heart!
</p><p>I thought of the glossy ringlets and pearly teeth; I thought
of the
Kalydor; I thought of the coachman's bruised ear and bloody nose;
I
thought of the tender love secrets which she had whispered to the
judge
and jury and a thousand tittering auditors,&mdash;and gave another
groan!
</p><p>``Mr. Bullfrog,'' said my wife.
</p><p>As I made no reply, she gently took my hands within her own,
removed
them from my face, and fixed her eyes steadfastly on mine.
</p><p>``Mr. Bullfrog,'' said she, not unkindly, yet with all the
decision of her
strong character, ``let me advise you to overcome this foolish
weakness,
and prove yourself, to the best of your ability, as good a husband
as I
will be a wife. You have discovered, perhaps, some little
imperfections in
your bride. Well, what did you expect? Women are not angels. If
they
were, they would go to heaven for husbands; or, at least, be more
difficult in their choice on earth.''
</p><p>``But why conceal those imperfections?'' interposed I,
tremulously.
</p><p>``Now, my love, are not you a most unreasonable little
man?'' said
Mrs. Bullfrog, patting me on the cheek. ``Ought a woman to disclose
her
frailties earlier than the wedding day? Few husbands, I assure you,
make
the discovery in such good season, and still fewer complain that
these
trifles are concealed too long. Well, what a strange man you are!
Poh!
you are joking.''
</p><p>``But the suit for breach of promise!'' groaned I.
   <pb n="1070"/>
</p><p>``Ah, and is that the rub?'' exclaimed my wife. ``Is it
possible that you
view that affair in an objectionable light? Mr. Bullfrog, I never
could
have dreamed it! Is it an objection that I have triumphantly
defended
myself against slander and vindicated my purity in a court of
justice? Or
do you complain because your wife has shown the proper spirit of a
woman, and punished the villain who trifled with her affections?''
</p><p>``But,'' persisted I, shrinking into a corner of the coach,
however,&mdash;for
I did not know precisely how much contradiction the proper spirit
of a
woman would endure,&mdash;``but, my love, would it not have been more
dignified to treat the villain with the silent contempt he
merited?''
</p><p>``That is all very well, Mr. Bullfrog,'' said my wife,
slyly; ``but, in
that case, where would have been the five thousand dollars which
are to
stock your dry goods store?''
</p><p>``Mrs. Bullfrog, upon your honor,'' demanded I, as if my
life hung
upon her words, ``is there no mistake about those five thousand
dollars?''
</p><p>``Upon my word and honor there is none,'' replied she. ``The
jury gave
me every cent the rascal had; and I have kept it all for my dear
Bullfrog.''
</p><p>``Then, thou dear woman,'' cried I, with an overwhelming
gush of tenderness, ``let me fold thee to my heart. The basis of
matrimonial
bliss is
secure, and all thy little defects and frailties are forgiven. Nay,
since the
result has been so fortunate, I rejoice at the wrongs which drove
thee to
this blessed lawsuit. Happy Bullfrog that I am!''</p>

</div1>

</body>
</text>
</TEI.2>

