<?xml version="1.0"?>

<?dlps id="HenGive"?>
<?dlps page-images="none" figure-images="no"?>
<?dlps transcription="other"?>

<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/tei-p4/tei2.dtd" [
<!ENTITY % POSTKB "INCLUDE">
<!ENTITY % TEI.extensions.ent SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.ent">
<!ENTITY % TEI.extensions.dtd SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.dtd">
<!ENTITY % ISOnum SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/charent/iso-num.ent"> %ISOnum;
<!ENTITY % ISOpub SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/charent/iso-pub.ent"> %ISOpub;

]>
<TEI.2 id="HenGive">
<teiHeader type="migrated" creator="Etext">
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title type="main">The War Inevitable (Give Me Liberty or Give Me Death!)</title>
<title type="sort">war inevitable give me liberty or give me death</title>
<author>Henry, Patrick</author>
<respStmt>
<resp>creation of machine-readable version</resp>
<name>NOVA</name>
<resp>Conversion to TEI-conformant markup</resp>
<name>University of Virginia Library Electronic Text Center</name>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt>
<extent>ca. <num type="kilobytes">6</num> kilobytes</extent>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>University of Virginia Library</publisher>
<pubPlace>Charlottesville, Virginia</pubPlace>
<idno type="ETC">HenGive</idno>
<date value="1994">1994</date>
<availability status="public">
<p n="copyright">Copyright &copy; 1994 by the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia</p>
<p n="access">Publicly accessible</p>
</availability>
<idno type="uva-pid">uva-lib:476072</idno>
</publicationStmt>
<seriesStmt>
<title>University of Virginia Library, Text collection</title>
<idno type="uva-set">UVA-LIB-Text</idno>
</seriesStmt>
<sourceDesc>
<biblFull>
<titleStmt>
<title type="main">The War Inevitable (Give Me Liberty or Give Me Death!)</title>
<title type="sort">war inevitable give me liberty or give me death</title>
<author>Patrick Henry</author>
</titleStmt>
<publicationStmt>
<p/>
</publicationStmt>
</biblFull>
</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc>
<encodingDesc>
<projectDesc>
<p>Prepared for the University of Virginia Library Electronic Text Center</p>
</projectDesc>
<editorialDecl>
<p>All quotation marks retained as data</p>
<p>All unambiguous end-of-line hyphens have been removed, and the
trailing part of a word has been joined to the preceding line.</p>
<p>Spell-check and verification made
against printed text using WordPerfect spell checker</p>
<p id="ETC">Keywords in the header are a local Electronic Text Center scheme to aid in establishing analytical groupings</p>
</editorialDecl>
<refsDecl>
<p>ID elements are given for each page element and are composed of the text's
unique cryptogram and the given page number, as in SpeFQue1 for page one of
Spenser's Faerie Queene.</p>
</refsDecl>
</encodingDesc>
<profileDesc>
<creation>
<date value="1775-03">March 1775</date>
</creation>
<langUsage>
<language id="eng" usage="main">English</language>
</langUsage>
<textClass>
<keywords>
<term>CORD</term>
<term>democracy</term>
</keywords>
<keywords>
<term>non-fiction; prose</term>
</keywords>
</textClass>
</profileDesc>
<revisionDesc>
<change>
<date value="1992-12">December 1992</date>
<respStmt>
<name>Electronic Text Center</name>
</respStmt>
<item>minimal TEI tagging and spell-check</item>
</change>
<change>
<date value="1994-08">August 1994</date>
<respStmt>
<name>Jamie L Spriggs, Electronic Text Center, University of Virginia</name>
</respStmt>
<item>updated header, updated markup</item>
</change>
<change>
<date value="2005-07">July 2005</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>Corrector</resp>
<name>John Ivor Carlson</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Converted SGML to XML. Fixed tagging.</item>
</change>
<change>
<date value="2007-09">September 2007</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>Migration</resp>
<name>Ethan Gruber, University of Virginia Library</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Converted XML markup from TEI Lite to uva-dl-tei (TEI P4 with local customizations).</item>
</change>
<change>
<date value="2008-01">January 2008</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>Migration</resp>
<name>Greg Murray, University of Virginia Library</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Programmatically updated TEI header markup (but not header content) for minimal compliance with current QA requirements.</item>
</change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>
<text id="d1">

<body id="d2">

<div1 type="decree" id="d3"> <pb n="1" id="HenGive1"/><head>The War Inevitable </head>

<p>They tell us, Sir, that we are weak &mdash; unable to cope with so
formidable an adversary.  But when shall we be stronger?  Will
it be the next week, or the next year? Will it be when we are
totally disarmed, and when a British guard shall be stationed
in every house?  Shall we gather strength by irresolution and
inaction?  Shall we acquire the means of effectual resistance
by lying supinely on our backs, and hugging the delusive phantom
of hope, until our enemies shall have bound us hand and
foot? Sir, we are not weak, if we make a proper use of
those means which the God of nature hath placed in our
power.
</p>
<p>Three millions of People, armed in the holy cause of
liberty, and in such a country as that which we possess,
are invincible by any force which our enemy can send
against us. Beside, Sir, we shall not fight our battles alone.
There is a just God who presides over the destinies of
Nations, and who will raise up friends to fight our battles
for us.  The battle, Sir, is not to the strong alone. It is to
the vigilant, the active, the brave.  Besides, Sir, we have
no election. If we were base enough to desire it, it is now
too late to retire from the contest.  There is no retreat but
in submission and slavery!  Our chains are forged! Their
clanking may be heard on the plains of Boston! The war
is inevitable. and let it come! I repeat, Sir, let it come!
</p>
<p>It is in vain, Sir, to extenuate the matter.  Gentlemen
may cry, Peace, Peace! &mdash; but there is no peace. The war
is actually begun! The next gale that sweeps from the
North will bring to our ears the clash of resounding arms!
Our brethren are already in the field! Why stand we here
idle? What is it that Gentlemen wish? What would they
have? Is life so dear, or peace so sweet, as to be purchased
at the price of chains and slavery! Forbid it, Almighty
God! I know not what course others may take; but as for
me, give me liberty or give me death!
</p>

</div1>
</body>
</text>
</TEI.2>
