<?xml version="1.0"?>

<?dlps id="HimMilt"?>
<?dlps page-images="none" figure-images="no"?>
<?dlps transcription="other"?>

<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/tei-p4/tei2.dtd" [
<!ENTITY % POSTKB "INCLUDE">
<!ENTITY % TEI.extensions.ent SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.ent">
<!ENTITY % TEI.extensions.dtd SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.dtd">
<!ENTITY % ISOnum SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/charent/iso-num.ent"> %ISOnum;
<!ENTITY % ISOlat1 SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/charent/iso-lat1.ent"> %ISOlat1;
<!ENTITY % ISOpub SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/charent/iso-pub.ent"> %ISOpub;

]>

<TEI.2 id="HimMilt">
<teiHeader type="migrated" creator="Etext">
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title type="main">Milton's Angels</title>
<title type="sort">miltons angels</title>
<author>Himes, John A.</author>
<respStmt>
<resp>Creation of machine-readable version:</resp>
<name>Judy Boss</name>
<resp>Creation of digital images:</resp>
<name>Carolyn M. Fay</name>
<resp>Conversion to TEI.2-conformant markup:</resp>
<name>University of Virginia Library Electronic Text Center.</name>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt>
<extent>ca. <num type="kilobytes">42</num> kilobytes</extent>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>University of Virginia Library</publisher>
<pubPlace>Charlottesville, Virginia</pubPlace>
<idno type="ETC">HimMilt</idno>
<date value="1997">1997</date>
<availability status="public">
<p n="copyright">Copyright &copy; 1997 by the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia</p>
<p n="access">Publicly accessible</p>
</availability>
<idno type="uva-pid">uva-lib:476079</idno>
</publicationStmt>
<seriesStmt>
<title>University of Virginia Library, Text collection</title>
<idno type="uva-set">UVA-LIB-Text</idno>
</seriesStmt>
<notesStmt>
<note>
<p>In line 4 of paragraph 2 on page 537, Judy Boss has changed Deep" to Deep."</p>
</note>
</notesStmt>
<sourceDesc>
<biblFull>
<titleStmt>
<title type="main">Milton's Angels</title>
<title level="j">The New Englander, Volume 43</title>
<title type="sort">miltons angels</title>
<author>John A. Himes</author>
</titleStmt>
<extent>pp. 527-543</extent>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>A.H. Maltby</publisher>
<pubPlace>New Haven, CT</pubPlace>
<date value="1884">1884</date>
<idno type="callNo">Print copy consulted: photocopy of print source obtained via ILL from the University of Rochester library</idno>
</publicationStmt>
</biblFull>
</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc>
<encodingDesc>
<projectDesc>
<p>Prepared for the University of Virginia Library Electronic Text Center.</p>
</projectDesc>
<editorialDecl>
<p>All quotation marks retained as data.</p>
<p>All unambiguous end-of-line hyphens have been removed, and the trailing part of a word has been joined to the preceding line.</p>
<p>The images exist as archived TIFF images, one or more JPEG versions for general use, and thumbnail GIFs.</p>
<p>Keywords in the header are a local Electronic Text Center scheme to aid in establishing analytical groupings.</p>
</editorialDecl>
</encodingDesc>
<profileDesc>
<creation>
<date value="1884">1884</date>
</creation>
<langUsage>
<language id="eng" usage="main">English</language>
<language id="la">Latin</language>
</langUsage>
<textClass>
<keywords>
<term>prose; non-fiction</term>
</keywords>
</textClass>
</profileDesc>
<revisionDesc>
<change>
<date value="1997-06">June, 1997</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>corrector</resp>
<name>Carolyn M. Fay, Electronic Text Center</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Added TEI header and tags</item>
</change>
<change>
<date value="2005-07">July 2005</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>Corrector</resp>
<name>John Ivor Carlson</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Converted SGML to XML. Fixed tagging.</item>
</change>
<change>
<date value="2007-09">September 2007</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>Migration</resp>
<name>Ethan Gruber, University of Virginia Library</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Converted XML markup from TEI Lite to uva-dl-tei (TEI P4 with local customizations).</item>
</change>
<change>
<date value="2008-01">January 2008</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>Migration</resp>
<name>Greg Murray, University of Virginia Library</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Programmatically updated TEI header markup (but not header content) for minimal compliance with current QA requirements.</item>
</change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text id="d1">
<body id="d2">

<div1 type="essay" id="d3"> <pb n="527"/>
<head>ARTICLE V. &mdash; MILTON'S ANGELS.</head>


<p>IN an article on the <hi rend="italic">Plan of Paradise Lost</hi>, published in
this periodical, March, 1883, the writer had occasion to speak of
certain characteristics of Milton's supernatural beings.  A systematic
account of these beings did not come within the scope of that paper,
but the interest of the subject may perhaps make its separate
treatment from a new standpoint not unwelcome.  Other writers have
considered Milton's angels mainly as products of literary art; I wish
to examine them as products of thought, giving attention to the inner
meaning rather than to the outward form.  Convinced that there has
already been too much unintelligent criticism, I venture upon the far
more difficult and in some respects perilous task of interpretation.
With little to say about the soundness or the propriety of the poet's
methods and opinions, I shall content myself with inquiring what they
are.

</p><p>A glance at the first drafts of <hi rend="italic">Paradise Lost</hi>, when the
subject was still under consideration for dramatic treatment, will
discover among the <foreign lang="la">dramatis
person&aelig;</foreign>a large preponderance
of what are known as allegorical characters, such as Conscience,
Death, Ignorance, Justice, Faith, Hope, and Wisdom.  There is a
noticeable tendency, as the work progresses, towards a substitution of
what may be called real for allegorical characters &mdash; a translation of
the abstract into the concrete.  The substitution is not complete even
in the finished epic, as we see in the presence of such characters as
Sin, Death, Chaos, and Night.  Hence have arisen the criticisms of
Addison, Landor and others condemning the mixture of allegory and
plain fact.

</p><p>The original abstractions, however, do not disappear from
the stage, but remain under the forms and names of the pagan
gods of western Asia and southern Europe.  The spirits who
meet and contend in battle are the virtues and vices that wage
perpetual war in man's moral nature and by sympathy cause
disorder and ruin even in the external world.  The gods of the
heathen had their origin in ideas.  Men did not grossly worship
   <pb n="528"/>

the rudely carved or moulded masses of wood, stone, and metal, but
they offered devotion to an idea which the image merely brought to
mind.  Mars was honored by every nation that delighted in war for its
own sake; Minerva was reverenced wherever philosophy was made the
chief end of life.  The ceremonies with which at special times the
divinity was worshiped were mere external signs of the inward life of
the people.  Starting with this spiritual conception of the gods of
old &mdash; gods still at the present day, though not openly acknowledged
&mdash; Milton was able to give his descriptions, a verisimilitude which
perhaps could have been gained in no other way, and at the same time
to proceed with that confidence and positiveness which come only from
the consciousness of stating unassailable truth.

</p><p>With a little careful thought it is possible in most cases to
determine with certainty what moral quality each of Milton's
characters is intended to represent.  The form, stature, attire, words
and actions of each are always consistent with its central nature.
Each is also associated with some force, agent, or phenomenon in the
material world which suggests and illustrates it.  Besides, the gods
of the Orient and those of the Occident were essentially the same, so
that while the poet commonly prefers the Biblical names and
descriptions, his spirits may and do reappear in the lines of Homer
and Virgil.  This fact often gives us the advantage of two sets of
examples to fix the precise nature of each spirit.  Even when a spirit
is merely named, and that but once, we have usually the means of
finding the reasons for its introduction.  Let us examine some of the
results which a course of study under the guidance of these principles
has given.

</p><p>To avoid the confusion which would come from an attempt to
carry on all the parts of the subject together, I propose to notice
first the moral qualities which the spirits represent, then the
external forms in which they appear, and afterward the relation of
Milton's characters to Homer's and Virgil's.  The moral part may be
regarded as the essential nature of the characters which the external
form is intended to manifest and illustrate to human sense; while the
identification of his characters with those of the epic writers of
old, gives Milton a literary authority which cannot be spoken against.
   <pb n="529"/>

</p><p>The good and the evil spirits, then, represent respectively the
virtues and the vices in the moral constitution of the world.  On one
side are arrayed right principles, noble aspirations, and pure
affections; on the other, wrong ambitions, headstrong passions, and
debasing lusts.  It is certain, to begin with, that the seven spirits
who rise singly after Satan and Beelzebub from the burning lake, are
intended to personate the Seven Deadly Sins so much celebrated in
early English poetry.  There is clear reason for bringing them out in
the order in which they come, &mdash; Murder, Lust, Pride, Envy,
Covetousness, Gluttony, and Idleness.  Murder and Lust are the first
recorded sins resulting from the Fall of Man; hence Moloch and Chemosh
are the first to respond to Satan's call.  There is no difficulty in
recognizing the spirit of Murder or War in the grim features and the
blood-stained form of Moloch.  The instruments of martial music (the
poet calls it "noise") and the tears of parents for slain sons are
inseparably associated with him who is worshiped in Rabbath
(Contention).  Nor are we left in doubt as to the identity of Chemosh
in "the flowery dale of Sibma clad with vines," revelling in obscenity
and scandal, in wanton rites and lustful orgies.  Astarte is crowned
with a crescent moon, whose horns are the symbol of haughtiness, and
she is the tutelary divinity of Tyre and Sidon, cities repeatedly
denounced in prophecy for their excessive Pride.  Astarte is followed
by Thammuz, as Pride is followed by Envy.  Thammuz is wounded by the
prosperity of others, just as the snows on Lebanon melt away and stain
with the color of blood the swollen Adonis under the beneficent heat
of the summer sun.  After Envy, and closely related, comes
Covetousness, typified in Dagon, the god of fertility and thrift,
whose temple was in Azotus (Theft).  After the spirit of Covetousness
has secured the bounties and luxuries of this life, the "sottish" Ahaz
(Possessor) turns to the worship of Rimmon (Pomegranate), a god of
agriculture and the fit representative of Gluttony.  It was precisely
at the point of transition from the worship of Covetousness to the
worship of Gluttony that the rich fool of the parable was arrested by
the hand of death (Luke xii. 15-20).  Rimmon is accompanied by the
Egyptian gods of brutish form, to signify that Gluttony is akin to all
sorts of Bestiality.

   <pb n="530"/>
Belial, the spirit of Idleness, which is called the sin of Sodom
and her daughters (Ezek. xvi. 59), fitly comes last of the seven
chief devils.  When Belial takes possession of the magistrates
in church or State, the filthiness of Sodom is sure to follow.

</p><p>Satan is the embodiment of Ambition, which is the best
expression in a single word of "the spirit that now worketh in the
children of disobedience."  There is a hint of its wandering,
unsettled nature in the very word.  Among men it is seen aspiring
sometimes to military glory, sometimes to wealth, and sometimes to
regal power, and descending to the lowest arts to gain its end.  Hence
Satan may act in the spirit of Moloch, of Mammon, or of Belial, and is
fitly called the head of the whole body of demons.  He is the
principle of evil in general and the adversary of all good.  Before
the truth-loving Uriel he represents Hypocrisy; before the wise
Gabriel, Folly; before the faithful Abdiel, Skepticism; before the
righteous Michael, the lifeless Letter of the Law.  In the colloquy
with Gabriel his acts and words are in every respect those ascribed in
Proverbs to the fool, scorner, and wicked person, while Gabriel
opposes him with the words and acts of the wise and faithful man who
is contrasted with the fool.  The breaking up of the colloquy is
exceedingly significant.  It is decided by the appearance of the
heavenly balance in which are two weights, &mdash; "the sequel each of
parting and of fight."  The two weights are nothing else than the two
consecutive proverbs: "Answer not a fool according to his folly, lest
thou also be like unto him," and "Answer a fool according to his
folly, lest he be wise in his own conceit."  To answer the fool, that
is, to continue the dispute, would be an act of useless folly on the
part of the censor; to cease answering, that is, to part, would leave
the fool to his folly; but there would then be only one fool instead
of two, as in the other case.  The latter, namely parting, is
therefore to the eye of Wisdom the weightier, making its scale of the
balance descend, and Gabriel brings the dispute to a close.

</p><p>Michael, the select Scriptural antagonist of Satan, is the
impersonation of Justice or Righteousness.  In one of the
original drafts of <hi rend="italic">Paradise Lost</hi> we find one of the characters
set down as "Michael or Moses," a hint that the two are somehow

   <pb n="531"/>
very nearly akin, if not identical, in meaning.  Moses is
the lawgiver, and the divine Law is the very embodiment of
Justice.  When Michael contends with Satan about the body
of Moses (Jude 9), the dispute is over the law which Moses
gave.  There was such a dispute when Satan tempted Christ
in the wilderness and quoted Scripture to gain his ends.
There was many a dispute like it afterwards, when the lawyers
at Jerusalem attempted to condemn Christ with the letter of
the Law and were by him confounded with its spirit.  In all
these cases Christ represented Michael defending the Law
against its enemy.  This, too, is the meaning of that victory
of Michael over Satan in the Heavenly War; and throughout
the poem every act of the martial angel is consistent with the
central idea of Justice.

</p><p>Beelzebub on the part of the apostates and Gabriel on the part
of the saints are spirits of Wisdom; the first that which resides in
the children of this world, the second that in the children of light.
Both spirits are distinguished by their calm deliberation and
self-restraint; and fitly therefore in the celestial strife is Gabriel
opposed to the furious Moloch.  Both are associated with Strength;
Beelzebub by his "Atlantean shoulders fit to bear the weight of
mightiest monarchies," Gabriel by having joined with himself Uzziel
(Strength of God) as his second in command.

</p><p>Uriel in his station at the sun, whence he views the whole
creation, is the angel of Truth, and furnishes Gabriel with the
information necessary to the fulfillment of his charge.  Sharpsighted
as he is, he cannot discern the hypocrisy in the heart of the
zealous-seeming Satan any more than the wise men of the East could of
themselves discover the deceit of the murderous Herod.  In battle he
defeats Adrammelech, who prob-ably stands for Ignorance and is a
truly formidable foe.  To vanquish the ignorance of men and with the
light of truth to dispel their superstitions is one of the most
important aims of Christianity.

</p><p>Raphael, the sensitive and sympathetic spirit of Love,
overcomes in Heaven the stolid and cruel Asmadai who probably
represents Indolence.  In accordance with his nature as the angel of
Love, Raphael is known as "the sociable spirit" and

   <pb n="532"/>

is selected by Heaven to bear to earth a message of pity and warning.
Like the Beloved in the Song of Songs, when coming into the Garden, he
takes his way, himself a dispenser of "heavenly fragrance," "through
groves of myrrh and flowering odors, cassia, nard, and balm."  He
hears in the evening of that blissful day in Paradise Adam's avowal of
love for Eve and the inquiry about love among the angels in Heaven.
The question innocently drawn at a venture touched the innermost
nature of Raphael and caused that smile "which glowed celestial
rosy-red, love's proper hue" to mantle the angel's countenance at
leave-taking.

</p><p>Of the remaining spirits Azazel, the ensign-bearer, represents
Fame, proud, fickle as the winds, brief as a meteor flash.  Mammon is
the spirit of Worldliness; Mulciber of Art and Industry, commendable
when holding the place of a servant in Heaven, but destined to
overthrow when assuming to be himself a god and making his works an
end instead of a means.  Ithuriel is Memory, and the spear in his hand
is the Divine command to Adam and Eve; Zephon is Conscience: both
Conscience and the Word of God are declared to be searchers of the
heart of man (Prov. xx. 27; Heb. iv. 12).  Abdiel is Faith, and a blow
from his sword staggers the skeptical Satan, or in Scriptural metaphor
removes the mountain into the sea (vi.  193-198).  Nisroch is
Selfishness; Zophiel the Modesty which blushes and is offended at the
sight of whatever is shameful.

</p><p>The three days of war in Heaven symbolize three distinct phases
of the conflict between good and evil in the history of the world and
in the life of man.  On the first day, as has been hinted, the contest
is over the Law, the Spirit of which dwells in Michael while the
Letter is usurped by Satan.  The perfect order and discipline in the
loyal army, the equipment of the least member of it with the force of
all the elements, and the possession by each legion of the fighting
strength of the whole army are not merely rhetorical flights but
profoundly significant truths.  The perfect consistency and
completeness of the Law, the fact that the smallest jot or tittle has
a greater validity than the course of nature, and that one commandment
cannot be broken without violating the whole Law, are some of the
Scriptural principles embodied.  The armor

   <pb n="533"/>

of the saints is the inviolable panoply spoken of in the letters of
St. Paul (Eph. vi. 10-18), while the spears, arrows, and swords are
the precepts of the Divine Word.  It will be remembered that in the
Song of Songs (iv. 4) the neck of the Bride is compared to a tower
"builded for an armory."  This is a part of the same figure setting
forth that the Divine precepts are proclaimed by the true church in
opposition to the dictates of injustice, wrong, and violence disguised
under the show of reason and justice.  We are thus led to see that
this conflict between the spirit and the letter of the law is
essentially the same as Milton means when he speaks elsewhere of the
grap-ple of truth and falsehood.

</p><p>On the second day the battle-ground is shifted by the defeated
rebels from the intellect to the affections.  In the preceding
night-council Nisroch, the spirit of Selfishness, had complained of
the pain suffered from wounds and exertion, and had called for an
easier mode of warfare.  Satan then proposed a plan which, when
stripped of its allegorical dress, means the enlistment of fleshly
lusts against the Divine Spirit.  Entertainment of these lusts in the
heart soon renders it callous &mdash; "past feeling" as Paul expresses it
&mdash; and thus secures Nisroch's wished-for painlessness.  The presence
of these same lusts, as is shown by the experience of Lot in Sodom, is
exceedingly offensive to the pure sensibilities of the good.  Hence
the significance of the modest Zephiel, turning his back to the gross
array of the enemy, and warning his friends to shield their eyes and
hearts against the coming attack.  Hence, too, the prominence into
which the idle Belial rises in the other host, and the low wit that
brings confusion upon the good.  The weapon of the satanic host now is
laughter propelled from callous hearts filled with lust.  The saints
throw away their armor; it is worse than useless to offer spiritual
truth to imbruted natures &mdash; to cast pearls before swine.  They hurl
mountains upon the devilish engines and upon the devisers of the
same.  In like manner upon earth the laughter of drunkards and
libertines is overwhelmed by wide-spread sorrow and disaster,
inflicted either by retributive justice, or as the inevitable
consequence of self-indulgence.  "The end of that mirth is
heaviness."  The good suffer somewhat in this last

   <pb n="534"/>

encounter, but, unlike their adversaries, are not impeded in their
movements by any armor.  So too when heavy calamities fall upon the
earth, the righteous, unwedded to worldly pleasures and riches, escape
with scarcely a sigh, while the pleasure-loving, bound to their
material possessions, release themselves with many a groan.

</p><p>The third is a "sacred" day upon which, under the visible
captaincy of the Messiah, the saints are finally victorious.  The
Divine Leader is arrayed in the majesty and terror of the last
judgment.  He rides on the clouds (cherubs), and his chariot moves
with the sound of a whirlwind reminding those who have sown the wind
that the time for reaping has now come.  He calls his faithful
warriors, approves their fidelity, unites them with his attendant
angels, and makes them one host.  He proposes to test the physical
strength of his enemies, just as at the last day, when he comes to
judge men, he will try their works, not their creeds.  The thunder
which he hurls is the Divine laughter at the folly of creatures made
reasonable, and is essentially that of wisdom: "I also will laugh at
your calamity; I will mock when your fear cometh."  It is in exact
harmony with what has recently been designated as "the laughter of the
soul at itself."

</p><p>A more minute interpretation of the points in this description
would be fitting, if we were annotating Milton's text, but enough has
been given to establish our proposition as to the allegorical
significance of the angels of <hi rend="italic">Paradise Lost</hi>.  Let us inquire,
in the next place, how the poet represents these beings to the natural
sense.  What are those "corporal forms" (v. 571-574) in which he
expresses spiritual things?

</p><p>Hints of external form for the angels, though somewhat
indefinite, are not rare in the Scriptures.  Satan is not only
the spirit that works in the children of disobedience; he is
also "the prince of the power of the air."  What meaning
Milton took from this and other expressions of a similar kind
is apparent in a hundred lines of the second book (528-628),
which contain a classification of the demons on the basis of
their physical nature.  In this passage, while the subdivisions
are variously marked, the word "part" is used with great
exactness to distinguish the main classes.  The first use of the

   <pb n="535"/>

word "part" is to introduce the spirits of <hi rend="italic">Water</hi> who hurry
through the air on wings as clouds or run fleetly over the land on foot
as mists.  The second "part" includes spirits of <hi rend="italic">Fire</hi>, celestial
and terrestrial, heat-producing and light-giving.<ref
target="n1">[*]</ref> The third "part" embraces spirits of <hi rend="italic">Air</hi>,
whether gentle as in rambling breezes, or violent as in tempest
("<foreign lang="la">velut agmine facto</foreign>") waging war
against whatever stands erect.  The Winds, four in number, Boreas,
Eurus, Notus, and Zephyrus, take up their "flying march" (through the
air as in flight and along the ground as in marching) to search for rest
every vale and highland in that world of darkness.

</p><p>From this may be understood the broad and important distinction
between Cherubim and Seraphim.  The quality of luminosity is the
foundation of the distinction.  The Seraphim are bright and furnish
light as original sources; the Cherubim may be either bright or dark,
but their brightness is always reflected.  Angels of heat and light
are Seraphim; those of air and vapor are Cherubim.  Uriel, regent of
the sun, is a Seraph; Gabriel, regent of the moon and the air is a
Cherub.  According to the same rule Raphael and Abdiel are Seraphim,
while Beelzebub and Azazel, Zephon and Zophiel are Cherubim.  When
Satan is at one time enclosed with "a globe of fiery Seraphim," and at
another "with flaming Cherubim and golden shields," there is the same
difference between the scenes as between the sun in a clear sky
encircled with his dazzling rays, and the same luminary at another
time surrounded with golden-edged clouds.

</p><p>As might be inferred from this, the activity of the spirits
always conforms to that of the elements in nature.  In the first
book the account telling of the formation of the devils from a
disordered mass into a perfect phalanx serves almost equally
well as a poetical description of sunrise in a deeply clouded
sky.  The obscure, doubtful glimpse of dawn at the discovery
of Satan's hopefulness, the meteor-gleam at the unfurling of
the imperial ensign, the orient colors of the waving banners,

   <pb n="536"/>

the rays of light in the bristling spears, the dazzling arms, the
half-eclipsed, new-risen sun, and finally the blaze of brightness
signalizing the birth of new enterprise, form a succession of scenes
like those attending the growth of the faintest glimmer of morning
into perfect day.  In the fourth book, the capture of Satan in
Paradise and his expulsion therefrom are described under figures
implying the generation of a night-cloud which blots the clear sky,
interferes with the moonlight, threatens disorder and ruin, but is
dissipated at the coming of day.  In the tenth book, the
transformation of the devils into serpents like those sprung from the
blood of Gorgon (the storm cloud) is suggested by the condensation of
clouds into rain fallen and winding about in brooks and rivers.

</p><p>The sixth book affords further illustrations.  The prophet
Ezekiel (xxxviii. 9) tells of enemies of God's people to come
out of the North, like a storm and like a cloud, to overspread
and lay waste the land of the faithful.  To this central idea
Milton most carefully conforms in describing the celestial wars
to human sense.

</p><p>The engagement of the first day is founded upon the idea of
a storm &mdash; a struggle between the adverse powers of heat and cold.
There is a premonition of it during the previous night, when
"in a flame of zeal severe" Abdiel "opposed the current" of
rebellious fury.  The army of apostates on its march, "hasting
with furious expedition," was like a wind from the North.  In
contrast with this disorderly haste moved the faithful host, &mdash;</p>

<lg type="verse">
<l>"In silence their bright legions to the sound</l>
<l>Of instrumental harmony that breathed</l>
<l>Heroic <hi rend="italic">ardour</hi> to adventurous deeds."</l>
</lg>

<p>A preliminary single combat took place between the zealous,
flaming Abdiel and the skeptical ruler of the North, haughty
and cold, fresh from his icy mountain palace.  When general
battle was joined,</p>

<lg type="verse">
<l>"Storming fury rose</l>
<l>And clamour such as heard in Heaven till now</l>
<l>Was never."</l>
</lg>

<p>While many of the citable expressions might be used metaphorically in
describing an earthly battle, we have the best authority, that of
Milton himself, for saying that they are not

   <pb n="537"/>

to be so understood.  On the other hand, when corporeal objects are
mentioned, they must be etherealized to reach the truth.  The spears,
darts, swords, shields and helmets, used by the contending hosts, are
nothing grosser than beams of light, rays of heat, flashes of flame,
and masses of cloud.  Spirits of cold, as well as spirits of heat may
hurl fiery darts, for intense cold produces the same sensation as
intense heat (ii. 595).

</p><p>Some of the individual powers who are active in the conflict
are easily recognized as embodiments of elemental phenomena.  Calm and
Bluster, Heat and Cold, Light and Darkness, meet and contend in the
persons of Gabriel and Moloch, Raphael and Asmadai, Uriel and
Adrammelech.  The spirits of Heat and Light are victorious in the
first encounter, and the defeated forces withdraw to reorganize during
the night for another struggle.  Nisroch rises in the council "with
cloudy aspect;" or, in other words, the North Wind changes countenance
and proposes a different mode of warfare for which preparation is at
once made.

</p><p>The second stage of the struggle spoken of by Ezekiel is
reached.  The enemies of the saints next come "like a cloud."  They
dig down through the heavenly mould and bring instruments of offence
from "the Deep."  They prepare to counterfeit the thunderbolts of the
Almighty.  They approach the field of battle on the next morning with
less haste, but threateningly, like a cloud laden with hail.  The
coming is heralded by Zophiel, a loyal scout, the Iris of <hi rend="italic">Paradise
Lost</hi>, the spirit of the Morning Red.  He is the swiftest of
Cherubim, flies in mid-air, announces the coming of the enemy as a
thick cloud and admonishes his friends to bear their shields,</p>

<lg type="verse">
<l>"Even or high: for this day will pour down,</l>
<l>If I conjecture aught, no drizzling shower,</l>
<l>But rattling storm of arrows barbed with fire."</l>
</lg>

<p>The enemy approaches "gross and huge," "with heavy pace," and with
"shadowing squadrons deep."  The rattling hailstones begin to fall,
benumbing whomever they touch.  But the angry heat of the loyal host
soon puts an end to the storm of hail, and the struggle goes on, under
the ever deepening cloud-masses, to the end of the day and through the
night, until at day-break of the third day the Messiah appears with
thunderbolts,

   <pb n="538"/>

and a rainbow, and the clear sky, and the sunlight &mdash; all at his
command.  Order is restored throughout the Empyrean, the horizon wall
is broken only where the defeated rebels are retreating, and the
scattered rear of the fleeing host is disappearing like a frightened
flock of goats.

</p><p>Enough has now been said to show the blunder of the many
who, following Dr. Johnson, down to the present time, have
laughed at</p>

<lg type="verse">
<l>"Those comic-dreadful wars</l>
<l>Where, armed with gross and inconclusive steel,</l>
<l>Immortals smite immortals mortal-wise,</l>
<l>And fill all Heaven with folly."<ref target="n2">[*]</ref></l>
</lg>

<p>Whether this exposition of his method will cause a greater admiration
of Milton is an entirely distinct question.  The present age, if I
read it aright, has little taste for allegory, and there may even be a
feeling of disappointment at the discovery that Milton's descriptions
are not light products of fancy with no deeper meaning than lies on
the surface.  My present purpose, however, is not to commend Milton to
men of this generation; it is only to reach a firm basis from which to
judge his work; though it must be evident from what is to follow that
if allegory can be charged as a fault against Milton the charge will
lie equally against Homer and Virgil, his models in epic poetry.

</p><p>In Milton, for example, the victory of Gabriel over Moloch
is clearly intended to teach the superiority of Wisdom to brute
Force, or of self-restraint to fury; but precisely the same
moral is taught in Homer by the victories of Pallas over Mars.
Besides, Pallas had among the Grecian heroes at Troy two
special favorites, Diomed and Ulysses: Milton's Gabriel, the
wisest of the angels, is copied chiefly from the former; while
Beelzebub, the wisest of the devils, is copied from the latter.
Gabriel has a subordinate in Uzziel (Strength of God), and
Diomed's second in command is Sthenelus (Strength).  The
strength of Beelzebub is shown in his "Atlantean shoulders;"
the strength of Ulysses also is in his broad shoulders.  The moral
of both poets is that wisdom is strong (Prov. viii. 14), and
moreover that it is better than strength (Eccl. ix. 16).

   <pb n="539"/>

</p><p>The nature of true Peace and Love is shown in Raphael, of false
Peace and Love in Belial; but Homer has set forth the same in his
Mercury and Juno.  The difference is that Homer has distinguished by
his two characters between Peace and Love, naming the former Mercury
and the latter Juno; while Milton has united Peace and Love, but has
divided the pure from the impure characteristics in each, giving the
former to Raphael and the latter to Belial.  When Raphael, attired like
Juno on her mission of reconciliation to the distracted household of
Oceanus (<hi rend="italic">Il.</hi> xiv. 178-189), is coming from Heaven, the earth
appears to him among the stars as Delos or Samos to a pilot among the
Cyclades.  Juno regarded Samos with special favor as the place where
she was worshiped as the goddess of marriage and birth, while she
looked upon Delos with abhorrence as the place that had given shelter
to her rival Latona (Death).  To Raphael the primitive earth might
appear either a Samos or a Delos, a place of either favor or
abhorrence, as it would prove a harbor of life or of death.

</p><p>Mammon, "the god of this world," is the ancient Jupiter who
overthrew his father Saturn (Time), and who is the patron deity of old
men like Nestor &mdash; conquerors of Time in outliving the natural age of
man.  The relation to old men will give a reason for the bent form of
Mammon; and his identity with Jupiter will account for almost every
sentiment of his speech in the council.  Moloch is Mars with the same
blustering and furious temper.  Satan is Apollo, manifesting the
characteristics of that god and of the men whom he inspires, chiefly
Hector, but also Paris, Sarpedon, and others.  Michael, the spirit of
retributive Justice, is governed by the same impulses as the
swift-footed Achilles (Pitiless), the son of the sea-deity Thetis
(Law).  The first day's battle in Heaven closely resembles the contest
of the Greeks and the Trojans over the dead body of Patroclus; and the
meeting of Michael and Satan has many striking points of likeness to
that of Achilles and Hector, one of the most important being that
Satan, like Hector, fights in armor belonging rightfully to his
adversary.

</p><p>The characters with English names follow the same law of
resemblance.  Sin in her attractive beauty has the characteristics of
Venus; in her power over the heart those of Hecate,
   <pb n="540"/>

the goddess of witchcraft; in her deceitfulness those of the Palladium
of Troy, which, strange as it may seem, is the representative of
falsehood.  Death is like Neptune, the dark-haired ruler of the seas.
He has the same god-like, terrible stride that shakes the earth, the
same trident, the same skill with horses, the same power to quiet
turbulent waves &mdash; human society being the waters over which he
rules.  Chaos is the same as Saturn, or Pluto, timid, irresolute,
guarding with jealous care the secrets and riches of his anarchy, and
swallowing up almost instantaneously the children which he begets.
Mulciber for good reasons has a Latin name; but reversing our process
we easily identify him with the Baal of the east, who in the contest
of his prophets with the prophet of the true God also fell "From morn
to noon, from noon to dewy eve, a summer's day."  (1 Kings xviii. 26,
29).

</p><p>Occasionally, or indeed frequently, a resemblance to Homer or
an allusion to mythology has attracted the attention of commentators;
but no one, not even Patrick Hume, seems to have suspected how far the
resemblance is carried, or how different from mere chance and whim has
been its determining motive.  Most of the points of likeness do not
lie on the surface, but they are easily discovered when we know the
underlying law that regulates them.  It is in virtue of the existence
of the same moral quality &mdash; ambition, wisdom, hate, love, or truth &mdash;
in Milton's characters and in Homer's that they act and speak alike.
Beelzebub never expresses the sentiments of Mars, nor Moloch those of
Minerva.  If we were to find these opposite spirits using the same
expressions in speech, we should infer that it came from accident.
When the identity of Moloch with Mars has once been discovered, the
field of classical investigation in his case becomes very limited.  It
is useless to look anywhere except at the words and acts of the war-god
and of the men whom he inspires.  And so of all the rest.  Hence it is
evident that the spirits cannot exchange places in the poem, that
Zephon and Ithuriel or Nisroch and Azazel cannot perform each other's
tasks.  The nature of the spirits, Homeric and Miltonic, is simple;
their activity manifests itself in but one direction.  However true it
is that one of them

   <pb n="541"/>

may overpower and dominate a man, yet one man has the capacity of
legions of spirits.

</p><p>One more important point of likeness between Homer's deities
and Milton's angels remains to be noticed.  It consists in the fact
that both kinds may become tutelary divinities of nations and places
and therefore have a representative function.  Jupiter was the special
deity of Elis, Juno of Argos, Minerva of Athens, Apollo of Lycia, and
Venus of Cyprus.  Certain angels have a like office assigned to them
by the prophet Daniel.  The closing part of the first book of
<hi rend="italic">Paradise Lost</hi> cannot be fully understood unless the
representative function of some of the angels is kept in mind.  Those
who are summoned to the council in Pandemonium "by place or choice the
worthiest," have such an office, and gather, like members of a
legislative body, to consult for the common welfare.  But in the case
before us they are wholly subordinated to the greater powers who
retain their own colossal dimensions in the council.  The
representative spirits, summoned "from every band and squared
regiment," find the council hall too small for their admittance in
their natural size; and for the privilege of going within they submit
to a reduction to "less than smallest dwarfs."  Unique as the scene
is, it is intended, like every other in the poem, to set forth a fact
in human history.  It proceeds upon the idea that since the Spirit of
Antichrist is the same, his operations are the same in Hell as in this
world.  The volcanic mountain, the plain near by with its busy
industries, the sluice from the burning lake, and lastly, the capital
"city and proud seat of Lucifer," strongly suggest to us Mount
Vesuvius, the Campania, Agrippa's sluice from Lake Avernus and
imperial Rome.  The council-hall itself is modeled upon the Roman
Pantheon, both in name and in architecture.  The thousand demigods in
their "secret conclave" represent to the Puritan poet the evil powers
and proud tyrannies that had their seats at Rome (Rev.  xviii. 2).
The spirits summoned from without represent the nations, tribes, and
municipalities of Europe.  The ambition of the emperors and then of
the popes, reaching out over the nations of Christendom, reduced to
insignificance the authority and dignity of their rulers.  The
comparison of the representative    <pb n="542"/>

spirits to <hi rend="italic">apes</hi> (the "Pygm&aelig;an race beyond the Indian
mount")<ref target="n3">[*]</ref> is the satire of a patriot who
always despised submission to a foreign potentate and all imitation of
the antics of a corrupt hierarchy.  During the Dark Ages there arose in
Europe a belief in a class of spirits known as fairies, whose diminutive
size compared with the heroic stature of the gods of old well sets forth
the difference between the real and the nominal power of civil
governments under the supremacy of Rome.  The representatives of
national dignity, intent upon their trifling pleasures and unconscious
of their littleness are compared to the fairies dancing under the eye of
the peasant who views them with mingled joy and fear &mdash; joy that the
tyranny of his home rulers is broken, and fear lest the foreign tyranny
is about to be something worse, or at least more degrading.

</p><p>A natural question arises here, Did Milton, then, reject
entirely the doctrine of Angels as real beings in the economy of the
spirit world?  Much as he has to say about spirits in <hi rend="italic">Paradise
Lost</hi>, the facts here brought to view might indicate that the
angels have no substantial, independent existence and are not believed
by the poet to have any.  It looks as though the characters of the
poem were mere forms of thought, the creation not of God but of man.
In the examination of Milton's prose writings, however, we find this
theory failing.  In the <hi rend="italic">Christian Doctrine</hi> the angels are
treated as independent essences, living before the creation of man and
acting first upon him instead of being originated by him.  We must not
imagine, either, that they are one thing in prose and another in
verse.  Whether in prose or verse, the prominent aim of Milton was
truth.  The invocation of the Holy Spirit at the

   <pb n="543"/>

beginning of his greatest poem would be unintelligible, if it did not
preface a reverent expression of divinely revealed truth.  We are,
then, shut up, apparently, to the conclusion that Milton intends to
treat what we know as abstractions, the virtues and the vices of our
moral constitution, as actual, independent beings in the invisible
world.  The world of spirits, at least it is evident, is on the same
plan as the world of spirit which we may become acquainted with by the
study of our own higher, immortal nature.
</p>

<note id="n1"><seg type="note-symbol">[*]</seg> <p>I am obliged to content myself with giving merely the
results derived from an extended and careful comparison of the games
described by Milton with those of the Iliad and the &AElig;neid and with
the various contests, physical, aesthetic, and intellectual described in
the histories and the fables of ancient Greece.</p></note>

<note id="n2"><seg type="note-symbol">[*]</seg> <p>Sidney Lanier in the <hi rend="italic">N. Y. Independent</hi>.</p></note>

<note id="n3"><seg type="note-symbol">[*]</seg> <p>I am perfectly aware that I differ from every one else
in my interpretation of this phrase.  The "Pygm&aelig;an race" is, I
believe, universally regarded as the same as the "faery elves," while
the "Indian mount" is supposed to be the Himalaya range.  To this notion
I oppose the following considerations: first, the unnaturalness of the
language if the poet intends merely to repeat or explain his first
expression; second, the individualized character of the name "Indian
mount" which could hardly be applied to the Himalaya range; third, the
fact that Mount Ophir in the Aurea Chersonesus was believed to be the
Ophir from which the ships of Solomon brought <hi rend="italic">apes</hi> and peacocks;
fourth, the popular fancy that the bodies of apes were inhabited by
devils.</p></note>

</div1>

</body>
</text>
</TEI.2>
