<?xml version="1.0"?>

<?dlps id="HowChar"?>
<?dlps page-images="none" figure-images="no"?>
<?dlps transcription="other"?>

<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/tei-p4/tei2.dtd" [
<!ENTITY % POSTKB "INCLUDE">
<!ENTITY % TEI.extensions.ent SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.ent">
<!ENTITY % TEI.extensions.dtd SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.dtd">
<!ENTITY % ISOnum SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/charent/iso-num.ent"> %ISOnum;
<!ENTITY % ISOpub SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/charent/iso-pub.ent"> %ISOpub;
]>

<TEI.2 id="HowChar">
<teiHeader type="migrated" creator="Etext">
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title type="main">"Mr. Charles W. Chesnutt's Stories."</title>
<title type="sort">mr charles w chesnutts stories</title>
<author>Howells, W. D.</author>
<respStmt>
<resp>Creation of machine-readable version:</resp>
<name>Judy Boss</name>
<resp>Conversion to TEI.2-conformant markup:</resp>
<name>University of Virginia Library Electronic Text Center</name>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt>
<extent>ca. <num type="kilobytes">12</num> kilobytes</extent>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>University of Virginia Library</publisher>
<pubPlace>Charlottesville, Virginia</pubPlace>
<idno type="ETC">HowChar</idno>
<date value="1995">1995</date>
<availability status="public">
<p n="copyright">Copyright &copy; 1995 by the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia</p>
<p n="access">Publicly accessible</p>
</availability>
<idno type="uva-pid">uva-lib:476089</idno>
</publicationStmt>
<seriesStmt>
<title>University of Virginia Library, Text collection</title>
<idno type="uva-set">UVA-LIB-Text</idno>
</seriesStmt>
<sourceDesc>
<biblFull>
<titleStmt>
<title type="main">"Mr. Charles W. Chesnutt's Stories."</title>
<title type="sort">mr charles w chesnutts stories</title>
<author>W.D. Howells</author>
</titleStmt>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>Houghton, Mifflin and Company</publisher>
<pubPlace>Boston, New York</pubPlace>
<date value="1900">1900</date>
</publicationStmt>
<seriesStmt>
<p>
<hi rend="italic">Atlantic Monthly</hi>
</p>
</seriesStmt>
<notesStmt>
<note>
<p>Vol. 85 (1900): Pages 699-701.</p>
</note>
</notesStmt>
</biblFull>
</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc>
<encodingDesc>
<projectDesc>
<p>Prepared for the University of Virginia Library Electronic Text Center</p>
</projectDesc>
<editorialDecl>
<p>All quotation marks retained as data</p>
<p>Spell-check and verification made
against printed text using WordPerfect spell checker</p>
<p>All unambiguous end-of-line hyphens have been removed, and the
trailing part of a word has been joined to the preceding line.</p>
<p id="ETC">Keywords in the header are a local Electronic Text Center scheme
to aid in establishing analytical groupings</p>
</editorialDecl>
<refsDecl>
<p>ID elements are given for each page element and are composed of the text's
unique cryptogram and the given page number, as in AusEmma1 for page one of
Jane Austen's Emma.</p>
</refsDecl>
</encodingDesc>
<profileDesc>
<creation>
<date value="1900">1900</date>
</creation>
<langUsage>
<language id="eng" usage="main">English</language>
</langUsage>
<textClass>
<keywords>
<term>non-fiction; prose</term>
</keywords>
</textClass>
</profileDesc>
<revisionDesc>
<change>
<date value="1995-08-02">August 2, 1995</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>corrector</resp>
<name>Lorrie S. Chisholm, Electronic Text Center, University of
Virginia Library System</name>
</respStmt>
<item>General TEI mark-up, removed unambiguous line-end hyphenation
and ran electronic spell-check using wp51.</item>
</change>
<change>
<date value="2005-07">July 2005</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>Corrector</resp>
<name>John Ivor Carlson</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Converted SGML to XML. Fixed tagging.</item>
</change>
<change>
<date value="2007-09">September 2007</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>Migration</resp>
<name>Ethan Gruber, University of Virginia Library</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Converted XML markup from TEI Lite to uva-dl-tei (TEI P4 with local customizations).</item>
</change>
<change>
<date value="2008-01">January 2008</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>Migration</resp>
<name>Greg Murray, University of Virginia Library</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Programmatically updated TEI header markup (but not header content) for minimal compliance with current QA requirements.</item>
</change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text id="d1">

<body id="d2">


<div1 type="article" id="d3"><pb n="699"/>
<head>MR. CHARLES W. CHESNUTT'S STORIES.</head>

<p>THE critical reader of the story called The Wife of his Youth,
which appeared in these pages two years ago, must have noticed
uncommon traits in what was altogether a remarkable piece of work.
The first was the novelty of the material; for the writer dealt not
only with people who were not white, but with people who were not
black enough to contrast grotesquely with white people,&mdash;who in
fact were of that near approach to the ordinary American in race
and color which leaves, at the last degree, every one but the
connoisseur in doubt whether they are Anglo-Saxon or Anglo-African.
Quite as striking as this novelty of the material was the author's
thorough mastery of it, and his unerring knowledge of the life he
had chosen in its peculiar racial characteristics.  But above all,
the story was notable for the passionless handling of a phase of
our common life which is tense with potential tragedy; for the
attitude, almost ironical, in which the artist observes the play of
contesting emotions in the drama under his eyes; and for his
apparently reluctant, apparently helpless consent to let the
spectator know his real feeling in the matter.  Any one accustomed
to study methods in fiction, to distinguish between good and bad
art, to feel the joy which the delicate skill possible only from a
love of truth can give, must have known a high pleasure in the
quiet self-restraint of the performance; and such a reader would
probably have decided that the social situation in the piece was
studied wholly from the outside, by an observer with special
opportunities for knowing it, who was, as it were, surprised into
final sympathy.
</p><p>Now, however, it is known that the author of this story is of
negro blood,&mdash;diluted, indeed, in such measure that if he did not
admit this descent few would imagine it, but still quite of that
middle

<pb n="700"/>
 world which lies next, though wholly outside, our
own.  Since his first story appeared he has contributed several
others to these pages, and he now makes a showing palpable to
criticism in a volume called The Wife of his Youth, and Other
Stories of the Color Line; a volume of Southern sketches called The
Conjure Woman; and a short life of Frederick Douglass, in the
Beacon Series of biographies.  The last is a simple, solid,
straight piece of work, not remarkable above many other
biographical studies by people entirely white, and yet important as
the work of a man not entirely white treating of a great man of his
inalienable race.  But the volumes of fiction <hi rend="italic">are</hi> remarkable
above many, above most short stories by people entirely white, and
would be worthy of unusual notice if they were not the work of a
man not entirely white.
</p><p>It is not from their racial interest that we could first wish
to speak of them, though that must have a very great and very just
claim upon the critic.  It is much more simply and directly, as
works of art, that they make their appeal, and we must allow the
force of this quite independently of the other interest.  Yet it
cannot always be allowed.  There are times in each of the stories
of the first volume when the simplicity lapses, and the effect is
as of a weak and uninstructed touch.  There are other times when
the attitude, severely impartial and studiously aloof, accuses
itself of a little pompousness.  There are still other times when
the literature is a little too ornate for beauty, and the diction
is journalistic, reporteristic.  But it is right to add that these
are the exceptional times, and that for far the greatest part Mr.
Chesnutt seems to know quite as well what he wants to do in a given
case as Maupassant, or Tourguenief, or Mr. James, or Miss Jewett,
or Miss Wilkins, in other given cases, and has done it with an art
of kindred quiet and force.  He belongs, in other words, to the
good school, the only school, all aberrations from nature being so
much truancy and anarchy.  He sees his people very clearly, very
justly, and he shows them as he sees them, leaving the reader to
divine the depth of his feeling for them.  He touches all the
stops, and with equal delicacy in stories of real tragedy and
comedy and pathos, so that it would be hard to say which is the
finest in such admirably rendered effects as The Web of
Circumstance, The Bouquet, and Uncle Wellington's Wives.  In some
others the comedy degenerates into satire, with a look in the
reader's direction which the author's friend must deplore.
</p><p>As these stories are of our own time and country, and as there
is not a swashbuckler of the seventeenth century, or a
sentimentalist of this, or a princess of an imaginary kingdom, in
any of them, they will possibly not reach half a million readers in
six months, but in twelve months possibly more readers will
remember them than if they had reached the half million.  They are
new and fresh and strong, as life always is, and fable never is;
and the stories of The Conjure Woman have a wild, indigenous
poetry, the creation of sincere and original imagination, which is
imparted with a tender humorousness and a very artistic reticence.
As far as his race is concerned, or his sixteenth part of a race,
it does not greatly matter whether Mr. Chesnutt invented their
motives, or found them, as he feigns, among his distant cousins of
the Southern cabins.  In either case, the wonder of their beauty is
the same; and whatever is primitive and sylvan or campestral in the
reader's heart is touched by the spells thrown on the simple black
lives in these enchanting tales.  Character, the most precious
thing in fiction, is as faithfully portrayed against the poetic
background as in the setting of the Stories of the Color Line.
</p><p>Yet these stories, after all, are Mr. Chesnutt's most
important work, whether we consider them merely as realistic
fiction, apart from their author, or as

<pb n="701"/>
 studies of that
middle world of which he is naturally and voluntarily a citizen.
We had known the nethermost world of the grotesque and comical
negro and the terrible and tragic negro through the white observer
on the outside, and black character in its lyrical moods we had
known from such an inside witness as Mr. Paul Dunbar; but it had
remained for Mr. Chesnutt to acquaint us with those regions where
the paler shades dwell as hopelessly, with relation to ourselves,
as the blackest negro.  He has not shown the dwellers there as very
different from ourselves.  They have within their own circles the
same social ambitions and prejudices; they intrigue and truckle and
crawl, and are snobs, like ourselves, both of the snobs that snub
and the snobs that are snubbed.  We may choose to think them droll
in their parody of pure white society, but perhaps it would be
wiser to recognize that they are like us because they are of our
blood by more than a half, or three quarters, or nine tenths.  It
is not, in such cases, their negro blood that characterizes them;
but it is their negro blood that excludes them, and that will
imaginably fortify them and exalt them.  Bound in that sad
solidarity from which there is no hope of entrance into polite
white society for them, they may create a civilization of their
own, which need not lack the highest quality.  They need not be
ashamed of the race from which they have sprung, and whose exile
they share; for in many of the arts it has already shown, during a
single generation of freedom, gifts which slavery apparently only
obscured.  With Mr. Booker Washington the first American orator of
our time, fresh upon the time of Frederick Douglass; with Mr.
Dunbar among the truest of our poets; with Mr. Tanner, a black
American, among the only three Americans from whom the French
government ever bought a picture, Mr. Chesnutt may well be willing
to own his color.
</p><p>But that is his personal affair.  Our own more universal
interest in him arises from the more than promise he has given in
a department of literature where Americans hold the foremost place.
In this there is, happily, no color line; and if he has it in him
to go forward on the way which he has traced for himself, to be
true to life as he has known it, to deny himself the glories of the
cheap success which awaits the charlatan in fiction, one of the
places at the top is open to him.  He has sounded a fresh note,
boldly, not blatantly, and he has won the ear of the more
intelligent public.
</p>
                 <signed><hi rend="italic">W. D. Howells.</hi></signed>

</div1>
</body>
</text>
</TEI.2>
