<?xml version="1.0"?>

<?dlps id="HumComm"?>
<?dlps page-images="none" figure-images="no"?>
<?dlps transcription="other"?>

<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/tei-p4/tei2.dtd" [
<!ENTITY % POSTKB "INCLUDE">
<!ENTITY % TEI.extensions.ent SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.ent">
<!ENTITY % TEI.extensions.dtd SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.dtd">
<!ENTITY % ISOnum SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/charent/iso-num.ent"> %ISOnum;

]>
<TEI.2 id="HumComm">
<teiHeader type="migrated" creator="Etext">
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title type="main">Idea of a perfect Commonwealth</title>
<title type="sort">idea of a perfect commonwealth</title>
<author>Hume, David</author>
<editor>Green, T. H. and T. H. Grose</editor>
<respStmt>
<resp>Creation of machine-readable version:</resp>
<name>Jon Roland, Consititution Society, www.constitution.org</name>
<resp>Conversion to TEI.2-conformant markup:</resp>
<name>University of Virginia Library Electronic Text Center.</name>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt>
<extent>ca. <num type="kilobytes">38</num> kilobytes</extent>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>University of Virginia Library</publisher>
<pubPlace>Charlottesville, Virginia</pubPlace>
<idno type="ETC">HumComm</idno>
<date value="2002">2002</date>
<availability status="public">
<p n="copyright">Copyright &copy; 2002 by the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia</p>
<p n="access">Publicly accessible</p>
</availability>
<idno type="uva-pid">uva-lib:476094</idno>
</publicationStmt>
<seriesStmt>
<title>University of Virginia Library, Text collection</title>
<idno type="uva-set">UVA-LIB-Text</idno>
</seriesStmt>
<seriesStmt>
<p>Essays moral, political, and literary, by David Hume; ed., with preliminary dissertations and notes, by T. H. Green ... and T.
H. Grose ... New impression.</p>
</seriesStmt>
<sourceDesc>
<biblFull>
<titleStmt>
<title type="main">Idea of a perfect Commonwealth</title>
<title level="m">Essays moral, political, and literary. Vol. 2</title>
<title type="sort">idea of a perfect commonwealth</title>
<author>David Hume</author>
<editor>T. H. Green and T. H. Grose</editor>
</titleStmt>
<extent>503 pp.</extent>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>Longmans, Green, and Co.</publisher>
<pubPlace>London</pubPlace>
<date value="1882">1882</date>
<idno type="callNo">Source copy consulted:  Alderman Library Copy B 1475 1882 v. 1</idno>
</publicationStmt>
<notesStmt>
<note>
<p>Some modernization of forms by editor in electronic file.</p>
</note>
</notesStmt>
</biblFull>
</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc>
<encodingDesc>
<projectDesc>
<p>Prepared for the University of Virginia Library Electronic Text Center.</p>
</projectDesc>
<editorialDecl>
<p>All unambiguous end-of-line hyphens have been removed, and the  trailing part of a word has been joined to the preceding line.</p>
<p id="ETC">Some keywords in the header are a local Electronic Text Center scheme  to aid in establishing analytical groupings.</p>
</editorialDecl>
</encodingDesc>
<profileDesc>
<creation>
<date value="1741">1741</date>
</creation>
<langUsage>
<language id="eng" usage="main">English</language>
</langUsage>
<textClass>
<keywords>
<term>CORD</term>
<term>democracy</term>
<term>philosophy</term>
</keywords>
<keywords>
<term>nonfiction</term>
<term>prose</term>
<term>masculine</term>
</keywords>
</textClass>
</profileDesc>
<revisionDesc>
<change>
<date value="2002-04">April 2002</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>corrector</resp>
<name>Stephen Martin for the Electronic Text Center at The University of Virginia</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Added TEI header and Tags</item>
</change>
<change>
<date value="2005-07">July 2005</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>Corrector</resp>
<name>John Ivor Carlson</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Converted SGML to XML. Fixed tagging.</item>
</change>
<change>
<date value="2007-09">September 2007</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>Migration</resp>
<name>Ethan Gruber, University of Virginia Library</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Converted XML markup from TEI Lite to uva-dl-tei (TEI P4 with local customizations).</item>
</change>
<change>
<date value="2008-01">January 2008</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>Migration</resp>
<name>Greg Murray, University of Virginia Library</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Programmatically updated TEI header markup (but not header content) for minimal compliance with current QA requirements.</item>
</change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text id="d1">

<body id="d2">
<div1 type="essay" id="d3">
<head>ESSAY XVI.--<hi rend="italic">Idea of a perfect Commonwealth</hi>.</head>

<div2 type="section" id="d4">


<p>

<ref target="n1">[1]</ref> IT is not with forms of government, as with
other artificial contrivances; where an old engine may be rejected, if
we can discover another more accurate and commodious, or where trials
may safely be made, even though the success be doubtful. An established
government has an infinite advantage, by that very circumstance of its
being established; the bulk of mankind being governed by authority, not
reason, and never attributing authority to any thing that has not the
recommendation of antiquity. To tamper, therefore, in this affair, or
try experiments merely upon the credit of supposed argument and
philosophy, can never be the part of a wise magistrate, who will bear a
reverence to what carries the marks of age; and though he may attempt
some improvements for the public good, yet will he adjust his
innovations, as much as possible, to the ancient fabric, and preserve
entire the chief pillars and supports of the constitution.

</p>
<p>

The mathematicians of <hi rend="small-caps">Europe</hi> have been much
divided concerning that figure of a ship, which is the most commodious
for sailing; and <hi rend="small-caps">Huygens</hi>, who at last
determined the controversy, is justly thought to have obliged the
learned, as well as commercial world; though <hi
rend="small-caps">Columbus</hi> had sailed to <hi
rend="small-caps">America</hi>, and Sir <hi rend="small-caps">Francis
Drake</hi> made the tour of the world, without any such discovery. As
one form of government must be allowed more perfect than another,
independent of the manners and humours of particular men; why may we not
enquire what is the most perfect of all, though the common botched and
inaccurate governments seem to serve the purposes of society, and though
it be not so easy to establish a new system of government, as to build a
vessel upon a new construction? The subject is surely the most worth
curiosity of any the wit of man can possibly devise. And who knows, if
this controversy were fixed by the universal consent of the wise and
learned, but, in some future age, an opportunity might be afforded by
reducing the theory to practice, either by a dissolution of some old
government, or by the combination of men to form a new one, in some
distant part of the world? In all cases, it must be advantageous to know
what is most perfect in the kind, that we may be able to bring any real
constitution or form of government as near it as possible, by such
gentle alterations and innovations as may not give too great disturbance
to society.

</p>
<p>

All I pretend to in the present essay is to revive this subject of
speculation; and therefore I shall deliver my sentiments in as few words
as possible. A long dissertation on that head would not, I apprehend, be
very acceptable to the public, who will be apt to regard such
disquisitions both as useless and chimerical.

</p>
<p>

All plans of government, which suppose great reformation in the manners
of mankind, are plainly imaginary. Of this nature, are the
<hi rend="italic">Republic</hi> of <hi rend="small-caps">Plato</hi>, and the
<hi rend="italic">Utopia</hi> of Sir <hi rend="small-caps">Thomas More</hi>.  The
<hi rend="italic">Oceana</hi> is the only valuable model of a commonwealth, that has
yet been offered to the public.

</p>
<p>

The chief defects of the <hi rend="small-caps">Oceana</hi> seem to be
these.  <hi rend="italic">First</hi>, Its rotation is inconvenient, by throwing men,
of whatever abilities, by intervals, out of public employments.
<hi rend="italic">Secondly</hi>, Its <hi rend="italic">Agrarian</hi> is impracticable. Men will soon
the art, which was practiced in ancient <hi rend="small-caps">Rome</hi>,
of concealing their possessions under other people's name; till at last,
the abuse will become so common, that they will throw off even the
appearance of restraint. <hi rend="italic">Thirdly</hi>, The <hi
rend="small-caps">Oceana</hi> provides not a sufficient security for
liberty, or the redress of grievances. The senate must propose, and the
people consent; by which means, the senate does not have a negative upon
the people, but, what is of much greater consequence, their negative
goes before the votes of the people. Were the King's negative of the
same nature in the <hi rend="small-caps">English</hi> constitution, and
could he prevent any bill from coming into parliament, he would be an
absolute monarch. As his negative follows the votes of the houses, it is
of little consequence: Such a difference is there in the manner of
placing the same thing. When a popular bill has been debated in
parliament, is brought to maturity, all its conveniencies and
inconveniencies, weighed and balanced; if afterwards it be presented for
the royal assent, few princes will venture to reject the unanimous
desire of the people. But could the King crush a disagreeable bill in
embryo (as was the case, for some time, in the <hi
rend="small-caps">Scottish</hi> parliament, by means of the lords of the
articles ), the <hi rend="small-caps">British</hi> government would have
no balance, nor would grievances ever be redressed: And it is certain,
that exorbitant power proceeds not, in any government, from new laws, so
much as from neglecting to remedy the abuses, which frequently rise from
the old ones.  A government, says <hi rend="small-caps">Machiavel</hi>,
must often be brought back to its original principles.  It appears then,
that, in the <hi rend="small-caps">Oceana</hi>, the whole legislature may
be said to rest in the senate; which <hi
rend="small-caps">Harrington</hi> would own to be an inconvenient form of
government, especially after the <hi rend="italic">Agrarian</hi> is abolished.

</p>
<p>

Here is a form of government, to which I cannot, in theory, discover any
considerable objection.

</p>
<p>

Let <hi rend="small-caps">Great Britain</hi> and <hi
rend="small-caps">Ireland</hi>, or any territory of equal extent, be
divided into 100 counties, and each county into 100 parishes, making in
all 10,000. If the country, proposed to be erected into a commonwealth
be of more narrow extent, we may diminish the number of counties; but
never bring them below thirty. If it be of greater extent, it were
better to enlarge the parishes, or throw more parishes into a county,
than increase the number of counties.

</p>
<p>

<ref target="n2">[2]</ref> Let all the freeholders of twenty pounds
a-year in the county, and all the householders worth 500 pounds in the
town parishes, meet annually in the parish church, and chuse, by ballot,
some freeholder of the county for their member, whom we shall call the
county <hi rend="italic">representative</hi>.

</p>
<p>

Let the 100 county representatives, two days after their election, meet
in the county town, and chuse by ballot, from their own body, ten county
<hi rend="italic">magistrates</hi>, and one <hi rend="italic">senator</hi>. There are, therefore, in
the whole commonwealth, 100 senators, 1100 county magistrates, and
10,000 county representatives. For we shall bestow on all senators the
authority of county magistrates, and on all county magistrates the
authority of county representatives.

</p>
<p>

Let the senators meet in the capital, and be endowed with the whole
executive power of the commonwealth; the power of peace and war, of
giving orders to generals, admirals, and ambassadors, and, in short, all
the prerogatives of a <hi rend="small-caps">British King</hi>, except his
negative.

</p>
<p>

Let the county representatives meet in their particular counties, and
possess the whole legislative power of the commonwealth; the greater
number of counties deciding the question; and where these are equal, let
the senate have the casting vote.

</p>
<p>

Every new law must first be debated in the senate; and though rejected
by it, if ten senators insist and protest, it must be sent down to the
counties. The senate, if they please, may join to the copy of the law
their reasons for receiving or rejecting it.

</p>
<p>

Because it would be troublesome to assemble all the county
representatives for every trivial law, that may be requisite, the senate
have their choice of sending down the law either to the county
magistrates or county representatives.

</p>
<p>

The magistrates, though the law be referred to them, may, if they
please, call the representatives, and submit the affair to their
determination.

</p>
<p>

Whether the law be referred by the senate to the county magistrates or
representatives, a copy of it, and of the senate's reasons, must be sent
to every representative eight days before the day appointed for the
assembling, in order to deliberate concerning it. And though the
determination be, by the senate, referred to the magistrates, if five
representatives of the county order the magistrates to assemble the
whole court of representatives, and submit the affair to their
determination, they must obey.

</p>
<p>

Either the county magistrates or representatives may give, to the
senator of the county, the copy of a law to be proposed to the senate;
and if five counties concur in the same order, the law, though refused
by the senate, must come either to the county magistrates or
representatives, as is contained in the order of the five counties.

</p>
<p>

Any twenty counties, by a vote either of their magistrates or
representatives, may throw any man out of all public offices for a year.
Thirty counties for three years.

</p>
<p>

The senate has a power of throwing out any member or number of members
of its own body, not to be re-elected for that year. The senate cannot
throw out twice in a year the senator of the same county.

</p>
<p>

The power of the old senate continues for three weeks after the annual
election of the county representatives. Then all the new senators are
shut up in a conclave, like the cardinals; and by an intricate ballot,
such as that of <hi rend="small-caps">Venice</hi> or <hi
rend="small-caps">Malta</hi>, they chuse the following magistrates; a
protector, who represents the dignity of the commonwealth, and presides
in the senate; two secretaries of state; these six councils, a council
of state, a council of religion and learning, a council of trade, a
council of laws, a council of war, a council of the admiralty, each
council consisting of five persons; together with six commissioners of
the treasury and a first commissioner. All these must be senators. The
senate also names all the ambassadors to foreign courts, who may either
be senators or not.

</p>
<p>

The senate may continue any or all of these, but must re-elect them
every year.

</p>
<p>

The protector and two secretaries have session and suffrage in the
council of state. The business of that council is all foreign politics.
The council of state has session and suffrage in all other councils.

</p>
<p>

The council of religion and learning inspects the universities and
clergy. That of trade inspects everything that may affect commerce. That
of laws inspects all the abuses of law by the inferior magistrates, and
examines what improvements may be made of the municipal law. That of war
inspects the militia and its discipline, magazines, stores, &amp;c. and
when the republic is at war, examines into the proper orders of
generals. The council of admiralty has the same power with regard to the
navy, together with the nomination of the captains and all inferior
officers.

</p>
<p>

None of these councils can give orders themselves, except where they
receive such powers from the senate. In other cases, they must
communicate every thing to the senate.

</p>
<p>

When the senate is under adjournment, any of the councils may assemble
it before the day appointed for its meeting.

</p>
<p>

Besides these councils or courts, there is another called the court of
<hi rend="italic">competitors</hi>; which is thus constituted. If any candidates for
the office of senator have more votes than a third of the
representatives, that candidate, who has most votes, next to the senator
elected, becomes incapable for one year of all public offices, even of
being a magistrate or representative: But he takes his seat in the court
of competitors. Here then is a court which may sometimes consist of a
hundred members, sometimes have no members at all; and by that means, be
for a year abolished.

</p>
<p>

The court of competitors has no power in the commonwealth. It has only
the inspection of public accounts, and the accusing of any man before
the senate. If the senate acquit him, the court of competitors may, if
they please, appeal to the people, either magistrates or
representatives. Upon that appeal, the magistrates or representatives
meet on the day appointed by the court of competitors, and chuse in each
county three persons, from which number every senator is excluded.
These, to the number of 300, meet in the capital, and bring the person
accused to a new trial.

</p>
<p>

The court of competitors may propose any law to the senate; and if
refused, may appeal to the people, that is, to the magistrates or
representatives, who examine it in their counties. Every senator, who is
thrown out of the senate by a vote of the court, takes his seat in the
court of competitors.

</p>
<p>

The senate possesses all the judicative authority of the house of Lords,
that is, all the appeals from the inferior courts. It likewise appoints
the Lord Chancellor, and all the officers of the law.

</p>
<p>

Every county is a kind of republic within itself, and the
representatives may make bye-laws; which have no authority 'till three
months after they are voted. A copy of the law is sent to the senate,
and to every other county. The senate, or any single county, may, at any
time, annul any bye-law of another county.

</p>
<p>

The representatives have all the authority of the <hi
rend="small-caps">British</hi> justices of peace in trials, commitments,
&amp;c.

</p>
<p>

The magistrates have the appointment of all the officers of the revenue
in each county. All causes with regard to the revenue are carried
ultimately by appeal before the magistrates. They pass the accounts of
all the officers; but must have their own accounts examined and passed
at the end of the year by the representatives.

</p>
<p>

The magistrates name rectors or ministers to all the parishes.

</p>
<p>

The Presbyterian government is established; and the highest
ecclesiastical court is an assembly or synod of all the presbyters of
the county. The magistrates may take any cause from this court, and
determine it themselves.

</p>
<p>

The magistrates may try, and depose or suspend any presbyter.

</p>
<p>

The militia is established in imitation of that of <hi
rend="small-caps">Swisserland</hi>, which being well known, we shall not
insist upon it.  It will only be proper to make this addition, that an
army of 20,000 men be annually drawn out by rotation, paid and encamped
during six weeks in summer; that the duty of a camp may not be
altogether unknown.

</p>
<p>

The magistrates appoint all the colonels and downwards. The senate all
upwards. During war, the general appoints the colonel and downwards, and
his commission is good for a twelvemonth. But after that, it must be
confirmed by the magistrates of the county, to which the regiment
belongs. The magistrates may break any officer in the county regiment.
And the senate may do the same to any officer in the service. If the
magistrates do not think proper to confirm the general's choice, they
may appoint another officer in the place of him they reject.

</p>
<p>

All crimes are tried within the county by the magistrates and a jury.
But the senate can stop any trial, and bring it before themselves.

</p>
<p>

Any county may indict any man before the senate for any crime.

</p>
<p>

The protector, the two secretaries, the council of state, with any five
or more that the senate appoints, are possessed, on extraordinary
emergencies, of <hi rend="italic">dictatorial</hi> power for six months.

</p>
<p>

The protector may pardon any person condemned by the inferior courts.

</p>
<p>

In time of war, no officer of the army that is in the field can have any
civil office in the commonwealth.

</p>
<p>

The capital, which we shall call <hi rend="small-caps">London</hi>, may
be allowed four members in the senate. It may therefore be divided into
four counties. The representatives of each of these chuse one senator,
and ten magistrates.  There are therefore in the city four senators,
forty-four magistrates, and four hundred representatives. The
magistrates have the same authority as in the counties.  The
representatives also have the same authority; but they never meet in one
general court: They give their votes in their particular county, or
division of hundreds.

</p>
<p>

When they enact any bye-law, the greater number of counties or divisions
determines the matter. And where these are equal, the magistrates have
the casting vote.

</p>
<p>

The magistrates chuse the mayor, sheriff, recorder, and other officers
of the city.

</p>
<p>

In the commonwealth, no representative, magistrate, or senator, as such,
has any salary. The protector, secretaries, councils, and ambassadors,
have salaries.

</p>
<p>

The first year in every century is set apart for correcting all
inequalities, which time may have produced in the representative. This
must be done by the legislature.

</p>
<p>

The following political aphorisms may explain the reason for these
orders.

</p>
<p>

The lower sort of people and small proprietors are good judges enough of
one not very distant from them in rank or habitation; and therefore, in
their parochial meetings, will probably chuse the best, or nearly the
best representative: But they are wholly unfit for county-meetings, and
for electing into the higher offices of the republic. Their ignorance
gives the grandees an opportunity of deceiving them.

</p>
<p>

Ten thousand, even though they were not annually elected, are a basis
large enough for any free government. It is true, the nobles in <hi
rend="small-caps">Poland</hi> are more than 10,000, and yet these oppress
the people. But as power always continues there in the same persons and
families, this makes them, in a manner, a different nation from the
people. Besides the nobles are there united under a few heads of
families.

</p>
<p>

All free governments must consist of two councils, a lesser and greater;
in other words, of a senate and people. The people, as <hi
rend="small-caps">Harrington</hi> observes, would want wisdom, without
the senate: The senate, without the people, would want honesty.

</p>
<p>

A large assembly of 1000, for instance, to represent the people, if
allowed to debate, would fall into disorder. If not allowed to debate,
the senate has a negative upon them, and the worst kind of negative,
that before resolution.

</p>
<p>

Here therefore is an inconvenience, which no government has yet fully
remedied, but which is the easiest to be remedied in the world. If the
people debate, all is confusion: If they do not debate, they can only
resolve; and then the senate carves for them. Divide the people into
many separate bodies; and then they may debate with safety, and every
inconvenience seems to be prevented.

</p>
<p>

Cardinal de <hi rend="small-caps">Retz</hi> says, that all numerous
assemblies, however composed, are mere mob, and swayed in their debates
by the least motive. This we find confirmed by daily experience. When an
absurdity strikes a member, he conveys it to his neighbor, and so on,
till the whole be infected.  Separate this great body, and though every
member be only of middling sense, it is not probable, that any thing but
reason can prevail over the whole. Influence and example being removed,
good sense will always get the better of bad among a number of people.
<ref target="n3">[3]</ref>

</p>
<p>

There are two things to be guarded against in every <hi rend="italic">senate</hi>: Its
combination, and its division. Its combination is most dangerous. And
against this inconvenience we have provided the following remedies. 1.
The great dependence of the senators on the people by annual elections;
and that not by an undistinguishing rabble, like the <hi
rend="small-caps">English</hi> electors, but by men of fortune and
education. 2. The small power they are allowed. They have few offices to
dispose of. Almost all are given by the magistrates in the counties. 3.
The court of competitors, which must be composed of men that are their
rivals, next to them in interest, and uneasy in their present situation,
will be sure to take all advantages against them.

</p>
<p>

The division of the senate is prevented, 1. By the smallness of their
number. 2. As faction supposes a combination in a separate interest, it
is prevented by their dependence on the people. 3. They have a power of
expelling any factious member. It is true, when another member of the
same spirit comes from the county, they have no power of expelling him:
Nor is it fit they should; for that shows the humour to be in the
people, and may possibly arise from some ill conduct in public affairs.
4. Almost any man, in a senate so regularly chosen by the people, may be
supposed fit for any civil office. It would be proper, therefore, for
the senate to form some general resolutions with regard to the disposing
of offices among the members: Which resolutions would not confine them
in critical times, when extraordinary parts on the one hand, or
extraordinary stupidity on the other, appears in any senator; but they
would be sufficient to prevent <ref target="n4">[4]</ref> intrigue and
faction, by making the disposal of the offices a thing of course. For
instance, let it be a resolution, That no shall enjoy any office, till
he has sat four years in the senate: That, except ambassadors, no man
shall be in office two years following: That no man shall attain the
higher offices but through the lower: That no man shall be protector
twice, &amp;c. The senate of <hi rend="small-caps">Venice</hi> governs
themselves by such resolutions.

</p>
<p>

In foreign politics the interest of the senate can scarcely ever be
divided from that of the people; and therefore it is fit to make the
senate absolute with regard to them; otherwise there could be no secrecy
or refined policy. Besides, without money no alliance can be executed;
and the senate is still sufficiently dependant. Not to mention, that the
legislative power being always superior to the executive, the
magistrates or representatives may interpose whenever they think proper.

</p>
<p>

The chief support of the <hi rend="small-caps">British</hi> government is
the opposition of interests; but that, though in the main serviceable,
breeds endless factions.  In the foregoing plan, it does all the good
without any of the harm. The <hi rend="italic">competitors</hi> have no power of
controlling the senate: They have only the power of accusing, and
appealing to the people.

</p>
<p>

It is necessary, likewise, to prevent both combination and division in
the thousand magistrates. This is done sufficiently by the separation of
places and interests.

</p>
<p>

But lest that should not be sufficient, their dependence on the 10,000
for their elections, serves the same purpose.

</p>
<p>

Nor is that all: For the 10,000 may resume the power whenever they
please; and not only when they all please, but when any five of a
hundred please, which will happen upon the very first suspicion of a
separate interest.

</p>
<p>

The 10,000 are two large a body either to unite or divide, except when
they meet in one place, and fall under the guidance of ambitious
leaders. Not to mention their annual election, <ref
target="n5">[5]</ref> by the whole body of the people, that are of any
consideration.

</p>
<p>

A small commonwealth is the happiest government in the world within
itself, because every thing lies under the eye of the rulers: But it may
be subdued by great force from without. This scheme seems to have all
the advantages both of a great and a little commonwealth.

</p>
<p>

Every county-law may be annulled either by the senate or another county;
because that shows an opposition of interest: In which case no part
ought to decide for itself. The matter must be referred to the whole,
which will best determine what agrees with general interest.

</p>
<p>

As to the clergy and militia, the reasons of these orders are obvious.
Without the dependence of the clergy on the civil magistrates, and
without a militia, it is in vain to think that any free government will
ever have security or stability.

</p>
<p>

In many governments, the inferior magistrates have no rewards but what
arise from their ambition, vanity, or public spirit. The salaries of the
<hi rend="small-caps">French</hi> judges amount not to the interest of
the sums they pay for their offices. The <hi rend="small-caps">Dutch</hi>
burgo-masters have little more immediate profit than the <hi
rend="small-caps">English</hi> justices of peace, or the members of the
house of commons formerly. But lest any should suspect, that this would
beget negligence in the administration (which is little to be feared,
considering the natural ambition of mankind), let the magistrates have
competent salaries. The senators have access to so many honourable and
lucrative offices, that their attendance needs to be bought.  There is
little attendance required of the representatives.

</p>
<p>

That the foregoing plan of government is practicable, no one can doubt,
who considers the resemblance that it bears to the commonwealth of the
United Provinces, <ref target="n6">[6]</ref> a wise and renowned
government. The alterations in the present scheme seem all evidently for
the better. 1. The representation is more equal. 2. The unlimited power
of the burgo-masters in the towns, which forms a perfect aristocracy in
the <hi rend="small-caps">Dutch</hi> commonwealth, is corrected by a
well-tempered democracy, in giving to the people the annual election of
the county representatives. 3. The negative, which every province and
town has upon the whole body of the <hi rend="small-caps">Dutch</hi>
republic, with regard to alliances, peace and war, and the imposition of
taxes, is here removed. 4. The counties, in the present plan, are not so
independent of each other, nor do they form separate bodies so much as
the seven provinces; where the jealousy and envy of the smaller
provinces and towns against the greater, particularly <hi
rend="small-caps">Holland</hi> and <hi rend="small-caps">Amsterdam</hi>,
have frequently disturbed the government.  5. Larger powers, though of
the safest kind, are intrusted to the senate than the States-General
possess; by which means, the former may become more expeditious, and
secret in their resolutions, than it is possible for the latter.

</p>
<p>

The chief alterations that could be made on the <hi
rend="small-caps">British</hi> government, in order to bring it to the
most perfect model of limited monarchy, seem to be the following.
<hi rend="italic">First</hi>, The plan of <ref target="n7">[7]</ref> <hi
rend="small-caps">Cromwell</hi>'s parliament ought to be restored, by
making the representation equal, and by allowing none to vote in the
county elections who possesses not <ref target="n8">[8]</ref> a
property of 200 pounds value.  <hi rend="italic">Secondly</hi>, As such a house of
Commons would be too weighty for a frail house of Lords, like the
present, the Bishops and <hi rend="small-caps">Scotch</hi> Peers ought to
be removed:  <ref target="n9">[9]</ref> The number of the upper house
ought to be raised to three or four hundred: Their seats not hereditary,
but during life: They ought to have the election of their own members;
and no commoner should be allowed to refuse a seat that was offered him.
By this means the house of Lords would consist entirely of the men of
chief credit, abilities, and interest in the nation; and every turbulent
leader in the house of Commons might be taken off, and connected by
interest with the house of Peers. Such an aristocracy would be an
excellent barrier both to the monarchy and against it. At present, the
balance of our government depends in some measure on the abilities and
behaviour of the sovereign; which are variable and uncertain
circumstances.

</p>
<p>

This plan of limited monarchy, however corrected, seems still liable to
three great inconveniencies. <hi rend="italic">First</hi>, It removes not entirely,
though it may soften, the parties of <hi rend="italic">court</hi> and
<hi rend="italic">country</hi>. <hi rend="italic">Secondly</hi>, The king's personal character must
still have great influence on the government. <hi rend="italic">Thirdly</hi>, The
sword is in the hands of a single person, who will always neglect to
discipline the militia, in order to have a pretence for keeping up a
standing army.  <ref target="n10">[10]</ref>

</p>
<p>

We will conclude this subject, with observing the falsehood of the
common opinion, that no large state, such as <hi
rend="small-caps">France</hi> or <hi rend="small-caps">Great Britain</hi>,
could ever be modelled into a commonwealth, but that such a form of
government can only take place in a city or small territory. The
contrary seems probable.  Though it is more difficult to form a
republican government in an extensive country than in a city; there is
more facility, once when it is formed, of preserving it steady and
uniform, without tumult and faction. It is not easy, for the distant
parts of a large state to combine in any plan of free government; but
they easily conspire in the esteem and reverence for a single person,
who, by means of this popular favour, may seize the power, and forcing
the more obstinate to submit, may establish a monarchical government. On
the other hand, a city readily concurs in the same notions of
government, the natural equality of property favours liberty, and the
nearness of habitation enables the citizens mutually to assist each
other. Even under absolute princes, the subordinate government of cities
is commonly republican; while that of counties and provinces is
monarchical. But these same circumstances, which facilitate the erection
of commonwealths in cities, render their constitution more frail and
uncertain. Democracies are turbulent. For however the people may be
separated or divided into small parties, either in their votes or
elections; their near habitation in a city will always make the force of
popular tides and currents very sensible. Aristocracies are better
adapted for peace and order, and accordingly were most admired by
ancient writers; but they are jealous and oppressive. In a large
government, which is modelled with masterly skill, there is compass and
room enough to refine the democracy, from the lower people, who may be
admitted into the first elections or first concoction of the
commonwealth. to the higher magistrates, who direct all the movements.
At the same time, the parts are so distant and remote, that it is very
difficult, either by intrigue, prejudice, or passion, to hurry them into
any measures against the public interest.

</p>
<p>

It is needless to enquire, whether such a government would be immortal.
I allow the justness of the poet's exclamation on the endless projects
of human race, <hi rend="italic">Man and for ever!</hi> The world itself probably is
not immortal. Such consuming plagues may arise as would leave even a
perfect government a weak prey to its neighbors. We know not to what
length enthusiasm, or other extraordinary movements of the human mind,
may transport men, to the neglect of all order and public good. Where
difference of interest is removed, whimsical and unaccountable factions
often arise, from personal favour or enmity. Perhaps, rust may grow to
the springs of the most accurate political machine, and disorder its
motions. Lastly, extensive conquests, when pursued, must be the ruin of
every free government; and of the more perfect governments sooner than
the imperfect; because of the very advantages which the former possess
above the latter. And though such a state ought to establish a
fundamental law against conquests; yet republics have ambition as well
as individuals, and present interest makes men forgetful of their
posterity. It is a sufficient incitement to human endeavours, that such
a government would flourish for many ages; without pretending to bestow,
on any work of man, that immortality, which the Almighty seems to have
refused to his own productions.

</p>

</div2>

<div2 type="notes" id="d5">


<note id="n1"><seg type="note-symbol">[1][Editions</seg> <p>H to P begin as follows : Of all mankind
there are none so pernicious as political projectors, if they have power
; nor so ridiculous, if they want it : As on the other hand, a wise
politician is the most beneficial character in nature, if accompanied
with authority ; and the most innocent and not altogether useless, even
if deprived of it.]</p></note>

<note id="n2"><seg type="note-symbol">[2][Editions</seg> <p>H and I read : Let all the freeholders in the
country parishes, and those who pay scot and lot in the town parishes,
&amp;c.  K to P, read : Let all the freeholders of ten pounds a year in
the country, and all the house-holders worth 200 pounds in the
town-parishes, &amp;c.]</p></note>

<note id="n3"><seg type="note-symbol">[3][Editions</seg> <p>H to P add : Good sense is one thing : But
follies are numberless ; and every man has a different one.  The only
way of making people wise, is to keep them from uniting into large
assemblies.]</p></note>

<note id="n4"><seg type="note-symbol">[4][Brigue</seg> <p>: Editions H to P.]</p></note>

<note id="n5"><seg type="note-symbol">[5][By</seg> <p>almost the whole body of the people : so editions H
to M end the paragraph.]</p></note>

<note id="n6"><seg type="note-symbol">[6][Formerly</seg> <p>one of the wisest and most renowned
governments in the world : Editions H to P.]</p></note>

<note id="n7"><seg type="note-symbol">[7][Of</seg> <p>the republican parliament : Editions H to P]</p></note>

<note id="n8"><seg type="note-symbol">[8][A</seg> <p>hundred a year : Editions H and I.]</p></note>

<note id="n9"><seg type="note-symbol">[9][Whose</seg> <p>behaviour, <hi rend="italic">in former par-liaments</hi>,
destroyed entirely the authority of that house : Editions H to
P.]</p></note>

<note id="n10"><seg type="note-symbol">[10][Editions</seg> <p>H to P add : It is evident, that this is a
mortal distemper in the <hi rend="small-caps">British</hi> government, of
which it must at last inevitably perish.  I must, however, confess, that
<hi rend="small-caps">Sweden</hi> seems, in some measure, to have
remedied this inconvenience, and to have a militia, with its limited
monarchy, as well as a standing army, which is less dangerous than the
<hi rend="small-caps">British</hi>.]</p></note>

</div2>
</div1>
</body>
</text>
</TEI.2>
