<?xml version="1.0"?>

<?dlps id="JewDunn"?>
<?dlps page-images="none" figure-images="no"?>
<?dlps transcription="other"?>

<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/tei-p4/tei2.dtd" [
<!ENTITY % POSTKB "INCLUDE">
<!ENTITY % TEI.extensions.ent SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.ent">
<!ENTITY % TEI.extensions.dtd SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.dtd">
<!ENTITY % ISOnum SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/charent/iso-num.ent"> %ISOnum;
<!ENTITY % ISOpub SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/charent/iso-pub.ent"> %ISOpub;
]>


<TEI.2 id="JewDunn">
<teiHeader type="migrated" creator="Etext">
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title type="main">A Dunnet Shepherdess</title>
<title type="sort">dunnet shepherdess</title>
<author>Jewett, Sarah Orne</author>
<respStmt>
<resp>Creation of machine-readable version:</resp>
<name>Judy Boss</name>
<resp>Conversion to TEI.2-conformant markup:</resp>
<name>University of Virginia Library Electronic Text Center</name>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt>
<extent>ca. <num type="kilobytes">42</num> kilobytes</extent>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>University of Virginia Library</publisher>
<pubPlace>Charlottesville, Virginia</pubPlace>
<idno type="ETC">JewDunn</idno>
<date value="1995">1995</date>
<availability status="public">
<p n="copyright">Copyright &copy; 1995 by the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia</p>
<p n="access">Publicly accessible</p>
</availability>
<idno type="uva-pid">uva-lib:476112</idno>
</publicationStmt>
<seriesStmt>
<title>University of Virginia Library, Text collection</title>
<idno type="uva-set">UVA-LIB-Text</idno>
</seriesStmt>
<sourceDesc>
<biblFull>
<titleStmt>
<title type="main">A Dunnet Shepherdess</title>
<title type="sort">dunnet shepherdess</title>
<author>Sarah Orne Jewett</author>
</titleStmt>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>Atlantic Monthly (Houghton, Mifflin &amp; Co.)</publisher>
<pubPlace>Cambridge, Mass</pubPlace>
<date value="1899-12">Dec 1899</date>
</publicationStmt>
<seriesStmt>
<p>Volume 84</p>
</seriesStmt>
<notesStmt>
<note>
<p>
<hi rend="italic">Atlantic Monthly</hi> 84 (Dec. 1899): 754-764.</p>
</note>
<note>
<p>Alderman Library AP2 / A8</p>
</note>
</notesStmt>
</biblFull>
</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc>
<encodingDesc>
<projectDesc>
<p>Prepared for the University of Virginia Library Electronic Text Center</p>
</projectDesc>
<editorialDecl>
<p>All quotation marks retained as data</p>
<p>All unambiguous end-of-line hyphens have been removed, and the
trailing part of a word has been joined to the preceding line.</p>
<p id="ETC">Keywords in the header are a local Electronic Text Center scheme
to aid in establishing analytical groupings</p>
</editorialDecl>
<refsDecl>
<p>ID elements are given for each page element and are composed of the text's
unique cryptogram and the given page number, as in AusEmma1 for page one of
Jane Austen's Emma.</p>
</refsDecl>
</encodingDesc>
<profileDesc>
<creation>
<date value="1899">1899</date>
</creation>
<langUsage>
<language id="eng" usage="main">English</language>
</langUsage>
<textClass>
<keywords>
<term>fiction ; prose</term>
<term>Women Writers</term>
</keywords>
</textClass>
</profileDesc>
<revisionDesc>
<change>
<date value="1995-06">June 1995</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>corrector</resp>
<name>Jamie L Spriggs, Electronic Text Center, University of Virginia</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Added header; Tagged text with TEI2-compatible SGML; Parsed text against
"teilite" dtd; All other major changes</item>
</change>
<change>
<date value="2005-07">July 2005</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>Corrector</resp>
<name>John Ivor Carlson</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Converted to XML and/or checked tags.</item>
</change>
<change>
<date value="2007-09">September 2007</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>Migration</resp>
<name>Ethan Gruber, University of Virginia Library</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Converted XML markup from TEI Lite to uva-dl-tei (TEI P4 with local customizations).</item>
</change>
<change>
<date value="2008-01">January 2008</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>Migration</resp>
<name>Greg Murray, University of Virginia Library</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Programmatically updated TEI header markup (but not header content) for minimal compliance with current QA requirements.</item>
</change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text id="d1">

<body id="d2">


<div1 type="chapter" n="1" id="d3"><pb n="754"/>
<head>I.</head>

<p>EARLY one morning at Dunnet Landing, as if it were still
night, I waked, suddenly startled by a spirited conversation
beneath my window.  It was not one of Mrs. Todd's morning
soliloquies; she was not addressing her plants and flowers in words
of either praise or blame.  Her voice was declamatory though
perfectly good-humored, while the second voice, a man's, was of
lower pitch and somewhat deprecating.
</p><p>The sun was just above the sea, and struck straight across my
room through a crack in the blind.  It was a strange hour for the
arrival of a guest, and still too soon for the general run of
business, even in that tiny Eastern haven where daybreak fisheries
and early tides must often rule the day.
</p><p>The man's voice suddenly declared itself to my sleepy ears.
It was Mr. William Blackett's.
</p><p>"Why, sister Almiry," he protested gently, "I don't need none
o' your nostrums."
</p><p>"Pick me a small han'ful," she commanded,&mdash;"no, no, a
<hi rend="italic">small</hi> han'ful, I said,&mdash;o' them large pennyr'yal sprigs!  I
go to all the trouble an' cossetin' of 'em just so as to have you
ready to meet such occasions, an' last year, you may remember, you
never stopped here at all, the day you went up country.  An' the
frost come at last an' blacked it.  I never saw any herb that so
objected to gardin ground; might as well try to flourish mayflowers
in a common front yard.  There, you can come in now, an' set an'
eat what breakfast you've got patience for.  I've found everything
I want, an' I'll mash 'em up an' be all ready to put 'em on."
</p><p>I heard such a pleading note of appeal as the speakers went
round the corner of the house, and my curiosity was so demanding,
that I dressed in haste, and joined my friends a little later, with
two unnoticed excuses, of the beauty of the morning and the early
mail boat.  William's breakfast had been slighted; he had taken his
cup of tea, and merely pushed back the rest on the kitchen table.
He was now sitting in a helpless condition by the side window, with
one of his sister's purple calico aprons pinned closely about his
neck.  Poor William was meekly submitting to being smeared, as to
his countenance, with a most pungent and unattractive lotion of
pennyroyal and other green herbs which had been hastily pounded and
mixed with cream in the little white stone mortar.
</p><p>I had to cast two or three looks at William to reassure myself
that he really looked happy and expectant in spite of his
melancholy circumstances, and was not being overtaken by
retribution.  The brother and sister seemed to be on delightful
terms with each other for once, and there was something of cheerful
anticipation in their morning talk.  I was reminded of Medea's
anointing Jason before the great episode of the iron bulls; but to-day William really could not be going up country to see a railroad
for the first time.  I knew this to be one of his great schemes;
but he was not fitted to appear in public, or to front an observing
world of strangers.  As I came in he essayed to rise, but Mrs. Todd
pushed him back into the chair.
</p><p>"Set where you be till it dries on," she insisted.  "Land
sakes, you'd think he'd get over bein' a boy some time or 'nother,
gettin' along in years as he is.  An' you'd think he'd seen full
enough o' fish; but once a year he has to break loose like this,
an' travel off 'way up back o' the Bowden place&mdash;far out o' my
beat, 'tis&mdash;an go a trout-fishin'!" <pb n="755"/>
</p><p>Her tone of amused scorn was so full of challenge that William
changed color even under the green streaks.
</p><p>"I want some change," he said, looking at me, and not at her.
"'Tis the prettiest little shady brook you ever saw."
</p><p>"If he ever fetched home more'n a couple o' minnies, 'twould
seem worth while," Mrs. Todd concluded, putting a last dab of the
mysterious compound so perilously near her brother's mouth that
William flushed again and was silent.
</p><p>A little later I witnessed his escape, when Mrs. Todd had
taken the foolish risk of going down cellar.  There was a horse and
wagon outside the garden fence, and presently we stood where we
could see him driving up the hill with thoughtless speed.  Mrs.
Todd said nothing, but watched him affectionately out of sight.
</p><p>"It serves to keep the mosquitoes off," she said, and a moment
later it occurred to my slow mind that she spoke of the pennyroyal
lotion.  "I don't know sometimes but William's kind of poetical,"
she continued, in her gentlest voice.  "You'd think, if anything
could cure him of it, 'twould be the fish business."
</p><p>It was only twenty minutes past six on a summer morning, but
we both sat down to rest as if the activities of the day were over.
Mrs. Todd rocked gently for a time, and seemed to be lost, though
not poorly, like Macbeth, in her thoughts.  At last she resumed
relations with her actual surroundings.  "I shall now put my
lobsters on.  They'll make us a good supper," she announced.  "Then
I can let the fire out for all day; give it a holiday, same's
William.  You can have a little one now, nice an' hot, if you ain't
got all the breakfast you want.  Yes, I'll put the lobsters on.
William was very thoughtful to bring 'em over.  William <hi rend="italic">is</hi>
thoughtful; if he only had a spark o' ambition, there be few could
match him."
</p><p>This unusual concession was afforded a sympathetic listener
from the depths of the kitchen closet.  Mrs. Todd was getting out
her old iron lobster pot, and began to speak of prosaic affairs.
I hoped that I should hear something more about her brother and
their island life, and sat idly by the kitchen window looking at
the morning-glories that shaded it, believing that some flaw of
wind might set Mrs. Todd's mind on its former course.  Then it
occurred to me that she had spoken about our supper rather than our
dinner, and I guessed that she might have some great scheme before
her for the day.
</p><p>When I had loitered for some time, and there was no further
word about William, and at last I was conscious of receiving no
attention whatever, I went away.  It was something of a
disappointment to find that she put no hindrance in the way of my
usual morning affairs, of going up to the empty little white
schoolhouse on the hill where I did my task of writing.  I had been
almost sure of a holiday when I discovered that Mrs. Todd was
likely to take one herself,&mdash;we had not been far afield to gather
herbs and pleasures for many days now; but a little later she had
silently vanished.  I found my luncheon ready on the table in the
little entry, wrapped in its shining old homespun napkin; and as if
by way of special consolation, there was a stone bottle of Mrs.
Todd's best spruce beer, with a long piece of cod-line wound round
it, by which it could be lowered, for coolness, into the deep
schoolhouse well.
</p><p>I walked away with a dull supply of writing paper and these
provisions, feeling like a reluctant child who hopes to be called
back at every step.  There was no relenting voice to be heard, and
when I reached the schoolhouse I found that I had left an open
window and a swinging shutter the day before, and the sea wind that
blew at evening had fluttered my poor sheaf of papers all about the
room.
</p><p>So the day did not begin very well, <pb n="756"/>  and I began to
recognize that it was one of the days when nothing could be done
without company.  The truth was that my heart had gone trouting
with William, but it would have been too selfish to say a word even
to one's self about spoiling his day.  If there is one way above
another of getting so close to nature that one simply is a piece of
nature, following a primeval instinct with perfect self-forgetfulness, and forgetting everything except the dreamy
consciousness of pleasant freedom, it is to take the course of a
shady trout brook.  The dark pools and the sunny shallows beckon
one on; the wedge of sky between the trees on either bank, the
speaking, companioning noise of the water, the amazing importance
of what one is doing, and the constant sense of life and beauty
make a strange transformation of the quick hours.  I had a sudden
memory of all this, and another, and another.  I could not get
myself free from "fishing and wishing."
</p><p>At that moment I heard the unusual sound of wheels, and I
looked past the high-growing thicket of wild roses and straggling
sumac to see the white nose and meagre shape of the Caplin horse;
then I saw William sitting in the open wagon, with a small
expectant smile upon his face.
</p><p>"I've got two lines," he said.  "I was quite a piece up the
road.  I thought perhaps 'twas so you'd feel like going."
</p><p>There was enough excitement for most occasions in hearing
William speak three sentences at once.  Words seemed but vain to me
at that bright moment.  I stepped back from the schoolhouse window
with a beating heart.  The spruce-beer bottle was not yet in the
well, and with that and my luncheon, and Pleasure at the helm, I
went out into the happy world.  The land breeze was blowing, and,
as we turned away, I saw a flutter of white go past the window as
I left the schoolhouse and my morning's work to their neglected
fate.
</p></div1>
<div1 type="chapter" n="2" id="d4"><head>II.</head>
<p>I seldom gave way to a cruel impulse to look at an ancient
seafaring William, but I felt as if he were a growing boy; I only
hope that he felt much the same about me.  He did not wear the
fishing clothes that belonged to his sea-going life, but a
strangely shaped old suit of tea-colored linen garments that might
have been brought home years ago from Canton or Bombay.  William
had a peculiar way of giving silent assent when you spoke, but of
answering your unspoken thoughts as if they reached him better than
words.  "I find them very easy," he said, frankly referring to the
clothes.  "Father had them in his old sea chest."
</p><p>The antique fashion, a quaint touch of foreign grace and even
imagination about the cut, were very pleasing; if ever Mr. William
Blackett had faintly resembled an old beau, it was upon that day.
He now appeared to feel as if everything had been explained between
us, as if everything were quite understood; and we drove for some
distance without finding it necessary to speak again about
anything.  At last, when it must have been a little past nine
o'clock, he stopped the horse beside a small farmhouse, and nodded
when I asked if I should get down from the wagon.  "You can steer
about northeast right across the pasture," he said, looking from
under the eaves of his hat with an expectant smile.  "I always
leave the team here."
</p><p>I helped to unfasten the harness, and William led the horse
away to the barn.  It was a poor-looking little place, and a
forlorn woman looked at us through the window before she appeared
at the door.  I told her that Mr. Blackett and I came up from the
Landing to go fishing.  "He keeps a-comin', don't he?" she
answered, with a funny little laugh, to which I was at a loss to
find answer.  When he joined us, I could not see that he took
notice <pb n="757"/>  of her presence in any way except to take an armful
of dried salt fish from a corded stack in the back of the wagon
which had been carefully covered with a piece of old sail.  We had
left a wake of their pungent flavor behind us all the way.  I
wondered what was going to become of the rest of them, and some
fresh lobsters which were also disclosed to view; but he laid the
present gift on the door-step without a word, and a few minutes
later, when I looked back as we crossed the pasture, the fish were
being carried into the house.
</p><p>I could not see any signs of a trout brook until I came close
upon it in the bushy pasture, and presently we struck into the low
woods of straggling spruce and fir mixed into a tangle of swamp
maples and alders which stretched away on either hand up and down
stream.  We found an open place in the pasture where some taller
trees seemed to have been overlooked rather than spared.  The sun
was bright and hot by this time, and I sat down in the shade, while
William produced his lines and cut and trimmed us each a slender
rod.  I wondered where Mrs. Todd was spending the morning, and if
later she would think that pirates had landed and captured me from
the schoolhouse.



</p></div1><div1 type="chapter" n="3" id="d5"><head>III.</head>

<p>The brook was giving that live, persistent call to a listener
that trout brooks always make; it ran with a free, swift current
even here where it crossed an apparently level piece of land.  I
saw two unpromising, quick barbel chase each other upstream from
bank to bank, as we solemnly arranged our hooks and sinkers.  I
noticed that William's glances changed from anxiety to relief when
he found that I was used to such gear; perhaps he felt that we must
stay together if I could not bait my own hook; but we parted
happily, full of a pleasing sense of companionship.
</p><p>William had pointed me up the brook, but I chose to go down,
which was only fair because it was his day, though one likes as
well to follow and see where a brook goes as to find one's way to
the places it comes from, and its tiny springs and head waters, and
in this case trout were not to be considered.  William's only real
anxiety was lest I might suffer from mosquitoes.  His own
complexion was still strangely impaired by its defenses; but I kept
forgetting it, and looking to see if we were treading fresh
pennyroyal underfoot, so efficient was Mrs. Todd's remedy.  I was
conscious, after we parted, and I turned to see if he were already
fishing, and saw him wave his hand gallantly as he went away, that
our friendship had made a great gain.
</p><p>The moment that I began to fish the brook I had a sense of its
emptiness; when my bait first touched the water and went lightly
down the quick stream, I knew that there was nothing to lie in wait
for it.  It is the same certainty that comes when one knocks at the
door of an empty house, a lack of answering consciousness and of
possible response; it is quite different if there is any life
within.  But it was a lovely brook, and I went a long way through
woods and breezy open pastures, and found a forsaken house and
overgrown farm, and laid up many pleasures for future joy and
remembrance.  At the end of the morning I came back to our meeting
place, hungry and without any fish.  William was already waiting,
and we did not mention the matter of trout.  We ate our luncheons
with good appetites, and William brought our two stone bottles of
spruce beer from the deep place in the brook where he had left them
to cool.  Then we sat awhile longer in peace and quietness on the
green bank.
</p><p>As for William, he looked more boyish than ever, and kept a
more remote and juvenile sort of silence.  Once I wondered how he
had come to be so curiously wrinkled,&mdash;forgetting, absent-<pb n="758"/>
mindedly, to recognize the effects of time.  He did not expect
any one else to keep up a vain show of conversation, and so I was
silent as well as he.  I glanced at him now and then, but I watched
the leaves tossing against the sky and the red cattle moving in the
pasture.  "I don't know's we need head for home.  It's early yet,"
he said at last, and I was as startled as if one of the gray firs
had spoken.
</p><p>"I guess I'll go up-along and ask after Thankful Hight's
folks," he continued.  "Mother'd like to get word."  And I nodded
a pleased assent.



</p></div1><div1 type="chapter" n="4" id="d6"><head>IV.</head>

<p>William led the way across the pasture, and I followed with a
deep sense of pleased anticipation.  I do not believe that my
companion had expected me to make any objection, but I knew that he
was gratified by the easy way that his plans for the day were being
seconded.  He gave a look at the sky to see if there were any
portents; but the sky was frankly blue; even the doubtful morning
haze had disappeared.
</p><p>We went northward along a rough, clayey road, across a bare-looking, sun-burnt country full of tiresome long slopes where the
sun was hot and bright, and I could not help observing the forlorn
look of the farms.  There was a great deal of pasture, but it
looked deserted; and I wondered afresh why the people did not raise
more sheep, when that seemed the only possible use to make of their
land.  I said so to Mr. Blackett, who gave me a look of pleased
surprise.
</p><p>"That's what She always maintains," he said eagerly.  "She's
right about it, too.  Well, you'll see!"
</p><p>I was glad to find myself approved, but I had not the least
idea whom he meant, and waited until he felt like speaking again.
</p><p>A few minutes later we drove down a steep hill and entered a
large tract of dark spruce woods.  It was delightful to be
sheltered from the afternoon sun, and when we had gone some
distance in the shade, to my great pleasure William turned the
horse's head toward some bars, which he let down, and I drove
through into one of those narrow, still, sweet-scented byways which
seem to be paths rather than roads.  Often we had to put aside the
heavy drooping branches which barred the way, and once, when a
sharp twig struck William in the face, he announced with such
spirit that somebody ought to go through there with an axe that I
felt unexpectedly guilty.  So far as I now remember, this was
William's only remark all the way through the woods to Thankful
Hight's folks, but from time to time he pointed or nodded at
something which I might have missed,&mdash;a sleepy little owl snuggled
into the bend of a branch, or a tall stalk of cardinal flowers
where the sunlight came down at the edge of a small, bright piece
of marsh.  Many times, being used to the company of Mrs. Todd and
other friends who were in the habit of talking, I came near making
an idle remark to William, but I was for the most part happily
preserved; to be with him only for a short time was to live on a
different level, where thoughts served best because they were
thoughts in common, the primary effect upon our minds of the simple
things and beauties that we saw.  Once when I caught sight of a
lovely gay pigeon woodpecker eyeing us curiously from a dead
branch, and instinctively turned toward William, he gave an
indulgent, comprehending nod which silenced me all the rest of the
way.  The wood road was not a place for common noisy conversation;
one would interrupt the birds and all the still little beasts that
belonged there.  But it was mortifying to find how strong the habit
of idle speech may become in one's self.  One need not always be
saying <pb n="759"/>  something in this noisy world.  I grew conscious of
the difference between William's usual fashion of life and mine;
for him there were long days of silence in a sea-going boat, and I
could believe that he and his mother usually spoke very little
because they so perfectly understood each other.  There was
something peculiarly unresponding about their quiet island in the
sea, solidly fixed into the still foundations of the world, against
whose rocky shores the sea beats and calls, and is unanswered.
</p><p>We were quite half an hour going through the woods; the
horse's feet made no sound on the brown, soft track under the dark
evergreens.  I thought that we should come out at last into more
pastures, but there was no half-wooded strip of land at the end;
the high woods grew squarely against an old stone wall and a
sunshiny open field, and we came out suddenly into broad daylight
that startled us, and even startled the horse, who might have been
napping as he walked, like an old soldier.  The field sloped up to
a low, unpainted house that faced the east.  Behind it were long,
frost-whitened ledges that made the hill, with strips of green turf
and bushes between.  It was the wildest, most Titanic sort of
pasture country up there; there was a sort of daring in putting a
frail wooden house before it, though it might have the homely field
and honest woods to front against.  You thought of the elements and
even of possible volcanoes as you looked up the stony heights.
Suddenly I saw that a region of what I had imagined gray stones was
slowly moving, as if the sun was making my eyesight unsteady.
</p><p>"There's the sheep!" exclaimed William, pointing eagerly.
"You see the sheep?"  And sure enough, it was a great company of
woolly backs, which seemed to have taken a mysterious protective
resemblance to the ledges themselves.  I could discover but little
chance for pasturage on that high, sunburnt ridge, but the sheep
were moving steadily in a satisfied way, as they fed along the
slopes and hollows.
</p><p>"I never have seen half so many sheep as these, all summer
long!" I cried, with admiration.
</p><p>"There ain't so many," answered William soberly.  "It's a
great sight.  They do so well because they're shepherded; but you
can't beat sense into some folks."
</p><p>"You mean that somebody stays and watches them?" I asked.
</p><p>She observed years ago in her reading that they don't turn out
their flocks without protection anywhere but in the state o'
Maine," returned William.  "First thing that put it into her mind
was a little old book mother's got; she read it one time when she
come out to the Island.  They call it the Shepherd o' Salisbury
Plain.  'Twasn't the purpose o' the book to most, but when she read
it, 'There, Mis' Blackett!' she said, 'that's where we've all
lacked sense; our Bibles ought to have taught us that what sheep
need is a shepherd.'  You see most folks about here gave up sheep-raisin' years ago 'count o' the dogs.  So she gave up school-teachin' and went out to tend her flock, and has shepherded ever
since, an' done well."
</p><p>For William this approached an oration.  He spoke with
enthusiasm, and I shared the triumph of the moment.  "There she is
now!" he exclaimed, in a different tone, as the tall figure of a
woman came following the flock and stood still on the ridge,
looking toward us as if her eyes had been quick to see a strange
object in the familiar emptiness of the field.  William stood up in
the wagon, and I thought he was going to call or wave his hand to
her; but he sat down again more clumsily than if the wagon had made
the familiar motion of a boat, and we drove on toward the house.
</p><p>It was a most solitary place to live in,<pb n="760"/> &mdash;a place where
one might think that a life could hide itself.  The thick woods
were between the farm and the main road, and as one looked up and
down the country there was no other house in sight.
</p><p>"Potatoes look well," announced William.  "The old folks used
to say that there wa'n't no better land outdoors than the Hight
field."
</p><p>I found myself possessed of a surprising interest in the
shepherdess, who stood far away in the hill pasture with her great
flock, like a figure of Millet's, high against the sky.



</p></div1><div1 type="chapter" n="5" id="d7"><head>V.</head>

<p>Everything about the old farmhouse was clean and orderly, as
if the green dooryard were not only swept, but dusted.  I saw a
flock of turkeys stepping off carefully at a distance, but there
was not the usual untidy flock of hens about the place to make
everything look in disarray.  William helped me out of the wagon as
carefully as if I had been his mother, and nodded toward the open
door with a reassuring look at me; but I waited until he had tied
the horse and could lead the way himself.  He took off his hat just
as we were going in, and stopped for a moment to smooth his thin
gray hair with his hand, by which I saw that we had an affair of
some ceremony.  We entered an old-fashioned country kitchen, the
floor scrubbed into unevenness, and the doors well polished by the
touch of hands.  In a large chair facing the window there sat a
masterful-looking old woman, with the features of a warlike Roman
emperor, emphasized by a bonnet-like black cap with a band of green
ribbon.  Her sceptre was a palm-leaf fan.
</p><p>William crossed the room toward her, and bent his head close
to her ear.
</p><p>"Feelin' pretty well to-day, Mis' Hight?" he asked, with all
the voice his narrow chest could muster.
</p><p>"No, I ain't, William.  Here I have to set," she answered
coldly, but she gave an inquiring glance over his shoulder at me.
</p><p>"This is the young lady who is stopping with Almiry this
summer," he explained, and I approached as if to give the
countersign.  She offered her left hand with considerable dignity,
but her expression never seemed to change for the better.  A moment
later she said that she was pleased to meet me, and I felt as if
the worst were over.  William must have felt some apprehension,
while I was only ignorant, as we had come across the field.  Our
hostess was more than disapproving,&mdash;she was forbidding; but I was
not long in suspecting that she felt the natural resentment of a
strong energy that has been defeated by illness and made the spoil
of captivity.
</p><p>"Mother well as usual since you was up last year?"  And
William replied by a series of cheerful nods.  The mention of dear
Mrs. Blackett was a help to any conversation.
</p><p>"Been fishin' ashore," he explained, in a somewhat
conciliatory voice.  "Thought you'd like a few for winter," which
at once accounted for the generous freight we had brought in the
back of the wagon.  I could see that the offering was no surprise,
and that Mrs. Hight was interested.
</p><p>"Well, I expect they're good as the last," she said, but did
not even approach a smile.  She kept a straight, discerning eye
upon me.
</p><p>"Give the lady a cheer," she admonished William, who hastened
to place close by her side one of the straight-backed chairs that
stood against the kitchen wall.  Then he lingered for a moment,
like a timid boy.  I could see that he wore a look of resolve, but
he did not ask the permission for which he evidently waited.
</p><p>"You can go search for Esther," she said, at the end of a long
pause that became anxious for both her guests.  "Es-<pb n="761"/> ther'd
like to see her."  And William in his pale nankeens disappeared
with one light step and was off.



</p></div1><div1 type="chapter" n="6" id="d8"><head>VI.</head>

<p>"Don't speak too loud; it jars a person's head," directed Mrs.
Hight plainly.  "Clear an' distinct is what reaches me best.  Any
news to the Landin'?"
</p><p>I was happily furnished with the particulars of a sudden
death, and an engagement of marriage between a Caplin, a seafaring
widower home from his voyage, and one of the younger Harrises; and
now Mrs. Hight really smiled and settled herself in her chair.  We
exhausted one subject completely before we turned to the other.
One of the returning turkeys took an unwarrantable liberty, and,
mounting the doorstep, came in and walked about the kitchen without
being observed by its strict owner; and the tin dipper slipped off
its nail behind us and made an astonishing noise, and jar enough to
reach Mrs. Hight's inner ear and make her turn her head to look at
it; but we talked straight on.  We came at last to understand each
other upon such terms of friendship that she unbent her majestic
port and complained to me as any poor old woman might of the
hardships of her illness.  She had already fixed various dates upon
the sad certainty of the year when she had the shock, which had
left her perfectly helpless except for a clumsy left hand which
fanned and gestured, and settled and resettled the folds of her
dress, but could do no comfortable time-shortening work.
</p><p>"Yes'm, you can feel sure I use it what I can," she said
severely.  "'Twas a long spell before I could let Esther go forth
in the mornin' till she'd got me up an' dressed me; but now she
leaves things ready overnight, and I get 'em as I want 'em with my
light pair o' tongs, and I feel very able about helpin' myself to
what I once did.  Then when Esther returns, all she has to do is to
push me out here into the kitchen.  Some parts o' the year Esther
stays out all night,&mdash;them moonlight nights when the dogs are apt
to be after the sheep,&mdash;but she don't use herself as hard as she
once had to.  She's well able to hire somebody, Esther is; but
there, you can't find no hired man that wants to git up before five
o'clock nowadays; 'tain't as 'twas in my time.  They're liable to
fall asleep, too; and them moonlight nights she's so anxious she
can't sleep, and out she goes.  There's a kind of a fold, she calls
it, up there in a sheltered spot, and she sleeps up in a little
shed she's got,&mdash;built it herself for lambin' time, and when the
poor foolish creatur's gets hurt or anything.  I've never seen it,
but she says it's in a lovely spot, and always pleasant in any
weather.  You see off, other side of the ridge, to the south'ard,
where there's houses.  I used to think some time I'd get up to see
it again, and all them spots she lives in, but I shan't now.  I'm
beginnin' to go back; an' 'tain't surprisin'.  I've kind of got
used to disappointments," and the poor soul drew a deep sigh.



</p></div1><div1 type="chapter" n="7" id="d9"><head>VII.</head>

<p>It was long before we noticed the lapse of time.  I not only
told every circumstance known to me of recent events among the
households of Mrs. Todd's neighborhood at the shore, but Mrs. Hight
became more and more communicative on her part, and went carefully
into the genealogical descent and personal experience of many
acquaintances, until between us we had pretty nearly
circumnavigated the globe and reached Dunnet Landing from an
opposite direction to that in which we had started.  It was long
before my own interest began to flag; there was a flavor of the
best sort in her definite and descriptive fash-<pb n="762"/> ion of
speech.  It may be only a fancy of my own that in the sound and
value of many words, with their lengthened vowels and doubled
cadences, there is some faint survival on the Maine coast of the
sound of English speech of Chaucer's time.
</p><p>At last Mrs. Thankful Hight gave a suspicious look through the
window.
</p><p>"Where do you suppose they be?" she asked me.  "Esther must
ha' been off to the far edge o' everything.  I doubt William ain't
been able to find her.  Can't he hear their bells?  His hearin' all
right?"
</p><p>William had heard some herons that morning which were beyond
the reach of my own ears, and almost beyond eye-sight in the upper
skies, and I told her so.  I was luckily preserved by some
unconscious instinct from saying that we had seen the shepherdess
so near, as we crossed the field.  Unless she had fled faster than
Atalanta, William must have been but a few minutes in reaching her
immediate neighborhood.  I now discovered, with a quick leap of
amusement and delight in my heart, that I had fallen upon a serious
chapter of romance.  The old woman looked suspiciously at me, and
I made a dash to cover with a new piece of information; but she
listened with lofty indifference, and soon interrupted my eager
statements.
</p><p>"Ain't William been gone some considerable time?" she
demanded, and then in a milder tone: "The time has re'lly flown; I
do enjoy havin' company.  I set here alone a sight o' long days.
Sheep is dreadful fools; I expect they heard a strange step, and
set right off through bush an' brier, spite of all she could do.
But William might have the sense to return, 'stead o' searchin'
about.  I want to inquire of him about his mother.  What was you
goin' to say?  I guess you'll have time to relate it."
</p><p>My powers of entertainment were on the ebb, but I doubled my
diligence, and we went on for another half hour, at least, with
banners flying; but still William did not reappear.  Mrs. Hight
frankly began to show fatigue.
</p><p>"Somethin's happened, an' he's stopped to help her!" groaned
the old lady, in the middle of what I had found to tell her about
a rumor of disaffection with the minister of a town I merely knew
by name, in the weekly newspaper to which Mrs. Todd subscribed.
"You step to the door, dear, an' look if you can't see 'em."
</p><p>I promptly stepped, and once outside the house I looked
anxiously in the direction which William had taken.
</p><p>To my astonishment, I saw all the sheep so near that I wonder
we had not been aware in the house of every bleat and tinkle; and
there, within a stone's throw, on the first long gray ledge that
showed above the juniper, were William and the shepherdess, engaged
in pleasant conversation.  At first I was provoked, and then
amused, and a thrill of sympathy warmed my whole heart.  They had
seen me and risen as if by magic; I had a sense of being the
messenger of Fate.  One could almost hear their sighs of regret as
I appeared; they must have passed a lovely afternoon.  I hurried
into the house with the reassuring news that they were not only in
sight, but perfectly safe, with all the sheep.



</p></div1><div1 type="chapter" n="8" id="d10"><head>VIII.</head>

<p>Mrs. Hight, like myself, was spent with conversation, and had
ceased even the one activity of fanning herself.  I brought a
desired drink of water, and happily remembered some fruit that was
left from my luncheon.  She revived with splendid vigor, and told
me the simple history of her later years since she had been smitten
in the prime of her life by the stroke of paralysis, and her
husband had died and left her alone with Esther and a mortgage on
their farm.  There was only one field of good land, <pb n="763"/>  but
they owned a great region of sheep pasture and a little woodland.
Esther had always been laughed at for her belief in sheep-raising,
when one by one their neighbors were giving up their flocks, and
when everything had come to the point of despair she had raised all
the money and bought all the sheep she could; insisting that Maine
lambs were as good as any, and that there was a straight path by
sea to Boston market.  And by tending her flock herself she had
managed to succeed: she had made money enough to pay off the
mortgage five years ago, and now what they did not spend was safe
in the bank.  "It has been stubborn work, day and night, summer and
winter, an' now she's beginnin' to get along in years," said the
old mother sadly.  "She's tended me 'long o' the sheep, an' she's
been a good girl right along, but she ought to have been a
teacher;" and Mrs. Hight sighed heavily and plied the fan again.
</p><p>We heard voices, and William and Esther entered; they did not
know that it was so late in the afternoon.  William looked almost
bold, and oddly like a happy young man rather than an ancient boy.
As for Esther, she might have been Jeanne d'Arc returned to her
sheep, touched with age and gray with the ashes of a great
remembrance.  She wore the simple look of sainthood and unfeigned
devotion.  My heart was moved by the sight of her plain, sweet
face, weatherworn and gentle in its looks, her thin figure in its
close dress, and the strong hand that clasped a shepherd's staff;
and I could only hold William in new reverence, this silent farmer-fisherman who knew, and he alone, the noble and patient heart that
beat within her breast.  I am not sure that they acknowledged even
to themselves that they had always been lovers,&mdash;they could not
consent to anything so definite or pronounced; but they were happy
in being together in the world.  Esther was untouched by the fret
and fury of life; she had lived in sunshine and rain among her
silly sheep, and been refined instead of coarsened, while her
touching patience with a ramping old mother, stung by the sense of
defeat and mourning her lost activities, had given back a lovely
self-possession and habit of sweet temper.  I had seen enough of
old Mrs. Hight to know that nothing a sheep might do could vex a
person who was used to the uncertainties and severities of her
companionship.



</p></div1><div1 type="chapter" n="9" id="d11"><head>IX.</head>

<p>Mrs. Hight told her daughter at once that she had enjoyed a
beautiful call, and got a great many new things to think of.  This
was said so frankly in my hearing that it gave a consciousness of
high reward, and I was indeed recompensed by the grateful look in
Esther's eyes.  We did not speak much together, but we understood
each other.  For the poor old woman did not read, and could not sew
or knit with her helpless hand, and they were far from any
neighbors, while her spirit was as eager in age as in youth, and
expected even more from a disappointing world.  She had lived to
see the mortgage paid and money in the bank, and Esther's success
acknowledged on every hand, and there were still a few pleasures
left in life.  William had his mother and Esther had hers, and they
had not seen each other for a year, though Mrs. Hight had spoken of
a year's making no change in William even at his age.  She must
have been in the far eighties herself, but of a noble courage and
persistence in the world she ruled from her stiff-backed rocking-chair.
</p><p>William unloaded his gift of dried fish, each one chosen with
perfect care, and Esther stood by, watching him; and then she
walked across the field with us, beside the wagon.  I believed that
I was the only one who knew their happy secret, and she blushed a
little as we said good-by. <pb n="764"/>
</p><p>"I hope you ain't goin' to feel too tired, mother's so deaf;
no, I hope you won't be tired," she said kindly, speaking as if she
well knew what tiredness was.  We could hear the neglected sheep
bleating on the hill in the next moment's silence.  Then she smiled
at me, a smile of noble patience, of uncomprehended sacrifice,
which I can never forget.  There was all the remembrance of
disappointed hopes, the hardships of winter, the loneliness of
single-handedness, in her look; but I understood, and I love to
remember her worn face and her young blue eyes.
</p><p>"Good-by, William," she said gently; and William said good-by
and gave her a quick glance, but he did not turn to look back,
though I did, and waved my hand as she was putting up the bars
behind us.  Nor did he speak again until we had passed through the
dark woods and were on our way homeward by the main road.  The
grave yearly visit had been changed from a hope into a happy
memory.
</p><p>"You can see the sea from the top of her pasture hill," said
William at last.
</p><p>"Can you?" I asked, with surprise.
</p><p>"Yes, it's very high land; the ledges up there show very plain
in clear weather from the top of our island, and there's a high
upstandin' tree that makes a landmark for the fishin' grounds."
And William gave a happy sigh.
</p><p>When we had nearly reached the Landing, my companion looked
over into the back of the wagon and saw that the piece of sailcloth
was safe with which he had covered the dried fish.  "I wish we had
got some trout," he said wistfully.  "they always appease Almiry,
and make her feel 'twas worth while to go."
</p><p>I stole a glance at William Blackett.  We had not seen a
solitary mosquito, but there was a dark stripe across his mild
face, which might have been an old scar won long ago in battle.
</p><signed>                    <hi rend="italic">Sarah Orne Jewett.</hi></signed>

</div1>
</body>
</text>
</TEI.2>
