<?xml version="1.0"?>

<?dlps id="JewLand"?>
<?dlps page-images="none" figure-images="no"?>
<?dlps transcription="other"?>

<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/tei-p4/tei2.dtd" [
<!ENTITY % POSTKB "INCLUDE">
<!ENTITY % TEI.extensions.ent SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.ent">
<!ENTITY % TEI.extensions.dtd SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.dtd">
<!ENTITY % ISOnum SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/charent/iso-num.ent"> %ISOnum;
<!ENTITY % ISOpub SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/charent/iso-pub.ent"> %ISOpub;
]>

<TEI.2 id="JewLand">
<teiHeader type="migrated" creator="Etext">
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title type="main">The Landscape Chamber</title>
<title type="sort">landscape chamber</title>
<author>Jewett, Sarah Orne</author>
<respStmt>
<resp>Creation of machine-readable version</resp>
<name>Judy Boss, University of Omaha</name>
</respStmt>
<respStmt>
<resp>Conversion to TEI-conformant markup</resp>
<name>University of Virginia Library Electronic Text Center</name>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt>
<extent>ca. <num type="kilobytes">42</num> kilobytes</extent>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>University of Virginia Library</publisher>
<pubPlace>Charlottesville, Virginia</pubPlace>
<idno type="ETC">JewLand</idno>
<date value="1994">1994</date>
<availability status="public">
<p n="copyright">Copyright &copy; 1994 by the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia</p>
<p n="access">Publicly accessible</p>
</availability>
<idno type="uva-pid">uva-lib:476115</idno>
</publicationStmt>
<seriesStmt>
<title>University of Virginia Library, Text collection</title>
<idno type="uva-set">UVA-LIB-Text</idno>
</seriesStmt>
<sourceDesc>
<biblFull>
<titleStmt>
<title type="main">The Landscape Chamber</title>
<title type="sort">landscape chamber</title>
<author>Sarah Orne Jewett</author>
</titleStmt>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>Atlantic Monthly</publisher>
<pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
<date value="1887-11">November 1887</date>
</publicationStmt>
<seriesStmt>
<p>Volume 60</p>
</seriesStmt>
<notesStmt>
<note>
<p>pp. 603-613</p>
</note>
</notesStmt>
</biblFull>
</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc>
<encodingDesc>
<projectDesc>
<p>Prepared for the University of Virginia Library Electronic Text Center</p>
</projectDesc>
<editorialDecl>
<p>All quotation marks retained as data</p>
<p>All unambiguous end-of-line hyphens have been removed, and the
trailing part of a word has been joined to the preceding line.</p>
<p id="ETC">Keywords in the header are a local Electronic Text Center scheme
to aid in establishing analytical groupings</p>
</editorialDecl>
<refsDecl>
<p>ID elements are given for each page element and are composed of the text's
unique cryptogram and the given page number, as in SpeFQue1 for page one of
Spenser's Faerie Queene.</p>
</refsDecl>
</encodingDesc>
<profileDesc>
<creation>
<date value="1887">1887</date>
</creation>
<langUsage>
<language id="eng" usage="main">English</language>
</langUsage>
<textClass>
<keywords>
<term>fiction; prose</term>
</keywords>
</textClass>
</profileDesc>
<revisionDesc>
<change>
<date value="1994-08">August 1994</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>corrector</resp>
<name>Kelly Tetterton</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Minimal TEI tagging</item>
</change>
<change>
<date value="2005-07">July 2005</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>Corrector</resp>
<name>John Ivor Carlson</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Converted to XML and/or checked tags.</item>
</change>
<change>
<date value="2007-09">September 2007</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>Migration</resp>
<name>Ethan Gruber, University of Virginia Library</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Converted XML markup from TEI Lite to uva-dl-tei (TEI P4 with local customizations).</item>
</change>
<change>
<date value="2008-01">January 2008</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>Migration</resp>
<name>Greg Murray, University of Virginia Library</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Programmatically updated TEI header markup (but not header content) for minimal compliance with current QA requirements.</item>
</change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>
<text id="d1">


<body id="d2">

<div1 type="section" n="1" id="d3"><pb n="603"/>
<head>Part I</head>
<p>I was tired of ordinary journeys, which involved either the
loneliness and discomfort of fashionable hotels, or the
responsibilities of a guest in busy houses.  One is always doing
the same things over and over; I now promised myself that I would
go in search of new people and new scenes, until I was again ready
to turn with delight to my familiar occupations.  So I mounted my
horse one morning, without any definite plan of my journey, and
rode eastward, with a business-like haversack strapped behind the
saddle.  I only wished that the first day's well-known length of
road had been already put behind me.  One drawback to a woman's
enjoyment of an excursion of this sort is the fact that when she is
out of the saddle she is uncomfortably dressed.  But I compromised
matters as nearly as possible by wearing a short corduroy habit,
light both in color and weight, and putting a linen blouse and belt
into my pack, to replace the stiff habit-waist.  The wallet on the
saddle held a flat drinking-cup, a bit of chocolate, and a few hard
biscuit, for provision against improbable famine.  Autumn would be
the best time for such a journey, if the evenings need not be so
often spent in stuffy rooms, with kerosene lamps for company.  This
was early summer, and I had long days in which to amuse myself.
For a book I took a much-beloved small copy of The Sentimental
Journey.
</p><p>After I left my own neighborhood I was looked at with curious
eyes.  I was now and then recognized with surprise, but oftener
viewed with suspicion, as if I were a criminal escaping from
justice.  The keepers of the two country taverns at which I rested
questioned me outright, until I gave a reassuring account of
myself.  Through the middle of the day I let the horse stand
unsaddled in the shade, by the roadside, while I sat near, leaning
against the broad trunk of a tree, and ate a bit of luncheon, or
slept, or read my book, or strolled away up the shore of a brook or
to the top of a hill.  On the third or fourth day I left my
faithful companion so long that he grew restless, and at last
fearful, as petted horses will.  The silence and strangeness of the
place and my disappearance frightened him.  When I returned, I
found that the poor creature had twisted a forward shoe so badly
that I could neither pull it off altogether, nor mount again.
There was nothing to do but to lead him slowly to some farmhouse,
where I could get assistance; so on went the saddle, and away we
plodded together sadly along the dusty road.  The horse looked at
me with anxious eyes, and was made fretful by the difficulty of the
projecting shoe.  I should have provided myself with some pincers,
he seemed to tell me; the foot was aching from the blows I had
given it with a rough-edged stone in trying to draw the tenacious
nails.  It was all my fault, having left him in such a desolate
place, fastened to a tree that grew against a creviced ledge of
rock.  We were both a little sulky at this mischance so early in
the careless expedition.
</p><p>The sea was near, and the salt-marshes penetrated deep into
the country, like abandoned beds of rivers winding inland among the
pine woods and upland pastures.  The higher land separated these
marshes, like a succession of low promontories trending seaward,
and the road climbed and crossed over from one low valley to
another.  There had been no houses for some distance behind us.  I
knew that there was a village with a good tavern a few miles ahead;
so far,
<pb n="604"/>
indeed, that I had planned to reach it at sundown.
I began to feel very tired, and the horse tossed his head more and
more impatiently, resenting my anxious, dragging hold upon the rein
close at his mouth.  There was nobody to be seen; the hills became
steeper, the sunshaded strips of marshland seemed hotter, and I
determined at last to wait until some traveler appeared who could
give us assistance.  Perhaps the blacksmith himself might be out
adventuring that afternoon.
</p><p>We halted by some pasture bars in the shade of an old cider-apple tree, and I threw the bridle over a leaning post in the
unsteady fence; and there the horse and I waited, and looked at
each other reproachfully.  It was some time before I discovered a
large rusty nail lying in the short grass, within reach of my hand.
My pocket-knife was already broken, because I had tried to use it
for a lever, and this was just what I needed.  I quickly caught up
the disabled hoof again, and with careful prying the tough nails
loosed their hold at last, and the bent shoe dropped with a clink.
The horse gave a whinny of evident relief, and seemed to respect me
again, and I was ready to mount at once; in an instant life lost
its depressing aspect.  "Keep your feet out of clefts now!" I said
joyfully, with a friendly stroke of the good creature's neck and
tangled mane, and a moment afterward we were back in the stony
road.  Alas, the foot had been strained, and our long halt had only
stiffened it.  I was mounted on three feet, not four.  Nothing was
to be done but to go forward, step by step, to the far-away
village, or to any friendly shelter this side of it.
</p><p>The afternoon was waning: sometimes I rode, sometimes I
walked; those three miles of marsh and hill seemed interminable.
At last I saw the chimneys of a house; the horse raised his head
high, and whinnied loud and long.
</p><p>These chimneys were most reassuring; being high and square,
they evidently belonged to a comfortable house of the last century,
and my spirits rose again.  The country was still abandoned by
human beings.  I had seen no one since noon, but the road was
little used, and was undoubtedly no longer the main highway of that
region.  I wondered what impression I should make in such a
migratory guise.  The saddle and its well-stuffed haversack and my
own dustiness amused me unexpectedly, and I understood for the
first time that the rest and change of this solitary excursion had
done me much good.  I was no longer listless and uninterested, but
ready for adventure of any sort.  It had been a most sensible thing
to go wandering alone through the country.  But now the horse's
ankle was swollen.  I grew anxious again, and looked at the
chimneys with relief.  Presently I came in sight of the house.
</p><p>It was disappointing, for the first view gave an impression of
dreariness and neglect.  The barn and straggling row of out-buildings were leaning this way and that, mossy and warped; the
blinds of the once handsome house were broken; and everything gave
evidence of unhindered decline from thrift and competence to
poverty and ruin.  A good colonial mansion, I thought, abandoned by
its former owners, and tenanted now by some shiftless outcasts of
society, who ask but meagre comfort, and are indifferent to the
decencies of life.  Full of uncertainty, I went along the approach
to the barn, noticing, however, with surprise that the front yard
had been carefully tended; there were some dark crimson roses in
bloom, and broken lines of box which had been carefully clipped at
no remote period.  Nobody was in sight.  I went to the side door,
and gave a knock with my whip at arm's length, for the horse was
eager to reach the uninviting, hungry-looking stable.  Some time
elapsed before my repeated summons were answered; then
<pb n="605"/>
the
door slowly opened, and a woman just this side of middle age stood
before me, waiting to hear my errand.  She had a pathetic look, as
if she were forced by circumstances to deny all requests, however
her own impulses might lead her toward generosity.  I was instantly
drawn toward her, in warm sympathy: the blooming garden was hers;
she was very poor.  I would plead my real fatigue, and ask for a
night's lodging, and perhaps my holiday might also give her
pleasure.  But a curious hardness drew her face into forbidding
angles, even as her sweet and womanly eyes watched me with
surprised curiosity.
</p><p>"I should be very sorry to take the horse any further to-day,"
said I, after stating my appealing case.  "I will give you as
little trouble as possible."  At this moment the haggard face of an
elderly man peered at me over her shoulder.
</p><p>"We don't keep tavern, young lady," he announced in an
unexpectedly musical, low voice, "but since your horse is" &mdash;
</p><p>"I am ready to pay any price you ask," I interrupted
impatiently; and he gave me an eager look, and then came to the
outer step, ignoring both his daughter and me, as he touched the
horse with real kindliness.  "'Tis a pretty creature!" he said
admiringly, and at once stooped stiffly down to examine the lifted
foot.  I explained the accident in detail, grateful for such
intelligent sympathy, while he stroked the lamed ankle.
</p><p>"There's no damage done," he assured me presently, looking up
with transient self-forgetfulness.  "A common liniment will do;
there's a bottle in the house, but 't will cost you something," and
his face clouded again.
</p><p>I turned to the daughter, who gave me a strange, appealing
look.  Her eyes begged me entreatingly, "Give him his own way;" her
firm-set mouth signified her assent to the idea that I had no right
to demand favors.
</p><p>"Do what you think best," I said, "at your own price.  I shall
be very grateful to you;" and having come to this understanding,
the father and I unbuckled the saddle-girths, while the daughter
stood watching us.  The old man led the limping horse across the
green dooryard to a weather-beaten stable, talking to him in a low
tone.  The creature responded by unusual docility.  I even saw him,
though usually so suspicious and fretful with strangers, put his
head close to his leader's shoulder with most affectionate impulse.
I gathered up my belongings, &mdash; my needments, as somebody had called
them, after Spenser's fashion, in the morning, &mdash; and entered the
door.
</p>
</div1>
<div1 type="section" n="2" id="d4">
<head>Part II</head>
<p>Along the by-ways and in the elder villages of New England
stand many houses like this, from which life and vigor have long
been ebbing, until all instincts of self-preservation seem to have
departed.  The commonplace, thrifty fears of increasing damage from
cracks, or leaks, or falling plaster no longer give alarm; as age
creeps through the human frame, pilfering the pleasures of
enthusiasm and activity one by one, so it is with a decaying house.
The old man's shrewd eyes alone seemed unrelated to his
surroundings.  What sorrow or misfortune had made him accept them?
I wondered, as I stared about the once elegant room.  Nothing new
had been brought to it for years; the leather-bound books in the
carved secretary might have belonged to his grandfather.  The floor
was carpetless and deeply worn; the faded paper on the walls and
the very paint looked as old as he.  The pinch of poverty could
nowhere be much sharper than here, but the exquisite cleanness and
order of the place made one ignore the thought of poverty in its
common aspect, for all its offensive and
<pb n="606"/>
repulsive
qualities were absent.  I sat down in a straight-backed mahogany
chair, feeling much relieved, and not without gratitude for this
unexpected episode.  The hostess left me alone.  I was glad enough
to have the long day shortened a little, and to find myself in this
lonely, mysterious house.  I was pleased by the thought that the
price of my food and lodging would be very welcome, and I grew more
and more eager to know the history of my new friends.  I have never
been conscious of a more intense desire to make myself harmonious,
or to win some degree of confidence.  And when the silence of the
old sitting-room grew tiresome I went out to the stable, whence my
host had not returned, and was quite reconciled at finding that I
was looked upon by him, at least, merely as an appendage to my
four-footed companion.
</p><p>The old man regarded me with indifference, and went on
patiently rubbing the horse's foot.  I was silent after having
offered to take his place and being contemptuously refused.  His
clothes were curiously old and worn, patched bravely, and an
embroidery of careful darns.  The color of them was not unlike the
dusty gray of long-neglected cobwebs.  There was unusual delicacy
and refinement in his hands and feet, and I was sure, from the
first glance at my new friends and the first sound of their voices,
that they had inherited gentle blood, though such an inheritance
had evidently come through more than one generation to whom had
been sternly denied any approach to luxury or social advantage.  I
have often noticed in country villages the descendants of those
clergymen who once ruled New England sternly and well, and while
they may be men and women of undeveloped minds, without authority
and even of humble circumstances, they yet bear the mark of
authority and dignified behavior, like silver and copper coins with
a guinea stamp.
</p><p>I was more and more oppressed by the haunting sense of
poverty, for I saw proofs everywhere that the inhabitants of the
old house made no practical protest against its slow decay.  The
woman's share of work was performed best, as one might see by their
mended clothes; but the master's domain was hopelessly untended,
not only as to the rickety buildings, but in the land itself, which
was growing wild bushes at its own sweet will, except for a rough
patch near the house, which had been dug and planted that year.
Was this brooding, sad old man discouraged by life?  Did he say to
himself, "Let things be; they will last my time"?  I found myself
watching his face with intense interest, but I did not dare to ask
questions, and only stood and watched him.  The sad mouth of the
man might have been a den from which stinging wild words could
assail a curious stranger.  I was afraid of what he might say to
me, yet I longed to hear him speak.
</p><p>The summer day was at its close.  I moved a step forward, to
get away from the level sunbeams which dazzled my eyes, and
ventured to give some news about myself and the lonely journey that
had hitherto brought me such pleasure.  The listener looked up with
sincere attention, which made me grow enthusiastic at once, and I
described my various experiences, and especially the amusing
comments which I had heard upon my mode of traveling about the
country.  It amazed me to think that I was within sixty miles of
home and yet a foreigner.  At last I asked a trivial question about
some portion of the scenery, which was pleasantly answered.  The
old man's voice was singularly sweet and varied in tone, the exact
reverse of a New Englander's voice of the usual rural quality.  I
was half startled at seeing my horse quickly turn his head to look
at the speaker, as if with human curiosity equal to my own.  I felt
a thrill of vague apprehension.  I was unwise
<pb n="607"/>
enough for a
moment to dread taking up my residence in this dilapidated mansion;
a creeping horror, such as one feels at hearing footsteps behind
one in a dark, strange place, made me foolishly uneasy, as I stood
looking off across the level country through the golden light of
closing day, beyond the marshes and beyond the sand dunes to the
sea.  What had happened to this uncanny father and daughter, that
they were contented to let the chances of life slip by untouched,
while their ancestral dwelling gradually made itself ready to
tumble about their ears?
</p><p>I could see that the horse's foot was much better already, and
I watched with great sympathy the way that the compassionate,
patient fingers touched and soothed the bruised joint.  But I saw
no sign of any other horse in the stable, save a few stiffened,
dusty bits of harness hung on a high peg in the wall; and as I
looked at these, and renewed my wonder that such a person should
have no horse of his own, especially at such a distance from any
town, the old man spoke again.
</p><p>"Look up at that bit of dry skin over the harnesses," said he.
"That was the pretty ear of the best mare that ever trod these
roads.  She leaped the stableyard gate one day, caught her foot in
a rope, and broke her neck.  She was like those swallows one
minute, and the next she was a heap of worthless flesh, a heavy
thing to be dragged away and hidden in the earth."  His voice
failed him suddenly, poor old fellow; it told me that he had
suffered cruel sorrows that made this loss of a pleasure almost
unbearable.  So far life had often brought me successes, and I had
gained a habit of expecting my own enterprises to be lucky.  I
stood appalled before this glimpse of a defeated life and its long
procession of griefs.
</p><p>Presently the master of the place went into the house, and
returned with a worn wooden trencher of bits of hard bread and some
meal.  The hungry creature in the stall whinnied eagerly, and
nestled about, while our host ascended the broken stairway to the
stable loft; and after waiting for some time, I heard the rustle of
an armful of hay which came down into the crib.  I looked that way,
and was not surprised, when I noticed the faded, dusty dryness of
it, to see my dainty beast sniff at it with disappointment, and
look round at me inquiringly.  The old man joined me, and I
protested hastily against such treatment of my favorite.
</p><p>"Cannot we get somebody to bring some better hay, and oats
enough for a day or two, if you are unprovided?" I asked.
</p><p>"The creature must not be overfed," he said grudgingly, with
a new harsh tone.  "You will heat the foot, and we must keep the
beast quiet.  Anything will serve to-night; to-morrow he can graze
all day, and keep the foot moving gently; next day, he can be
shod."
</p><p>"But there is danger in giving him green grass," I suggested.
"This is too rich pasturage about the house; surely you know enough
of horses to have learned that.  He will not be fit to ride,
either.  If I meant to give him a month of pasture, it would be
another thing.  No; send somebody for at least an armful of decent
hay.  I will go myself.  Are there houses near?"
</p><p>The old man had gone into the stall, and was feeding the
hungry horse from the trencher.  I was startled to see him snatch
back two or three bits of the bread and put them into his pocket,
as if, with all his fondness for the horse and a sincere desire to
make him comfortable, he nevertheless grudged the food.  I became
convinced that the poor soul was a miser.  He certainly played the
character exactly, and yet there was an appealing look in his eyes,
which, joined with the tones of his voice, made me sure that he
fought against his tyrannous inclinations.  I wondered irreverently
<pb n="608"/>
if I should be killed that night, after the fashion of
traditional tavern robberies, for the sake of what might be found
in my pocket, and sauntered toward the house.  It remained to be
proved whether the daughter was the victim or the upholder of her
father's traits.
</p><p>I had the satisfaction of finding that the daughter was just
arranging a table for supper.  As I passed the wide-open door of a
closet, I was tempted to look in by the faint ancient odor of plum
cakes and Madeira wine which escaped; but I never saw a barer
closet than that, or one that looked hungrier in spite of the
lingering fragrance of hospitality.  It gave me a strange feeling
as if there were a still subtler link with the past, and some
invisible presence would have me contrast the house's former
opulence with its present meagreness.  When we sat at table I was
not surprised to find, on a cloth that was half covered with darns
and patches, some pieces of superb old English silver and delicate
china.  The fare was less than frugal, but was nobly eked out with
a dish of field strawberries, as if kind Nature had come to the
rescue.  Cream there was none, nor sugar, nor even tea or butter.
I had an aching sense of the poverty of the family, and curiously
questioned in my own mind how far they found it possible to live
without money.  There was some thin, crisp corn bread, which had
been baked in the morning, or whenever there had last been a fire.
It was very good.  Perhaps my entertainers even gathered their own
salt from the tide-pools, to flavor the native corn.  Look where I
would, I could see nothing for which money had been lately spent;
here was a thing to be wondered at in this lavish America, and I
pushed back my chair at last, while I was still half hungry, from
a dread that there would be nothing for breakfast unless I saved it
then.
</p><p>The father and daughter were very agreeable, I must confess;
they talked with me about my journey now, and my plans, as if they
were my personal friends, and the strange meal was full of
pleasure, after all.  What had brought a lady and gentleman to such
a pass?
</p><p>After supper the daughter disappeared for a time, busy with
her household cares; a little later the father went out of the
stable and across the fields, before I could call to him or offer
my company.  He walked with a light, quick step, like an Indian, as
if he were used to taking journeys on foot.  I found myself
uncommonly tired; the half illness which had fettered me seemed to
have returned, after the unusual anxiety and weariness of the
afternoon, and I longed to go to bed and to sleep.  I had been
interested in much that my entertainers had said of the early
history of that part of the country, and while we sat at the table
I had begun to look forward to a later evening talk, but almost
before daylight faded I was forced to go to bed.
</p><p>My hostess led me through a handsome empty hall, of the wide
and stately colonial type, to a comfortable upper room, furnished
with a gloomy-looking curtained bedstead and heavy mahogany
furniture of the best old fashion.  It seemed as if the room had
been long unused, and also as if the lower part of the house were
in a much worse state of disrepair and threadbareness than this.
But the two large windows stood open to the fading sky and sweet
country air, and I bade my hostess good-night cheerfully.  She
lingered to see if I were comfortable; it was the first time I had
been alone with her.  "You can see that we are not used to
entertaining company," she whispered, reddening with sensitiveness,
and smiling apologetically.  "Father has kept everybody away for so
many years that I rarely have any one to speak to, or anything to
do but to keep the poor old house clean.  Father means to be kind
but he" &mdash; and she turned away, much embarrassed by
<pb n="609"/>
my
questioning look &mdash; "he has a monomania; he inherits it from my
grandfather.  He fears want, yet seems to have no power to provide
against it.  We are poor, God knows, yet we have resources; or had
them once," she added, sorrowfully.  "It was the horse that made
him willing to let you in.  He loves horses, yet he has long denied
himself even that useful pleasure."
</p><p>"But surely he ought to be controlled," I urged.  "You must
have suffered."
</p><p>"I know all that you are eager to say," she replied; "but I
promised my dear mother to be patient with him.  It will not be
long now; he is very feeble.  I have a horror that this habit of
parsimony has rooted itself too deeply in my own life to be shaken
off.  You will hear mockery enough of us among the farmers."
</p><p>"You surely have friends?"
</p><p>"Only at a distance," said she, sadly.  "I fear that they are
no longer friends.  I have you," she added, turning to me quickly,
in a pathetic way that made me wish to put my arms about her.  "I
have been longing for a friendly face.   Yes, it is very hard," and
she drearily went out of the door, and left me alone with the dim
light of the sky outside, the gloomy shadows of the room within.
I tried to fancy some clue to the weird misery of this poverty-stricken household, as I lay down; but I fell asleep very soon, and
slept all night, without even a dream.
</p>
</div1>
<div1 type="section" n="3" id="d5">
 <head>Part III</head>
<p>Daylight brought a new eagerness and a less anxious curiosity
about my strange entertainers.  I opened my eyes in broad sunlight.
I was puzzled by the unfamiliar India-cotton hangings of the great
bedstead; then I caught sight of my dusty habit and my riding-cap
and whip, near by.  I instantly resolved that even if I found my
horse in the restored condition there was every reason to expect,
I would make this house my headquarters for as long time as its
owners would keep me, or I could content myself.  I would try to
show some sisterly affection to the fast-aging woman who was so
enslaved by her father's delusions.  I had come out in search of
adventure; it would be a difficult task to match my present
surroundings.
</p><p>I listened for the sound of footsteps or voices from below,
but it was still very early, and I looked about the long-untenanted
room with deliberate interest and scrutiny.  As I changed my
position a little, I caught sight of a curious old painting on the
large oval panel above the empty fireplace.  The colors were dull,
the drawing was quaintly conventional, and I recognized the
subject, though not immediately.  The artist had pleased himself by
making a study of the old house itself, and later, as I dressed, I
examined it in detail.
</p><p>From the costume of the figures I saw that it must have been
painted more than a hundred years before.  In astonishing contrast
to the present condition, it appeared like a satirical show of the
house's possibilities.  Servants held capering steeds for gay
gentlemen to mount, and ladies walked together in fine attire down
the garden alleys of the picture.  Once a hospitable family had
kept open house behind the row of elms, and once the follies of the
world and the fashions of brilliant, luxurious life had belonged to
this decayed and withering household.  I wondered if the miserly
old man, to whose strangely sweet and compelling voice I had
listened the evening before, could bear to look at this picture,
and acknowledge his unlikeness to his prosperous ancestors.

</p><p>It was well for me that the keeping of hens is comparatively
inexpensive, for I breakfasted comfortably, and was never so
heartily rejoiced at the vicinity of a chicken-coop.  My proposal
to stay with
<pb n="610"/>
my new friends for a few days met with no
opposition from either host or hostess; and again, as I looked in
their pinched and hopeless faces, I planned some secret excuses for
making a feast of my own, or a happy holiday.  The fields and hills
of the old picture were still unchanged, but what ebb and flow of
purpose, of comfort, of social condition, had enriched and
impoverished the household!
</p><p>"Where did she sleep?" asked the master of the house,
suddenly, with a strange, suspicious glance at his daughter.
</p><p>"In the landscape chamber," the pale woman said, without
lifting her eyes to his, though she grew whiter and thinner as she
spoke.
</p><p>I looked at him instinctively to see his eyes blaze with
anger, and expected a torrent of abuse, because he was manifestly
so much displeased.  Nothing was said, but with a feeling of
uneasiness we left the table, and I went out to the kitchen with my
new friend.
</p><p>"There is no reason why I should not have put you into the
landscape chamber," she told me instantly.  "It is a fancy of my
father's.  I had aired that room thoroughly in the morning, but the
front guest-chambers have been closed for some time."
</p><p>"Who painted the strange old picture?" I asked.  "Some member
of the family?"  But I was answered that it was the work of a
Frenchman, who was captured in war-time, and paroled under the care
of her great-grandfather.
</p><p>"He must have had a gay visit," I suggested, "if he has left
a faithful picture of the house as he saw it."
</p><p>"The house used to be like that always," was the faint
response, and the speaker hesitated, as if she considered whether
we did right in discussing her family history; then she turned
quickly away.  "I believe we are under some miserable doom.  Father
will be sure to tell you so, at any rate," she added, with an
effort at gayety.  "He thinks that he fights against it, but I
always say that he was cowardly, and accepted it," and she sighed
wearily.
</p><p>I looked at her with fresh surprise and conjecture.  I forgot
for the time this great, busy, prosaic world of which we were both
a part, and I felt as if I had lost a score of years for each day's
journey, and had gone backward into the past.  New England holds
many strange households within its borders, but there could not be
another which approached this.  The very air of the house oppressed
me, and I strayed out into the beautiful wide fields, and found my
spirits rising again at once.  I turned at last to look back at the
group of gray buildings in the great level landscape.  They were
such a small excrescence upon the fruitful earth, those roofs which
covered awful stagnation and hindrance of the processes of
spiritual life and growth.  What power could burst the bonds, and
liberate the man and woman I had left, from a mysterious tyranny?
</p><p>I was bareheaded, and the morning grew very hot.  I went
toward a group of oaks, to shelter myself in the shade, and found
the ancient burying-place of the family.  There were numerous
graves, but none were marked except the oldest.  There was a group
of rude but stately stones, with fine inscriptions, yet curiously
enough the latest of them bore a date soon after the beginning of
the century; all the more recent graves were low and unmarked in
any way.  The family fortunes had waned long ago, perhaps; I might
be wronging the present master of the house, though I remembered
what had been said to me of some mysterious doom.  I could not help
thinking of my new acquaintances most intently, and was startled at
the sound of footsteps.  I saw the old man, muttering and bending
his head until he could see nothing but the ground at his feet.  He
only picked up some dead branches that had fallen from the oaks,
and went away toward the house again; always looking at the ground,
as if he expected to find
<pb n="611"/>
something.  It came to my mind
with greater distinctness that he was a miser, poor only by his own
choice; and I indignantly resolved to urge the daughter to break
her allegiance to him for a time, to claim her own and set herself
free.  But the miser had no cheerful sense of his hoards, no
certainty of a munificence which was more to him than any use of
it; there was a look upon his face as of a preying conscience
within, a gnawing reptile of shame and guilt and evil memory.  Had
he sacrificed all sweet family life and natural ties to his craving
for wealth?  I watched the bent and hungry figure out of sight.
</p><p>When I reached the house again, I went through the open door
of the wide hall, and gained my landscape chamber without being
seen by any one.  I was tired and dizzy with the unusual heat, and,
quickly drawing the close shutters, I threw myself on the bed to
rest.  All the light in the room came from the shaded hall; there
was absolute silence, except some far-off country sounds of birds
high in air or lowing cattle.  The house itself was still as a
tomb.
</p><p>I went to sleep, but it was not sound sleep.  I grew heavy and
tired with my own weight.  I heard soft footsteps coming up the
stairs; some one stopped as if to listen outside the wide-open
door; then the gray, shadowy figure of the old man stood just
within, and his eyes peered about the room.  I was behind the
curtains; one had been unfastened, and hid me from his sight at
first, but as he took one step forward he saw me, lying asleep.  He
bent over me, until I felt my hair stir with his breath, but I did
not move.  His presence was not frightful, strange to say; I felt
as if I were only dreaming.  I opened my eyes a little as he went
away, apparently satisfied, to the closet door, and unlocked it,
starting and looking at me anxiously as the key turned in the lock.
Then he disappeared.  I had a childish desire to shut him in and
keep him prisoner, for reasons that were not clear to myself.
Whether he only wished to satisfy himself that a concealed treasure
was untouched I do not know, but presently he came out, and
carefully locked the door again, and went away on tiptoe.  I
fancied that he lingered before the picture above the chimney-place, and wondered if his conscience pricked him as he
acknowledged the contrast between past and present.  Then he
groaned softly, and went out.  My heart began to beat very fast.
I sprang up and tried to lock the door into the hall.  My
enthusiasm about spending a few days in this dismal place suddenly
faded out, for I could not bear the thought that the weird old man
was free to prowl about at his own sad will.  But as I stood
undecided in my doorway, a song sparrow perched on the sill of the
wide hall window, and sang his heart away in a most cheerful
strain.  There was something so touching and appealing in the
contrast that I felt a wistful clutch at my throat, while I smiled,
as one does when tears are coming like April showers to one's eyes.
Without thinking what I did, I went back into the room, threw open
the shutters again, and stood before the dingy landscape.  How the
horses pranced up to the door, and how fine the ladies were in
their hoop-petticoats and high feathers!  I imagined that the
picture had been a constant rebuke to the dwellers in the house
through their wasting lives and failing fortunes.  In every human
heart, said I, there is such a picture of the ideal life, &mdash; the high
possibilities and successes, the semblance of duties done and of
spiritual achievements.  It forever measures our incompleteness by
its exact likeness to that completeness which we would not fight
hard enough to win.  But as I looked up at the panel, the old
landscape became dim, and I knew that it was only because a cloud
was hiding the sun; yet I was glad to leave the shadows of the
room, and to hurry down the wide stairway.
<pb n="612"/>
</p><p>I saw nothing of the daughter, though I searched for her, and
even called her, through the house.  When I reached the side door
I found her father crossing the yard, and wondered if he would show
any consciousness of our having so lately met.  He stood still and
waited for me, and my first impulse made me ask, "What did you want
just now?  I was not asleep when you were in my room; you
frightened me."
</p><p>"Do not be afraid," he answered, with unexpected patience.
"You must take us as you find us.  It is a sad old house, but you
need not be afraid; we are much more afraid of you!" and we both
smiled amiably.
</p><p>"But your daughter," said I; "I have been asking her to come
away for a time, to visit me or take a journey.  It would be much
better for you both; and she needs a change and a little
pleasuring.  God does not mean that we shall make our lives utterly
dismal."  I was afraid, and did not dare to meet the old man's eyes
after I had spoken so plainly.
</p><p>He laughed coldly, and glanced at his mended coat-sleeve.
</p><p>"What do you know about happiness?  You are too young," said
he.  "At your age I thought I knew the world.  What difference
would it make if the old place here were like the gay ghost of it
in our landscape chamber?  The farmers would be jealous of our
luxury; reverence and respect would be turned into idle curiosity.
This quiet countryside would be disgraced by such a flaunting
folly.  No, we are very comfortable, my child and I; you must not
try to disturb us," and he looked at me with a kind of piteous
suspicion.
</p><p>There was a large block of stone under one of the old elms,
which had been placed there long ago for a mounting-block, and here
we seated ourselves.  As I looked at my companion, he seemed like
a man unused to the broad light of day.  I fancied that a prisoner,
who had just ended many years of dungeon life, would wear exactly
such a face.  And yet it was such a lovely summer day of a joyful
world, if he would only take or make it so.  Alas, he matched the
winter weather better.  I could not bear to think of the old house
in winter!
</p><p>"Who is to blame?" said the old man suddenly, in a strange,
eager tone which startled me, and made me shrink away from him.
"We are in bondage.  I am a generous-hearted man, yet I can never
follow my own impulses.  I longed to give what I had with a lavish
hand, when I was younger, but some power restrained me.  I have
grown old while I tried to fight it down.  We are all in prison
while we are left in this world, &mdash; that is the truth; in prison for
another man's sin."  For the first time I understood that he was
not altogether sane.  "If there were an ancestor of mine, as I have
been taught, who sold his soul for wealth, the awful price was
this, that he lost the power of using it.  He was greedy for gain,
and now we cannot part with what we have, even for common comfort.
His children and his children's children have suffered for his
fault.  He has lived in the hell of watching us from generation to
generation; seeing our happiness spoiled, our power of usefulness
wither away.  Wherever he is, he knows that we are all misers
because he was miserly, and stamped us with the mark of his own
base spirit.  He has watched his descendants shrivel up and
disappear one by one, poor and ungenerous in God's world.  We fight
against the doom of it, but it wins at last.  Thank God, there are
only two of us left."
</p><p>I had sprung to my feet, frightened by the old man's
vehemence.  I could not help saying that God meant us to be free
and unconquered by any evil power; the gray, strange face looked
blindly at me, and I could not speak again.  This was the secret of
the doom,
<pb n="613"/>
then.  I left the old man crying, while I hurried
away to find the mistress of the desolate house, and appealed to
her to let me send a companion for her father, who could properly
care for him here, or persuade him to go away to some place where
he would forget his misery among new interests and scenes.  She
herself must not be worn out by his malady of unreason.
</p><p>But I only dashed my sympathy against the rock of her
hopelessness.  "I think we shall all disappear some night in a
winter storm, and the world will be rid of us, &mdash; father and the
house and I, all three," she said, with bitter dreariness, and
turned to her work again.
</p><p>Early that evening, I said good-by to my new friends, for the
horse was sound, and not to be satisfied by such meagre stabling.
Our host seemed sorry to let the creature go, and stood stroking
him affectionately after I had mounted.  "How the famous old breed
holds its own!" he said wistfully.  "I should like to have seen the
ancestor who has stamped his likeness so unmistakably on all his
descendants."
</p><p>"But among human beings," I could not resist saying, "there is
freedom, thank God!  We can climb to our best possibilities, and
outgrow our worst inheritance."
</p><p>"No, no!" cried the old man bitterly.  "You are young and
fortunate.  Forget us, if you can; we are of those who have no hope
in a world of fate."
</p><p>I looked back again and again, as I rode away.  It was a house
of shadows and strange moods, and I was glad when I had fairly left
it behind me; yet I look forward to seeing it again.  I well
remember the old man's clutch at the money I offered him, and the
kiss and the bunch of roses that the daughter gave to me.  But late
that evening I was not sorry to shut myself into my prosaic room at
a village hotel, rather than try to sleep again behind the faded
figured curtains of the landscape chamber. </p>
<signed>Sarah Orne Jewett.</signed>

</div1>
</body>
</text>
</TEI.2>
