<?xml version="1.0"?>

<?dlps id="JewMour"?>
<?dlps page-images="none" figure-images="no"?>
<?dlps transcription="other"?>

<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/tei-p4/tei2.dtd" [
<!ENTITY % POSTKB "INCLUDE">
<!ENTITY % TEI.extensions.ent SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.ent">
<!ENTITY % TEI.extensions.dtd SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.dtd">
<!ENTITY % ISOnum SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/charent/iso-num.ent"> %ISOnum;
<!ENTITY % ISOpub SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/charent/iso-pub.ent"> %ISOpub;

]>


<TEI.2 id="JewMour">
<teiHeader type="migrated" creator="Etext">
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title type="main">From A Mournful Villager</title>
<title type="sort">from a mournful villager</title>
<author>Jewett, Sarah Orne</author>
<respStmt>
<resp>Creation of machine-readable version:</resp>
<name>Judy Boss</name>
<resp>Conversion to TEI.2-conformant markup:</resp>
<name>University of Virginia Library Electronic Text Center</name>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt>
<extent>ca. <num type="kilobytes">33</num> kilobytes</extent>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>University of Virginia Library</publisher>
<pubPlace>Charlottesville, Virginia</pubPlace>
<idno type="ETC">JewMour</idno>
<date value="1995">1995</date>
<availability status="public">
<p n="copyright">Copyright &copy; 1995 by the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia</p>
<p n="access">Publicly accessible</p>
</availability>
<idno type="uva-pid">uva-lib:476116</idno>
</publicationStmt>
<seriesStmt>
<title>University of Virginia Library, Text collection</title>
<idno type="uva-set">UVA-LIB-Text</idno>
</seriesStmt>
<sourceDesc>
<biblFull>
<titleStmt>
<title type="main">From A Mournful Villager</title>
<title type="sort">from a mournful villager</title>
<author>Sarah Orne Jewett</author>
</titleStmt>
<editionStmt>
<p>1st Edition</p>
</editionStmt>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>Atlantic Monthly</publisher>
<pubPlace>Boston</pubPlace>
<date value="1881">1881</date>
</publicationStmt>
<seriesStmt>
<p>Volume 48</p>
</seriesStmt>
<notesStmt>
<note>
<p>Atlantic Monthly 48 (Nov. 1881): 664-672</p>
</note>
</notesStmt>
</biblFull>
</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc>
<encodingDesc>
<projectDesc>
<p>Prepared for the University of Virginia Library Electronic Text Center</p>
</projectDesc>
<editorialDecl>
<p>All quotation marks retained as data</p>
<p>All unambiguous end-of-line hyphens have been removed, and the
trailing part of a word has been joined to the preceding line.</p>
<p id="ETC">Keywords in the header are a local Electronic Text Center scheme
to aid in establishing analytical groupings</p>
<p>Note: Ms.Boss has added a period after the last word on page 667.</p>
</editorialDecl>
<refsDecl>
<p>ID elements are given for each page element and are composed of the text's
unique cryptogram and the given page number, as in AusEmma1 for page one of
Jane Austen's Emma.</p>
</refsDecl>
</encodingDesc>
<profileDesc>
<creation>
<date value="1881">1881</date>
</creation>
<langUsage>
<language id="eng" usage="main">English</language>
</langUsage>
<textClass>
<keywords>
<term>fiction; prose</term>
<term>Women Writers</term>
</keywords>
</textClass>
</profileDesc>
<revisionDesc>
<change>
<date value="1995-09">September 1995</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>corrector</resp>
<name>Deirdre Johnson, Electronic Text Center, University of Virginia</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Header added, basic TEI markup added</item>
</change>
<change>
<date value="2005-07">July 2005</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>Corrector</resp>
<name>John Ivor Carlson</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Converted to XML and/or checked tags.</item>
</change>
<change>
<date value="2007-09">September 2007</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>Migration</resp>
<name>Ethan Gruber, University of Virginia Library</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Converted XML markup from TEI Lite to uva-dl-tei (TEI P4 with local customizations).</item>
</change>
<change>
<date value="2008-01">January 2008</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>Migration</resp>
<name>Greg Murray, University of Virginia Library</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Programmatically updated TEI header markup (but not header content) for minimal compliance with current QA requirements.</item>
</change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text id="d1">
<body id="d2">


<div1 type="story" id="d3"><pb n="664"/><head> FROM A MOURNFUL VILLAGER.</head>

    <p> LATELY I have been thinking, with much sorrow, of the
approaching extinction of front yards, and of the type of New
England village character and civilization with which they are
associated.  Formerly, because I lived in an old-fashioned New
England village, it would have been hard for me to imagine<pb n="665"/>
that there were parts of the country where the front yard, as I
knew it, was not in fashion, and that grounds (however small) had
taken its place.  No matter how large a piece of land lay in front
of a house in old times, it was still a front yard, in spite of
noble dimension and the skill of practiced gardeners.</p>
<p>      There are still a good many examples of the old manner of out-of-door life and customs, as well as a good deal of the old-fashioned provincial society, remaining in the eastern parts of the
New England States; but if put side by side with the society that
is American rather than provincial, one discovers it to be in a
small minority.  The representative United States citizen will be,
or already is, a Westerner, and his instincts and ways of looking
at things have certain characteristics of their own which are
steadily growing more noticeable.</p>
<p>     For many years New England was simply a bit of Old England
transplanted.  We all can remember elderly people whose ideas were
wholly under the influence of their English ancestry.  It is hardly
more than a hundred years since we were English colonies, and not
independent United States, and the customs and ideas of the mother
country were followed from force of habit.  Now one begins to see
a difference; the old traditions have had time to disappear almost
entirely even in the most conservative and least changed towns, and
a new element has come in.  The true characteristics of American
society, as I have said, are showing themselves more and more
distinctly to the westward of New England, and come back to it in
a tide that steadily sweeps away the old traditions.  It rises over
the heads of the prim and stately idols before which our
grandfathers and grandmothers bowed down and worshiped, and which
we ourselves were at least taught to walk softly by as they toppled
on their thrones.</p>
<p>     One cannot help wondering what a lady of the old school will
be like a hundred years from now!  But, at any rate, she will not
be in heart and thought and fashion of good breeding as truly an
Englishwoman as if she had never stepped out of Great Britain.  If
one of our own elderly ladies were suddenly dropped into the midst
of provincial English society, she would be quite at home; but west
of her own Hudson River she is lucky if she does not find herself
behind the times, and almost a stranger and a foreigner.</p>
<p>     And yet from the first there was a little difference, and the
colonies were New England and not Old.  In some ways more radical,
yet in some ways more conservative, than the people across the
water, they showed a new sort of flower when they came into bloom
in this new climate and soil.  In the old days there had not been
time for the family ties to be broken and forgotten.  Instead of
the unknown English men and women who are our sixth and seventh
cousins now, they had first and second cousins then; but there was
little communication between one country and the other, and the
mutual interest in every-day affairs necessarily faded out quickly.
A traveler was a curiosity, and here, even between the villages
themselves, there was far less intercourse than we can believe
possible.  People stayed on their own ground; their horizons were
of small circumference, and their whole interest and thought were
spent upon their own land, their own neighbors, their own affairs,
while they were not only contented with this state of things, but
encouraged it.  One has only to look at the high-walled pews of the
old churches, at the high fences of the town gardens, and at even
the strong fortifications around some family lots in the burying-grounds, to be sure of this.  The interviewer was not besought and
encouraged in those days; he was defied.  In that quarter at least
they had the advantage of us.  Their interest was as real and
<pb n="666"/>  heart-felt in each other's affairs as ours, let us hope; but
they never allowed idle curiosity to show itself in the world's
market-place, shameless and unblushing.</p>
<p>     There is so much to be said in favor of our own day, and the
men and women of our own time, that a plea for a recognition of the
quaintness and pleasantness of village life in the old days cannot
seem unwelcome, or without deference to all that has come with the
later years of ease and comfort, or of discovery in the realms of
mind or matter.  We are beginning to cling to the elderly people
who are so different from ourselves, and for this reason: we are
paying them instinctively the honor that is due from us to our
elders and betters; they have that grand prestige and dignity that
belongs to age; they are like old wines,&mdash;perhaps no better than
many others when they were young, but now, after many years, they
have come to be worth nobody knows how many dollars a dozen, and
the connoisseurs make treasures of the few bottles of that vintage
which are left.</p>
<p>     It was a restricted and narrowly limited life in the old days.
Religion, or rather sectarianism, was apt to be simply a matter of
inheritance, and there was far more bigotry in every cause and
question,&mdash;a fiercer partisanship; and because there were fewer
channels of activity, and those undivided into specialties, there
was a whole-souled concentration of energy that was as efficient as
it was sometimes narrow and short-sighted.  People were more
contented in the sphere of life to which it had pleased God to call
them, and they do not seem to have been so often sorely tempted by
the devil with a sight of the kingdoms of the world and the glory
of them.  We are more likely to busy ourselves with finding things
to do than in doing with our might the work that is in our hands
already.  The disappearance of many of the village front yards may
come to be typical of the altered position of woman, and mark a
stronghold on her way from the much-talked-of slavery and
subjection to a coveted equality.  She used to be shut off from the
wide acres of the farm, and had no voice in the world's politics;
she must stay in the house, and could only hold sway out-of-doors
in this prim corner of land where she was queen.  No wonder that
women clung to their rights in their flower-gardens then, and no
wonder that they have grown a little careless of them now, and that
lawn mowers find so ready a sale!  The whole world is their front
yard nowadays!</p>
<p>     There might be written a history of front yards in New England
which would be very interesting to read.  It would end in a
treatise upon landscape gardening and its possibilities, and wild
flights of imagination about the culture of plants under glass, the
application of artificial heat in forcing, and the curious mingling
and development of plant life; but it would begin in the simple
time of the early colonists.  It must have been hard when, after
being familiar with the gardens and parks of England and Holland,
they found themselves restricted to front yards by way of pleasure-grounds.  Perhaps they thought such things were wrong, and that
having a pleasant place to walk about in out-of-doors would
encourage idle and lawless ways in the young; at any rate, for
several years it was more necessary to raise corn and potatoes to
keep themselves from starving than to lay out alleys and plant
flowers and box borders among the rocks and stumps.  There is a
great pathos in the fact that in so stern and hard a life there was
time or place for any gardens at all.  I can picture to myself the
little slips and cuttings that had been brought over in the ship,
and more carefully guarded than any of the household goods.  I can
see the women look at them tearfully when they came into bloom,
because nothing <pb n="667"/>  else could be a better reminder of their
old home.  What fears there must have been lest the first winter's
cold might kill them, and with what love and care they must have
been tended!  I know a rose-bush, and a little while ago I knew an
apple-tree, that were brought over by the first settlers; the rose
still blooms, and until it was cut down the old tree bore apples.
It is strange to think that civilized New England is no older than
the little red roses that bloom in June on that slope above the
river in Kittery.  Those earliest gardens were very pathetic in the
contrast of their extent and their power of suggestion and
association.  Every seed that came up was thanked for its kindness,
and every flower that bloomed was the child of a beloved ancestry.</p>
<p>     It would be interesting to watch the growth of the gardens as
life became easier and more comfortable in the colonies.  As the
settlements grew into villages and towns, and the Indians were less
dreadful, and the houses were better and more home-like, the busy
people began to find a little time, now and then, when they could
enjoy themselves soberly.  Beside the fruits of the earth they
could have some flowers, and a sprig of sage and southernwood and
tansy, or lavender that had come from Surrey, and could be dried to
be put among the linen, as it used to be strewn through the chests
and cupboards in the old country.</p>
<p>     I like to think of the changes as they came slowly: that after
a while tender plants could be kept through the winter, because the
houses were better built and warmer, and were no longer rough
shelters, which were only meant to serve until there could be
something better.  Perhaps the parlor, or best room, and a special
separate garden for the flowers were two luxuries of the same date,
and they made a noticeable change in the manner of living,&mdash;the
best room being a formal recognition of the claims of society, and
the front yard an appeal for the existence of something that gave
pleasure, beside the merely useful and wholly necessary things of
life.  When it was thought worth while to put a fence around the
flower-garden, the respectability of art itself was established and
made secure.  Whether the house was a fine one and its inclosure
spacious, or whether it was a small house with only a narrow bit of
ground in front, this yard was kept with care, and it was different
from the rest of the land altogether.  The children were not often
allowed to play there, and the family did not use the front door
except upon occasions of more or less ceremony.  I think that many
of the old front yards could tell stories of the lovers who found
it hard to part under the stars, and lingered over the gate; and
who does not remember the solemn group of men who gather there at
funerals, and stand with their heads uncovered as the mourners go
out and come in, two by two!  I have always felt rich in the
possession of an ancient York tradition of an old fellow who
demanded, as he lay dying, that the grass in his front yard should
be cut at once; it was no use to have it trodden down and spoilt by
the folks at the funeral.  I always hoped it was good hay weather;
but he must have been certain of that when he spoke.  Let us hope
he did not confuse this world with the next, being so close upon
the borders of it!  It was not man-like to think of the front yard,
since it was the special domain of the women.  The men of the
family respected but ignored it: they had to be teased in the
spring to dig the flower-beds; but it was the busiest time of the
year,&mdash;one should remember that.</p>
<p>     I think many people are sorry, without knowing why, to see the
fences pulled down; and the disappearance of plain white palings
causes almost as deep regret as that of the handsome ornamental
fences and their high posts with urns or great white balls on top.
<pb n="668"/>  A stone coping does not make up for the loss of them; it
makes a little yard look a good deal like a lot in a cemetery, for
one thing; and then in a small town the grass is not smooth, and
looks uneven where the flower-beds have not been properly smoothed
down.  The stray cows trample about where they never went before;
the bushes and little trees that were once protected grow ragged
and scraggly and out at elbows, and a few forlorn flowers come up
of themselves, and try hard to grow and to bloom.  The ungainly red
tubs that are perched on little posts have plants in them, but the
poor posies look as if they would rather be in the ground, and as
if they are held too near the fire of the sun.  If everything must
be neglected and forlorn, so much the more reason there should be
a fence, if but to hide it.  Americans are too fond of being stared
at; they apparently feel as if it were one's duty to one's
neighbor.  Even if there is nothing really worth looking at about
a house, it is still exposed to the gaze of the passers-by.
Foreigners are far more sensible than we, and the out-of-door home
life among them is something we might well try to copy.  They often
have their meals served out-of-doors, and one can enjoy an
afternoon nap in a hammock, or can take one's work out into the
shady garden with great satisfaction, unwatched; and even a little
piece of ground can be made, if shut in and kept for the use and
pleasure of the family alone, a most charming unroofed and
trellised summer ante-room to the house.  In a large, crowded town
it would be selfish to conceal the rare bits of garden, where the
sight of anything green is a godsend; but where there is the whole
wide country of fields and woods within easy reach, I think there
should be high walls around our gardens, and that we lose a great
deal in not making them entirely separate from the highway,&mdash;as
much as we should lose in making the walls of our parlors and
dining-rooms of glass, and building the house as close to the
street as possible.</p>
<p>     But to go back to the little front yards: we are sorry to miss
them, and their tangle or orderliness of roses and larkspur and
honeysuckle, Canterbury bells and London pride, lilacs and peonies.
These may all bloom better than ever in the new beds that are cut
in the turf; but with the side fences that used to come from the
corners of the house to the front fence, other barriers, as I have
said here over and over, have been taken away, and the old-fashioned village life is already out of date.  People do not know
what they lose when they make way with the reserve, the
separateness, the sanctity, of the front yard of their
grandmothers.  It is like writing down the family secrets for any
one to read; it is like having everybody call you by your first
name, and sitting in any pew in church, and like having your house
in the middle of a road, to take away the fence which, slight as it
may be, is a fortification round your home.  More things than one
may come in without being asked.  We Americans had better build
more fences than take any away from our lives.  There should be
gates for charity to go out and in, and kindness and sympathy, too;
but his life and his house are together each man's stronghold and
castle, to be kept and defended.</p>
<p>     I was much amused, once, at thinking that the fine old solid
paneled doors were being unhinged faster than ever nowadays, since
so many front gates have disappeared, and the click of the latch
can no longer give notice of the approach of a guest.  Now the
knocker sounds or the bell rings without note or warning, and the
village housekeeper cannot see who is coming in until they have
already reached the door.  Once the guests could be seen on their
way up the walk.  It must be a satisfaction to look through the
clear spots of the <pb n="669"/>  figured ground-glass in the new doors,
and I believe, if there is a covering inside, few doors will be
found unprovided with a peep-hole.  It was better to hear the gate
open and shut; and if it caught and dragged, as front gates are
very apt to do, you could have time always for a good look out of
the window at the approaching friend.</p>
<p>     There are few of us who cannot remember a front-yard garden,
which seemed to us a very paradise in childhood.  It was like a
miracle when the yellow and white daffies came into bloom in the
spring; and there was a time when the tiger-lilies and the taller
rose-bushes were taller than we were, and we could not look over
their heads as we do now.  There were always a good many lady's-delights that grew under the bushes, and came up anywhere in the
chinks of the walk or the door-step; and there was a little green
sprig called ambrosia that was a famous stray-away.  Outside the
fence one was not unlikely to see a company of French pinks, which
were forbidden standing-room inside, as if they were tiresome poor
relations of the other flowers.  I always felt a sympathy for
French pinks; they have a fresh, sweet look, as if they resigned
themselves to their lot in life and made the best of it, and
remembered that they had the sunshine and rain, and could see what
was going on in the world, if they were outlaws.</p>
<p>     I like to remember being sent on errands, and being asked to
wait while the mistress of the house picked some flowers to send
back to my mother.  They were almost always prim, flat bouquets in
those days; the larger flowers were picked first, and stood at the
back and looked over the heads of those that were shorter of stem
and stature, and the givers always sent a message that they had not
stopped to arrange them.  I remember that I had even then a great
dislike to lemon verbena, and that I would have waited patiently
outside a gate all the afternoon if I knew that some one would
kindly give me a sprig of lavender in the evening.  And lilies did
not seem to be overdressed, but it was easy for me to believe that
Solomon in all his glory was not arrayed like a great yellow
marigold, or even the dear little single ones that were yellow and
brown, and bloomed until the snow came.</p>
<p>     I wish that I had lived for a little while in those days when
lilacs were a novelty, and it was a great distinction to have some
growing in a front yard.  It always seems as if lilacs and poplars
belonged to the same generation with a certain kind of New English
gentlemen and ladies, who were ascetic and severe in some of their
fashions, while in others they were more given to pleasuring and
mild revelry than either their ancestors or the people who have
lived in their houses since.  Fifty years ago there appears to have
been a last tidal wave of Puritanism, which swept over the country,
and drowned for a time the sober feasting and dancing which before
had been considered no impropriety in the larger villages.  Whist-playing was clung to only by the most worldly citizens, and as for
dancing, it was made a sin in itself and a reproach, as if every
step was taken willfully in seven-leagued boots toward a place
which is to be the final destination of all the wicked.</p>
<p>     A single poplar may have a severe and uncharitable look, but
a row of them suggests the antique and pleasing pomp and ceremony
of their early days, before the sideboard cupboards were used only
to keep the boxes of strings, and nails, and the duster, and the
best decanters were put on a high shelf, while the plain ones were
used for vinegar in the kitchen closet.  There is far less social
visiting from house to house than there used to be.  People in the
smaller towns have more acquaintances who live at a distance than
was the case before the days of railroads, and there <pb n="670"/>  are
more guests who come from out of town to pay visits, which has
something to do with making tea-parties and the entertainment of
one's neighbors less frequent than in former times.  But most of
the New England towns have changed their characters in the last
twenty years, since the manufactories have come in and brought
together large numbers either of foreigners or of a different class
of people from those who used to make the most of the population.
A certain class of families is rapidly becoming extinct.  There
will be found in the older villages very few persons left who
belong to this class, which was once far more important and
powerful.  The oldest churches are apt to be most thinly attended,
simply because a different sort of ideas, even of heavenly things,
attract the newer residents.  I suppose that elderly people have
said, ever since the time of Shem, Ham, and Japhet's wives in the
ark, that society is nothing to what it used to be, and we may
expect to be always told what unworthy successors we are of our
grandmothers.  But the fact remains that a certain element of
American society is fast dying out, giving place to the new; and
with all our glory and pride in modern progress and success, we
cling to the old associations regretfully.  There is nothing to
take the place of the pleasure we have in going to see our old
friends in the parlors which have changed little since our
childhood.  No matter how advanced in years we seem to ourselves,
we are children still to the gracious hostess.  Thank Heaven for
the friends who have always known us!  They may think us unreliable
and young still; they may not understand that we have become busy
and more or less important people to ourselves and to the world,&mdash;
we are pretty sure to be without honor in our own country; but they
will never forget us, and we belong to each other, and always
shall.</p>
<p>     I have received many kindnesses at my friends' hands, but I do
not know that I have ever felt myself to be a more fortunate or
honored guest than when I sometimes went, years ago, to call upon
an elderly friend of my mother, who lived in most pleasant and
stately fashion.  I used to put on my very best manner, and I have
no doubt that my thoughts were well ordered, and my conversation as
proper as I knew how to make it.  I can remember that I used to sit
on a tall ottoman, with nothing to lean against, and my feet were
off soundings, I was so high above the floor.  We used to discuss
the weather, and I said that I went to school (sometimes), or that
it was then vacation, as the case might be, and we tried to make
ourselves agreeable to each other.  Presently my lady would take
her keys out of her pocket, and sometimes a maid would come to
serve me, or else she herself would bring me a silver tray with
some pound-cakes baked in hearts and rounds, and a small glass of
wine; and I proudly felt that I was a guest,&mdash;though I was such a
little thing, an attention was being paid me,&mdash;and a thrill of
satisfaction used to go over me at the thought of my consequence
and importance.  A handful of sugar-plums would have seemed nothing
beside this entertainment.  I used to be careful not to crumble the
cake, and I used to eat it with my gloves on, and a pleasant
fragrance would cling for some time afterward to the ends of the
short Lisle-thread fingers.  I have no doubt that my manners as I
took leave were almost as distinguished as those of my hostess,
though I might have been wild and shy all the rest of the week.  It
was not many years ago that I went to my old friend's funeral, and
saw them carry her down the long, wide walk, between the tall box
borders which were her pride; and all the air was heavy and sweet
with the perfume of the early summer blossoms; the white lilacs and
the flowering currants were still in bloom, and the rows of her
dear <pb n="671"/>  Dutch tulips stood dismayed in their flaunting colors
and watched her go away.</p>
<p>     My sketch of the already out-of-date or fast-vanishing village
fashions perhaps should be ended here, but I cannot resist a wish
to add another bit of autobiography, of which I have been again and
again reminded in writing these pages.  The front yard I knew best
belonged to my grandfather's house.  My grandmother was a proud and
solemn woman, and she hated my mischief, and rightly thought my
elder sister a much better child than I.  I used to be afraid of
her when I was in the house, but I shook off even her authority,
and forgot I was under anybody's rule, when I was out-of-doors.  I
was first cousin to a caterpillar if they called me to come in, and
I was own sister to a giddy-minded bobolink when I ran away across
the fields, as I used to do very often.  But when I was a very
little child indeed my world was bounded by the fences that were
around my home: there were wide green yards, and tall elm-trees to
shade them; there was a long line of barns and sheds, and one of
these had a large room in its upper story, with an old ship's
foresail spread over the floor, and made a capital play-room in wet
weather.  Here fruit was spread in the fall, and there were some
old chests and pieces of furniture that had been discarded; it was
like the garret, only much pleasanter.  The children in the village
now cannot possibly be so happy as I was then.  I used to mount the
fence next the street, and watch the people go in and out of the
quaint-roofed village shops that stood in a row on the other side,
and looked as if they belonged to a Dutch or old English town.
They were burnt down long ago, but they were charmingly
picturesque; the upper stories sometimes projected over the lower,
and the chimneys were sometimes clustered together, and built of
bright red bricks.</p>
<p>     And I was too happy when I could smuggle myself into the front
yard, with its four lilac bushes and its white fences to shut it in
from the rest of the world, beside other railings that went from
 the porch down each side of the brick walk, which was laid in a
pattern, and had H. C., 1818, cut deep into one of the bricks near
the door-step.  The H. C. was for Henry Currier, the mason, who had
signed this choice bit of work as if it were a picture; and he had
been dead so many years that I used to think of his initials as if
the corner brick were a little grave-stone for him.  The knocker
used to be so bright that it shone at you, and caught your eye
bewilderingly, as you came in from the street on a sunshiny day.
There were very few flowers, for my grandmother was old and feeble
when I knew her, and could not take care of them; but I remember
that there were blush roses and white roses and cinnamon roses all
in a tangle in one corner, and I used to pick the crumpled petals
of those to make myself a delicious coddle with ground cinnamon and
damp brown sugar.  In the spring I always found the first green
grass there, for it was warm and sunny, and I used to pick the
little French pinks when they dared show their heads in the
crevices of the flag-stones that were laid around the house.  There
were small shoots of lilac, too, and their leaves were brown and
had a faint, sweet fragrance, and a little later the dandelions
came into bloom; the largest ones I knew grew there, and they have
always been to this day my favorite flowers.</p>
<p>     I had my trials and sorrows in this paradise, however: I lost
a cent there one day, which I have never found yet!  And one
morning there suddenly appeared in one corner a beautiful dark-blue
fleur-de-lis, and I joyfully broke its neck and carried it into the
house; but everybody had seen it, and wondered that I could not
have left it alone.  Besides this, it befell me later to sin more
<pb n="672"/>  gravely still.  My grandmother had kept some plants through
the winter on a three-cornered green stand, built like a flight of
steps, and when the warm spring weather came this was put out-of-doors.  She had a cherished tea-rose bush, and what should I find
but a bud on it!  It was opened just enough to give a hint of its
color.  I was very pleased.  I snapped it off at once, for I had
heard so many times that it was hard to make roses bloom; and I ran
in through the hall and up the stairs, where I met my grandmother
on the square landing.  She sat down in the window-seat, and I
showed her proudly what was crumpled in my warm little fist.  I can
see it now!&mdash;it had no stem at all, and for many days afterward I
was bowed down with a sense of my guilt and shame, for I was made
to understand it was an awful thing to have blighted and broken a
treasured flower like that.</p>
<p>     It must have been the very next winter that my grandmother
died.  She had a long illness, which I do not remember much about;
but the night she died might have been yesterday night, it is all
so fresh and clear in my mind.  I did not live with her in the old
house then, but in a new house close by, across the yard.  All the
family were at the great house, and I could see that lights were
carried hurriedly from one room to another.  A servant came to
fetch me, but I would not go with her.  My grandmother was dying,
whatever that might be, and she was taking leave of every one,&mdash;she
was ceremonious even then.  I did not dare to go with the rest; I
had an intense curiosity to see what dying might be like, but I was
afraid to be there with her, and I was afraid to stay at home
alone.  I was only five years old.  It was in December, and the
house seemed to grow darker and darker, until I went out at last to
sit on a door-step and cry softly to myself; while I was there some
one came to another door next the street, and rang the bell loudly
again and again.  I suppose I was afraid to answer the summons,&mdash;
indeed, I do not know that I thought of it; all the world had been
still before, and the bell sounded loud and awful through the empty
house.  It seemed as if the messenger from an unknown world had
come to the wrong house to call my poor grandmother away; and that
loud ringing is curiously linked in my mind with the knocking at
the gate in Macbeth.  I never can think of one without the other,
though there was no fierce Lady Macbeth to bid me not be lost so
poorly in my thoughts; for when they all came back, awed and
tearful, and found me waiting in the cold, alone, and afraid more
of this world than the next, they were very good to me.  But as for
the funeral, it gave me vast entertainment; it was the first grand
public occasion in which I had taken any share.</p>

                                       <signed><hi rend="italic">Sarah Orne Jewett</hi></signed>


</div1>
</body>
</text>
</TEI.2>
