<?xml version="1.0"?>

<?dlps id="JewPass"?>
<?dlps page-images="none" figure-images="no"?>
<?dlps transcription="other"?>

<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/tei-p4/tei2.dtd" [
<!ENTITY % POSTKB "INCLUDE">
<!ENTITY % TEI.extensions.ent SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.ent">
<!ENTITY % TEI.extensions.dtd SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.dtd">
<!ENTITY % ISOnum SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/charent/iso-num.ent"> %ISOnum;
<!ENTITY % ISOpub SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/charent/iso-pub.ent"> %ISOpub;

]>
<TEI.2 id="JewPass">
<teiHeader type="migrated" creator="Etext">
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title type="main">The Passing of Sister Barsett</title>
<title type="sort">passing of sister barsett</title>
<author>Jewett, Sarah Orne</author>
<respStmt>
<resp>Creation of machine-readable version:</resp>
<name>Judy Boss</name>
<resp>Creation of digital images:</resp>
<name/>
<resp>Conversion to TEI.2-conformant markup:</resp>
<name>University of Virginia Library Electronic Text Center.</name>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt>
<extent>ca. <num type="kilobytes">28</num> kilobytes</extent>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>University of Virginia Library</publisher>
<pubPlace>Charlottesville, Virginia</pubPlace>
<idno type="ETC">JewPass</idno>
<date value="1996">1996</date>
<availability status="public">
<p n="copyright">Copyright &copy; 1996 by the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia</p>
<p n="access">Publicly accessible</p>
</availability>
<idno type="uva-pid">uva-lib:476117</idno>
</publicationStmt>
<seriesStmt>
<title>University of Virginia Library, Text collection</title>
<idno type="uva-set">UVA-LIB-Text</idno>
</seriesStmt>
<sourceDesc>
<biblFull>
<titleStmt>
<title type="main">The Passing of Sister Barsett</title>
<title level="j">Cosmopolitan Magazine, V 13, No. 1</title>
<title type="sort">passing of sister barsett</title>
<author>Sarah Orne Jewett</author>
</titleStmt>
<editionStmt>
<p>1st Edition</p>
</editionStmt>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>Cosmopolitan Publishing Co., Schlicht &amp; Field</publisher>
<pubPlace>Rochester, New York</pubPlace>
<date value="1892-05">May, 1892</date>
<idno type="callNo">Print copy consulted:</idno>
</publicationStmt>
<seriesStmt>
<p>cosmopolitan Magazine</p>
</seriesStmt>
<notesStmt>
<note>
<p>UVA Alderman Library Microform Reel #664</p>
</note>
</notesStmt>
</biblFull>
</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc>
<encodingDesc>
<projectDesc>
<p>Prepared for the University of Virginia Library Electronic Text Center.</p>
</projectDesc>
<editorialDecl>
<p>All quotation marks retained as data.</p>
<p>All unambiguous end-of-line hyphens have been removed, and the trailing part of a word has been joined to the preceding line.</p>
<p>Keywords in the header are a local Electronic Text Center scheme to aid in establishing analytical groupings.</p>
</editorialDecl>
</encodingDesc>
<profileDesc>
<creation>
<date value="1893-05">May 1893</date>
</creation>
<langUsage>
<language id="eng" usage="main">English</language>
</langUsage>
<textClass>
<keywords>
<term>fiction; prose</term>
<term>Women Writers</term>
</keywords>
</textClass>
</profileDesc>
<revisionDesc>
<change>
<date value="1996-10">October 1996</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>corrector</resp>
<name>Tom Lukas</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Added tei tagging.</item>
</change>
<change>
<date value="2005-07">July 2005</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>Corrector</resp>
<name>John Ivor Carlson</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Converted to XML and/or checked tags.</item>
</change>
<change>
<date value="2007-09">September 2007</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>Migration</resp>
<name>Ethan Gruber, University of Virginia Library</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Converted XML markup from TEI Lite to uva-dl-tei (TEI P4 with local customizations).</item>
</change>
<change>
<date value="2008-01">January 2008</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>Migration</resp>
<name>Greg Murray, University of Virginia Library</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Programmatically updated TEI header markup (but not header content) for minimal compliance with current QA requirements.</item>
</change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text id="d1">
<body id="d2">

<div1 type="story" id="d3">
	<pb n="59"/>
	<head>THE PASSING OF SISTER BARSETT.<lb/>
		BY SARAH ORNE JEWETT.</head>

<p>MRS. MERCY CRANE was of such firm persuasion that a house is
meant to be lived in, that during many years she was never known
to leave her own neat two-storied dwelling place on the Ridge road.
Yet she was very fond of company, and in pleasant weather often
sat in the side doorway looking out on her green yard, where the
grass grew short and thick and was undisfigured even by a path
toward the steps.  All her faded green blinds were securely tied
together and knotted on the inside by pieces of white tape; but now
and then, when the sun was not too hot for her carpets, she opened
one window at a time for a few hours, having pronounced views
upon the necessity of light and air.  Although Mrs. Crane was
acknowledged by her best friends to be a peculiar person and very
set in her ways, she was much respected, and one acquaintance vied
with another in making up for her melancholy seclusion by bringing
her all the news they could gather.  She had been left alone many
years before by the sudden death of her husband from sunstroke,
and though she was by no means poor, she had, as someone said,
"such a pretty way of taking a little present that you couldn't help
being pleased when you gave her anything."
</p><p>For a lover of society, such a life must have had its difficulties
at times, except that the Ridge road was more travelled than any
other in the township, and Mrs. Crane had invented a system of
signals to which she always resorted in case of wishing to speak to
some one of her neighbors.
</p><p>The afternoon was wearing late one day toward the end of
summer, and Mercy Crane sat in her doorway dressed in a favorite
old-fashioned light calico and a small shoulder shawl figured with
large palm leaves.  She was making some tatting of a somewhat
intricate pattern; she believed it to be the prettiest and most durable
of trimmings, and having decorated her own wardrobe in the course
of unlimited leisure, she was now making a few yards apiece for
each of her more intimate friends, so that they might have
something to remember her by.  She kept glancing up the road as if
she expected some one, but the time went slowly by, until at last a
woman appeared to view, walking fast and carrying a large bundle
in a checked handkerchief.
</p><p>Then Mercy Crane worked steadily for a short time without
looking up, until the desired friend was crossing the grass between
the dusty road and the steps.  The visitor was out of breath and did
not respond to the polite greeting of her hostess until she had
recovered herself to her satisfaction.  Mrs. Crane made her the kind
offer of a glass of water or a few peppermints, but was answered
only by a shake of the head, so she resumed her work for a time
until the silence should be broken.
</p><p>"I have come from the house of mourning," said Sarah Ellen
Dow at last, unexpectedly.
</p><p>"You don't tell me that Sister Barsett&mdash;"
</p><p>"She's left us this time, she's really gone," and the excited
newsbringer burst into tears.  The poor soul was completely
overwrought; she looked tired and wan, as if she had spent her
forces in sympathy as well as hard work.  She felt in her great
bundle for a pocket handkerchief, but was not successful in the
search, and finally produced a faded gingham apron with long,
narrow strings, with which she hastily dried her tears.  The sad news
appealed also to Mercy Crane, who looked across to her apple trees
and could not see them for a dazzle of tears in her own eyes.  The
spectacle of Sarah Ellen Dow going home with her humble work-a-day possessions, from the house where she had gone in haste only a
few days before, to care for a sick person well known to them both,
was a very sad sight.
</p><p>"You sent word yesterday that you should be returnin' early
this afternoon, and would stop.  I presume I received the <pb n="60"/>
message as you gave it?" asked Mrs. Crane, who was tenacious in
such matters; "but I do declare I never looked to hear she was
gone."
</p><p>"She's been failin' right along sence yisterday about this time,"
said the nurse.  "She's taken no notice to speak of, and been eatin'
the vally o' nothin' I may say, since I went there a-Tuesday.  Her
sisters both come back yisterday, an', of course, I was expected to
give up charge to them.  They're used to sickness, an' both havin'
such a name for bein' great housekeepers!"
</p><p>Sarah Ellen spoke with bitterness, but Mrs. Crane was
reminded instantly of her own affairs.  "I feel condemned that I ain't
begun my own fall cleanin' yet," she said, with an ostentatious sigh.
</p><p>"Plenty o' time to worry about that," her friend hastened to
console her.
</p><p>"I do desire to have everything decent about my house,"
resumed Mrs. Crane.  "There's nobody to do anything but me.  If I
was to be taken away sudden myself, I shouldn't want to have it said
afterwards that there was wisps under my sofy or&mdash;there!  I can't
dwell on my own troubles with Sister Barsett's loss right before me.
I can't seem to believe she's really passed away; she always was
saying she should go in some o' these spells, but I deemed her to be
troubled with narves."
</p><p>Sarah Ellen Dow shook her head.  "I'm all nerved up myself,"
she said brokenly.  "I made light of her sickness when I went there
first, I'd seen her what she called dreadful low so many times; but I
saw her looks this morning and I begun to believe her at last.  Them
sisters o' hers is the master for unfeelin' hearts.  Sister Barsett was a-layin' there yesterday, an' one of 'em was a settin' right by her tellin'
how difficult 'twas fer her to leave home, her niece was goin' to
graduate to the high school, an' they was goin' to have a time in the
evening and all the exercises promised to be extry interesting.  Poor
Sister Barsett knew what she said an' looked at her with contempt,
and then she give a glance at me and closed up her eyes as if 'twas
for the last time.  I know she felt it."
</p><p>Sarah Ellen Dow was more and more excited by a sense of
bitter grievance.  Her rule of the afflicted household had evidently
been interfered with; she was not accustomed to be ignored and set
aside at such times.  Her simple nature and [illustration omitted]
uncommon ability found satisfaction in the exercise of authority,
but she had now left her post feeling hurt and wronged, besides
knowing something of the pain of honest affliction.
</p><p>"If it hadn't been for esteemin' Sister Barsett as I always have
done, I should have told 'em no, an' held to it, when they asked me
to come back an' watch tonight.  'Tain't for none o' their sakes, but
Sister Barsett was a good friend to me in her <pb n="61"/>  way."  Sarah
Ellen broke down once more and felt in her bundle again hastily,
but the handkerchief was again elusive, while a small object fell out
upon the doorstep with a bounce.
</p><p>"'Tain't nothin' but a little taste-cake I spared out o' the loaf I
baked this mornin'," she explained with a blush.  "I was so shoved
out that I seemed to want to turn my hand to somethin' useful an'
feel I was still doin' for Sister Barsett.  Try a little piece, won't you,
Mis' Crane?  I thought it seemed light an' good."
</p><p>They shared the taste-cake with serious enjoyment, and
pronounced it very good indeed when they had finished and shaken
the crumbs out of their laps.  "There's nobody but you shall come
an' do for me at the last if I can have my way about things," said
Mercy Crane impulsively.  She meant it for a tribute to Miss Dow's
character and general ability, and as such it was meekly accepted.
</p><p>"You're a younger person than I be, an' less wore," said Sarah
Ellen, but she felt better now that she had rested, and her
conversational powers seemed to be refreshed by her share of the
little cake.  "Doctor Bangs has behaved real pretty, I can say that,"
she continued presently in a mournful tone.
</p><p>"Heretofore, in the sickness of Sister Barsett, I have always
felt to hope certain that she would survive; she's recovered from a
sight o' things in her day.  She has been the first to have all the new
diseases that's visited this region.  I know she had the spinal
mergeetis months before there was any other case about," observed
Mrs. Crane with satisfaction.
</p><p>"An' the new throat troubles, all of 'em," agreed Sarah Ellen,
"an' has made trial of all the best patent medicines, and could tell
you their merits as no one else could in this vicinity.  She never was
one that depended on herbs alone, though she considered 'em
extremely useful in some cases.  Everybody has their herb, as we
know, but I'm free to say that Sister Barsett sometimes done
everything she could to kill herself with such rovin' ways o' dosin'.
She must see it now she's gone an' can't stuff down no more
invigorators."  Sarah Ellen Dow burst out suddenly with this as if
she could no longer contain her honest opinion.  "Sister Barsett
never knowed no other way to make herself o' consequence in this
community except with her ailments, an' when one thing would
cease to draw attention she'd 'tend right to workin' up the particulars
of another.  I may seem to you unfeelin', but now she's gone I see
that side o' her character in its true light."
</p><p>"There, there! you're all worked up," answered placid Mercy
Crane, looking more interested than ever.
</p><p>"An' she was dreadful handy to talk religion to other folks, but
I've come to a realizin' sense that religion is somethin' besides
opinions.  She an' Elder French has been mostly o' one mind, but I
don't know's they've got hold of all the religion there is."
</p><p>"Why, why, Sarah Ellen!" exclaimed Mrs. Crane, but there
was still something in her tone that urged the speaker to further
expression of her feelings.  The good creature was much excited,
her face was clouded with disapproval.
</p><p>"I ain't forgettin' nothin' about their good points either," she
went on in a more subdued tone, and suddenly stopped.
</p><p>"Preachin'll be done away with soon or late; preachin' o' Elder
French's kind," announced Mercy Crane after waiting to see if her
guest did not mean to say anything more.  "I should like to read 'em
out that verse another fashion: 'Be ye doers o' the word, not
preachers only,' would hit it about right; but there, it's easy for all of
us to talk.  In my early days I used to like to get out to meetin'
regular, because sure as I didn't I had bad luck all the week.  I didn't
feel pacified 'less I'd been half a day, but I was out all day the
Sabbath before Mr. Barlow died as he did.  So you mean to say that
Sister Barsett's really gone?"
</p><p>Mrs. Crane's tone changed to one of real concern, and her
manner indicated that she had put the preceding conversation
behind her with decision.
</p><p>"She was herself to the last," instantly responded Miss Down.
"I see her put out a thumb an' finger from under the spread an' pinch
up a fold of her sister Deckett's dress, to try an' see if 'twas all wool.
I thought 'twan't all wool myself, an' I know it now by the way she
looked.  She was a very knowin' person about materials; we shall
miss poor Mis' Barsett in many ways, she was always the one to
consult with about matters o' dress." <pb n="62"/>
</p><p>"She passed away easy at the last, I hope?" asked Mrs. Crane
with interest.
</p><p>"Why, I wan't there, if you'll believe it!" exclaimed Sarah
Ellen, flushing and looking at her friend for sympathy.  "Sister
Barsett revived up the first o' the afternoon and they sent for Elder
French.  She took notice of him and he exhorted quite a spell and
then he spoke o' there being need of air in the room, Mis' Deckett
havin' closed every window, an' she asked me of all folks if I hadn't
better step out; but Elder French come too, an' he was very
reasonable an' had a word with me about Mis' Deckett and Mis'
Peak an' the way they was workin' things.  I told him right out how
they never come near when the rest of us was havin' it so hard with
her along in the spring, but now they thought she was re'lly goin' to
die they come settlin' down like a pair o' old crows in a field to pick
for what they could get.  I just made up my mind they should have
all the care if they wanted it; it didn't seem as if there was anything
more I could do for Sister Barsett, an' I set there in the kitchen
within call an' waited, an' when I heard 'em sayin', 'There, she's
gone, she's gone!' and Mis' Deckett a-weepin', I put on my bunnit
and stepped myself out into the road.  I felt to repent after I had
gone but a rod, but I was so worked up, an' I thought they'd call me
back an' then I was put out because they didn't, and so here I be.  I
can't help it now."  Sarah Ellen was crying again; she and Mrs.
Crane could not look at each other.
</p><p>"Well, you set an' rest," said Mrs. Crane kindly and with the
merest shadow of disapproval.  "You set an' rest an' by an' by if
you'd feel better you could go back an' just make a little stop an'
inquire about the arrangements.  I wouldn't harbor no feelin's if they
be inconsiderate folks.  Sister Barsett has often deplored their
actions in my hearing an' wished she had sisters like other folks.
With all her faults she was a useful person an' a good neighbor,"
mourned Mercy Crane sincerely.  "She was one that always had
somethin' interestin' to tell, an' if it wan't for her dyin' spells an' all
that sort o' nonsense she'd make a figger in the world, she would so.
She walked with an air always, Mis' Barsett did; you'd asked who
she was if you hadn't known, as she passed you by.  How quick we
forget the outs about anybody that's gone, but I always feel grateful
to anybody that's friendly, situated as I be.  I shall miss her, runnin'
over.  I can seem to see her now coming over the rise in the road.
But don't you get in a way of takin' things too hard, Sarah Ellen!
You've worked yourself all to pieces since I saw you last; you're
gettin' to be as lean as a meetin' house fly.  Now you're comin' in to
have a cup o' tea with me an' then you'll feel better.  I've got some
new molasses gingerbread that I baked this mornin'."
</p><p>"I do feel beat out, Mis' Crane," acknowledged the poor little
soul, glad of a chance to speak, but touched by this unexpected
mark of consideration.  "If I could ha' done as I wanted to I should
be feelin' well enough, but to be set aside an' ordered about, where
I'd taken the lead in sickness so much, an' knew how to deal with
Sister Barsett so well!  She might be livin' now perhaps&mdash;"
</p><p>"Come, we'd better go in, 'tis gettin' damp," and the mistress of
the house rose so hurriedly as to seem bustling.  "Don't dwell on
Sister Barsett and her foolish folks no more; I wouldn't if I was
you."
</p><p>They went into the front room, which was dim with the
twilight of the half-closed blinds and two great syringa bushes that
grew against them.  Sarah Ellen put down her bundle and bestowed
herself in the large, cane-seated rocking chair.  Mrs. Crane directed
her to stay there awhile and rest, and then come out into the kitchen
when she got ready.
</p><p>A cheerful clatter of dishes was heard at once upon Mrs.
Crane's disappearance.  "I hope she's goin' to make one o' her nice
shortcakes, but I don't know's she'll think it quite worth while,"
thought the guest humbly.  She desired to go out into the kitchen,
but it was proper behavior to wait until she should be called.  Mercy
Crane was not a person with whom one could venture to take
liberties.  Presently Sarah Ellen began to feel better.  She did not
often find such a quiet place or the quarter of an hour of idleness in
which to enjoy it, and was glad to make the most of this
opportunity.  Just now she felt tired and lonely.  She was a busy,
unselfish, eager-minded creature by nature, but <pb n="63"/>  now, while
grief was sometimes uppermost in her mind and sometimes a sense
of wrong, every moment found her more peaceful, and the great
excitement little by little faded away.
</p><p>"What a person poor Sister Barsett was to dread growing old
so she couldn't get about.  I'm sure I shall miss her as much as
anybody," said Mrs. Crane, suddenly opening the kitchen door and
letting in an unmistakable and delicious odor of shortcake that
revived still more the drooping spirits of her guest.  "An' a good deal
of knowledge has died with her," she added, coming into the dark
room and seeming to make it lighter.
</p><p>"There, she knew a good deal, but she didn't know all,
especially o' doctorin'," insisted Sarah Ellen from the rocking chair,
with an unexpected little laugh.  "She used to lay down the law to
me as if I had neither sense nor experience, but when it came to her
bad spells she'd always send for me.  It takes everybody to know
everything, but Sister Barsett was of an opinion that her information
was sufficient for the town.  She was tellin' me the day I went there
how she disliked to have old Mis' Doubleday come and visit with
her, an' remarked that she called Mis' Doubleday very officious.
'Went right down on her knees an' prayed,' says she.  Anybody
would have thought I was a heathen!'  But I kind of pacified her
feelin's, an' told her I supposed the old lady meant well."
</p><p>"Did she give away any of her things?  Mis' Barsett, I mean,"
inquired Mrs. Crane.
</p><p>"Not in my hearin'," replied Sarah Ellen Dow.  "Except one
day, the first of the week, she told her oldest sister, Mis' Deckett&mdash;'twas that first day she rode over&mdash;that she might have her green
quilted petticoat; you see, 'twas a rainy day an' Mis' Deckett had
complained o' feelin' thin.  She went right up an' got it and put it on
an' wore it off, an' I'm [illustration omitted] sure I thought no more
about it until I heard Sister Barsett groanin' dreadful in the night.  I
got right up to see what the matter was, an' what do you think but
she was wantin' that petticoat back, and not thinking any too well o'
Nancy Deckett for takin' it when 'twas offered.  'Nancy never
showed no sense o' propriety,' says Sister Barsett; I just wish you'd
heard her go on!"
</p><p>"If she had felt to remember me," continued Sarah Ellen, after
they had laughed a little, "I'd full as soon have some of her nice
crockery ware.  She told me once, years ago, when I was stopping to
tea with her and we were havin' it real friendly, that she should
leave me her Britannia teaset, but I ain't got it in writin' and I can't
say she's ever referred to the matter since.  It ain't as if I had a home
o' my own to keep it in, but I should have thought a great deal of it
for her sake," and the speaker's voice faltered.  "I must say that with
all her virtues she never was a first-class housekeeper, but I
wouldn't say it to any but a friend.  You never eat no preserves o'
hers that wa'n't <pb n="64"/>  commencin' to work, and you know as well
as I how little forethought she had about putting away her woollens.
I sat behind her once in meetin' when I was stoppin' with the
Tremletts and so occupied a seat in their pew, an' I see between ten
an' a dozen moth millers come workin' out o' her fitch-fur tippet.
They was flutterin' round her bonnet same's 'twas a lamp.  I should
be mortified to death to have such a thing happen to me."
</p><p>"Every housekeeper has her weak point; I've got mine as much
as anybody else," acknowledged Mercy Crane with spirit, "but you
never see no moth millers come workin' out o' me in a public
place."
</p><p>"Ain't your oven beginning to get overhet?" anxiously inquired
Sarah Ellen Dow, who was sitting more in the draught and could not
bear to have any accident happen to the supper.  Mrs. Crane flew to
a shortcake's rescue, and presently called her guest to the table.
</p><p>The two women sat down to deep and brimming cups of tea.
</p><p>Sarah Ellen noticed with great gratification that her hostess
had put on two of the best teacups and some citron-melon preserves.
It was not an every-day tea.  She was used to hard fare, poor, hard-working Sarah Ellen, and this handsome social attention did her
good.  Sister Crane rarely entertained a friend, and it would be a
pleasure to speak of this tea-drinking for weeks to come.
</p><p>"You've put yourself out quite a consid'able for me," she
acknowledged.  "How pretty these cups is! you oughtn't to use 'em
so common or for me.  I wish I had a home I could really call my
own to ask you to, but 'tain't never been so I could.  Sometimes I
wonder what's goin' to become o' me when I get so I'm past work.
Takin' care o' sick folks and bein' in houses where there's a sight
goin' on and everybody in a hurry kind of wears on me now I'm
most a-gittin' in years.  I was wishin' the other day that I could get
with some comfortable kind of a sick person where I could live
right along quiet as other folks do, but folks never sends for me 'less
they're drove to it.  I ain't laid up anything to really depend upon."
</p><p>The situation appealed to Mercy Crane, well to do as she was
and not burdened with responsibilities.  She stirred uneasily in her
chair but could not bring herself to the point of offering Sarah Ellen
the home she coveted.
</p><p>"Have some hot tea?" she insisted in a matter of fact tone, and
Sarah Ellen's face, which had been lighted by a sudden eager
hopefulness, grew dull and narrow again.
</p><p>"Plenty, plenty, Mis' Crane," she said sadly, "'tis beautiful tea&mdash;you always have good tea," but she could not turn her thoughts from
her own uncertain future.  "None of our folks has ever lived to be a
burden," she said presently in a pathetic tone, putting down her cup.
"My mother was thought to be doing well until four o'clock and was
dead at ten.  My Aunt Nancy come to our house well at twelve
o'clock and died that afternoon; my father was sick but ten days.
There was dear sister Betsey, she did go in consumption, but 'twan't
an expensive sickness."
</p><p>"I've thought sometimes about you, how you'd get past rovin'
from house to house one o' these days.  I guess your friends will
stand by you."  Mrs. Crane spoke with unwonted sympathy, and
Sarah Ellen's heart leaped with joy.
</p><p>"You're real kind," she said simply.  "There's nobody I set so
much by.  But I shall miss Sister Barsett, when all's said an' done.
She's asked me many a time to stop with her when I wasn't doin'
nothin'.  We all have our failin's, but she was a friendly creatur'.  I
sha'n't want to see her laid away."
</p><p>"Yes, I was thinkin' a few minutes ago that I shouldn't want to
look out an' see the funeral go by.  She's one o' the old neighbors.  I
s'pose I shall have to look, or I shouldn't feel right afterward," said
Mrs. Crane mournfully.  "If I hadn't got so kind of housebound," she
added with touching frankness, "I'd just as soon go over with you
an' offer to watch this night."
</p><p>"'Twould astonish Sister Barsett so I don't know but she'd
return."  Sarah Ellen's eyes danced with amusement; she could not
resist her own joke, and Mercy Crane herself had to smile.
</p><p>"Now I must be goin' or 'twill be dark," said the guest, rising
and sighing after she had eaten her last crumb of gingerbread.  "Yes,
thank ye, you're real good, I will come back if I find I ain't wanted.
Look what a pretty sky there <pb n="65"/>  is!" and the two friends went to
the side door and stood together in a moment of affectionate
silence, looking out toward the sunset across the wide fields.  The
country was still with that deep rural stillness which seems to mean
the absence of humanity.  Only the thrushes were singing far away
in the walnut woods beyond the orchard, and some crows were
flying over and cawed once loudly, as if they were speaking to the
women at the door.
</p><p>Just as the friends were parting, after most grateful
acknowledgments from Sarah Ellen Dow, someone came driving
along the road in a hurry and stopped.
</p><p>"Who's that with you, Mis' Crane?" called one of their near
neighbors.
</p><p>"It's Sarah Ellen Dow," answered Mrs. Crane.  "What's the
matter?"
</p><p>"I thought so, but I couldn't rightly see.  Come, they are in a
peck o' trouble up to Sister Barsett's, wonderin' where you be,"
grumbled the man.  "They can't do nothin' with her; she's drove off
everybody an' keeps a screechin' for you.  Come, step along, Sarah
Ellen, do!"
</p><p>"Sister Barsett!" exclaimed both the women.  Mercy Crane
sank down upon the doorstep, but Sarah Ellen stepped out upon the
grass all of a tremble, and went toward the wagon.  "They said this
afternoon that Sister Barsett was gone," she managed to say.  "What
did they mean?"
</p><p>"Gone where?" asked the impatient neighbor.  "I expect 'twas
one of her spells.  She's come to; they say she wants somethin'
hearty for her tea.  Nobody can't take one step till you get there
neither."
</p><p>Sarah Ellen was still dazed; she returned to the doorway where
Mercy Crane sat shaking with laughter.  "I don't know but we might
as well laugh as cry," she said in an aimless sort of way.  "I know
you too well to think you're going to repeat a single word.  Well, I'll
get my bonnet an' start; I expect I've got considerable to cope with,
but I'm well rested.  Good night, Mis' Crane, I certain did have a
beautiful tea whatever the future may have in store."
</p><p>She wore a solemn expression as she mounted into the wagon
in haste and departed, but she was far out of sight when Mercy
Crane stopped laughing and went into the house.
<lb/>
[illustration omitted]</p>

</div1>
</body>
</text>
</TEI.2>
