<?xml version="1.0"?>

<?dlps id="JohCoun"?>
<?dlps page-images="none" figure-images="no"?>
<?dlps transcription="other"?>

<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/tei-p4/tei2.dtd" [
<!ENTITY % POSTKB "INCLUDE">
<!ENTITY % TEI.extensions.ent SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.ent">
<!ENTITY % TEI.extensions.dtd SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.dtd">
<!ENTITY % ISOnum SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/charent/iso-num.ent"> %ISOnum;
<!ENTITY % ISOlat1 SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/charent/iso-lat1.ent"> %ISOlat1;
<!ENTITY % ISOpub SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/charent/iso-pub.ent"> %ISOpub;

]>

<TEI.2 id="JohCoun">
<teiHeader type="migrated" creator="Etext">
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title type="main">Count Tolstoy at Home</title>
<title type="sort">count tolstoy at home</title>
<author>Johnston, Charles</author>
<respStmt>
<resp>Creation of machine-readable version:</resp>
<name>Judy Boss</name>
<resp>Conversion to TEI.2-conformant markup:</resp>
<name>University of Virginia Library Electronic Text Center.</name>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt>
<extent>ca. <num type="kilobytes">26</num> kilobytes</extent>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>University of Virginia Library</publisher>
<pubPlace>Charlottesville, Virginia</pubPlace>
<idno type="ETC">JohCoun</idno>
<date value="1996">1996</date>
<availability status="public">
<p n="copyright">Copyright &copy; 1996 by the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia</p>
<p n="access">Publicly accessible</p>
</availability>
<idno type="uva-pid">uva-lib:476124</idno>
</publicationStmt>
<seriesStmt>
<title>University of Virginia Library, Text collection</title>
<idno type="uva-set">UVA-LIB-Text</idno>
</seriesStmt>
<sourceDesc>
<biblFull>
<titleStmt>
<title type="main">Count Tolstoy at Home</title>
<title level="j">The Arena</title>
<title type="sort">count tolstoy at home</title>
<author>Charles Johnston</author>
</titleStmt>
<extent>pp. 480-490</extent>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>Arena Publishing Company</publisher>
<pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
<date value="1898">1898</date>
<idno type="callNo">Print copy consulted: print source not available.</idno>
</publicationStmt>
<notesStmt>
<note>
<p>The Arena, Vol. 20, October, 1898.</p>
</note>
</notesStmt>
</biblFull>
</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc>
<encodingDesc>
<projectDesc>
<p>Prepared for the University of Virginia Library Electronic Text Center.</p>
</projectDesc>
<editorialDecl>
<p>All quotation marks retained as data.</p>
<p>All unambiguous end-of-line hyphens have been removed, and the trailing part of a word has been joined to the preceding line.</p>
<p>Keywords in the header are a local Electronic Text Center scheme to aid in establishing analytical groupings.</p>
</editorialDecl>
</encodingDesc>
<profileDesc>
<creation>
<date value="1898">1898</date>
</creation>
<langUsage>
<language id="eng" usage="main">English</language>
</langUsage>
<textClass>
<keywords>
<term>nonfiction; prose</term>
</keywords>
</textClass>
</profileDesc>
<revisionDesc>
<change>
<date value="1996-11">November 1996</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>corrector</resp>
<name>Stephen Ramsay, Electronic Text Center</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Added TEI header and tags.</item>
</change>
<change>
<date value="2005-07">July 2005</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>Corrector</resp>
<name>John Ivor Carlson</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Converted to XML and/or checked tags.</item>
</change>
<change>
<date value="2007-09">September 2007</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>Migration</resp>
<name>Ethan Gruber, University of Virginia Library</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Converted XML markup from TEI Lite to uva-dl-tei (TEI P4 with local customizations).</item>
</change>
<change>
<date value="2008-01">January 2008</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>Migration</resp>
<name>Greg Murray, University of Virginia Library</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Programmatically updated TEI header markup (but not header content) for minimal compliance with current QA requirements.</item>
</change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>
<text id="d1">



<body id="d2">

<div1 type="essay" id="d3"><pb n="480"/>
<head>COUNT TOLSTOY AT HOME.<lb/>
BY CHARLES JOHNSTON.</head>

<p>WHILE I was reading "What is Art?" it occurred to me that it would
be a very interesting thing if one could get a sense of Tolstoy's
personality, and his surroundings,&mdash;something comparable in
vividness and truth to the innumerable portraits in his own books.
The study of a work so sincere, so full of power, so overburdened
even with moral earnestness, and representing, as its author says,
the work and the best thought of fifteen years, brings with it an
almost irresistible curiosity to look through the page to the man
behind it.
</p><p>And then with all its merits, with all its force, the book has
great faults and shortcomings, and one feels that, with a closer
knowledge of the author's character, it might be much easier to
understand these and make allowance for them.  For instance, one is
sensible, all through the book, of a great lack of urbanity, a
tendency to impatience, almost an inveterate habit of scolding; is
there any outward and visible cause for this acerbity? or can we
trace it back to anything in the author's life?  And again, the
almost morbid and prudish attitude towards the human body, that
comes out again and again in Tolstoy's strictures on modern art;
one is tempted to think he believes the Elohim, having made man,
made haste to create fig-trees; or to imagine Tolstoy coming
unawares to the gateway of Eden, and then, greatly scandalized,
hastening to lay a complaint before the park-keeper.  And, once
more, his very strange and almost inexplicable hostility towards
all things Hellenic, so that in one place he seriously describes
the Greeks as a "slave-owning, half-barbarous little nation, with
a trick of depicting the human body, and who had put up some pretty
buildings"&mdash;one does not speak of Phidias and the Parthenon like
that, unless one's feeling's are very strongly
<pb n="481"/>
involved; how
did this come about, and what are the outward traces of it?  Can
one find the reason by a closer acquaintance with this very
dogmatic prophet?
</p><p>It happened that one of Tolstoy's pronouncements, whether on
the dissenting sects, or the likelihood of famine, or whatever it
may have been, had brought him into unusual prominence in his
native land, where they regard him with a queer mixture of
admiration and dislike; and a number of visitors had found their
way to Yasnaya Polnaya, to talk to him about the universe.  Several
of them put on record the details of their visits, and published
them.  And three of these records found their way to me.
</p><p>Now there is nothing of very remarkable interest in anything
that was said at any of these interviews, as there seems to have
been nothing very striking about the personalities of the visitors;
yet it seems to me that they have managed to get Tolstoi's
likeness, with a quite unexpected fidelity, and the fact that there
are three points of view for the three observers gives the picture
a stereoscopic relief and completeness.  They give discordant
accounts, which nevertheless make a harmonious unity, something in
the fashion of "The Ring and the Book."
</p><p>The first visitor was a little Russian journalist, who was
very familiar, and at the same time very much afraid.  He has not
described himself, but he has let himself ooze out between the
lines, so to speak, in describing Tolstoy, and one can form a very
accurate picture of his outward and inward man.  He is the sort of
person who would wear a rather faded frock coat with a low hat and
thick boots, and be very respectful to the footman, and make great
play with his hat.  Well, let us introduce him to the Count, whom,
by the way, he calls by his first name.
</p><p>"Lyef Nicolai&euml;vitch," he says, "turned towards the sofa
and sat down in an armchair between the sofa and the table.  Alas!
in such a place, I had not the right to give myself wholly up to
observing the great writer who had placed himself so near me.  From
under gray, shaggy brows, those gifted
<pb n="482"/>
all-observing eyes,
brown, alert, gleaming, gazed at me steadily; every feature had
long been familiar to me from portraits; every curl of his bushy
beard, the locks growing scant on his gifted brow, and most of all,
those powerful eyes of his, which no portrait can render.
</p><p>"And looking so closely, not at the great writer's portrait,
but at himself, I became acutely conscious that I could find no
justification either for my presence there or for the presumptuous
demand which I had meant to make; for I had come prepared to say
this: 'Lyef Nicolai&euml;vitch, I have come with the single purpose
of seeing the great writer, and perhaps to interchange a word or
two with him, perhaps even to press his gifted hand, and perhaps,
. . . taking advantage of his unlimited good-nature, to carry away
with me a memento of his gifted hand, in the form of a signature on
his latest portrait. . . .  But now I felt clearly that I could not
pronounce the words.  For if every one of the many million people
who pronounce the name of Lyef Tolstoy with a true glow in their
hearts had the hardihood to disturb him with a like intent, then
not only would the great old man have not a second for his mighty
work, but he would not even have a second for rest and repose.  I
grew conscious of all this, in the first few seconds, and felt that
I was not only an intruder, but even impertinent.
</p><p>"So in coward's fashion I hid the true purpose of my visit to
the Count, and tried to give an answer to his enquiry, hostile to
the truth, if you wish, but at least a little more reasonable.  For
he had asked me: 'In what way can I be of service to you?'
</p><p>"I tried to explain that, being a victim of the literary itch,
I could in no wise hinder myself from writing artistic productions.
And as I had read in an article by the Frenchman Andr&eacute;
Bonnier that the Count followed all the most trivial effusions of
contemporary literature with the greatest patience, I had decided
to ask him whether he would not be so good as to look over my
printed works, and pronounce his opinion on them, an opinion which
would be precious to me.
<pb n="483"/>
</p><p>"The Count listened very attentively.  When my tongue had got
altogether tangled up, and would proceed no further, the Count
continued to watch me with the utmost seriousness, nodding his head
the while, as who should say: 'Do not take the trouble to tell me
too minutely what you are after; I understand you pretty well
already.'
</p><p>"But it seems that I either confused terribly what I wanted to
say, or that the Count was too used to find that if a writer came
to him it would certainly be for help, and for that reason he
answered me:
</p><p>"Unfortunately, I cannot grant your request.  I do not follow
the type of literature of which you speak at all.  And if they were
to tell me that all the writers of belles-lettres in the whole
white world had ceased altogether to write their novels, stories,
and tales, I should not regret it in the least.  I have no longer
anything to do with all that.  If you wish to occupy yourself with
belles-lettres, that is your business; you will give your work
where there is a demand for it.  But my opinion counts for nothing.
If a paper does not want a thing, it will not take it because I
recommend it.  Not long ago a paper refused to print the really
excellent poem, in my opinion, of a young poet, although I wrote to
the editor to say that, to my mind, it was an excellent poem.'
</p><p>"And then I tried to explain that I had not come for
protection and patronage, because my efforts were already accepted
where they were wanted; and that I had only come to learn the
Count's opinion about my little things, and that I did not make a
point of it in the least, and apologized for disturbing the Count.
</p><p>"'But why should you want to know my opinion about your
writings?  And why should I read your writings?  Let us suppose
that you make a table'&mdash;and the count laid his hand on the polished
surface of the table, and spread his handsome fingers out on it;
'let us suppose that you wish to know how other people like your
table, you must take it where tables are sold, and they will tell
you there whether your work is good or bad.  This is just what I
say to you.  Why should I
<pb n="484"/>
read your work, when it does not
interest me in the least?  And it is probably not worth reading.
At least a hundred and fifty people have come to me with the same
request.  I tried to read their works.  And in the majority of
cases, they turned out to be neither the one thing nor the other.
One could not call them good.  Why should I waste my time reading
your works?  I have not much time; I am seventy years old.'
</p><p>"Good heavens," exclaims the interviewer, now thoroughly
abashed, "how I regretted that my feet rested on the polished oak
floor, and not on soft earth that would open and let me through.
</p><p>"I repeated that I did not in the least wish to insist on my
request, and with a desperate and half-formless determination to
bring my mission to an end I explained to the great writer, in what
words I know not, my desire to have his signature on a photograph
which I drew forth from a portfolio.
</p><p>"'With pleasure,' said Lyef Nicolai&euml;vitch, 'I will sign
the portrait.'
</p><p>"I felt that I was ready to jump with joy, and hastened to
take leave of the Count, to apologize for his time which I had
taken up, and to thank him for his kindness.
</p><p>"How opportune was my action I afterwards understood from the
circumstance that at that very moment the Countess entered and came
to her husband with something confidential.
</p><p>"'Here,' said the great writer, handing me the portrait, with
the ink still wet; 'forgive me for not being able to grant your
request.'
</p><p>"And he shook hands with me," says the little journalist.  We
will allow him to bow himself out.
</p><p>It is very refreshing to find that there is real humility in
the world, even if it does come perilously near to abjectness, as
in the present case.  We may simply note that the said journalist
sacrificed the honorarium for his article to a charitable
institution in which Count Tolstoy takes an interest.  The whole
thing is refreshing in its simplicity; at the same time
<pb n="485"/>
one
must admit that this abject person has a keen enough eye for vivid
detail.
</p><p>The next account which I have is a record of the visit of M.
Andr&eacute; Bonnier, whom the little journalist mentions as saying
that Tolstoy followed the light literature of the day.  Perhaps he
should have come first, but I found the little journalist much
stronger in the outward details which come first in our composite
picture.  M. Andr&eacute; Bonnier has not the slightest inclination
to sink through the floor.  He is a rather gloomy, sceptical
person, who wears the air of being a very great sinner, but of
despising even his own sins, the fashionable tone with French men
of letters since the <hi rend="italic">d&eacute;cadent</hi> and
<hi rend="italic">d&eacute;linquent</hi> movement set in.
</p><p>"The first thing," he writes, "that struck me about Tolstoy is
the confidence with which he affirms that he knows the truth.  This
conviction penetrates his glance, the vigor of his voice, the
firmness of his step.  On his whole personality stands the stamp of
truth.  It very rarely happens that he speaks very loud, or that he
grows excited, when expressing or defending an idea.  Even when you
feel that he is growing dissatisfied, he speaks without loudness,
in exactly the same tone.  He is so confident that he is not
mistaken and that he is speaking truth absolute, impersonal, and
self-evident, that he evidently does not think it necessary to
defend it jealously and passionately, as an opinion belonging to
him individually.  Doubt is wholly foreign to him.  What he wishes
to know, he knows; and what he does not know does not interest him.
If his eyes are sometimes clouded, and if at times the clear vision
of the sage deserts him, he is grieved not at himself, but because
he has failed to inspire belief in others in consequence of their
unwillingness to give way before evident truth.
</p><p>"So I saw, in my own century, a man who really has faith, whom
no sense of the unknown disturbs, and who lives without tormenting
doubts, a stranger to vacillation and weakness.  It was worth
coming so far to see that.  I think that from this point of view
Tolstoy stands alone; for most of us live by
<pb n="486"/>
hazard; and in
this lies the saddest side of our existence.  The best of us do all
that is in our power, but without really feeling certain that we
are doing right.  We wander, feeling our way along the line of
least resistance.  But now I have seen a man who believes in what
he does.
</p><p>"They tell me that one of Tolstoy's friends once expressed
himself in the Count's presence in a manner hostile to Tolstoy's
ideas, but, of course, with perfect courtesy.  Tolstoy remained
silent for a certain time, and then, looking straight in his
opponent's face, or to speak quite accurately, in the face of the
opponent of truth, he spoke: 'I cannot bear when anyone does not
share my opinion.'
</p><p>"This caused a certain awkwardness, and Tolstoy thus explained
his words: 'Because there can only be one truth.'
</p><p>"'Truth is one,' said his opponent; 'I agree with that
perfectly; but opinions concerning truth are many.'
</p><p>"Then Tolstoy closed the conversation with these words: 'There
are no opinions; there is only truth!'
</p><p>"Perhaps," adds M. Bonnier, "I ought not to record this
anecdote, because it may be understood in an unfavorable sense.  I
fear it may lead people to believe that Tolstoy is proud.  This
would be unjust.  But such is the weakness of our nature that we
who are not men of genius put ourselves right in our own eyes by
accusing men with convictions of pride.  No, Tolstoy is not proud,
although he has much more reason for pride than many people who are
really proud."
</p><p>In what this interviewer says we seem to get a clew to much
that we have found faulty in "What is Art?"  There is the extreme
dogmatism of an intense and yet rather narrow nature; and there is,
most of all, a total lack of the sense of humor.  One has noticed,
in Tolstoy's relations with the humble, effusive journalist, that
the writer is before all else a man of his caste, exclusive by
instinct, to the tips of his fingers, and, although he is himself
a writer, with a great deal of that haughty contempt for mere
writers which was felt in England in the days of Elizabeth, and in
Russia up till the middle of this generation.  Writing was a thing
a gentleman could only
<pb n="487"/>
concern himself with at the cost of
a certain loss of dignity.  So that we can hardly agree that
Tolstoy is not proud; he is even arrogant, by temperament and
education,&mdash;pre&euml;minently a caste man.  And, with this, he is
at war with his caste.  His inmost nature is utterly at variance
with his habitual nature.  Universal man, in him, is warring
against caste.  And hence, I think, we have this bitterness, this
impatience, this lack of urbanity, which rather mars his work,
unless, as in the case of his analysis of Wagner, it goes so far as
to be absolutely amusing.
</p><p>To speak of Tolstoy's shyness of the human body is a delicate
task, and one which had better, perhaps, be left alone.  But one
may suggest that here too education and conviction have had a hard
fight; that the rich officers of Tolstoy's youth had a habit of
sensuousness not easily combated; and that this reaction has become
almost morbid in its intensity, and, once more, has suffered from
Tolstoy's deficient sense of humor.  And this, I think, is why he
bears the Greeks a grudge.  After all, if they made statues of
Theseus, they did not forget Aphrodite, and, if a sensuous society
suddenly or even slowly and painfully reformed, they would
certainly bear a grudge against the patroness of Sappho, the lady
brilliant and undying, whose chariot was drawn by sparrows.
</p><p>But it is a great deficiency, this lack of the Greek sense.
As one who has painfully translated page after page of Tolstoy, who
has had to uncoil his long and tangled sentences, again and again
numbering a hundred words and more, I cannot but wish that Tolstoy
had gone through a severe course of iambic trimeters until he came
to appreciate the true beauty of a short sentence.  The Russians in
general have not much feeling for verse, that is for even rhythm
and the melody of words; and to this is due a certain harshness and
crudeness in so much of what they write.  And Tolstoy sins beyond
the measure of his countrymen.  Again, in the Greek spirit there
are two great qualities, lucidity and buoyancy.  Who would not
thank fate to find Tolstoy more buoyant and less lugubrious?  Where
is the joy of living, the contagion of good-nature
<pb n="488"/>
and
comity, which are so eminently Greek?  It seems to me that Tolstoy
looks at Greece through the corruption of Byzantium, and altogether
misses the lightness and brightness of the true Hellas.
</p><p>But to come back to the last of his three visitors, a Russian
prince.  And here the caste man comes out instantly.  Look at the
totally different greeting he receives, from the condescension
which overawed the little journalist and the cold reserve which
confronted the Frenchman.
</p><p>"I drove up to his house," says the prince, "and found him at
home; somewhat indisposed, but on his feet, and, as usual, taking
a lively interest in everything.  Count Lyef Nicolai&euml;vitch had
caught cold; he does not know exactly when; but, two or three weeks
back, true to his practice of physical work, he toiled a long time
with a shovel, and, sweating, caught a cold in the back.  Or
perhaps it was when he was skating, as he spends an hour or more on
the ice every day, and he is sixty-eight years old.  For the moment
he feels better, though still feverish and unable to write.
Otherwise he works daily with his pen in his study from ten in the
morning till four in the afternoon.  Lyef Nicolai&euml;vitch came
to meet me, holding a book of Heine's poetry in his hand, and he
read to me several beautiful poems of the famous writer with
evident delight.  Tolstoy reads small German type, even in the
evening, with ease, so perfect is his eyesight.
</p><p>"'I am taking advantage of my illness,' he said, 'to read
Heine again.  I am very fond of him.  I cannot write just now.'
</p><p>"From Heine the conversation turned to Zola and Dreyfus.  Lyef
Nicolai&euml;vitch was very much astonished when I told him that
Zola was generally believed to be a Venetian Jew.
</p><p>"'For me, with my convictions,' he said, 'this anti-Semitism
in France is very odious; and all this Chauvinism and out-cry for
the army, too.  And I confess that I strongly sympathized with this
movement of Zola's, until I discovered that the students were
against him.  I believe in the students, and hold that truth dwells
ever with the young.'
</p><p>"The subject was changed to women.
<pb n="489"/>
</p><p>"'Women,' said Count Tolstoy, 'are all talking of liberty, and
saying that, as Christians, they have a right to everything.  But
should a free Christian woman be like our ladies&mdash;in low dresses,
flying to balls and dinners, and, for this, not dressing, but
undressing?  My understanding of a Christian woman is far
different: strict, full of Christian love towards her neighbors,
understanding and strictly fulfilling her family duties; such a
woman is free.  In early Christian days women did not undress like
the heathen; they wore loose robes, hiding their forms; they did
not strip themselves, as the heathen do.  I am unwell just at
present, and unable to write; but I hope I shall not die, so that
I may write much about women.  Before I die, I shall say all that
is in my heart concerning womankind.'"
</p><p>This last sentence calls to mind a reflection that often
occurred to me while I was reading "What is Art?"  In setting forth
the new ideal of the future, which is to revolutionize not only
art, but life, Tolstoy persistently speaks of it as the Christian
ideal, and of its outcome as true Christian art.  Now, while it is
quite true that one fundamental principle, which he holds to be of
the greatest importance, and which is indeed of the greatest
importance, may well be called Christian, yet it seems to me that
this continuous harping on a single string is likely to do more
harm than good; that he is likely rather to drive people away from
his ideal than to attract people to what he holds to be real
Christianity.  This allusion to the early Christian women in their
long robes suggests the same thought.  It is quite certain that the
consideration of what the early Christian women did, or left
undone, will weigh for very little in the future development of the
idea of woman's liberty.  And in saying this I am not for a moment
blind to the fact that the Christian religion, in the strictest
sense, has done very much to elevate the life of women.  But what
I should like to say is this: Christianity has done this, not from
any exclusive or supernatural quality which it possesses, but
because it rings true in this particular to our best sense of human
life.  We have in our inmost
<pb n="490"/>
hearts the love of liberty, of
fair dealing, of loving-kindness, and of tender mercy; and these
things go far deeper than the fact that we do or do not believe in
a certain dogmatic system.  They are the heart's core of the human
heart.  And what we shall reach in the future in the ideals of
liberty and the intuition of each other's lives, we shall reach,
not because these things are called Christian or were advocated by
the Christian faith, but because they are real; because they lie at
the heart of human life.  Now human life is something which we all
have, and which we all reverence in our best hours; while a
dogmatic faith is something we may or may not have, may or may not
reverence.  Why then appeal to the less instead of to the greater?
Why not appeal to life itself?  Why not judge all things, and faith
among the rest, by our deepest intuition of the reality of life&mdash;
something we have ever with us and can always verify; something
which all lands and all ages have held in common, while their
faiths have too often only served to separate them?
</p><p>Tolstoy, if he feels called on to express a judgment, should
judge womankind not by what he fancies he knows of the early
Christian women, but by his intuition of life&mdash;set up for them the
standard of the immortal soul, with its power, its gladness, its
penetrating beauty, and its everlasting mystery, which no faith or
philosophy has ever perfectly understood.</p>

<closer>
    <dateline>NEW YORK.</dateline>
</closer>

</div1>
</body>
</text>
</TEI.2>

