<?xml version="1.0"?>

<?dlps id="JohShal"?>
<?dlps page-images="none" figure-images="no"?>
<?dlps transcription="other"?>

<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/tei-p4/tei2.dtd" [
<!ENTITY % POSTKB "INCLUDE">
<!ENTITY % TEI.extensions.ent SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.ent">
<!ENTITY % TEI.extensions.dtd SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.dtd">
<!ENTITY % ISOnum SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/charent/iso-num.ent"> %ISOnum;
<!ENTITY % ISOpub SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/charent/iso-pub.ent"> %ISOpub;

]>
<TEI.2 id="JohShal">
<teiHeader type="migrated" creator="Etext">
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title type="main">We Shall Overcome</title>
<title type="sort">we shall overcome</title>
<author>Johnson, Lyndon B.</author>
<respStmt>
<resp>Creation of machine-readable version</resp>
<name>NOVA (Perdue)</name>
<resp>Conversion to TEI-conformant markup</resp>
<name>University of Virginia Library Electronic Text Center</name>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt>
<extent>ca. <num type="kilobytes">28</num> kilobytes</extent>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>University of Virginia Library</publisher>
<pubPlace>Charlottesville, Virginia</pubPlace>
<idno type="ETC">JohShal</idno>
<date value="1994">1994</date>
<availability status="public">
<p n="copyright">Copyright &copy; 1994 by the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia</p>
<p n="access">Publicly accessible</p>
</availability>
<idno type="uva-pid">uva-lib:476126</idno>
</publicationStmt>
<seriesStmt>
<title>University of Virginia Library, Text collection</title>
<idno type="uva-set">UVA-LIB-Text</idno>
</seriesStmt>
<sourceDesc>
<biblFull>
<titleStmt>
<title type="main">We Shall Overcome</title>
<title type="sort">we shall overcome</title>
<author>Lyndon B. Johnson</author>
</titleStmt>
<publicationStmt>
<p/>
</publicationStmt>
<notesStmt>
<note>
<p>Print source unknown</p>
</note>
</notesStmt>
</biblFull>
</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc>
<encodingDesc>
<projectDesc>
<p>Prepared for the University of Virginia Library Electronic Text Center</p>
</projectDesc>
<editorialDecl>
<p>All quotation marks retained as data</p>
<p>All unambiguous end-of-line hyphens have been removed, and the
trailing part of a word has been joined to the preceding line.</p>
<p id="ETC">Keywords in the header are a local Electronic Text Center scheme
to aid in establishing analytical groupings</p>
</editorialDecl>
<refsDecl>
<p>ID elements are given for each page element and are composed of the text's
unique cryptogram and the given page number, as in SpeFQue1 for page one of
Spenser's Faerie Queene.</p>
</refsDecl>
</encodingDesc>
<profileDesc>
<creation>
<date value="1965">1965</date>
</creation>
<langUsage>
<language id="eng" usage="main">English</language>
</langUsage>
<textClass>
<keywords>
<term>non-fiction; prose</term>
</keywords>
</textClass>
</profileDesc>
<revisionDesc>
<change>
<date value="1992-12">December 1992</date>
<respStmt>
<name>David Seaman, University of Virginia Electronic Text Center</name>
</respStmt>
<item>minimal TEI tagging and spell-check</item>
</change>
<change>
<date value="1994-08">August 1994</date>
<respStmt>
<name>Jamie L Spriggs, Electronic Text Center, University of Virginia</name>
</respStmt>
<item>updated header, updated tagging</item>
</change>
<change>
<date value="2005-07">July 2005</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>Corrector</resp>
<name>John Ivor Carlson</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Converted to XML and/or checked tags.</item>
</change>
<change>
<date value="2007-09">September 2007</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>Migration</resp>
<name>Ethan Gruber, University of Virginia Library</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Converted XML markup from TEI Lite to uva-dl-tei (TEI P4 with local customizations).</item>
</change>
<change>
<date value="2008-01">January 2008</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>Migration</resp>
<name>Greg Murray, University of Virginia Library</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Programmatically updated TEI header markup (but not header content) for minimal compliance with current QA requirements.</item>
</change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>
<text id="d1">

<front id="d2">

<div1 type="introduction" id="d3">
<head>Introduction</head>
<pb n="1" id="JohShal1"/>

<p>"Somehow you never forget what poverty and hatred can do when you
see its scars on the hopeful face of a young child."  So spoke
President Lyndon B. Johnson in the course of one of the most deeply
felt, and deeply moving, addresses ever delivered by an American
president.  The date was March 15, 1965; the occasion was an
extraordinary joint session at night of the Senate and the House of
Representatives, televised across the nation.  It was the "time of
Selma" &mdash; only a few days after the historic mass demonstration in
support of voter registration in Alabama, in which many of the
peaceful marchers were physically attacked and one of them, a white
clergyman from the north, was killed.  The nation itself was a shocked
witness, via television, of much of that unforgettable scene:  the
long rows of marchers, a cross-section of American courage, among them
nuns and schoolteachers, priests and rabbis, old men and young women,
Negroes and white, Californians and New Yorkers &mdash; resolutely striding,
smiling, singing to hide their exhaustion, trying not to see the
hate-twisted faces and shouting menace of the sidewalk crowd, trying
not to fear the armored troopers and police with their notorious
supporting artillery of dogs, clubs, and cattle prods. . .
</p><p>This was the moment chosen by the President, himself a Southerner
with a reputation for compromise, to bear witness before the nation,
and to call upon his former associates of Congress to stand up and be
counted with him &mdash; more specifically, to take action on a bill which
would correct the conspicuous weakness of the 1964 Civil Rights Bill,
its failure to protect the right of Negroes to vote "when local
officials are determined to deny it."  In forthright terms, President
Johnson spelled out the full cruelty and ingenuity of that
discrimination, and crisply defined the central issue involved:
"there is no Constitutional issue here.  The command of the
Constitution is plain.  There is no moral issue.  It is wrong &mdash; deadly
wrong &mdash; to deny any of your fellow Americans the right to vote in this
country.  There is no issue of state's rights or national rights.
There is only the struggle for human rights."
</p><p>The President spoke slowly, solemnly, with unmistakable
determination.  His words and his manner were perfectly synchronized;
indeed he made the nationwide audience aware of how deeply personal
the issue of Negro rights was to him.  He recalled his own southern
origins, and his shattering encounter with Mexican-American children
as a young schoolteacher ("they never seemed to know why people
disliked them, but they knew it was so because I saw it in their
<pb n="2" id="JohShal2"/>
eyes").  He spoke more directly, more explicitly, and more warmly of
the human experience of prejudice than any president before him.  But
he also placed the problem of Negro rights in a broader frame of
reference &mdash; that of poverty and ignorance, bigotry and fear.  "Their
cause must be our cause too.  Because it's not just Negroes, but
really it's all of us, who must overcome the crippling legacy of
bigotry and injustice.  And we shall overcome."
</p><p>In terms of its immediate objective, at least, the President's
address to Congress was a complete success.  The Voting Rights Bill of
1965, enacted shortly after, contains these three main provisions:
(1) it permits the Federal government to send Federal examiners into
voting districts within the states where less than 50 percent of
voters are registered, and to take over registration; (2) it suspends
the so-called "literacy tests" in such areas as Alabama, Alaska,
Georgia, Louisiana, Mississippi, South Carolina, and thirty-four
counties of North Carolina; (3) it authorizes the Attorney General to
take court action toward declaring the poll tax unconstitutional in
state and local elections.  The new legislation thus supplements the
broader civil rights measure of 1964 at precisely the points where it
was being rendered inoperative.
</p>
<signed>LYNDON B. JOHNSON</signed>

</div1>
</front>
<body id="d4">
<div1 type="decree" id="d5">
<head>WE SHALL OVERCOME </head>

<pb n="3" id="JohShal3"/>

<p>Mr. Speaker, Mr. President, members of the Congress, I speak
tonight for the dignity of man and the destiny of Democracy.  I urge
every member of both parties, Americans of all religions and of all
colors, from every section of this country, to join me in that cause.
</p><p>At times, history and fate meet at a single time in a single
place to shape a turning point in man's unending search for freedom.
</p><p>So it was at Lexington and Concord.  So it was a century ago at
Appomattox.  So it was last week in Selma, Alabama.
</p><p>There, long suffering men and women peacefully protested the
denial of their rights as Americans.  Many of them were brutally
assaulted.  One good man &mdash; a man of God &mdash; was killed.
</p><p>There is no cause for pride in what has happened in Selma.  There
is no cause for self-satisfaction in the long denial of equal rights
of millions of Americans.  But there is cause for hope and for faith
in our Democracy in what is happening here tonight.
</p><p>For the cries of pain and the hymns and protests of oppressed
people have summoned into convocation all the majesty of this great
government &mdash; the government of the greatest nation on earth.
</p><p>Our mission is at once the oldest and the most basic of this
country &mdash; to right wrong, to do justice, to serve man.
</p><p>In our time we have come to live with the moments of great
crises.  Our lives have been marked with debate about great issues,
issues of war and peace, issues of prosperity and depression.
</p><p>But rarely in any time does an issue lay bare the secret heart of
America itself.  Rarely are we met with a challenge, not to our growth
or abundance, or our welfare or our security, but rather to the values
and the purposes and the meaning of our beloved nation.
</p><p>The issue of equal rights for American Negroes is such an issue.
</p><p>And should we defeat every enemy, and should we double our wealth
and conquer the stars, and still be unequal to this issue, then we
will have failed as a people and as a nation.
</p><p>For, with a country as with a person, "what is a man profited if
he shall gain the whole world, and lose his own soul?"
</p><p>There is no Negro problem.  There is no Southern problem.  There
is no Northern problem.  There is only an American problem.
</p><p>And we are met here tonight as Americans &mdash; not as Democrats or
Republicans; we're met here as Americans to solve that problem.
</p><p>This was the first nation in the history of the world to be
founded with a purpose.  The great phrases of that purpose still sound
in every American heart, north and south: </p>
<pb n="4" id="JohShal4"/>
<p>"All men are created equal."  "Government by consent of the
governed."  "Give me liberty or give me death."
</p><p>And those are not just clever words, and those are not just empty
theories.
</p><p>In their name Americans have fought and died for two centuries
and tonight around the world they stand there as guardians of our
liberty risking their lives.
</p><p>Those words are promised to every citizen that he shall share in
the dignity of man.  This dignity cannot be found in a man's
possessions.  It cannot be found in his power or in his position.  It
really rests on his right to be treated as a man equal in opportunity
to all others.
</p><p>It says that he shall share in freedom.  He shall choose his
leaders, educate his children, provide for his family according to his
ability and his merits as a human being.
</p><p>To apply any other test, to deny a man his hopes because of his
color or race or his religion or the place of his birth is not only to
do injustice, it is to deny Americans and to dishonor the dead who
gave their lives for American freedom.
</p><p>Our fathers believed that if this noble view of the rights of man
was to flourish it must be rooted in democracy.  This most basic right
of all was the right to choose your own leaders.
</p><p>The history of this country in large measure is the history of
expansion of the right to all of our people.  Many of the issues of
civil rights are very complex and most difficult.  But about this
there can and should be no argument:  every American citizen must have
an equal right to vote.
</p><p>There is no reason which can excuse the denial of that right.
There is no duty which weighs more heavily on us than the duty we have
to insure that right.  Yet the harsh fact is that in many places in
this country men and women are kept from voting simply because they
are Negroes.
</p><p>Every device of which human ingenuity is capable has been used to
deny this right.  The Negro citizen may go to register only to be told
that the day is wrong, or the hour is late, or the official in charge
is absent.
</p><p>And if he persists and, if he manages to present himself to the
registrar, he may be disqualified because he did not spell out his
middle name, or because he abbreviated a word on the application.  And
if he manages to fill out an application, he is given a test.
</p><pb n="5" id="JohShal5"/>
<p>The registrar is the sole judge of whether he passes this test.
He may be asked to recite the entire Constitution, or explain the most
complex provisions of state law.
</p><p>And even a college degree cannot be used to prove that he can
read and write.  For the fact is that the only way to pass these
barriers is to show a white skin.
</p><p>Experience has clearly shown that the existing process of law
cannot overcome systematic and ingenious discrimination.  No law that
we know have on the books, and I have helped to put three of them
there, can insure the right to vote when local officials are
determined to deny it.  In such a case, our duty must be clear to all
of us.
</p><p>The Constitution says that no person shall be kept from voting
because of his race or his color.  We have all sworn an oath before
God to support and to defend that Constitution.  We must now act in
obedience to that oath.
</p><p>Wednesday, I will send to Congress a law designed to eliminate
illegal barriers to the right to vote.
</p><p>The broad principles of that bill will be in the hands of the
Democratic and Republican leaders tomorrow.  After they have reviewed
it, it will come here formally as a bill.
</p><p>I am grateful for this opportunity to come here tonight at the
invitation of the leadership to reason with my friends, to give them
my views and to visit with my former colleagues.
</p><p>I have had prepared a more comprehensive analysis of the
legislation which I had intended to transmit to the clerk tomorrow,
but which I will submit to the clerks tonight.  But I want to really
discuss the main proposals of this legislation.
</p><p>This bill will strike down restrictions to voting in all
elections, federal, state and local, which have been used to deny
Negroes the right to vote.
</p><p>This bill will establish a simple, uniform standard which cannot
be used, however ingenious the effort, to flout our Constitution.  It
will provide for citizens to be registered by officials of the United
States Government, if the state officials refuse to register them.
</p><p>It will eliminate tedious, unnecessary lawsuits which delay the
right to vote.
</p><p>Finally, this legislation will insure the properly registered
individuals are not prohibited from voting.
</p><pb n="6" id="JohShal6"/>
<p>I will welcome the suggestions from all the members of Congress &mdash;
I have no doubt that I will get some &mdash; on ways and means to strengthen
this law and to make it effective.
</p><p>But experience has plainly shown that this is the only path to
carry out the command of the Constitution.  To those who seek to avoid
action by their national government in their home communities, who
want to and who seek to maintain purely local control over elections,
the answer is simple:  open your polling places to all your people.
</p><p>Allow men and women to register and vote whatever the color of
their skin.
</p><p>Extend the rights of citizenship to every citizen of this land.
</p><p>There is no Constitutional issue here.  The command of the
Constitution is plain.  There is no moral issue.  It is wrong &mdash; deadly
wrong &mdash; to deny any of your fellow Americans the right to vote in this
country.
</p><p>There is no issue of state's rights or national rights.  There is
only the struggle for human rights.
</p><p>I have not the slightest doubt what will be your answer.  But the
last time a President sent a civil rights bill to the Congress it
contained a provision to protect voting rights in Federal elections.
That civil rights bill was passed after eight long months of debate.
And when that bill came to my desk from the Congress for signature,
the heart of the voting provision had been eliminated.
</p><p>This time, on this issue, there must be no delay, or no
hesitation, or no compromise with our purpose.
</p><p>We cannot, we must not, refuse to protect the right of every
American to vote in every election that he may desire to participate
in.
</p><p>And we ought not, and we cannot, and we must not wait another
eight months before we get a bill.
</p><p>We have already waited 100 years and more and the time for
waiting is gone.
</p><p>So I ask you to join me in working long hours and nights and
weekends, if necessary, to pass this bill.
</p><p>And I don't make that request lightly, for from the window where
I sit with the problems of our country I recognize that from outside
this chamber is the outraged conscience of a nation, the grave concern
of many nations and the harsh judgment of history on our acts.
</p><p>But even if we pass this bill the battle will not be over.
</p><pb n="7" id="JohShal7"/>
<p>What happened in Selma is part of a far larger movement which
reaches into every section and state of America.  It is the effort of
American Negroes to secure for themselves the full blessings of
American life.
</p><p>Their cause must be our cause too.  Because it's not just
Negroes, but really it's all of us, who must overcome the crippling
legacy of bigotry and injustice.
</p><p>And we shall overcome.
</p><p>As a man whose roots go deeply into southern soil, I know how
agonizing racial feelings are.  I know how difficult it is to reshape
the attitudes and the structure of our society.  But a century has
passed &mdash; more than 100 years &mdash; since the Negro was freed.
</p><p>And he is not fully free tonight.
</p><p>It was more than 100 years ago that Abraham Lincoln &mdash; a great
President of another party &mdash; signed the Emancipation Proclamation.  But
emancipation is a proclamation and not a fact.
</p><p>A century has passed &mdash; more than 100 years &mdash; since equality was
promised, and yet the Negro is not equal.
</p><p>A century has passed since the day of promise, and the promise is
unkept.  The time of justice has now come, and I tell you that I
believe sincerely that no force can hold it back.  It is right in the
eyes of man and God that it should come, and when it does, I think
that day will brighten the lives of every American.
</p><p>For Negroes are not the only victims.  How many white children
have gone uneducated?  How many white families have lived in stark
poverty?  How many white lives have been scarred by fear, because we
wasted energy and our substance to maintain the barriers of hatred and
terror?
</p><p>And so I say to all of you here and to all in the nation tonight
that those who appeal to you to hold on to the past do so at the cost
of denying you your future.  This great rich, restless country can
offer opportunity and education and hope to all &mdash; all, black and white,
north and south, sharecropper and city dweller.
</p><p>These are the enemies:  poverty, ignorance, disease.  They are
our enemies, nor our fellow man, not our neighbor.  And these enemies
too &mdash; poverty, disease and ignorance &mdash; we shall overcome.
</p><p>Now let none of us in any section look with prideful
righteousness on the troubles in another section or the problems of
our neighbors.
</p><pb n="8" id="JohShal8"/>
<p>There is really no part of America where the promise of equality
has been fully kept.  In Buffalo as well as in Birmingham, in
Philadelphia as well as Selma, Americans are struggling for the fruits
of freedom.  This is one nation.  What happens in Selma and Cincinnati
is a matter of legitimate concern to every American.
</p><p>But let each of us look within our own hearts and our own
communities and let each of us put our shoulder to the wheel to root
out injustice wherever it exists.
</p><p>As we meet here in this peaceful historic chamber tonight, men
from the south, some of whom were at Iwo Jima, men from the north who
have carried Old Glory to the far corners of the world and who brought
it back without a stain on it, men from the east and from the west are
all fighting together without regard to religion or color or region in
Vietnam.  Men from every region fought for us across the world 20
years ago.  And now in these common dangers, in these common
sacrifices, the south made its contribution of honor and gallantry no
less than any other region in the great republic.  And in some
instances, a great many of them, more.
</p><p>And I have not the slightest doubt that good men from everywhere
in this country, from the Great Lakes to the Gulf of Mexico, from the
Golden Gate to the harbors along the Atlantic, will rally now together
in this cause to vindicate the freedom of all Americans.
</p><p>For all of us owe this duty and I believe that all of us will
respond to it.  Your president makes that request of every American.
</p><p>The real hero of this struggle is the American Negro.  His
actions and protests, his courage to risk safety, and even to risk his
life, have awakened the conscience of this nation.  His demonstrations
have been designed to call attention to injustice, designed to provoke
change; designed to stir reform.
</p><p>He has been called upon to make good the promise of America.  And
who among us can say that we would have made the same progress were it
not for his persistent bravery and his faith in American democracy?
</p><p>For at the real heart of the battle for equality is a deep-seated
belief in the democratic process.  Equality depends, not on the force
of arms or tear gas, but depends upon the force of moral right &mdash; not on
recourse to violence, but on respect for law and order.
</p><p>There have been many pressures upon your President and there will
be others as the days come and go.  But I pledge to you tonight that
we intend to fight this battle where it should be fought &mdash; in the
<pb n="9" id="JohShal9"/>
courts, and in the Congress, and the hearts of men.
</p><p>We must preserve the right of free speech and the right of free
assembly.
</p><p>But the right of free speech does not carry with it &mdash; as has been
said &mdash; the right to holler fire in a crowded theatre.
</p><p>We must preserve the right to free assembly.  But free assembly
does not carry with it the right to block public thoroughfares to
traffic.
</p><p>We do have a right to protest.  And a right to march under
conditions that do not infringe the Constitutional rights of our
neighbors.  And I intend to protect all those rights as long as I am
permitted to serve in this office.
</p><p>We will guard against violence, knowing it strikes from our hands
the very weapons which we seek &mdash; progress, obedience to law, and belief
in American values.
</p><p>In Selma, as elsewhere, we seek and pray for peace.  We seek
order, we seek unity, but we will not accept the peace of stifled
rights or the order imposed by fear, or the unity that stifles protest
&mdash; for peace cannot be purchased at the cost of liberty.
</p><p>In Selma tonight &mdash; and we had a good day there &mdash; as in every city
we are working for a just and peaceful settlement.  We must all
remember after this speech I'm making tonight, after the police and
the F.B.I. And the Marshals have all gone, and after you have promptly
passed this bill, the people of Selma and the other cities of the
nation must still live and work together.
</p><p>And when the attention of the nation has gone elsewhere they must
try to heal the wounds and to build a new community.  This cannot be
easily done on a battleground of violence as the history of the south
itself shows.  It is in recognition of this that men of both races
have shown such an outstandingly impressive responsibility in recent
days &mdash; last tuesday and again today.
</p><p>The bill I am presenting to you will be known as a civil rights
bill.
</p><p>But in a larger sense, most of the program I am recommending is a
civil rights program.  Its object is to open the city of hope to all
people of all races, because all Americans just must have the right to
vote, and we are going to give them that right.
</p><p>All Americans must have the privileges of citizenship, regardless
of race, and they are going to have those privileges of citizenship
regardless of race.
</p><pb n="10" id="JohShal10"/>
<p>But I would like to caution you and remind you that to exercise
these privileges takes much more than just legal right.  It requires a
trained mind and a healthy body.  It requires a decent home and the
chance to find a job and the opportunity to escape from the clutches
of poverty.
</p><p>Of course people cannot contribute to the nation if they are
never taught to read or write; if their bodies are stunted from
hunger; if their sickness goes untended; if their life is spent in
hopeless poverty, just drawing a welfare check.
</p><p>So we want to open the gates to opportunity.  But we're also
going to give all our people, black and white, the help that they need
to walk through those gates.
</p><p>My first job after college was as a teacher in Cotulla, Texas, in
a small Mexican-American school.  Few of them could speak English and
I couldn't speak much Spanish.
</p><p>My students were poor and they often came to class without
breakfast and hungry.  And they knew even in their youth the pain of
prejudice.  They never seemed to know why people disliked them, but
they knew it was so because I saw it in their eyes.
</p><p>I often walked home late in the afternoon after the classes were
finished wishing there was more that I could do.  But all I knew was
to teach them the little that I knew, hoping that I might help them
against the hardships that lay ahead.
</p><p>And somehow you never forget what poverty and hatred can do when
you see its scars on the hopeful face of a young child.
</p><p>I never though then, in 1928, that I would be standing here in
1965.  It never even occurred to me in my fondest dreams that I might
have the chance to help the sons and daughters of those students, and
to help people like them all over this country.
</p><p>But now I do have that chance.  And I'll let you in on a secret &mdash;
I mean to use it.
</p><p>And I hope that you will use it with me.  This is the richest,
most powerful country which ever occupied this globe.  The might of
past empires is little compared to ours.  But I do not want to be the
president who built empires, or sought grandeur, or extended dominion.
I want to be the president who educated young children to the wonders
of their world.
</p><p>I want to be the President who helped to feed the hungry and to
prepare them to be taxpayers instead of tax eaters.
</p><p>I want to be the President who helped the poor to find their own
<pb n="11" id="JohShal11"/>
way and who protected the right of every citizen to vote in every
election.
</p><p>I want to be the President who helped to end hatred among his
fellow men and who promoted love among the people of all races, all
regions and all parties.
</p><p>I want to be the President who helped to end war among the
brothers of this earth.
</p><p>And so at the request of your beloved Speaker and the Senator
from Montana, the Majority Leader, the Senator from Illinois, the
Minority Leader, Mr. McCullock and other members of both parties, I
came here tonight, not as President Roosevelt came down one time in
person to veto a bonus bill; not as President Truman came down one
time to urge passage of a railroad bill, but I came down here to ask
you to share this task with me.  And to share it with the people that
we both work for.
</p><p>I want this to be the Congress &mdash; Republicans and Democrats alike &mdash;
which did all these things for all these people.
</p><p>Beyond this great chamber &mdash; out yonder &mdash; in fifty states are the
people that we serve.  Who can tell what deep and unspoken hopes are
in their hearts tonight as they sit there and listen?
</p><p>We all can guess, from our own lives, how difficult they often
find their own pursuit of happiness.
</p><p>How many problems each little family has.  They look most of all
to themselves for their future, but I think that they also look to
each of us.
</p><p>Above the pyramid on the Great Seal of the United States it says
in Latin, "God has favored our undertaking."  God will not favor
everything that we do.  It is rather our duty to divine his will.  But
I cannot help but believe that he truly understands and that he really
favors the understaking that we begin here tonight.</p>

</div1>
</body>
</text>
</TEI.2>
