<?xml version="1.0"?>

<?dlps id="JonName"?>
<?dlps page-images="none" figure-images="no"?>
<?dlps transcription="other"?>

<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/tei-p4/tei2.dtd" [
<!ENTITY % POSTKB "INCLUDE">
<!ENTITY % TEI.extensions.ent SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.ent">
<!ENTITY % TEI.extensions.dtd SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.dtd">
<!ENTITY % ISOnum SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/charent/iso-num.ent"> %ISOnum;
<!ENTITY % ISOpub SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/charent/iso-pub.ent"> %ISOpub;

]>
<TEI.2 id="JonName">
<teiHeader type="migrated" creator="Etext">
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title type="main">In the Name of His Ancestor</title>
<title type="sort">in the name of his ancestor</title>
<author>Jones, William</author>
<respStmt>
<resp>Creation of machine-readable version:</resp>
<name>Judy Boss</name>
<resp>Creation of digital images:</resp>
<name/>
<resp>Conversion to TEI.2-conformant markup:</resp>
<name>University of Virginia Library Electronic Text Center.</name>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt>
<extent>ca. <num type="kilobytes">18</num> kilobytes</extent>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>University of Virginia Library</publisher>
<pubPlace>Charlottesville, Virginia</pubPlace>
<idno type="ETC">JonName</idno>
<date value="1996">1996</date>
<availability status="public">
<p n="copyright">Copyright &copy; 1996 by the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia</p>
<p n="access">Publicly accessible</p>
</availability>
<idno type="uva-pid">uva-lib:476129</idno>
</publicationStmt>
<seriesStmt>
<title>University of Virginia Library, Text collection</title>
<idno type="uva-set">UVA-LIB-Text</idno>
</seriesStmt>
<notesStmt>
<note>
<p>Print version not consulted in tagging.</p>
</note>
</notesStmt>
<sourceDesc>
<biblFull>
<titleStmt>
<title type="main">In the Name of His Ancestor</title>
<title level="j">Harvard Monthly</title>
<title type="sort">in the name of his ancestor</title>
<author>William Jones</author>
</titleStmt>
<editionStmt>
<p>1st Edition</p>
</editionStmt>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>Harvard Monthly</publisher>
<pubPlace>Boston</pubPlace>
<date value="1899">1899</date>
<idno type="callNo">Print copy consulted: none</idno>
</publicationStmt>
</biblFull>
</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc>
<encodingDesc>
<projectDesc>
<p>Prepared for the University of Virginia Library Electronic Text Center.</p>
</projectDesc>
<editorialDecl>
<p>All quotation marks retained as data.</p>
<p>All unambiguous end-of-line hyphens have been removed, and the trailing part of a word has been joined to the preceding line.</p>
<p>Keywords in the header are a local Electronic Text Center scheme to aid in establishing analytical groupings.</p>
</editorialDecl>
</encodingDesc>
<profileDesc>
<creation>
<date value="1899-12">December 1899</date>
</creation>
<langUsage>
<language id="eng" usage="main">English</language>
</langUsage>
<textClass>
<keywords>
<term>Fiction; prose.</term>
<term>Native American</term>
</keywords>
</textClass>
</profileDesc>
<revisionDesc>
<change>
<date value="1996-10">October, 1996</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>corrector</resp>
<name>Tom Lukas</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Tagged according to tei-2</item>
</change>
<change>
<date value="2005-07">July 2005</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>Corrector</resp>
<name>John Ivor Carlson</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Converted to XML and/or checked tags.</item>
</change>
<change>
<date value="2007-09">September 2007</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>Migration</resp>
<name>Ethan Gruber, University of Virginia Library</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Converted XML markup from TEI Lite to uva-dl-tei (TEI P4 with local customizations).</item>
</change>
<change>
<date value="2008-01">January 2008</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>Migration</resp>
<name>Greg Murray, University of Virginia Library</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Programmatically updated TEI header markup (but not header content) for minimal compliance with current QA requirements.</item>
</change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>
<text id="d1">

<body id="d2">


<div1 type="story" id="d3"><pb n="109"/>
<head><hi rend="italic">IN THE NAME OF HIS ANCESTOR.</hi></head>

<p>TELL me, mother, what is keeping my father away so late to-night?
</p><p>The traps, the beaver traps, my son.  You know in these wintry
moons when his fur is smooth and soft the beaver can hear from
afar the crack of the tiniest twig, can see as far as you, and can
scent, oh&mdash;I was going to say almost as far as he can see.  One of
these days you will accompany your father with the traps, and then
you will no longer wonder why he has to work so long over them.
Come, sit here with me on the buffalo robe before the light of this
blaze.  Now put your feet close up to the fire, but take care not to
burn your moccasins.
</p><p>Ooh, mother, how the wigwam is shaking!  Is Nutenwi, the
wind, angry?
</p><p>Do not fear, my son.  But hark, listen to the voices of the trees,
our grandparents!  It snows, it is growing cold, and the night
blackens.  Lonely out in the dark stand our grandparents.  Now
Nutenwi, the wind, is passing among them; and so, bowing together
their heads, they are wailing one to another how cold, how lonely,
and how sad they are.  Their voices are not so full of mirth as in the
warm summer moons, when the whip-poor-will, resting upon their
shoulders, sings to them songs of the ripening corn.
</p><p>Hish, listen, my son!  Do you hear one moaning out slowly,
"Ketona!  Ketona!"?
</p><p>It is Mitwiwa, mother, the old cottonwood down by the spring.
I wonder why he should be calling me on a night like this?
</p><p>Perhaps it is not you he is calling.  It may be that the Chipiya,
the spirit of the ancestor after whom you are named, is walking
forth this night, revisiting the lodges of his people.  If so, then it is
he old Mitwiwa is calling by name.
</p><p>Does old Mitwiwa know as much about Ketona as my father?
As you, mother?
</p><p>Yes, and more. <pb n="110"/>
</p><p>He was the one who long ago&mdash;do tell me about him again, will
you, mother?
</p><p>Lay your head down upon my lap then.
</p><p>You are now eight winters of age.  One morning, a moon after
you were born, when it was beginning to whiten in the Wabeneki, in
the land of the dawn, your father brought Tacumisawa into our
wigwam.  Tacumisawa, you know, is still the chief of the Eagles,
our gens.  Shortly after, there came other Eagles, until thirty,
perhaps forty, of them were seated in a circle within the lodge.  I sat
over in a corner among the women and the children, holding you in
my lap.  After the priests had chanted prayers to Gisha Munetoa,
and your father had done serving turkey, venison, and corn to the
guests, there fell a silence so quiet in the lodge that we could hear
one another breathe.  And like the mist that was rising that morning
from our brook down there under the hill, lifted the smoke from the
long red-stone pipes of the men, floating in slowly-whirling rings
and in tiny clouds up through the opening in the top of the wigwam.
Tacumisawa had long been watching the smoke.  By and by he
gently laid aside his pipe and, in a tone as low as mine is now, said
to us all:
</p><p>"My brother and my sister Eagles, Gisha Munetoa is looking
down upon us.  The Eagles who have lived before us are listening.  I
name this child, Ketona.  Hear, and let me tell you why."
</p><p>And then he went on with the story you have heard over and
again from your father.  Now all the events of that story happened
winters and winters ago in our old Rock River country, far away off
in the land of the North.  The bitterest foes of our nation then were
the Sioux, men of the long nose, hooked like the beak of a hawk.
Coming again and again from the country beyond the Mississippi,
they tried to drive us away from the Rock River; but finding that
they were losing too many scalps, and feeling after each fight that
the hearts of our men and of our women were growing stronger and
braver, they finally decided that it was better to remain on the
western side of the Mississippi.
</p><p>At sunrise of a morning after the Sioux had been driven over
the <pb n="111"/>  Great River, four of their men appeared on the bluffs of
the eastern bank within sight of our lodges.  Even while the runners
were yelling the alarm fifteen men had started at the top of their
speed toward the bluffs to kill or to capture the hated foe.  But when
the four Sioux lifted high their left hands, and pressed their right
over their hearts, and after the old men down in the village yelled,
"Messengers of peace!  Messengers of peace!  Let them alone!  Let
them come!" the men halted and unwillingly returned to their
lodges.  Then the runners went part way out to beckon and to escort
the Sioux in.
</p><p>When the strangers drew near, certain old men met them and
shook hands.  The Sioux at once asked to meet the chiefs and head
men in Council, because they claimed to have had a message of
great import from their nation.
</p><p>Powashik was our chief in those days.  After he had called his
head men together in his lodge, he sent a runner to fetch in the
messengers.  When they came and seated themselves by the
entrance way, Powashik filled four pipes with sacred tobacco, rolled
a live coal into the bowl of each, and then handed a pipe to each of
the Sioux.  You have seen buzzards sitting on the limb of a tree,
how their heads droop, and how still and stiff are their bodies.  That
was the way the Sioux were sitting as they smoked our sacred pipes,
their blankets pulled tightly about their waists and over their
shoulders.  And when they were done smoking, they rose one after
the other and spoke like this:
</p><p>"Our nation sends us to you with this message.  Once upon a
time our young men married your young women, and your young
men married our young women.  We went to war together, and we
were friends, close friends.  We want to see the days when all these
things happened come back again.  So let us stop fighting.  Winter
will soon be here, and neither of us have laid in our buffalo meat.
Our messengers will shake hands with you.  Shake hands with them,
and we will make ready a great feast at our village, two days'
journey by canoe up the river.  And we would ask you to come to
the feast and rejoice with us, because we are once more friends."
<pb n="112"/>

</p><p>Powashik and the old men went out, leaving the Sioux alone in
the lodge.  Many were so glad at heart that they were for shaking
hands with the messengers at once; but some, who in their younger
days had won the scalp-lock and eagle feather in wars with the
Sioux, shook their heads and counselled against haste.  But
Powashik was old and gray.  He was tired of war.  Like most of the
old men, he believed in what the Sioux had told him, so went in and
shook hands with them.  He told them to say to their nation that his
heart was glad, that he wished the things they wished, and that he
and many of his head men would go to the feast.
</p><p>In the morning, the people thronged the shore and the bluffs of
the Mississippi to watch Powashik and twenty of his counsellors
depart for the village of the Sioux.  The old chief and a few of the
older men who were weak with the paddle were in their newest
buckskins, wore black-tipped eagle feathers on their scalp-locks,
and hung beaded and bear-claw necklaces about their necks.  They
took no war-club, no bow, no arrow, no kind of weapon whatever,
because Gisha Munetoa had bade our people long ago never to have
these things about them when on a mission of peace.  But instead of
these things, they had in the canoes tobacco, buckskins, and eagle
feathers, all presents of peace to be given to the Sioux at the feast.
And the people kept watching the canoes till the last turned the big
bend far up the river.
</p><p>On the evening of the second day before it had begun to grow
dark in earnest, Ketona, a young man of twenty winters who had
gone to help paddle his father's canoe, was seen coming toward the
village.  As he drew near, men, women, and children pressed round
about him, eager to know about the feast.  But when they saw that
his leggins and moccasins were torn and spattered with mud, that
his naked body and arms had been gashed by thorns and briers, and
when they noticed that he hung his head and made no reply, and
was making straight for his lodge, they all stopped and gazed after
him with mouths wide open.  Old men leaning upon their canes
crossed fore-fingers over the lips, and, shaking their heads,
murmured one to another, "Something bad!  Something

<pb n="113"/>
bad!"  As Ketona sat with legs crossed before the fire in his lodge
and stared into the flickering blaze with eyes gleaming like those of
a panther at bay, his mother stepped softly near, and, fearing she
would hear something bad, asked, "My son!  My son!  What has
happened?  Why these deep scratches on your body?  How came
these leggins, these moccasins, to be so yellow with mud?"
</p><p>Ketona kept looking steadily into the fire, while the eyes of his
mother were overflowing with tears.  Then she put before him on a
mat some dried venison and a wooden bowl with corn in it, and
begged:
</p><p>"Eat, my son.  You look tired and hungry.  Eat all you want.
There is plenty left for your father.  Tell me, when will he be
home?"
</p><p>Ketona beckoned his mother to sit down beside him.
</p><p>"My father," he began in an undertone, "will never come home
again.  His scalp, and that of old Powashik, and of all who went
away yesterday morning, are hanging to-night in the lodges of the
Sioux.  I am the only one to escape.  My heart is too sick to tell you
how as we turned in shore last evening to camp, the Sioux pounced
upon us as quickly as a hawk upon a dove; how my father yelled to
me then, 'Dive, my son!  Dive!'; and how, shortly after, when I
raised my head above water among the tall reeds under the bank, I
saw two men standing proudly over my father's body, one with a
tomahawk that had crushed in his skull, the other with a knife that
had just taken off his scalp.  Do not weep, mother.  Be brave.  Go
tell the people the little I have told you.  The rest, they will know
later.  Tell them not to fear, for the Sioux are far off now on their
way to the North into the land of the wild rice.  Wait, mother.  Give
me your right hand.  As sure as I am a Red-Earth, as sure as I am an
Eagle, and as sure as I am your son, I will see our nation and you
and me avenged."
</p><p>The runners took up the message of the mother and carried it
from lodge to lodge.  When the women heard it, they gasped, and,
for a time, were speechless.  By and by, slowly gathering their
cloaks about their waists and over their heads, they slipped softly
out of the wigwams; and each going to a lonely spot in the forest or
on the bluffs of the <pb n="114"/>  river, there prayed in silence to Gisha
Munetoa.  But the men on hearing the news said never a word.
Some of them straightened up, clinched their fists, and gritted their
teeth.
</p><p>Two moons had come and gone, and the snow lay deep on the
hills, in the valleys, and in the forest.  One night Nutenwi, the wind,
roared and the snow fell deeper than ever.  Even though the snow
had banked almost half way up the lodges, yet in the morning rumor
flew through all the village that Ketona and fifty young men were
missing, gone no one knew whither.  Each of those fifty young men
had slipped from his wigwam as a fox from his lair, so that even the
nearest kinsman did not know when he had gone.  Runners slid over
the country far and wide upon snow-shoes, but they could find
nowhere the faintest sign of a trail.
</p><p>That was a bitter winter for our nation.  Day and night the
women wept, and the men were sick at heart.  It was hard enough to
lose the old men, but what will become of our nation, they thought,
if we must lose our young men, too?  But the men and the women
were mindful that they were Red-Earth people, and so waited
patiently for the day when their young men would return.
</p><p>And they did return, but not till the snow was melting and the
ice was floating in the rivers.  Forty of them came home.  And the
light of day was never so bright as on the afternoon when the forty
were seen coming in single file down the bluffs of the river toward
the village.  And as they came on, men and boys rushed whooping
from all the lodges, and, gathering round the young men,
accompanied them home.  All the while, the women, the girls, and
the little children waited in groups before their lodges, their hearts
glad, their faces beaming, and all of them proud at seeing long,
black scalps dangling like horse-tails from the belts of the young
warriors.
</p><p>In the night a fire was kindled from a pile of logs in front of
old Powashik's lodge.  The scalp-pole was set up, and on it were
hung the scalps of the Sioux.  And all around within the firelight sat
the men, the women, and the children, all wrapped snugly in
blankets.  Then back and forth and around the pole danced the
young men, stepping to the <pb n="115"/>  time of the drum and of the
war songs sung by the old warriors.  Now and again was a pause in
the dance long enough for one to tell a short story of how he had
taken a scalp.  And when he was done speaking, the chief of his
gens amid the whoops of the old warriors stepped up and gave him
an eagle feather.
</p><p>Last of all to speak was Ketona himself.  He told how he and
the others had slipped into the land of the Sioux, how they had slain
warriors and ripped off their scalps before the very eyes of their
women, and how they had not let up pursuing the Sioux till they had
more than avenged the death of Powashik and that of those slain
with him.  And when the people saw Ketona standing there in the
light of the blaze, holding in his right hand the scalps of the two
Sioux who had slain his father, and in the left was holding the knife
he had plunged into their hearts and had used to rip off their scalps,
they breathed easier and felt that they were beginning to be
avenged.
</p><p>Such, my son, is the story of Ketona as Tacumisawa told it on
the morning he gave you your name.  And I remember so well when
closing he said to us all:
</p><p>"Now, my brother and my sister Eagles, now that this Eaglet
may be brave and do valiant deeds to make him forever
remembered by his people, I name him Ketona.  And when he is old
enough to know this story, this war story of the Eagles, may he wish
to be like the Ketona who winters ago leading fifty young braves
avenged the death of his father and of the leaders of his nation."
</p><p>When Tacumisawa was done, your father stepped over to
where I was and took you from me.  He handed you to Tacumisawa,
who stood you on your wabbling legs, your back against his breast.
Then rose all the Eagles, the men first; and as they filed past you
out of the lodge, they stopped long enough to shake gently this little
right hand of yours.
</p><p>Hish, mother!
</p><p>Yes, my son, that is the tramp of your father's footstep.
</p><p><hi rend="italic">W. Jones.</hi></p>

</div1>
</body>

</text>

</TEI.2>

