<?xml version="1.0"?>

<?dlps id="JosIndi"?>
<?dlps page-images="none" figure-images="no"?>
<?dlps transcription="other"?>

<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/tei-p4/tei2.dtd" [
<!ENTITY % POSTKB "INCLUDE">
<!ENTITY % TEI.extensions.ent SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.ent">
<!ENTITY % TEI.extensions.dtd SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.dtd">
<!ENTITY % ISOnum SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/charent/iso-num.ent"> %ISOnum;
<!ENTITY % ISOlat1 SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/charent/iso-lat1.ent"> %ISOlat1;
<!ENTITY % ISOpub SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/charent/iso-pub.ent"> %ISOpub;

]>
<TEI.2 id="JosIndi">
<teiHeader type="migrated" creator="Etext">
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title type="main">An Indian's Views of Indian Affairs</title>
<title type="sort">indians views of indian affairs</title>
<author>Young Joseph</author>
<respStmt>
<resp>Creation of machine-readable version:</resp>
<name>Judy Boss</name>
<resp>Creation of digital images:</resp>
<name>Electronic Text Center</name>
<resp>Conversion to TEI.2-conformant markup:</resp>
<name>Text prepared by the 1997-98 J. Wallace Sieg Graduate Fellow Lisa Spiro
for the University of Virginia Library Electronic Text Center.</name>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt>
<extent>ca. <num type="kilobytes">57</num> kilobytes</extent>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>University of Virginia Library</publisher>
<pubPlace>Charlottesville, Virginia</pubPlace>
<idno type="ETC">JosIndi</idno>
<date value="1998">1998</date>
<availability status="public">
<p n="copyright">Copyright &copy; 1998 by the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia</p>
<p n="access">Publicly accessible</p>
</availability>
<idno type="uva-pid">uva-lib:476130</idno>
</publicationStmt>
<seriesStmt>
<title>University of Virginia Library, Text collection</title>
<idno type="uva-set">UVA-LIB-Text</idno>
</seriesStmt>
<sourceDesc>
<biblFull>
<titleStmt>
<title type="main">An Indian's Views of Indian Affairs</title>
<title level="j">North American Review, Vol. 128</title>
<title type="sort">indians views of indian affairs</title>
<author>Young Joseph</author>
<respStmt>
<resp>Editor</resp>
<name>William Hare</name>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt>
<extent>412-433</extent>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>D. Appleton and Company</publisher>
<pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
<date value="1879-04">1879, April</date>
<idno type="callNo">Print copy consulted: University of Virginia Library call number AP 2 .N7 v. 128</idno>
</publicationStmt>
<notesStmt>
<note>
<p>This electronic text consists of an introductory piece by William H. Hare, followed by a longer essay by Young Joseph.</p>
</note>
</notesStmt>
</biblFull>
</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc>
<encodingDesc>
<projectDesc>
<p>Prepared for the University of Virginia Library Electronic Text Center.</p>
</projectDesc>
<editorialDecl>
<p>All unambiguous end-of-line hyphens have been removed, and the trailing part of a word has been joined to the preceding line.</p>
<p>The images exist as archived TIFF images, one or more JPEG versions for general use, and thumbnail GIFs.</p>
<p>Some keywords in the header are a local Electronic Text Center scheme to aid in establishing analytical groupings.</p>
</editorialDecl>
</encodingDesc>
<profileDesc>
<creation>
<date value="1879">1879</date>
</creation>
<langUsage>
<language id="eng" usage="main">English</language>
</langUsage>
<textClass>
<keywords>
<term>nonfiction</term>
<term>prose</term>
<term>masculine</term>
<term>Native American</term>
</keywords>
</textClass>
</profileDesc>
<revisionDesc>
<change>
<date value="1998-06">June, 1998</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>corrector</resp>
<name>Lisa Spiro, Electronic Text Center</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Added TEI header and tags.</item>
</change>
<change>
<date value="2005-07">July 2005</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>Corrector</resp>
<name>John Ivor Carlson</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Converted to XML and/or checked tags.</item>
</change>
<change>
<date value="2007-09">September 2007</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>Migration</resp>
<name>Ethan Gruber, University of Virginia Library</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Converted XML markup from TEI Lite to uva-dl-tei (TEI P4 with local customizations).</item>
</change>
<change>
<date value="2008-01">January 2008</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>Migration</resp>
<name>Greg Murray, University of Virginia Library</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Programmatically updated TEI header markup (but not header content) for minimal compliance with current QA requirements.</item>
</change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>
<text id="d1">
<body id="d2">

<div1 type="introduction" id="d3"> <pb n="412"/>
<head>
VII.<lb/>
AN INDIAN'S VIEWS OF INDIAN AFFAIRS.<lb/>
INTRODUCTION.
</head>

<p>I WISH that I had words at command in which to express
adequately the interest with which I have read the extraordinary
narrative which follows, and which I have the privilege of
introducing to the readers of this "Review."  I feel, however, that
this <hi rend="italic">apologia</hi> is so boldly marked by the charming
 <hi rend="italic">na&iuml;vet&eacute;</hi> and tender pathos which characterize
the red-man, that it needs no introduction, much less any
authentication; while in its smothered fire, in its deep sense of
eternal righteousness and of present evil, and in its hopeful
longings for the coming of a better time, this Indian chief's appeal
reminds us of one of the old Hebrew prophets of the days of the
captivity.
</p><p>I have no special knowledge of the history of the Nez
Perc&eacute;s, the Indians whose tale of sorrow Chief Joseph so
pathetically tells &mdash; my Indian missions lying in a part at the West
quite distant from their old home &mdash; and am not competent to judge
their case upon its merits.  The chief's narrative is, of course, <hi rend="italic">ex
parte</hi>, and many of his statements would no doubt be ardently
disputed.  General Howard, for instance, can hardly receive justice
at his hands, so well known is he for his friendship to the Indian and
for his distinguished success in pacifying some of the most
desperate.
</p><p>It should be remembered, too, in justice to the army, that it is
rarely called upon to interfere in Indian affairs until the relations
between the Indians and the whites have reached a desperate
condition, and when the situation of affairs has become so involved
and feeling on both sides runs so high that perhaps only more than
human forbearance would attempt to solve the difficulty by
disentangling the knot and not by cutting it.
</p><p>Nevertheless, the chief's narrative is marked by so much candor,

    <pb n="413"/>
and so careful is he to qualify his statements, when
qualification seems necessary, that every reader will give him credit
for speaking his honest, even should they be thought by some to be
mistaken, convictions.  The chief, in his treatment of his defense,
reminds one of those lawyers of whom we have heard that their
splendid success was gained, not by disputation, but simply by their
lucid and straightforward statement of their case.  That he is
something of a strategist as well as an advocate appears from this
description of an event which occurred shortly after the breaking
out of hostilities: "We crossed over Salmon River, hoping General
Howard would follow.  We were not disappointed.  He did follow
us, and we got between him and his supplies, and cut him off for
three days."  Occasionally the reader comes upon touches of those
sentiments and feelings which at once establish a sense of kinship
between all who possess them.  Witness his description of his
desperate attempt to rejoin his wife and children when a sudden
dash of General Miles's soldiers had cut the Indian camp in two:
"About seventy men, myself among them, were cut off. . . .  I
thought of my wife and children, who were now surrounded by
soldiers, and I resolved to go to them.  With a prayer in my mouth
to the Great Spirit Chief who rules above, I dashed unarmed
through the line of soldiers. . . .  My clothes were cut to pieces, my
horse was wounded, but I was not hurt."  And again, when he
speaks of his father's death: "I saw he was dying.  I took his hand in
mine.  He said: 'My son, my body is returning to my mother Earth,
and my spirit is going very soon to see the Great Spirit Chief. . . .  A
few more years and the white men will be all around you.  They
have their eyes on this land.  My son, never forget my dying words.
This country holds your father's body &mdash; never sell the bones of your
father and your mother.'  I pressed my father's hand, and told him I
would protect his grave with my life.  My father smiled, and passed
away to the spirit-land.  I buried him in that beautiful valley of
Winding Waters.  I love that land more than all the rest of the
world.  A man who would not love his father's grave is worse than a
wild animal."
</p><p>His appeals to the natural rights of man are surprisingly fine,
and, however some may despise them as the utterances of an Indian,
they are just those which, in our Declaration of Independence, have
been most admired.  "We are all sprung from a woman," he says,
"although we are unlike in many things.  You are as you were made,
and, as you were made, you can remain.

   <pb n="414"/>

We are just as we were made by the Great Spirit, and you can not
change us: then, why should children of one mother quarrel?  Why
should one try to cheat another?  I do not believe that the Great
Spirit Chief gave one kind of men the right to tell another kind of
men what they must do."

</p><p>But I will not detain the readers of the "Review" from the
pleasure of perusing for themselves Chief Joseph's statement longer
than is necessary to express the hope that those who have time for
no more will at least read its closing paragraph, and to remark that
the narrative brings clearly out these facts which ought to be
regarded as well-recognized principles in dealing with the red-man:
</p><p>1.  The folly of any mode of treatment of the Indian which is
not based upon a cordial and operative acknowledgment of his
rights as our <hi rend="italic">fellow man</hi>.
</p><p>2.  The danger of riding rough-shod over a people who are
capable of high enthusiasm, who know and value their national
rights, and are brave enough to defend them.
</p><p>3.  The liability to want of harmony between different
departments and different officials of our complex Government,
from which it results that, while many promises are made to the
Indians, few of them are kept.  It is a home-thrust when Chief
Joseph says: "The white people have too many chiefs.  They do not
understand each other. . . .  I can not understand how the
Government sends a man out to fight us, as it did General Miles,
and then break his word.  Such a Government has something wrong
about it."
</p><p>4.  The unwisdom, in most cases in dealing with Indians, of
what may be termed <hi rend="italic">military short-cuts</hi>, instead of patient
discussion, explanations, persuasion, and reasonable concessions.
</p><p>5.  The absence in an Indian tribe of any truly representative
body competent to make a treaty which shall be binding upon all the
bands.  The failure to recognize this fact has been the source of
endless difficulties.  Chief Joseph, in this case, did not consider a
treaty binding which his band had not agreed to, no matter how
many other bands had signed it; and so it has been in many other
cases.
</p><p>6.  Indian chiefs, however able and influential, are really
without power, and for this reason, as well as others, the Indians,
when by the march of events they are brought into intimate relations
with the whites, should at the earliest practicable moment be given
the support and protection of our Government and of our law; not

   <pb n="415"/>

<hi rend="italic">local</hi> law, however, which is apt to be the result of
<hi rend="italic">special</hi> legislation, adopted solely in the interest of the
stronger race.

</p>

<closer>
<signed><name type="person">WILLIAM H. HARE</name>,
 <hi rend="italic">Missionary Bishop of Niobrara.</hi>
</signed>
</closer>
</div1>


<div1 type="essay" id="d4">

<p>MY friends, I have been asked to show you my heart.  I am glad
to have a chance to do so.  I want the white people to understand my
people.  Some of you think an Indian is like a wild animal.  This is a
great mistake.  I will tell you all about our people, and then you can
judge whether an Indian is a man or not.  I believe much trouble and
blood would be saved if we opened our hearts more.  I will tell you
in my way how the Indian sees things.  The white man has more
words to tell you how they look to him, but it does not require many
words to speak the truth.  What I have to say will come from my
heart, and I will speak with a straight tongue.  Ah-cum-kin-i-ma-me-hut (the Great Spirit) is looking at me, and will hear me.
</p><p>My name is In-mut-too-yah-lat-lat (Thunder traveling over the
Mountains).  I am chief of the Wal-lam-wat-kin band of Chute-pa-lu, or Nez Perc&eacute;s (nose-pierced Indians).  I was born in
eastern Oregon, thirty-eight winters ago.  My father was chief
before me.  When a young man, he was called Joseph by Mr.
Spaulding, a missionary.  He died a few years ago.  There was no
stain on his hands of the blood of a white man.  He left a good name
on the earth.  He advised me well for my people.
</p><p>Our fathers gave us many laws, which they had learned from
their fathers.  These laws were good.  They told us to treat all men
as they treated us; that we should never be the first to break a
bargain; that it was a disgrace to tell a lie; that we should speak only
the truth; that it was a shame for one man to take from another his
wife, or his property without paying for it.  We were taught to
believe that the Great Spirit sees and hears everything, and that he
never forgets; that hereafter he will give every man a spirit-home
according to his deserts: if he has been a good man, he will have a
good home; if he has been a bad man, he will have a bad home.
This I believe, and all my people believe the same.
</p><p>We did not know there were other people besides the Indian
until about one hundred winters ago, when some men with white
faces came to our country.  They brought many things with them to
trade for furs and skins.  They brought tobacco, which was new to
us.  They brought guns with flint stones on them, which fright-
   <pb n="416"/>

tened our women and children.  Our people could not talk with
these white-faced men, but they used signs which all people
understand.  These men were Frenchmen, and they called our
people "Nez Perc&eacute;s," because they wore rings in their noses
for ornaments.  Although very few of our people wear them now,
we are still called by the same name.  These French trappers said a
great many things to our fathers, which have been planted in our
hearts.  Some were good for us, but some were bad.  Our people
were divided in opinion about these men.  Some thought they taught
more bad than good.  An Indian respects a brave man, but he
despises a coward.  He loves a straight tongue, but he hates a forked
tongue.  The French trappers told us some truths and some lies.
</p><p>The first white men of your people who came to our country
were named Lewis and Clarke.  They also brought many things that
our people had never seen.  They talked straight, and our people
gave them a great feast, as a proof that their hearts were friendly.
These men were very kind.  They made presents to our chiefs and
our people made presents to them.  We had a great many horses, of
which we gave them what they needed, and they gave us guns and
tobacco in return.  All the Nez Perc&eacute;s made friends with
Lewis and Clarke, and agreed to let them pass through their country,
and never to make war on white men.  This promise the Nez
Perc&eacute;s have never broken.  No white man can accuse them
of bad faith, and speak with a straight tongue.  It has always been
the pride of the Nez Perc&eacute;s that they were the friends of the
white men.  When my father was a young man there came to our
country a white man (Rev. Mr. Spaulding) who talked spirit law.
He won the affections of our people because he spoke good things
to them.  At first he did not say anything about white men wanting
to settle on our lands.  Nothing was said about that until about
twenty winters ago, when a number of white people came into our
country and built houses and made farms.  At first our people made
no complaint.  They thought there was room enough for all to live
in peace, and they were learning many things from the white men
that seemed to be good.  But we soon found that the white men
were growing rich very fast, and were greedy to possess everything
the Indian had.  My father was the first to see through the schemes
of the white men, and he warned his tribe to be careful about trading
with them.  He had suspicion of men who seemed so anxious to
make money.  I was a boy then, but I remember well my father's
caution.  He had sharper eyes than the rest of our people.

   <pb n="417"/>

</p><p>Next there came a white officer (Governor Stevens), who
invited all the Nez Perc&eacute;s to a treaty council.  After the
council was opened he made known his heart.  He said there were a
great many white people in the country, and many more would
come; that he wanted the land marked out so that the Indians and
white men could be separated.  If they were to live in peace it was
necessary, he said, that the Indians should have a country set apart
for them, and in that country they must stay.  My father, who
represented his band, refused to have anything to do with the
council, because he wished to be a free man.  He claimed that no
man owned any part of the earth, and a man could not sell what he
did not own.
</p><p>Mr. Spaulding took hold of my father's arm and said, "Come
and sign the treaty."  My father pushed him away, and said: "Why
do you ask me to sign away my country?  It is your business to talk
to us about spirit matters, and not to talk to us about parting with
our land."  Governor Stevens urged my father to sign his treaty, but
he refused.  "I will not sign your paper," he said; "you go where you
please, so do I; you are not a child, I am no child; I can think for
myself.  No man can think for me.  I have no other home than this.
I will not give it up to any man.  My people would have no home.
Take away your paper.  I will not touch it with my hand."
</p><p>My father left the council.  Some of the chiefs of the other
bands of the Nez Perc&eacute;s signed the treaty, and then
Governor Stevens gave them presents of blankets.  My father
cautioned his people to take no presents, for "after a while," he said,
"they will claim that you have accepted pay for your country."
Since that time four bands of the Nez Perc&eacute;s have received
annuities from the United States.  My father was invited to many
councils, and they tried hard to make him sign the treaty, but he was
firm as the rock, and would not sign away his home.  His refusal
caused a difference among the Nez Perc&eacute;s.
</p><p>Eight years later (1863) was the next treaty council.  A chief
called Lawyer, because he was a great talker, took the lead in this
council, and sold nearly all the Nez Perc&eacute;s country.  My
father was not there.  He said to me: "When you go into council
with the white man, always remember your country.  Do not give it
away.  The white man will cheat you out of your home.  I have
taken no pay from the United States.  I have never sold our land."
In this treaty Lawyer acted without authority from our band.  He
had no right to sell the Wallowa (<hi rend="italic">winding water</hi>) country.
That

   <pb n="418"/>

had always belonged to my father's own people, and the other bands
had never disputed our right to it.  No other Indians ever claimed
Wallowa.
</p><p>In order to have all people understand how much land we
owned, my father planted poles around it and said:
</p><p>"Inside is the home of my people &mdash; the white man may take
the land outside.  Inside this boundary all our people were born.  It
circles around the graves of our fathers, and we will never give up
these graves to any man."
</p><p>The United States claimed they had bought all the Nez
Perc&eacute;s country outside of Lapwai Reservation, from Lawyer
and other chiefs, but we continued to live on this land in peace until
eight years ago, when white men began to come inside the bounds
my father had set.  We warned them against this great wrong, but
they would not leave our land, and some bad blood was raised.  The
white men represented that we were going upon the war-path.  They
reported many things that were false.
</p><p>The United States Government again asked for a treaty
council.  My father had become blind and feeble.  He could no
longer speak for his people.  It was then that I took my father's place
as chief.  In this council I made my first speech to white men.  I said
to the agent who held the council:
</p><p>"I did not want to come to this council, but I came hoping that
we could save blood.  The white man has no right to come here and
take our country.  We have never accepted any presents from the
Government.  Neither Lawyer nor any other chief had authority to
sell this land.  It has always belonged to my people.  It came
unclouded to them from our fathers, and we will defend this land as
long as a drop of Indian blood warms the hearts of our men."
</p><p>The agent said he had orders, from the Great White Chief at
Washington, for us to go upon the Lapwai Reservation, and that if
we obeyed he would help us in many ways.  "You <hi rend="italic">must</hi>
move to the agency," he said.  I answered him: "I will not.  I do not
need your help; we have plenty, and we are contented and happy if
the white man will let us alone.  The reservation is too small for so
many people with all their stock.  You can keep your presents; we
can go to your towns and pay for all we need; we have plenty of
horses and cattle to sell, and we won't have any help from you; we
are free now; we can go where we please.  Our fathers were born
here.  Here they lived, here they died, here are their graves.  We

   <pb n="419"/>

will never leave them."  The agent went away, and we had peace for
a little while.
</p><p>Soon after this my father sent for me.  I saw he was dying.  I
took his hand in mine.  He said: "My son, my body is returning to
my mother earth, and my spirit is going very soon to see the Great
Spirit Chief.  When I am gone, think of your country.  You are the
chief of these people.  They look to you to guide them.  Always
remember that your father never sold his country.  You must stop
your ears whenever you are asked to sign a treaty selling your home.
A few years more, and white men will be all around you.  They
have their eyes on this land.  My son, never forget my dying words.
This country holds your father's body.  Never sell the bones of your
father and your mother."  I pressed my father's hand and told him I
would protect his grave with my life.  My father smiled and passed
away to the spirit-land.
</p><p>I buried him in that beautiful valley of winding waters.  I love
that land more than all the rest of the world.  A man who would not
love his father's grave is worse than a wild animal.
</p><p>For a short time we lived quietly.  But this could not last.
White men had found gold in the mountains around the land of
winding water.  They stole a great many horses from us, and we
could not get them back because we were Indians.  The white men
told lies for each other.  They drove off a great many of our cattle.
Some white men branded our young cattle so they could claim
them.  We had no friend who would plead our cause before the law
councils.  It seemed to me that some of the white men in Wallowa
were doing these things on purpose to get up a war.  They knew that
we were not strong enough to fight them.  I labored hard to avoid
trouble and bloodshed.  We gave up some of our country to the
white men, thinking that then we could have peace.  We were
mistaken.  The white man would not let us alone.  We could have
avenged our wrongs many times, but we did not.  Whenever the
Government has asked us to help them against other Indians, we
have never refused.  When the white men were few and we were
strong we could have killed them all off, but the Nez Perc&eacute;s
wished to live at peace.
</p><p>If we have not done so, we have not been to blame.  I believe
that the old treaty has never been correctly reported.  If we ever
owned the land we own it still, for we never sold it.  In the treaty
councils the commissioners have claimed that our country had been
sold to the Government.  Suppose a white man should come to me

   <pb n="420"/>

and say, "Joseph, I like your horses, and I want to buy them."  I say
to him, "No, my horses suit me, I will not sell them."  Then he goes
to my neighbor, and says to him: "Joseph has some good horses.  I
want to buy them, but he refuses to sell."  My neighbor answers,
"Pay me the money, and I will sell you Joseph's horses."  The white
man returns to me, and says, "Joseph, I have bought your horses,
and you must let me have them."  If we sold our lands to the
Government, this is the way they were bought.
</p><p>On account of the treaty made by the other bands of the Nez
Perc&eacute;s, the white men claimed my lands.  We were troubled
greatly by white men crowding over the line.  Some of these were
good men, and we lived on peaceful terms with them, but they were
not all good.
</p><p>Nearly every year the agent came over from Lapwai and
ordered us on to the reservation.  We always replied that we were
satisfied to live in Wallowa.  We were careful to refuse the presents
or annuities which he offered.
</p><p>Through all the years since the white men came to Wallowa we
have been threatened and taunted by them and the treaty Nez
Perc&eacute;s.  They have given us no rest.  We have had a few
good friends among white men, and they have always advised my
people to bear these taunts without fighting.  Our young men were
quick-tempered, and I have had great trouble in keeping them from
doing rash things.  I have carried a heavy load on my back ever
since I was a boy.  I learned then that we were but few, while the
white men were many, and that we could not hold our own with
them.  We were like deer.  They were like grizzly bears.  We had a
small country.  Their country was large.  We were contented to let
things remain as the Great Spirit Chief made them.  They were not;
and would change the rivers and mountains if they did not suit
them.
</p><p>Year after year we have been threatened, but no war was made
upon my people until General Howard came to our country two
years ago and told us that he was the white war-chief of all that
country.  He said: "I have a great many soldiers at my back.  I am
going to bring them up here, and then I will talk to you again.  I will
not let white men laugh at me the next time I come.  The country
belongs to the Government, and I intend to make you go upon the
reservation."
</p><p>I remonstrated with him against bringing more soldiers to the
Nez Perc&eacute;s country.  He had one house full of troops all the
time at Fort Lapwai.

   <pb n="421"/>

</p><p>The next spring the agent at Umatilla agency sent an Indian
runner to tell me to meet General Howard at Walla Walla.  I could
not go myself, but I sent my brother and five other head men to
meet him, and they had a long talk.
</p><p>General Howard said: "You have talked straight, and it is all
right.  You can stay in Wallowa."  He insisted that my brother and
his company should go with him to Fort Lapwai.  When the party
arrived there General Howard sent out runners and called all the
Indians in to a grand council.  I was in that council.  I said to
General Howard, "We are ready to listen."  He answered that he
would not talk then, but would hold a council next day, when he
would talk plainly.  I said to General Howard: "I am ready to talk
to-day.  I have been in a great many councils, but I am no wiser.
We are all sprung from a woman, although we are unlike in many
things.  We can not be made over again.  You are as you were made,
and as you were made, you can remain.  We are just as we were
made by the Great Spirit, and you can not change us; then why
should children of one mother and one father quarrel &mdash; why should
one try to cheat the other?  I do not believe that the Great Spirit
Chief gave one kind of men the right to tell another kind of men
what they must do."
</p><p>General Howard replied: "You deny my authority, do you?
You want to dictate to me, do you?"
</p><p>Then one of my chiefs &mdash; Too-hool-hool-suit &mdash; rose in the
council and said to General Howard: "The Great Spirit Chief made
the world as it is, and as he wanted it, and he made a part of it for us
to live upon.  I do not see where you get authority to say that we
shall not live where he placed us."
</p><p>General Howard lost his temper and said: "Shut up!  I don't
want to hear any more of such talk.  The law says you shall go upon
the reservation to live, and I want you to do so, but you persist in
disobeying the law" (meaning the treaty).  "If you do not move, I
will take the matter into my own hand, and make you suffer for
your disobedience."
</p><p>Too-hool-hool-suit answered: "Who are you, that you ask us to
talk, and then tell me I sha'n't talk?  Are you the Great Spirit?  Did
you make the world?  Did you make the sun?  Did you make the
rivers to run for us to drink?  Did you make the grass to grow?  Did
you make all these things, that you talk to us as though we were
boys?  If you did, then you have the right to talk as you do."

   <pb n="422"/>

</p><p>General Howard replied, "You are an impudent fellow, and I
will put you in the guard-house," and then ordered a soldier to arrest
him.
</p><p>Too-hool-hool-suit made no resistance.  He asked General
Howard: "Is that your order?  I don't care.  I have expressed my
heart to you.  I have nothing to take back.  I have spoken for my
country.  You can arrest me, but you can not change me or make me
take back what I have said."
</p><p>The soldiers came forward and seized my friend and took him
to the guard-house.  My men whispered among themselves whether
they should let this thing be done.  I counseled them to submit.  I
knew if we resisted that all the white men present, including
General Howard would be killed in a moment, and we would be
blamed.  If I had said nothing, General Howard would never have
given another unjust order against my men.  I saw the danger, and,
while they dragged Too-hool-hool-suit to prison, I arose and said:
<hi rend="italic">"I am going to talk now</hi>.  I don't care whether you arrest me
or not."  I turned to my people and said: "The arrest of Too-hool-hool-suit was wrong, but we will not resent the insult.  We were
invited to this council to express our hearts, and we have done so."
Too-hool-hool-suit was prisoner for five days before he was
released.
</p><p>The council broke up for that day.  On the next morning
General Howard came to my lodge, and invited me to go with him
and White-Bird and Looking-Glass, to look for land for my people.
As we rode along we came to some good land that was already
occupied by Indians and white people.  General Howard, pointing to
this land, said: "If you will come on to the reservation, I will give
you these lands and move these people off."
</p><p>I replied: "No.  It would be wrong to disturb these people.  I
have no right to take their homes.  I have never taken what did not
belong to me.  I will not now."
</p><p>We rode all day upon the reservation, and found no good land
unoccupied.  I have been informed by men who do not lie that
General Howard sent a letter that night, telling the soldiers at Walla
Walla to go to Wallowa Valley, and drive us out upon our return
home.
</p><p>In the council, next day, General Howard informed me, in a
haughty spirit, that he would give my people <hi rend="italic">thirty days</hi> to
go back home, collect all their stock, and move on to the
reservation, saying, "If you are not here in that time, I shall consider
that you want to fight, and will send my soldiers to drive you on."

   <pb n="423"/>

</p><p>I said: "War can be avoided, and it ought to be avoided.  I want
no war.  My people have always been the friends of the white man.
Why are you in such a hurry?  I can not get ready to move in thirty
days.  Our stock is scattered, and Snake River is very high.  Let us
wait until fall, then the river will be low.  We want time to hunt up
our stock and gather supplies for winter."
</p><p>General Howard replied, "If you let the time run over one day,
the soldiers will be there to drive you on to the reservation, and all
your cattle and horses outside of the reservation at that time will fall
into the hands of the white men."
</p><p>I knew I had never sold my country, and that I had no land in
Lapwai; but I did not want bloodshed.  I did not want my people
killed.  I did not want anybody killed.  Some of my people had been
murdered by white men, and the white murderers were never
punished for it.  I told General Howard about this, and again said I
wanted no war.  I wanted the people who lived upon the lands I was
to occupy at Lapwai to have time to gather their harvest.
</p><p>I said in my heart that, rather than have war, I would give up
my country.  I would give up my father's grave.  I would give up
everything rather than have the blood of white men upon the hands
of my people.
</p><p>General Howard refused to allow me more than thirty days to
move my people and their stock.  I am sure that he began to prepare
for war at once.
</p><p>When I returned to Wallowa I found my people very much
excited upon discovering that the soldiers were already in the
Wallowa Valley.  We held a council, and decided to move
immediately, to avoid bloodshed.
</p><p>Too-hool-hool-suit, who felt outraged by his imprisonment,
talked for war, and made many of my young men willing to fight
rather than be driven like dogs from the land where they were born.
He declared that blood alone would wash out the disgrace General
Howard had put upon him.  It required a strong heart to stand up
against such talk, but I urged my people to be quiet, and not to begin
a war.
</p><p>We gathered all the stock we could find, and made an attempt
to move.  We left many of our horses and cattle in Wallowa, and we
lost several hundred in crossing the river.  All of my people
succeeded in getting across in safety.  Many of the Nez
Perc&eacute;s came together in Rocky Ca&ntilde;on to hold a
grand council.  I went with all my people.  This council lasted ten
days.  There was a

   <pb n="424"/>

great deal of war-talk, and a great deal of excitement.  There was
one young brave present whose father had been killed by a white
man five years before.  This man's blood was bad against white
men, and he left the council calling for revenge.
</p><p>Again I counseled peace, and I thought the danger was past.
We had not complied with General Howard's order because we
could not, but we intended to do so as soon as possible.  I was
leaving the council to kill beef for my family, when news came that
the young man whose father had been killed had gone out with
several other hot-blooded young braves and killed four white men.
He rode up to the council and shouted: "Why do you sit here like
women?  The war has begun already."  I was deeply grieved.  All
the lodges were moved except my brother's and my own.  I saw
clearly that the war was upon us when I learned that my young men
had been secretly buying ammunition.  I heard then that
Too-hool-hool-suit, who had been imprisoned by General Howard, had
succeeded in organizing a war-party.  I knew that their acts would
involve all my people.  I saw that the war could not then be
prevented.  The time had passed.  I counseled peace from the
beginning.  I knew that we were too weak to fight the United States.
We had many grievances, but I knew that war would bring more.
We had good white friends, who advised us against taking the war-path.
My friend and brother, Mr. Chapman, who has been with us
since the surrender, told us just how the war would end.  Mr.
Chapman took sides against us, and helped General Howard.  I do
not blame him for doing so.  He tried hard to prevent bloodshed.
We hoped the white settlers would not join the soldiers.  Before the
war commenced we had discussed this matter all over, and many of
my people were in favor of warning them that if they took no part
against us they should not be molested in the event of war being
begun by General Howard.  This plan was voted down in the
war-council.
</p><p>There were bad men among my people who had quarreled
with white men, and they talked of their wrongs until they roused all
the bad hearts in the council.  Still I could not believe that they
would begin the war.  I know that my young men did a great wrong,
but I ask, Who was first to blame?  They had been insulted a
thousand times; their fathers and brothers had been killed; their
mothers and wives had been disgraced; they had been driven to
madness by whisky sold to them by white men; they had been told
by General Howard that all their horses and cattle which

   <pb n="425"/>

they had been unable to drive out of Wallowa were to fall into the
hands of white men; and, added to all this, they were homeless and
desperate.
</p><p>I would have given my own life if I could have undone the
killing of white men by my people.  I blame my young men and I
blame the white men.  I blame General Howard for not giving my
people time to get their stock away from Wallowa.  I do not
acknowledge that he had the right to order me to leave Wallowa at
any time.  I deny that either my father or myself ever sold that land.
It is still our land.  It may never again be our home, but my father
sleeps there, and I love it as I love my mother.  I left there, hoping
to avoid bloodshed.
</p><p>If General Howard had given me plenty of time to gather up
my stock, and treated Too-hool-hool-suit as a man should be
treated, there <hi rend="italic">would have been no war</hi>.
</p><p>My friends among white men have blamed me for the war.  I
am not to blame.  When my young men began the killing, my heart
was hurt.  Although I did not justify them, I remembered all the
insults I had endured, and my blood was on fire.  Still I would have
taken my people to the buffalo country without fighting, if possible.
</p><p>I could see no other way to avoid a war.  We moved over to
White Bird Creek, sixteen miles away, and there encamped,
intending to collect our stock before leaving; but the soldiers
attacked us, and the first battle was fought.  We numbered in that
battle sixty men, and the soldiers a hundred.  The fight lasted but a
few minutes, when the soldiers retreated before us for twelve miles.
They lost thirty-three killed, and had seven wounded.  When an
Indian fights, he only shoots to kill; but soldiers shoot at random.
None of the soldiers were scalped.  We do not believe in scalping,
nor in killing wounded men.  Soldiers do not kill many Indians
unless they are wounded and left upon the battle-field.  Then they
kill Indians.
</p><p>Seven days after the first battle, General Howard arrived in the
Nez Perc&eacute;s country, bringing seven hundred more soldiers.
It was now war in earnest.  We crossed over Salmon River, hoping
General Howard would follow.  We were not disappointed.  He did
follow us, and we got back between him and his supplies, and cut
him off for three days.  He sent out two companies to open the way.
We attacked them, killing one officer, two guides, and ten men.

   <pb n="426"/>

</p><p>We withdrew, hoping the soldiers would follow, but they had
got fighting enough for that day.  They intrenched themselves, and
next day we attacked them again.  The battle lasted all day, and was
renewed next morning.  We killed four and wounded seven or eight.
</p><p>About this time General Howard found out that we were in his
rear.  Five days later he attacked us with three hundred and fifty
soldiers and settlers.  We had two hundred and fifty warriors.  The
fight lasted twenty-seven hours.  We lost four killed and several
wounded.  General Howard's loss was twenty-nine men killed and
sixty wounded.
</p><p>The following day the soldiers charged upon us, and we
retreated with our families and stock a few miles, leaving eighty
lodges to fall into General Howard's hands.
</p><p>Finding that we were outnumbered, we retreated to Bitter Root
Valley.  Here another body of soldiers came upon us and demanded
our surrender.  We refused.  They said, "You can not get by us."
We answered, "We are going by you without fighting if you will let
us, but we are going by you anyhow."  We then made a treaty with
these soldiers.  We agreed not to molest any one, and they agreed
that we might pass through the Bitter Root country in peace.  We
bought provisions and traded stock with white men there.
</p><p>We understood that there was to be no more war.  We intended
to go peaceably to the buffalo country, and leave the question of
returning to our country to be settled afterward.
</p><p>With this understanding we traveled on for four days, and,
thinking that the trouble was all over, we stopped and prepared tent-poles
to take with us.  We started again, and at the end of two days
we saw three white men passing our camp.  Thinking that peace had
been made, we did not molest them.  We could have killed or taken
them prisoners, but we did not suspect them of being spies, which
they were.
</p><p>That night the soldiers surrounded our camp.  About daybreak
one of my men went out to look after his horses.  The soldiers saw
him and shot him down like a coyote.  I have since learned that
these soldiers were not those we had left behind.  They had come
upon us from another direction.  The new white war-chief's name
was Gibbon.  He charged upon us while some of my people were
still asleep.  We had a hard fight.  Some of my men crept around
and attacked the soldiers from the rear.  In this battle we lost nearly
all our lodges, but we finally drove General Gibbon back.

   <pb n="427"/>

</p><p>Finding that he was not able to capture us, he sent to his camp
a few miles away for his big guns (cannons), but my men had
captured them and all the ammunition.  We damaged the big guns
all we could, and carried away the powder and lead.  In the fight
with General Gibbon we lost fifty women and children and thirty
fighting men.  We remained long enough to bury our dead.  The Nez
Perc&eacute;s never make war on women and children; we could
have killed a great many women and children while the war lasted,
but we would feel ashamed to do so cowardly an act.
</p><p>We never scalp our enemies, but when General Howard came
up and joined General Gibbon, their Indian scouts dug up our dead
and scalped them.  I have been told that General Howard did not
order this great shame to be done.
</p><p>We retreated as rapidly as we could toward the buffalo
country.  After six days General Howard came close to us, and we
went out and attacked him, and captured nearly all his horses and
mules (about two hundred and fifty head).  We then marched on to
the Yellowstone Basin.
</p><p>On the way we captured one white man and two white women.
We released them at the end of three days.  They were treated
kindly.  The women were not insulted.  Can the white soldiers tell
me of one time when Indian women were taken prisoners, and held
three days and then released without being insulted?  Were the Nez
Perc&eacute;s women who fell into the hands of General Howard's
soldiers treated with as much respect?  I deny that a Nez
Perc&eacute; was ever guilty of such a crime.
</p><p>A few days later we captured two more white men.  One of
them stole a horse and escaped.  We gave the other a poor horse and
told him he was free.
</p><p>Nine days' march brought us to the mouth of Clarke's Fork of
the Yellowstone.  We did not know what had become of General
Howard, but we supposed that he had sent for more horses and
mules.  He did not come up, but another new war-chief (General
Sturgis) attacked us.  We held him in check while we moved all our
women and children and stock out of danger, leaving a few men to
cover our retreat.
</p><p>Several days passed, and we heard nothing of General Howard,
or Gibbon, or Sturgis.  We had repulsed each in turn, and began to
feel secure, when another army, under General Miles, struck us.
This was the fourth army, each of which outnumbered our fighting
force, that we had encountered within sixty days.

   <pb n="428"/>

</p><p>We had no knowledge of General Miles's army until a short
time before he made a charge upon us, cutting our camp in two, and
capturing nearly all of our horses.  About seventy men, myself
among them, were cut off.  My little daughter, twelve years of age,
was with me.  I gave her a rope, and told her to catch a horse and
join the others who were cut off from the camp.  I have not seen her
since, but I have learned that she is alive and well.
</p><p>I thought of my wife and children, who were now surrounded
by soldiers, and I resolved to go to them or die.  With a prayer in my
mouth to the Great Spirit Chief who rules above, I dashed unarmed
through the line of soldiers.  It seemed to me that there were guns
on every side, before and behind me.  My clothes were cut to pieces
and my horse was wounded, but I was not hurt.  As I reached the
door of my lodge, my wife handed me my rifle, saying: "Here's your
gun.  Fight!"
</p><p>The soldiers kept up a continuous fire.  Six of my men were
killed in one spot near me.  Ten or twelve soldiers charged into our
camp and got possession of two lodges, killing three Nez
Perc&eacute;s and losing three of their men, who fell inside our
lines.  I called my men to drive them back.  We fought at close
range, not more than twenty steps apart, and drove the soldiers back
upon their main line, leaving their dead in our hands.  We secured
their arms and ammunition.  We lost, the first day and night,
eighteen men and three women.  General Miles lost twenty-six
killed and forty wounded.  The following day General Miles sent a
messenger into my camp under protection of a white flag.  I sent my
friend Yellow Bull to meet him.
</p><p>Yellow Bull understood the messenger to say that General
Miles wished me to consider the situation; that he did not want to
kill my people unnecessarily.  Yellow Bull understood this to be a
demand for me to surrender and save blood.  Upon reporting this
message to me, Yellow Bull said he wondered whether General
Miles was in earnest.  I sent him back with my answer, that I had
not made up my mind, but would think about it and send word soon.
A little later he sent some Cheyenne scouts with another message.  I
went out to meet them.  They said they believed that General Miles
was sincere and really wanted peace.  I walked on to General
Miles's tent.  He met me and we shook hands.  He said, "Come, let
us sit down by the fire and talk this matter over."  I remained with
him all night; next morning Yellow Bull came over to see if I was
alive, and why I did not return.

   <pb n="429"/>

</p><p>General Miles would not let me leave the tent to see my friend
alone.
</p><p>Yellow Bull said to me: "They have got you in their power,
and I am afraid they will never let you go again.  I have an officer in
our camp, and I will hold him until they let you go free."
</p><p>I said: "I do not know what they mean to do with me, but if
they kill me you must not kill the officer.  It will do no good to
avenge my death by killing him."
</p><p>Yellow Bull returned to my camp.  I did not make any
agreement that day with General Miles.  The battle was renewed
while I was with him.  I was very anxious about my people.  I knew
that we were near Sitting Bull's camp in King George's land, and I
thought maybe the Nez Perc&eacute;s who had escaped would
return with assistance.  No great damage was done to either party
during the night.
</p><p>On the following morning I returned to my camp by
agreement, meeting the officer who had been held a prisoner in my
camp at the flag of truce.  My people were divided about
surrendering.  We could have escaped from Bear Paw Mountain if
we had left our wounded, old women, and children behind.  We
were unwilling to do this.  We had never heard of a wounded Indian
recovering while in the hands of white men.
</p><p>On the evening of the fourth day General Howard came in
with a small escort, together with my friend Chapman.  We could
now talk understandingly.  General Miles said to me in plain words,
"If you will come out and give up your arms, I will spare your lives
and send you to your reservation."  I do not know what passed
between General Miles and General Howard.
</p><p>I could not bear to see my wounded men and women suffer
any longer; we had lost enough already.  General Miles had
promised that we might return to our own country with what stock
we had left.  I thought we could start again.  I believed General
Miles, or <hi rend="italic">I never would have surrendered</hi>.  I have heard that
he has been censured for making the promise to return us to Lapwai.
He could not have made any other terms with me at that time.  I
would have held him in check until my friends came to my
assistance, and then neither of the generals nor their soldiers would
have ever left Bear Paw Mountain alive.
</p><p>On the fifth day I went to General Miles and gave up my gun,
and said, "From where the sun now stands I will fight no more."
My people needed rest &mdash; we wanted peace.

   <pb n="430"/>

</p><p>I was told we could go with General Miles to Tongue River
and stay there until spring, when we would be sent back to our
country.  Finally it was decided that we were to be taken to Tongue
River.  We had nothing to say about it.  After our arrival at Tongue
River, General Miles received orders to take us to Bismarck.  The
reason given was, that subsistence would be cheaper there.
</p><p>General Miles was opposed to this order.  He said: "You must
not blame me.  I have endeavored to keep my word, but the chief
who is over me has given the order, and I must obey it or resign.
That would do you no good.  Some other officer would carry out the
order."
</p><p>I believe General Miles would have kept his word if he could
have done so.  I do not blame him for what we have suffered since
the surrender.  I do not know who is to blame.  We gave up all our
horses &mdash; over eleven hundred &mdash; and all our saddles &mdash; over one
hundred &mdash; and we have not heard from them since.  Somebody has
got our horses.
</p><p>General Miles turned my people over to another soldier, and
we were taken to Bismarck.  Captain Johnson, who now had charge
of us, received an order to take us to Fort Leavenworth.  At
Leavenworth we were placed on a low river bottom, with no water
except river-water to drink and cook with.  We had always lived in a
healthy country, where the mountains were high and the water was
cold and clear.  Many of my people sickened and died, and we
buried them in this strange land.  I can not tell how much my heart
suffered for my people while at Leavenworth.  The Great Spirit
Chief who rules above seemed to be looking some other way, and
did not see what was being done to my people.
</p><p>During the hot days (July, 1878) we received notice that we
were to be moved farther away from our own country.  We were not
asked if we were willing to go.  We were ordered to get into the
railroad-cars.  Three of my people died on the way to Baxter
Springs.  It was worse to die there than to die fighting in the
mountains.
</p><p>We were moved from Baxter Springs (Kansas) to the Indian
Territory, and set down without our lodges.  We had but little
medicine, and we were nearly all sick.  Seventy of my people have
died since we moved there.
</p><p>We have had a great many visitors who have talked many
ways.  Some of the chiefs (General Fish and Colonel Stickney) from

   <pb n="431"/>

Washington came to see us, and selected land for us to live upon.
We have not moved to that land, for it is not a good place to live.
</p><p>The Commissioner Chief (E. A. Hayt) came to see us.  I told
him, as I told every one, that I expected General Miles's word would
be carried out.  He said it "could not be done; that white men now
lived in my country and all the land was taken up; that, if I returned
to Wallowa, I could not live in peace; that law-papers were out
against my young men who began the war, and that the Government
could not protect my people."  This talk fell like a heavy stone upon
my heart.  I saw that I could not gain anything by talking to him.
Other law chiefs (Congressional Committee) came to see me and
said they would help me to get a healthy country.  I did not know
who to believe.  The white people have too many chiefs.  They do
not understand each other.  They do not all talk alike.
</p><p>The Commissioner Chief (Mr. Hayt) invited me to go with him
and hunt for a better home than we have now.  I like the land we
found (west of the Osage reservation) better than any place I have
seen in that country; but it is not a healthy land.  There are no
mountains and rivers.  The water is warm.  It is not a good country
for stock.  I do not believe my people can live there.  I am afraid
they will all die.  The Indians who occupy that country are dying
off.  I promised Chief Hayt to go there, and do the best I could until
the Government got ready to make good General Miles's word.  I
was not satisfied, but I could not help myself.
</p><p>Then the Inspector Chief (General McNiel) came to my camp
and we had a long talk.  He said I ought to have a home in the
mountain country north, and that he would write a letter to the Great
Chief at Washington.  Again the hope of seeing the mountains of
Idaho and Oregon grew up in my heart.
</p><p>At last I was granted permission to come to Washington and
bring my friend Yellow Bull and our interpreter with me.  I am glad
we came.  I have shaken hands with a great many friends, but there
are some things I want to know which no one seems able to explain.
I can not understand how the Government sends a man out to fight
us, as it did General Miles, and then breaks his word.  Such a
Government has something wrong about it.  I can not understand
why so many chiefs are allowed to talk so many different ways, and
promise so many different things.  I have seen the Great Father
Chief (the President), the next Great Chief (Secretary of the
Interior), the Commissioner Chief (Hayt), the Law

   <pb n="432"/>

Chief (General Butler), and many other law chiefs (Congressmen),
and they all say they are my friends, and that I shall have justice,
but while their mouths all talk right I do not understand why
nothing is done for my people.  I have heard talk and talk, but
nothing is done.  Good words do not last long unless they amount to
something.  Words do not pay for my dead people.  They do not pay
for my country, now overrun by white men.  They do not protect my
father's grave.  They do not pay for all my horses and cattle.  Good
words will not give me back my children.  Good words will not
make good the promise of your War Chief General Miles.  Good
words will not give my people good health and stop them from
dying.  Good words will not get my people a home where they can
live in peace and take care of themselves.  I am tired of talk that
comes to nothing.  It makes my heart sick when I remember all the
good words and all the broken promises.  There has been too much
talking by men who had no right to talk.  Too many
misrepresentations have been made, too many misunderstandings
have come up between the white men about the Indians.  If the
white man wants to live in peace with the Indian he can live in
peace.  There need be no trouble.  Treat all men alike.  Give them
all the same law.  Give them all an even chance to live and grow.
All men were made by the same Great Spirit Chief.  They are all
brothers.  The earth is the mother of all people, and all people
should have equal rights upon it.  You might as well expect the
rivers to run backward as that any man who was born a free man
should be contented when penned up and denied liberty to go where
he pleases.  If you tie a horse to a stake, do you expect he will grow
fat?  If you pen an Indian up on a small spot of earth, and compel
him to stay there, he will not be contented, nor will he grow and
prosper.  I have asked some of the great white chiefs where they get
their authority to say to the Indian that he shall stay in one place,
while he sees white men going where they please.  They can not tell
me.
</p><p>I only ask of the Government to be treated as all other men are
treated.  If I can not go to my own home, let me have a home in
some country where my people will not die so fast.  I would like to
go to Bitter Root Valley.  There my people would be healthy; where
they are now they are dying.  Three have died since I left my camp
to come to Washington.
</p><p>When I think of our condition my heart is heavy.  I see men of

   <pb n="433"/>

my race treated as outlaws and driven from country to country, or
shot down like animals.
</p><p>I know that my race must change.  We can not hold our own
with the white men as we are.  We only ask an even chance to live
as other men live.  We ask to be recognized as men.  We ask that the
same law shall work alike on all men.  If the Indian breaks the law,
punish him by the law.  If the white man breaks the law, punish him
also.
</p><p>Let me be a free man &mdash; free to travel, free to stop, free to
work, free to trade where I choose, free to choose my own teachers,
free to follow the religion of my fathers, free to think and talk and
act for myself &mdash; and I will obey every law, or submit to the penalty.
</p><p>Whenever the white man treats the Indian as they treat each
other, then we will have no more wars.  We shall all be alike &mdash;
brothers of one father and one mother, with one sky above us and
one country around us, and one government for all.  Then the Great
Spirit Chief who rules above will smile upon this land, and send
rain to wash out the bloody spots made by brothers' hands from the
face of the earth.  For this time the Indian race are waiting and
praying.  I hope that no more groans of wounded men and women
will ever go to the ear of the Great Spirit Chief above, and that all
people may be one people.
</p><p>In-mut-too-yah-lat-lat has spoken for his people.</p>
<closer>
<signed><name type="person">YOUNG JOSEPH.
</name><lb/>
<name type="place">WASHINGTON CITY, D. C.
</name>
</signed>
</closer>
</div1>

</body>
</text>
</TEI.2>

