<?xml version="1.0"?>

<?dlps id="KayLeon"?>
<?dlps page-images="none" figure-images="no"?>
<?dlps transcription="other"?>

<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/tei-p4/tei2.dtd" [
<!ENTITY % POSTKB "INCLUDE">
<!ENTITY % TEI.extensions.ent SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.ent">
<!ENTITY % TEI.extensions.dtd SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.dtd">
<!ENTITY % ISOnum SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/charent/iso-num.ent"> %ISOnum;
<!ENTITY % ISOpub SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/charent/iso-pub.ent"> %ISOpub;

]>
<TEI.2 id="KayLeon">
<teiHeader type="migrated" creator="Etext">
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title type="main">Leonid Andreyev: 1871-1919</title>
<title type="sort">leonid andreyev 1871 1919</title>
<author>Kayden, Eugene M.</author>
<respStmt>
<resp>Creation of machine-readable version:</resp>
<name>Judy Boss</name>
<resp>Creation of digital images:</resp>
<name/>
<resp>Conversion to TEI.2-conformant markup:</resp>
<name>University of Virginia Library Electronic Text Center.</name>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt>
<extent>ca. <num type="kilobytes">22</num> kilobytes</extent>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>University of Virginia Library</publisher>
<pubPlace>Charlottesville, Virginia</pubPlace>
<idno type="ETC">KayLeon</idno>
<date value="1998">1998</date>
<availability status="public">
<p n="copyright">Copyright &copy; 1998 by the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia</p>
<p n="access">Publicly accessible</p>
</availability>
<idno type="uva-pid">uva-lib:476131</idno>
</publicationStmt>
<seriesStmt>
<title>University of Virginia Library, Text collection</title>
<idno type="uva-set">UVA-LIB-Text</idno>
</seriesStmt>
<sourceDesc>
<biblFull>
<titleStmt>
<title type="main">Leonid Andreyev: 1871-1919</title>
<title level="j">The Dial, Vol. 67 (15 Nov. 1919)</title>
<title type="sort">leonid andreyev 1871 1919</title>
<author>Eugene M. Kayden</author>
</titleStmt>
<extent>pp. 425-428</extent>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>Kraus Reprint Corporation</publisher>
<pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
<date value="1966">1966</date>
<idno type="callNo">Print copy consulted: UVA Library call number AP2 .D48 v. 67 1919</idno>
</publicationStmt>
<notesStmt>
<note>
<p>The Kraus edition is a reprint of the 1919 version of The Dial.</p>
</note>
</notesStmt>
</biblFull>
</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc>
<encodingDesc>
<projectDesc>
<p>Prepared for the University of Virginia Library Electronic Text Center.</p>
</projectDesc>
<editorialDecl>
<p>All unambiguous end-of-line hyphens have been removed, and the trailing part of a word has been joined to the preceding line.</p>
<p>The images exist as archived TIFF images, one or more JPEG versions for general use, and thumbnail GIFs.</p>
<p>Some keywords in the header are a local Electronic Text Center scheme to aid in establishing analytical groupings.</p>
</editorialDecl>
</encodingDesc>
<profileDesc>
<creation>
<date value="1919">1919</date>
</creation>
<langUsage>
<language id="eng" usage="main">English</language>
</langUsage>
<textClass>
<keywords>
<term>nonfiction</term>
<term>prose</term>
<term>masculine</term>
</keywords>
</textClass>
</profileDesc>
<revisionDesc>
<change>
<date value="1998-05">May, 1998</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>corrector</resp>
<name>Carol Osborne, Electronic Text Center</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Added TEI tags and header</item>
</change>
<change>
<date value="2005-07">July 2005</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>Corrector</resp>
<name>John Ivor Carlson</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Converted to XML and/or checked tags.</item>
</change>
<change>
<date value="2007-09">September 2007</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>Migration</resp>
<name>Ethan Gruber, University of Virginia Library</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Converted XML markup from TEI Lite to uva-dl-tei (TEI P4 with local customizations).</item>
</change>
<change>
<date value="2008-01">January 2008</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>Migration</resp>
<name>Greg Murray, University of Virginia Library</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Programmatically updated TEI header markup (but not header content) for minimal compliance with current QA requirements.</item>
</change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text id="d1">
<body id="d2">

<div1 type="article" id="d3"> <pb n="425"/>
<head><hi rend="italic">Leonid Andreyev: 1871-1919</hi></head>

<p>BETWEEN THE TWO REVOLUTIONS of 1905 and 1917
Leonid Andreyev was without a doubt the foremost writer in
Russia.  His name was always spoken with veneration, in
mysterious whispers, as a grim portentous magician who descended
into the ultimate depths of the nether side of life and fathomed the
beauty and tragedy of the struggle.  Leonid Nickolayevitch was born
in the province of Oryol, in 1871, and studied law at the University
of Moscow.  Those were days of suffering and starvation; he gazed
into the abyss of sorrow and despair.  In January 1894 he made an
unsuccessful attempt to kill himself by shooting, and then was
forced by the authorities to severe penitence, which augmented the
natural morbidness of his temperament.  As a lawyer his career was
short-lived, and he soon abandoned it for literature, beginning as a
police-court reporter on the Moscow Courier.  In 1902 he published
the short story In the Fog, which for the first time brought him
universal recognition.  He was imprisoned during the revolution of
1905, together with Maxim Gorky, on political charges.  Such are
the few significant details of his personal life, for the true Andreyev
is entirely in his stories and plays.
</p><p>Andreyev belongs to that great fellowship of Russian authors
who did not accept the scientific advance of the century with its
unquestioning ambition and belief in the saving grace of mere
action and work.  An unflinching realist seeking truth with a terrible
zeal, he divested things of their good nature and gloss, and his
chosen themes were the failure of the cultured man in the face of
all-pervading coarseness, and the moral decay of middle-class
correctness and order.  At first he told himself that it was best to
live without theories and misgivings, and unheeding joy seemed the
solution, which he expressed in There Was, In Springtime, On the
River, A Present, Holiday, and others.  "Neither truth nor falsehood
will conquer," he then wrote; "only that will conquer which is in
complete consonance with the foundation of life itself."  But
aloofness was foreign to his nature, and the themes which won
undiminished ascendancy in his writings were the problems of
man's solitude in the midst of conventional social life, his loneliness
before inexplicable fate, and his eager yearning for human
solidarity, for a moral &mdash; not economic &mdash; bond in human existence.
In the everyday kingdom of mere things, in contact with our joyless
existence and the adamantean wall of social customs and
falsehoods, he saw nothing but confusion, madness, death.  Not life
itself was terrible, but its debasement to meaner ends, our fierce
absorption in inconsequential aims and activities, and the
employment of intelligence in works that negate civilization,
although presumptuously and solemnly undertaken to ameliorate
and save.  It was man's haughty belief in his power to be master of
his fate, and of the dark mysterious forces compassing our life, that
was the cause of confusion and madness.  Pride of intellect, in the
face of endless time and space, only increases man's desolation and
makes his ruin certain.  Andreyev's lone-faring man saw reason
overtopping itself, sufficiency and philistinism making a cursed
waste of life where dreams of excellence are squandered in sin's
distress, and his existence tended to withdraw from external activity
and achievement deeper into the silences of mental life; in the place
of ambition, action, love, we have the tragedy of the intellect and
the sufferings of lonely thought.  This was the tragedy of his Dr.
Kerzhentsev, who wanted by his intellect and will alone to span the
abyss of doubt, committing a crime in the name of culture.  It is no
less the tragedy of the gray little average man who revolts against
the idea that he has no other destiny than to be a means of "general"
happiness, a "social manure."  Sergey Petrovich would not enslave
nor be enslaved, and so he dies, following the pitiless injunction of
Zarathustra, "If thy life is not successful, if a venomous worm is
gnawing at thy heart, know that death will succeed."
</p><p>A pessimist?  True.  But Andreyev does not end with
pessimism.  He was not the brilliant author toying with his
changeful moods and fancies, but a fiery soul gripped by the world's
sorrow, and seeing visions of new worlds and beauty.  By
temperament a man of combat, he yearned for a wider heaven and
real people.  Denying life he yet

   <pb n="426"/>

vibrates with love and sorrow of life, convinced that life is great,
invincible.  Refuting life, he believes in the symbol.  The dying will
thirsts for the impossible, looking for the miracle in the order of
gloom and bestiality.  Before the impenetrable Wall, against which
are piled the dead of generations and ages, it is the leper who cries:
"Let it stand.  But is not each corpse a step to the summit?  We are
many, and our life is burdensome.  Let us cover the earth with our
bodies, body on body, and we shall reach the very summit.  And if
one of us should remain &mdash; he will behold the new world."  Here was
faith within fear and confusion, a bugle call to action for the sake of
one short shuddering step to the Unseen, to the doorway of the new
life; here was a sufficient answer to the question why struggle and
die.  Young revolutionary Russia heard the call.  The mysticism
which Andreyev accepted was not the comfort of an undisturbed
faith, but a mysticism born out of great combat and striving, a
mysticism of belief and asseveration.  No wonder then that with the
revolution of 1905 the cordial swiftness of Andreyev's art and his
infinite love for the thwarted hopes and agonies of his people had
completely captivated the imagination and the deep worship of his
compatriots.  No pessimist could have produced in rapid succession
the individual and social dramas which followed after 1905: To the
Stars, Savva, King Hunger, Life of Man, and Anathema.  In these
Andreyev reached the acme of his poetic utterance.
</p><p>The light which was breaking through the gloom and
confusion of Andreyev's early work was the conception of man as
the son of eternity, a citizen of countless worlds, a sun-snarer.
"Earth is wax in man's hands," cries the dreamy worker Treitch, in
To the Stars, who would light a new sun with his own blood if the
old were to go out.  What if the noble and the beautiful spirits, like
the student Nicholas, perish in the struggle?  Man knows no death;
the earth is full with his perfume.  Treitch understands the old father
astronomer who dreams of untriangulated stars and "the mystery of
things above us" where he discerns the birth of unknown friends
"seven hundred years from now."  Earth and sky join hands,
revolutionist and astronomer are equally seekers through the dusk of
struggle and failure for the living spark, to get where life begins
anew.  And the astronomer sends Marie to die as Nicholas died, and
he promises her immortality.  To the stars!  Work and combat on
earth in the name of a wonderful dream.
</p><p>The revolutionary character unfolds itself fully in Savva, the
man who could not forgive all those who turned the world into "a
cesspool, a slaughter-house."  Savva came to sweep away the
civilization of centuries and clear the way for great deeds, to give
thought its wings.  "It is necessary to strip the earth naked, Lippa,"
he cries to his sister; "to strip away all the hideous old rags!  Earth is
worthy of a royal mantle, but what have they done with her?  She is
dressed in coarse fustian, in prisoner's rags."  He would sweep away
all the past, all that imprisons man within the iron round of things
already accomplished.  Only the brave will remain, only those who
will build up a new life, new beauty.  Savva burns with a beautiful
passion and a mad love for an ideal.  He, too, is lonely; he loves
only the society of children.  But he too must perish, for life is a
continuous process, and humanity an old man, refusing to be
decompounded and rebuilt to the linear utopianism of the dreamer
and theorist, come out of the silence with his ideal to be foisted on
unregenerate society.  Old Kondraty thinks that man is sly, that he
would hide and save something of the old order and then backslide
into his former ways.  With his sister Lippa, Andreyev cannot forget
the unfortunate victims: "No, Savva, you don't love anyone.  You
love only yourself and your dreams.  He who loves men will not
take away from them all they love.  He will not regard his own
wishes more than their lives.  Destroy everything!  Destroy
Golgotha?  Consider: destroy Golgotha!  The brightest, the most
glorious hope that ever was on earth!  All right, you don't believe in
Christ.  But if you have a single drop of nobility in your nature, you
must respect and honor His noble memory.  He also was unhappy.
He was crucified &mdash; crucified, Savva!  You are silent?"
</p><p>Andreyev cannot forget the individual "speck of dust," our
common brother who is demanded as a sacrifice to brotherhood.  He
tells many stories of the life of the ordinary "gray" men, souls lost
and bewildered, and yet dreaming of excellence.  He cannot
reconcile himself to man doomed to nothing.  In Life of Man we see
him suffering for this gray man of the crowd.  He chooses common
incidents &mdash; poverty, heedless pleasures of youth, ambition, rise to
wealth, family happiness, dreams of home and big fireplaces,
comfort at maturity, the loss of the only son, and man's
bewilderment before misfortune and unknown fate.  Imperceptibly
we begin to understand that the tragedy of the modern individualist
consists in his failure to relate himself organically with the plangent
life about him, to establish an immediate bond between himself and
the larger social life, in the absence of which personal achievement
hangs like a pall that shrouds dullness and vacancy.

   <pb n="427"/>

</p><p>But though the soul is lost, and the sick beast defiles man, he
is reaching out for indissoluble truth.  This is the eternal ageless
reality so significant to Andreyev, for it is a power which flouts
deformity and laughs at failure.  This common concrete
circumstance Andreyev traces out divinely on the walls of man's
thought.  He pursues this fateful idea of man thinking himself the
center of the universe, demanding happiness and reason, while life
goes on heedless of man's desires and sufferings, until he creates the
symbols Anathema and King Hunger, spirits which at once despise
and love man, suffering for him, betraying him, and striving to cast
the chaos of life into some mold of rational conscious will.
Anathema is modern and original.  Not Milton's reason rising
against God, nor Byron's fallen spirit of romantic daring and protest,
nor the cold, calculating, disdainful spirit of Goethe's creation;
Anathema is "gray," cautious and bold, lying and yet truthful,
ambitious, loving work and fame, seeking justice and eternity.  He
is the "devil" of an oppressed and enslaved industrial people;
self-confident reason struggling towards happiness and truth.  Anathema
is in science only &mdash; in numbers, weight, and measure; in a word, a
modern parvenu.  He would prove to the Guardian at the Gate in
heaven that misery is eternal, man worthless, and compassion futile.
The poor Jew David should be the test.  Anathema brings millions
to David, and David goes forth to give joy to all men.  The masses
come to him "like four oceans of tears," he gives them everything
until he is poor again, and when he is powerless to satisfy the
unending poverty of the earth, he would try a miracle &mdash; only to give
them happiness.  He deceives their hopes and expectations, and
David, who was ready to squeeze his heart "like a sponge between
the millstones of his palms," perishes at their hands.  Love and
compassion end in hatred and death.  But in spite of the great evil
done, the Guardian at the Gate affirms the deathlessness of love.
David is immortal.  "He lives in the immortality of fire which is
life."  Anathema, who is numbers and measures, cannot understand.
A tragic solution this &mdash; the failure and the immortality of David.
But is Andreyev wrong?  Has love ever vanquished by mere giving
of wealth away?  Has Christianity won by the mere surrendering of
the two coats?  David was only a philanthropist, a poor man after
all.  Love does not bind men this way, and money charity does not
make society one and organic.  Riches only stirred in David the fear
of death whom he waited as a friend when he was poor.  David has
no essential beauty.  Nevertheless this moral outgoing of man,
spanning the chasm between self and the world, is precious.  Truth
saves mankind.  Truth is immortal in David, in man's emotional
yearning for man, but truth must perish in Anathema, who is
numbers and measures.
</p><p>King Hunger appeared at a moment of universal desperation
when the defeat of the revolutionary movement produced a state of
chaos in the life and literature of Russia.  Andreyev seized the spirit
of the desperate condition of the struggle, the tragic spirit of
rebellion among the peasants, and the monstrosity of a spiritually
barren class in a position of power.  The dramatic pictures of King
Hunger reveal the masterful broad strokes of a great artist's brush.
We feel the presence of Stygian shadows; they waver, fading into
transparent colossal shapes, incomprehensible and gruesome as the
figures of Time, Death, and King Hunger.  We hear earth groaning,
we hear the weeping of her children.  The despotic power of the
machine crushes the life and blood of the earth and her fair
children.  Time is waiting for man to grow indignant and to revolt.
King Hunger knows that nature is gathering her gigantic force to
hurl into oblivion the whole burden of false, man-destroying
culture, its shames and lies, and the arrogance of privilege.  This
releasing force is both the revolution and the inauguration of the
new world.  Not unlike destiny, playing with social forces, King
Hunger is dual in nature.  He is lackey and leader.  He fawns on the
rich, their pride and over-confidence in perpetuating themselves in
power; he instigates the underworld of thieves, paupers, strumpets &mdash;
the legitimate counterpart of the mercantile order &mdash; to murder,
violence, and destruction.  Among the laborers, in the factory, he
appears as leader.  He sees their unceasing toil without beginning or
end, he hears their demands for joy and life, he feels the reserve
power of great spirits and their inarticulate cries, and he calls them
to revolt.  "Let us give back to man his might and beauty!  Let's
fling him again into the torrent of infinite motion!"  Man must cease
to be the thrall of the machine.  Only free man can live in joy of
life; only such can love; only love proclaims itself in pure artistic
impulses and creative thought.
</p><p>Into this fantastic struggle of social forces Andreyev projected
the dark mood of The Girl in Black.  She represents the best and
noblest instincts of the ruling classes, who, confronted with a
dreadful social overthrow, and exhausted under the pressure of
historic evolution, blindly strive to live with their backward faith.
She cannot merge herself with the hopes and struggles of the
masses, her princely offering of sympathy is spurned, but she would
not

   <pb n="428"/>

"laugh at the fallen."  The cruelty and cynicism of her class
exasperate her.  She feels that their greed and malice have produced
delusions and monsters.  Moving in a class which can no longer
fight for its power as an ideal, she can only advise them "to meet
death dancing," to die beautifully.  She knows that the growing
solidarity of the toiling masses will end all passive submission to
the myth of authority.  Her mood of defeat seizes the ruling class on
the night of the great revolt, when hope rebounds on the barricades
and the prophecy of Cassandra rings in the air.  They can only see
"shaggy, half-naked monsters" in revolt, slaying women and
children, burning libraries and art galleries.  She and her class can
only hear voices roaring revenge and poison.  Deceived by the
immediate utterances of indignation, blind to the deeper and nobler
instincts demanding a worthy share in the joys of life whose
physical sustenance shall no longer exhaust man's forces in weary
service, she and her class mistake the true nature of the great
upheaval.  But &mdash; "I am not Stephano, but a cramp."  She and her
class are the "cramp" of the social revolution.
</p><p>The revolt is drowned in blood.  The devourers of the people
triumph.  But is there not another King, not King Hunger?  In the
factory scene, one workingman demands sternly, "To go to freedom
over violence?"  He believes in another King, but does not know his
name.  He is young and daring, consumptive, and thinks that a new
world will blossom on his blood.  The picture of collective man at
work, creating, is not found in Andreyev: he lacked enthusiasm and
the strength of a soul willing to give itself to those who blunderingly
but earnestly labor for a larger life.  Andreyev was not the man to
reveal the subterranean ideas and passions generating within life
itself.  He was never the <hi rend="italic">conscience</hi> of Russia, with lips
touched by divine living fire, as Tolstoy was, but the <hi rend="italic">mood</hi>
of Russia, falling and rising with the dreams and hopes of the
struggle.
</p><p>In 1905 the revolt was blind and elemental, and apparently
without constructive force.  It was a trial of strength.  But the young
consumptive workingman, and Andreyev's mood, look forward to a
King yet to come.  They have faith in the final victory; they feel that
the human race, like Chekhov's Cherry-Tree Garden, though blasted
for a while, will bloom again in the end.  The powers of evil will
die, poisoned by their own crimes and greed.  A new order will be
born.  The workingmen of Andreyev are different from
Hauptmann's weavers; they do not demolish machines, cut belts,
quench boilers.  They have no hatred of persons and machines.
Hunger leads them to collective solidarity and consciousness.
Mutilated and decimated, they will conquer in the end, rising on
their dead selves, from the tears and sweat and blood of the torment.
The dead field, of the last scene, strewn with the bodies of the
perished and slain, the field on which the victors laugh and jeer at
the fallen, breathes lasting defiance and resistance.
A thousand-strong murmur rises on the dead field, the voice
of the united armies
of labor: "We shall yet come!  We shall yet come!  Woe to the
victorious!"  And the victors run.  The dead are rising.</p>
<closer>
<signed>EUGENE M. KAYDEN.</signed>
</closer>
</div1>

</body>
</text>
</TEI.2>

