<?xml version="1.0"?>

<?dlps id="KipAndr"?>
<?dlps page-images="none" figure-images="no"?>
<?dlps transcription="other"?>

<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/tei-p4/tei2.dtd" [
<!ENTITY % POSTKB "INCLUDE">
<!ENTITY % TEI.extensions.ent SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.ent">
<!ENTITY % TEI.extensions.dtd SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.dtd">
<!ENTITY % ISOnum SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/charent/iso-num.ent"> %ISOnum;
<!ENTITY % ISOpub SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/charent/iso-pub.ent"> %ISOpub;

]>
<TEI.2 id="KipAndr">
<teiHeader type="migrated" creator="Etext">
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title type="main">McAndrew's Hymn</title>
<title type="sort">mcandrews hymn</title>
<author>Kipling, Rudyard, 1865-1936</author>
<respStmt>
<resp>Creation of machine-readable version</resp>
<name>Online Book Initiative</name>
<resp>Conversion to TEI-conformant markup</resp>
<name>University of Virginia Library Electronic Text Center</name>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt>
<extent>ca. <num type="kilobytes">18</num> kilobytes</extent>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>University of Virginia Library</publisher>
<pubPlace>Charlottesville, Virginia</pubPlace>
<idno type="ETC">KipAndr</idno>
<date value="1992">1992</date>
<availability status="public">
<p n="copyright">Copyright &copy; 1992 by the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia</p>
<p n="access">Publicly accessible</p>
</availability>
<idno type="uva-pid">uva-lib:476139</idno>
</publicationStmt>
<seriesStmt>
<title>University of Virginia Library, Text collection</title>
<idno type="uva-set">UVA-LIB-Text</idno>
</seriesStmt>
<sourceDesc>
<biblFull>
<titleStmt>
<title type="main">McAndrew's Hymn</title>
<title type="sort">mcandrews hymn</title>
<author>Rudyard Kipling</author>
</titleStmt>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>Doubleday, Doran, and Co.</publisher>
<pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
<date value="1942">1942</date>
</publicationStmt>
<seriesStmt>
<p>Rudyard Kipling's Verse, Definitive Edition</p>
</seriesStmt>
<notesStmt>
<note>
<p>This machine-readable edition was paginated acccording to the 1942
edition, individual copy PR4851 1942, University of Virginia Alderman
Library.  The source of the scanned text is unclear.</p>
</note>
</notesStmt>
</biblFull>
</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc>
<encodingDesc>
<projectDesc>
<p>Prepared for the University of Virginia Library Electronic Text Center</p>
</projectDesc>
<editorialDecl>
<p>All quotation marks retained as data</p>
<p>All unambiguous end-of-line hyphens have been removed, and the
trailing part of a word has been joined to the preceding line.</p>
<p id="ETC">Keywords in the header are a local Electronic Text Center scheme
to aid in establishing analytical groupings</p>
</editorialDecl>
<refsDecl>
<p>ID elements are given for each page element and are composed of the text's
unique cryptogram and the given page number, as in SpeFQue1 for page one of
Spenser's Faerie Queene.</p>
</refsDecl>
</encodingDesc>
<profileDesc>
<creation>
<date value="1893">1893</date>
</creation>
<langUsage>
<language id="eng" usage="main">English</language>
</langUsage>
<textClass>
<keywords>
<term>fiction; poetry</term>
</keywords>
</textClass>
</profileDesc>
<revisionDesc>
<change>
<date value="1992">1992</date>
<respStmt>
<name>Electronic Text Center, University of Virginia</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Minimal TEI tagging</item>
</change>
<change>
<date value="2005-07">July 2005</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>Corrector</resp>
<name>John Ivor Carlson</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Converted to XML and/or checked tags.</item>
</change>
<change>
<date value="2007-09">September 2007</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>Migration</resp>
<name>Ethan Gruber, University of Virginia Library</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Converted XML markup from TEI Lite to uva-dl-tei (TEI P4 with local customizations).</item>
</change>
<change>
<date value="2008-01">January 2008</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>Migration</resp>
<name>Greg Murray, University of Virginia Library</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Programmatically updated TEI header markup (but not header content) for minimal compliance with current QA requirements.</item>
</change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>
<text id="d1">
<body id="d2">

<div1 type="poem" id="d3"><pb id="KipAndra"/>
<head>McAndrew's Hymn</head>
<lg>
<l>LORD, Thou hast made this world below the shadow of a dream,</l>
<l>An', taught by time, I tak' it so &mdash; exceptin' always Steam.</l>
<l>From coupler-flange to spindle-guide I see Thy Hand, O God &mdash; </l>
<l>Predestination in the stride o' yon connectin'-rod.</l>
<l>John Calvin might ha' forged the same &mdash; enorrmous, certain, slow &mdash; </l>
<l>Ay, wrought it in the furnace-flame &mdash; <hi rend="italic">my</hi> ``Institutio.''</l>
<l>I cannot get my sleep to-night; old bones are hard to please;</l>
<l>I'll stand the middle watch up here &mdash; alone wi' God an' these</l>
<l>My engines, after ninety days o' rase an' rack an' strain</l>
<l>Through all the seas of all Thy world, slam-bangin' home again.</l>
<l>Slam-bang too much &mdash; they knock a wee &mdash; the crosshead-gibs are loose,</l>
<l>But thirty thousand mile o' sea has gied them fair excuse. . . . </l>
<l>Fine, clear an'dark &mdash; a full-draught breeze, wi' Ushant out o' sight,</l>
<l>An' Ferguson relievin' Hay.  Old girl, ye'll walk to-night!</l>

<pb n="121" id="KipAndr121"/>
<l>His wife's at Plymouth. . . . Seventy &mdash; One &mdash; Two &mdash; Three since he began &mdash; </l>
<l>Three turns for Mistress Ferguson . . .  and who's to blame the man?</l>
<l>There's none at any port for me, by drivin' fast or slow,</l>
<l>Since Elsie Campbell went to Thee, Lord, thirty years ago.</l>
<l>(The year the <hi rend="italic">Sarah Sands</hi> was burned.  Oh roads we used to tread,</l>
<l>Fra' Maryhill to Pollokshaws&mdash;fra' Govan to Parkhead!)</l>
<l>Not but that they're ceevil on the Board.  Ye'll hear Sir Kenneth say:</l>
<l>``Good morn, McAndrew!  Back again?  An' how's your bilge to-day?''</l>
<l>Miscallin' technicalities but handin' me my chair</l>
<l>To drink Madeira wi' three Earls &mdash; the auld Fleet Engineer</l>
<l>That started as a boiler-whelp &mdash; when steam and he were low.</l>
<l><hi rend="italic">I</hi> mind the time we used to serve a broken pipe wi' tow!</l>
<l>Ten pound was all the pressure then &mdash; Eh!  Eh! &mdash; a man wad drive;</l>
<l>An' here, our workin' gauges give one hunder sixty-five!</l>
<l>We're creepin' on wi' each new rig &mdash; less weight an' larger power;</l>
<l>There'll be the loco-boiler next an' thirty miles an hour!</l>
<l>Thirty an' more.  What I ha' seen since ocean-steam began</l>
<l>Leaves me na doot for the machine: but what about the man?</l>
<l>The man that counts, wi' all his runs, one million mile o' sea:</l>
<l>Four time the span from Earth to Moon. . . . How far, O Lord from thee</l>
<l>That wast beside him night an' day?  Ye mind my first typhoon?</l>
<l>It scoughed the skipper on his way to jock wi' the saloon.</l>
<l>Three feet were on the stokehold-floor &mdash; just slappin' to an' fro &mdash; </l>
<l>An' cast me on a furnace-door.  I have the marks to show.</l>
<l>Marks! I ha' marks o' more than burns &mdash; deep in my soul an' black,</l>
<l>An' times like this, when things go smooth, my wickudness comes back.</l>
<l>The sins o' four an' forty years, all up an' down the seas.</l>
<l>Clack an' repeat like valves half-fed. . . . Forgie's our trespasses!</l>
<l>Nights when I'd come on to deck to mark, wi' envy in my gaze,</l>
<l>The couples kittlin' in the dark between the funnel-stays;</l>
<l>Years when I raked the Ports wi' pride to fill my cup o' wrong &mdash; </l>
<l>Judge not, O Lord, my steps aside at Gay Street in Hong-Kong!</l>
<l>Blot out the wastrel hours of mine in sin when I abode &mdash; </l>
<l>Jane Harrigan's an' Number Nine, The Reddick an' Grant Road!</l><pb n="122" id="KipAndr122"/>
<l>An' waur than all &mdash; my crownin' sin &mdash; rank blasphemy an' wild.</l>
<l>I was not four and twenty then &mdash; Ye wadna judge a child?</l>
<l>I'd seen the Tropics first that run &mdash; new fruit, new smells, new air &mdash; </l>
<l>How could I tell &mdash; blinf-fou wi' sun &mdash;  the Deil was lurkin' there?</l>
<l>By day like playhouse-scenes the shore slid past our sleepy eyes;</l>
<l>By night thos soft, lasceevious stars leered from those velvet skies,</l>
<l>In port (we used no cargo-steam) I'd daunder down the streets &mdash; </l>
<l>An ijjit grinnin' in a dream &mdash; for shells an' parrakeets,</l>
<l>An' walkin'-sticks o' carved bamboo an' blowfish stuffed an' dried &mdash; </l>
<l>Fillin' my bunk wi' rubbishry the Chief put overside.</l>
<l>Till, off Sambawa Head, Ye mind, I heard a land-breeze ca',</l>
<l>Milk-warm wi' breath o' spice an' bloom: ``McAndrew, Come awa'!''</l>
<l>Firm, clear an' low &mdash; no haste, no hate &mdash; the ghostly whisper went,</l>
<l>Just statin' eevidential facts beyon' all argument:</l>
<l>``Your mither's god's a graspin' deil, the shadow o' yoursel',</l>
<l>``Got out o' books by meenisters clean daft on Heaven an' Hell.</l>
<l>``They mak' him in the Broomielaw, o' Glasgie cold an' dirt,</l>
<l>``A jealous, pridefu' fetich, lad, that's only strong to hurt.</l>
<l>``Ye'll not go back to Him again an' kiss His red-hot rod,</l>
<l>``But come wi' Us'' (Now who were <hi rend="italic">They?</hi>) ``an' know the Leevin' God,</l>
<l>``That does not kipper souls for sport or break a life in jest,</l>
<l>``But swells the ripenin' cocoanuts an' ripes the woman's breast.''</l>
<l>An' there it stopped: cut off: no more; that quiet, certain voice &mdash; </l>
<l>For me, six months o' twenty-four, to leave or take at choice.</l>
<l>'Twas on me like a thunderclap &mdash; it racked me through an' through &mdash; </l>
<l>Temptation past the show o' speech, unnameable an' new &mdash; </l>
<l>The Sin against the Holy Ghost? . . . An' under all, our screw.</l>
</lg>
<lg>
<l>That storm blew by but left behind her anchor-shiftin' swell.</l>
<l>thou knowest all my heart an' mind, Thou knowest, Lord, I fell &mdash; </l>
<l>Third on the <hi rend="italic">Mary Gloster</hi> then, and first that night in Hell!</l>
<l>Yet was Thy Hand beneath my head, about my feet Thy Care &mdash; </l>
<l>Fra' Deli clear to Torres Strait, the trial o' despair,</l>
<l>But when we touched the Barrier Reef Thy answer to my prayer! . . . </l><pb n="123" id="KipAndr123"/>
<l>We wared na run that sea by night but lay an' held our fire,</l>
<l>An' I was drowsin' on the hatch &mdash; sick &mdash; sick wi' doubt an' tire:</l>
<l><hi rend="italic">``Better the sight of eyes that see than wanderin' o' desire!''</hi></l>
<l>Ye mind that word?  Clear as gongs &mdash; again, an' once again,</l>
<l>When rippin' down through coral-trash ran out our moorin'-chain:</l>
<l>An', by Thy Grace, I had the light to see my duty plain.</l>
<l>Light on the engine-room &mdash; no more &mdash; bright as our carbons burn.</l>
<l>I've lost it since a thousand times, but never past return!</l>
<l>   .   .   .   .   .   .   .   .   .   .   .   .   .   .   . </l>
</lg>
<lg>
<l>Obsairve!  Per annum we'll have here two thousand souls aboard &mdash; </l>
<l>Think not I dare to justify myself before the Lord,</l>
<l>But &mdash; average fifteen hunder souls safe-born fra' port to port &mdash; </l>
<l>I <hi rend="italic">am</hi> o' service to my kind.  Ye wadna blame the thought?</l>
<l>Maybe they steam from Grace to Wrath &mdash; to sin by folly led &mdash; </l>
<l>It isna mine to judge their path &mdash; their lives are on my head.</l>
<l>Mine at the last &mdash; when all is done it all comes back to me,</l>
<l>The fault that leaves six thousand ton a log upon the sea.</l>
<l>We'll tak' one stretch &mdash; three weeks an odd by ony road ye steer &mdash; </l>
<l>Fra' Cape Town east to Wellington &mdash; ye need an engineer.</l>
<l>Fail there &mdash; ye've time to weld your shaft &mdash; ay, eat it, ere ye're spoke;</l>
<l>Or make Kergueen under sail &mdash; three jiggers burned wi' smoke!</l>
<l>An' home again &mdash; the Rio run: it's no child's play to go</l>
<l>Steamin' to bell for fourteen days o' snow an' floe an' blow.</l>
<l>The bergs like kelpies overside that girn an' turn an' shift</l>
<l>Whaur, grindin' like the Mills o' God, goes by the big South drift.</l>
<l>(Hail, Snow and Ice that praise the Lord.  I've met them at their work,</l>
<l>An wished we had anither route or they another kirk.)</l>
<l>Yon's strain, hard strain, o' head an' hand, for though Thy Power brings</l>
<l>All skill to naught, Ye'll underatand a man must think o' things.</l>
<l>Then, at the last, we'll get to port an' hoist their baggage clear &mdash; </l>
<l>The passengers, wi' gloves an' canes &mdash; an' this is what I'll hear:</l>
<l>``Well, thank ye for a pleasant voyage.  The tender's comin' now.''</l>
<l>While I go testin' follower-bolts an' watch the skipper bow.</l>
<l>They've words for every one but me &mdash; shake hands wi' half the crew,</l>
<l>Except the dour Scots engineer, the man they never knew.</l><pb n="124" id="KipAndr124"/>
<l>An' yet I like the wark for all we've dam' few pickin's here &mdash; </l>
<l>No pension, an' the most we'll earn's four hunder pound a year.</l>
<l>Better myself abroad?  Maybe.  <hi rend="italic">I'd</hi> sooner starve than sail</l>
<l>Wi' such as call a snifter-rod <hi rend="italic">ross</hi>. . . .  French for nightingale.</l>
<l>Commeesion on my stores?  Some do; but I cannot afford</l>
<l>To lie like stewards wi' patty-pans.  I'm older than the Board.</l>
<l>A bonus on the coal I save?  Ou ay, the Scots are close,</l>
<l>But when I grudge the strength Ye gave I'll grudge their food to <hi rend="italic">those</hi>.</l>
<l>(There's bricks that I might recommend &mdash; an' clink the firebars cruel.</l>
<l>No!  Welsh &mdash; Wangarti at the worst &mdash; an' damn all patent fuel!)</l>
<l>Inventions?  Ye must stay in port to mak' a patent pay.</l>
<l>My Deeferential Valve-Gear taught me how that business lay.</l>
<l>I blame no chaps wi' clearer heads for aught they make or sell.</l>
<l><hi rend="italic">I</hi> found that I could not invent an' look to these as well.</l>
<l>So, wrestled wi' Apollyon &mdash; Nah! &mdash; fretted like a bairn &mdash; </l>
<l>But burned the workin'-plans last run, wi' all I hoped to earn.</l>
<l>Ye know how hard an Idol dies, an' what that meant to me &mdash; </l>
<l>E'en tak' it for a sacrifice acceptable to Thee. . . .</l>
<l><hi rend="italic">Below there!  Oiler!  What's your wark?  Ye find it runnin'
hard?</hi></l>
<l><hi rend="italic">Ye needn't swill the cup wi' oil &mdash; this isn't the Cunard!</hi></l>
<l><hi rend="italic">Ye thought?  Ye are not paid to think.  Go, sweat that off again!</hi></l>
<l>Tck!  Tck!  It's deeficult to sweer nor tak' The Name in vain!</l>
<l>Men, ay an' women, call me stern.  Wi' these to oversee,</l>
<l>Ye'll note I've little time to burn on social repartee.</l>
<l>The bairns see what their elders miss; they'll hunt me to an' fro,</l>
<l>Till for the sake of &mdash; well, a kiss &mdash; I tak' 'em down below.</l>
<l>That minds me of our Viscount loon &mdash; Sir Kenneth's kin &mdash; the chap</l>
<l>Wi' Russia leather tennis-shoon an' spar-decked yachtin'-cap.</l>
<l>I showed him round last week, o'er all &mdash; an' at the last says he:</l>
<l>``Mister McAndrew, Don't you think steam spoils romance at sea?''</l>
<l>Damned ijjit!  I'd been doon that morn to see what ailed the throws,</l>
<l>Manholin', on my back &mdash; the cranks three inches off my nose.</l>
<l>Romance!  Those first-class passengers they like it very well,</l>
<l>Printed an' bound in little books; but why don't poets tell?</l>
<l>I'm sick of all their quirks an' turns &mdash; the loves an' doves they dream &mdash; </l><pb n="125" id="KipAndr125"/>
<l>Lord, send a man like Robbie Burns to sing the Song o' Steam!</l>
<l>To match wi' Scotia's noblest speech yon orchestra sublime</l>
<l>Whaurto &mdash; uplifted like the Just &mdash; the tail-rods mark the time.</l>
<l>The crank-throws give the double-bass, the feed-pump sobs an' heaves,</l>
<l>An' now the main eccentrics start their quarrel on the sheaves:</l>
<l>Her time, her own appointed time, the rocking link-head bides,</l>
<l>Till &mdash; hear that note? &mdash; the rod's return whings glimmerin' through the guides.</l>
<l>They're all awa'!  True beat, full power, the clangin' chorus goes</l>
<l>Clear to the tunnel where they sit, my purrin' dynamos.</l>
<l>Interdependence absolute, forseen, ordained, decreed,</l>
<l>To work, Ye'll note, at ony tilt an' every rate o' speed.</l>
<l>Fra' Skylight-lift to furnace-bars, backed, bolted, braced an' stayed.</l>
<l>An' singin' like the Mornin' Stars for joy that they are made;</l>
<l>While, out o' touch o' vanity, the sweatin' thrust-block says:</l>
<l>``Not unto us the praise, or man &mdash; not unto us the praise!''</l>
<l>Now, a' together, hear them lift their lesson &mdash; theirs an' mine:</l>
<l>``Law, Orrder, Duty an' Restraint, Obedience, Discipline!''</l>
<l>Mill, forge an' try-pit taught them that when roarin' they arose,</l>
<l>An' whiles I wonder if a soul was gied them wi' the blows.</l>
<l>Oh for a man to weld it then, in one trip-hammer strain,</l>
<l>Till even first-class passengers could tell the meanin' plain!</l>
<l>But no one cares except mysel' that serve an' understand</l>
<l>My seven thousand horse-power here.  Eh Lord!  They're grand &mdash; they're grand!</l>
<l>Uplift am I?  When first in store the new-made beasties stood,</l>
<l>Were Ye cast down that breathed the Word declarin' all things good?</l>
 <l>Not so!  O' that warld-liftin' joy no after-fall could vex,</l>
<l>Ye've left a glimmer still to cheer the Man &mdash; the Arrtifex!</l>
<l><hi rend="italic">That</hi> holds, in spite o' knock and scale, o' friction, waste an' slip,</l>
<l>An' by that light &mdash; now, mark my word &mdash; we'll build the Perfect Ship.</l>
<l>I'll never last to judge her lines, or take her curve &mdash; not I.</l>
<l>But I ha' lived an' I ha' worked.  Be thanks to Thee, Most High!</l>
<l>An' I ha' done what I ha' done &mdash; judge Thou if ill or well &mdash; </l>
<l>Always Thy grace preventin' me. . . .</l>
<l>                            Losh!  Yon's the ``Stand-by'' bell.</l><pb n="126" id="KipAndr126"/>
<l>Pilot so soon?  His flare it is.  The mornin'-watch is set.</l>
<l>Well, God be thanked, as I was sayin', I'm no Pelagian yet.</l>
<l>Now, I'll tak' on. . . .</l>
<l>  <hi rend="italic">'Morrn, Ferguson.  Man, have ye ever thought</hi></l>
<l><hi rend="italic">What your good leddy costs in coal? . . . I'll burn 'em down to port.</hi></l>
</lg>

</div1>
</body>
</text>
</TEI.2>
