<?xml version="1.0"?>

<?dlps id="LagRobi"?>
<?dlps page-images="none" figure-images="no"?>
<?dlps transcription="other"?>

<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/tei-p4/tei2.dtd" [
<!ENTITY % POSTKB "INCLUDE">
<!ENTITY % TEI.extensions.ent SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.ent">
<!ENTITY % TEI.extensions.dtd SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.dtd">
<!ENTITY % ISOnum SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/charent/iso-num.ent"> %ISOnum;
<!ENTITY % ISOpub SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/charent/iso-pub.ent"> %ISOpub;
]> 
<TEI.2 id="LagRobi"> 
<teiHeader type="migrated" creator="Etext">
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title type="main">Robin Redbreast</title>
<title type="sort">robin redbreast</title>
<author>Lagerlof, Selma</author>
<respStmt>
<resp>Creation of machine-readable version:</resp> 
<name>Judy Boss</name> 
<resp>Conversion to TEI-conformant markup:</resp> 
<name>University of Virginia Library Electronic Text Center</name>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt> 
<extent>ca. <num type="kilobytes">16</num> kilobytes</extent> 
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>University of Virginia Library</publisher>
<pubPlace>Charlottesville, Virginia</pubPlace> 
<idno type="ETC">LagRobi</idno> 
<date value="1995">1995</date>
<availability status="public">
<p n="copyright">Copyright &copy; 1995 by the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia</p>
<p n="access">Publicly accessible</p>
</availability>
<idno type="uva-pid">uva-lib:476146</idno>
</publicationStmt>
<seriesStmt>
<title>University of Virginia Library, Text collection</title>
<idno type="uva-set">UVA-LIB-Text</idno>
</seriesStmt> 
<sourceDesc>
<biblFull>
<titleStmt>
<title type="main">Robin Redbreast</title>
<title type="sort">robin redbreast</title>
<author>Lagerlof, Selma</author>
<respStmt>
<resp>Translator</resp> 
<name>Volma Swanston Howard</name>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt> 
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>Current Literature</publisher> 
<date value="1903-03">Mar. 1903</date>
</publicationStmt> 
<notesStmt>
<note>
<p>Volume 42</p>
</note>
</notesStmt>
</biblFull>
</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc> 
<encodingDesc>
<projectDesc>
<p>Prepared for the University of Virginia Library Electronic Text Center</p>
</projectDesc> 
<editorialDecl>
<p>All quotation marks retained as data</p> 
<p>Verification made against printed text</p> 
<p id="ETC">Keywords in the header are a local Electronic Text Center scheme  
to aid in establishing analytical groupings</p>
</editorialDecl> 
<refsDecl>
<p>ID elements are given for each page element and are composed of the text's 
unique cryptogram and the given page number, as in SpeFQue1 for page one of  
Spenser's Faerie Queene.</p>
</refsDecl>
</encodingDesc> 
<profileDesc>
<creation>
<date value="1903">1903</date>
</creation> 
<langUsage>
<language id="eng" usage="main">English</language>
</langUsage> 
<textClass>
<keywords>
<term>fiction; prose</term> 
<term>Literature in Translation</term>
</keywords>
</textClass>
</profileDesc> 
<revisionDesc>
<change>
<date value="1995-01">January 1995</date> 
<respStmt>
<resp>corrector</resp>
<name>David Seaman</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Header and basic TEI SGML encoding added.</item>
</change> 
<change>
<date value="2005-07">July 2005</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>Corrector</resp>
<name>John Ivor Carlson</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Converted SGML to XML and/or corrected tagging.</item>
</change>
<change>
<date value="2007-09">September 2007</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>Migration</resp>
<name>Ethan Gruber, University of Virginia Library</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Converted XML markup from TEI Lite to uva-dl-tei (TEI P4 with local customizations).</item>
</change>
<change>
<date value="2008-01">January 2008</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>Migration</resp>
<name>Greg Murray, University of Virginia Library</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Programmatically updated TEI header markup (but not header content) for minimal compliance with current QA requirements.</item>
</change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader> 

<text id="d1">  
<body id="d2"> 
<div1 type="story" id="d3"> 
<head> 
Lagerlof, Selma.  "Robin Redbreast."  Trans. Volma Swanston Howard.<lb/> 
<hi rend="italic"> Current Literature</hi> 42 (Mar. 1903): 346-48.</head> 
<pb n="346"/>  
 
<p>This little tale by Sweden's noted writer of mystical stories 
has in it the simplicity of a nursery rhyme and the beauty of 
perfect art.  The translation from the Swedish is made by Volma 
Swanston Howard for <hi rend="italic"> The Bookman</hi>, with whose permission we 
reproduce it. 
</p>
<lb/>
<p> 
IT happened at that time when our Lord created the world, when He 
not only made heaven and earth, but all the animals and the 
vegetable growths as well, at the same time giving them their 
names. 
</p><p>There have been many histories concerning that time, and if we 
knew them all, we would then have light upon everything in this 
world which we cannot now comprehend. 
</p><p>At that time it happened, one day, when our Lord sat in His 
Paradise and painted the little birds, that the colors in our 
Lord's paint pot gave out, and the goldfinch would have been 
without color if our Lord had not wiped all His paint brushes on 
its feathers. 
</p><p>It was then that the donkey got his long ears, because he 
could not remember the name that had been given him.  No sooner had 
he taken a few steps along the meadows of Paradise than he forgot, 
and three times he came back to ask his name.  At last our Lord 
grew somewhat impatient, took him by his two ears and said: "Thy 
name is ass, ass, ass!"  And while He thus spake our Lord pulled 
both of his ears that the ass might hear better, and remember what 
was said to him. 
</p><p>It was on the same day, also, that the bee was punished. 
</p><p>Now, when the bee was created, it began immediately to gather 
honey, and the animals and human beings who caught the delicious 
odor of the honey came and wanted to taste of it.  But the bee 
wanted to keep it all for himself, and with his poisonous sting 
pursued every living creature that approached his hive.  Our Lord 
saw this and at once called the bee and punished it. 
</p><p>"I gave thee the gift of gathering honey, which is the 
sweetest thing in all creation," said our Lord, "but I did not give 
thee the right to be cruel to thy neighbor.  Remember well that 
every time thou stingest any creature who desires to taste of thy 
honey thou shalt surely die!" 
</p><p>Ah, yes!  it was at that time that the cricket became blind 
and the ant missed her wings. 
</p><p>So many strange things happened on that day! 
</p><p>Our Lord sat there, big and gentle, and planned and created 
all day long, and towards evening He conceived the idea of making 
a little grey bird.  "Remember your name is robin redbreast," said 
our Lord to the bird, as soon as it was finished.  Then He held it 
in the palm of His open hand and let it fly. 
</p><p>After the bird had been testing his wings a bit, and had seen 
something of the beautiful world in which he was destined to live, 
he became curious to see what he himself was like.  He noticed that 
he was entirely grey, and that the breast was just as grey as all 
the rest of him.  Robin redbreast twisted and turned in every 
direction as he viewed himself in the mirror of a clear lake, but 
he couldn't find a single red feather.  Then he flew back to our 
Lord. 
</p><p>Our Lord sat there on His throne, big and gentle.  Out of His 
hands came butterflies that fluttered about His head, doves cooed 
on His shoulders, and out of the earth about Him grew the rose, the 
lily and the daisy. 
</p><p>The little bird's heart beat heavily with fright, but with 
easy curves he flew nearer and nearer our Lord till at last he 
rested on our Lord's hand.  Then our Lord asked what the little 
bird wanted. 
</p><p>"I only want to ask you about one thing," said the little 
bird. 
</p><p>"What is it that you wish to know?" said our Lord. 
</p><p>"Why should I be called redbreast, when I am all grey, from 
the bill to the very end of my tail?  Why am I called redbreast 
when I do not possess one single red feather?" 
</p><p>The bird looked beseechingly on our Lord with its tiny black 
eyes&mdash;then turned its head.  About him he saw pheasants all red 
under a sprinkle of gold dust, cocks with red combs, parrots with 
marvelous red-neck bands, to say nothing about the butterflies, the 
goldfinches and the roses!  And naturally he thought how little he 
needed&mdash;just one tiny drop of color on his breast&mdash;and he, too, 
would be a beautiful bird, and not a misnomer.  "Why should I be 
called redbreast when I am so entirely grey?" asked the bird once 
again, and waited for our Lord to say&mdash;Ah! my friend, I see that I 
have forgotten to paint your breast feathers red, but wait a moment 
and all shall be done. 
</p><p>But our Lord only smiled a little and said: "I have called you 
robin redbreast, and robin redbreast shall your name be, but you 
must look to it that you yourself earn your red breast feathers."  
Then our Lord lifted His hand and let the bird fly once more&mdash;out 
into the world. <pb n="347"/>  
</p><p>The bird flew down into Paradise, meditating deeply.  What 
could a little bird like him do to earn for himself red feathers?  
The only thing he could think of was to make his nest in a brier 
bush.  He built it in among the thorns in the close thicket.  It 
looked as if he waited for a roseleaf to cling to his throat and 
give him color. 
 
</p><p>Countless years had come and gone since that day, which was 
the happiest in all the world!  Human beings had already advanced 
so far that they had learned to cultivate the earth and sail the 
seas.  They had procured clothes and ornaments for themselves, and 
had long since learned to build big temples and great cities&mdash;such 
as Thebes, Rome and Jerusalem. 
</p><p>Then there dawned a new day, one that will long be remembered 
in the world's history.  On the morning of this day robin redbreast 
sat upon a little naked hillock outside of Jerusalem's walls and 
sang to his young ones, who rested in a tiny nest in a brier bush. 
</p><p>Robin redbreast told the little ones all about that wonderful 
day of creation, and how the Lord had given names to everything, 
just as each redbreast had told it, ever since the first redbreast 
had heard God's word and gone out of God's hand.  "And mark you," 
he ended sorrowfully, "so many years have gone, so many roses have 
bloomed, so many little birds have come out of their eggs since 
Creation day, but robin redbreast is still a little grey bird.  He 
has not yet succeeded in gaining his red feathers." 
</p><p>The young ones opened wide their tiny bills, and asked if 
their forbears had never tried to do any great thing to earn the 
priceless red color. 
</p><p>"We have all done what we could," said the little bird, "but 
we have all gone amiss.  Even the first robin redbreast met one day 
another bird exactly like himself, and he began immediately to love 
it with such a mighty love that he could feel his breast glow.  Ah! 
he thought then, now I understand!  It was our Lord's meaning that 
I should love with so much ardor that my breast should grow red in 
color from the very warmth of the love that lives in my heart.  But 
he missed it, as all those who came after him had missed it, and as 
even you shall miss it." 
</p><p>The little ones twittered, utterly bewildered, and began to 
mourn because the red color would not come to beautify their little 
downy grey breasts. 
</p><p>"We had also hoped that song would help us," said the grown-up 
bird, speaking in long drawn-out tones.  "The first robin redbreast 
sang until his breast swelled within him, he was so carried away&mdash; 
and he dared to hope anew.  Ah! he thought, it is the glow of the 
song which lives in my soul that will color my breast feathers red.  
But he missed it, as all the others have missed it, and as even you 
shall miss it."  Again was heard a sad "peep" from the young ones' 
half-naked throats. 
</p><p>"We had also counted on our courage and our valor," said the 
bird.  "The first robin redbreast fought bravely with other birds 
until his breast flamed with the pride of conquest.  Ah! he 
thought, my breast feathers shall become red from the love of 
battle which burns in my heart.  He too missed it, as all those who 
came after him had missed it, and, as even you shall miss it."  The 
young ones peeped courageously that they still wished to try and 
win the much-sought-after prize, but the bird answered them 
sorrowfully that it would be impossible.  What could they do when 
so many splendid ancestors had missed the mark?  What could they do 
more than love, sing and fight?  What could&mdash;. 
</p><p>The little bird stopped short in the middle of the sentence, 
for out of one of Jerusalem's gates came a crowd of people 
marching, and the whole procession rushed up towards the hillock 
where the bird had its nest.  There were riders on proud horses, 
soldiers with long spears, executioners with nails and hammers.  
There were judges and priests in the procession, weeping women, and 
above all a mob of mad, loose people running about&mdash;a filthy, 
howling mob of loiterers. 
</p><p>The little grey bird sat trembling on the edge of his nest.  
He feared each instant that the little brier bush would be trampled 
down and his young ones killed! 
</p><p>"Be careful!" he cried to the little defenceless young ones, 
"creep together and remain quiet.  Here comes a horse that will 
ride right over us!  Here comes a warrior with iron-shod sandals!  
Here comes the whole wild, storming mob!"  Immediately the bird 
ceased his cry of warning and grew calm and quiet.  He almost 
forgot the danger hovering over him.  Finally he hopped down into 
his nest and spread his wings over the young ones. 
</p><p>"Oh! this is too terrible," said he; "I don't want you to 
witness this awful sight!  There are three miscreants who are going 
to be crucified!"  And he spread his wings so the little ones could 
see nothing. 
</p><p>They caught only the sound of hammers, the cries of anguish 
and the wild shrieks of the mob. 
</p><p>Robin redbreast followed the whole spectacle with his eyes, 
which grew big with terror.  He could not take his glance from the 
three unfortunates. <pb n="348"/>  
</p><p>"How terrible human beings are!" said the bird after a little.  
"It isn't enough that they should nail these poor creatures to a 
cross, but they must needs place a crown of piercing thorns on the 
head of one of them.  I see that the thorns have wounded his brow 
so that the blood flows," he continued.  "And this man is so 
beautiful&mdash;and he looks about him with such mild glances that every 
one ought to love him.  I feel as if an arrow were shooting through 
my heart when I see him suffer!" 
</p><p>The little bird began to feel a stronger and stronger pity for 
the thorn-crowned sufferer.  Oh! if I were only my brother the 
eagle, thought he, I would draw the nails from his hands, and with 
my strong claws I would drive away all those who torture him.  He 
saw how the blood trickled down, from the brow of the crucified 
one, and he could no longer remain quiet in his nest.  Even if I am 
little and weak, I can still do something for this poor tortured 
one&mdash;thought the bird.  Then he left his nest and flew out into the 
air, striking wide circles around the crucified one.  He flew about 
him several times without daring to approach, for he was a shy 
little bird who had never dared to go near a human being.  But 
little by little he gained courage, flew close to him and drew with 
his little bill a thorn that had become imbedded in the brow of the 
crucified one.  And as he did this there fell on his breast a drop 
of blood from the face of the crucified one.  It spread quickly and 
colored all the little thin breast feathers. 
</p><p>Then the crucified one opened his lips and whispered to the 
bird: "Because of thy compassion, thou hast won all that thy kind 
have been striving after ever since the world was created." 
</p><p>As soon as the bird had returned to his nest his young ones 
cried to him: "Thy breast is red, thy breast feathers are redder 
than the roses!" 
</p><p>"It is only a drop of blood from the poor man's forehead," 
said the bird.  "It will vanish as soon as I bathe in a pool or a 
clear well." 
</p><p>But no matter how much the little bird bathed, the red color 
did not vanish.  And when his little ones grew up, the blood-red 
color shone also on their breast feathers, just as it shines on 
every robin redbreast's throat and breast until this very day. 
</p>

</div1>
</body>
</text>
</TEI.2>
