<?xml version="1.0"?>

<?dlps id="Law1Rex"?>
<?dlps page-images="none" figure-images="no"?>
<?dlps transcription="other"?>

<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/tei-p4/tei2.dtd" [
<!ENTITY % POSTKB "INCLUDE">
<!ENTITY % TEI.extensions.ent SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.ent">
<!ENTITY % TEI.extensions.dtd SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.dtd">
<!ENTITY % ISOnum SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/charent/iso-num.ent"> %ISOnum;
<!ENTITY % ISOlat1 SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/charent/iso-lat1.ent"> %ISOlat1;
<!ENTITY % ISOpub SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/charent/iso-pub.ent"> %ISOpub;
 
]> 
<TEI.2 id="Law1Rex"> 
<teiHeader type="migrated" creator="Etext">
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title type="main">Rex</title>
<title type="sort">rex</title>
<author>Lawrence, D. H.</author>
<respStmt>
<resp>Creation of machine-readable version:</resp>  
<name>Judy Boss</name>  
<resp>Creation of digital images:</resp>  
<name/>  
<resp>Conversion to TEI.2-conformant markup:</resp>  
<name>University of Virginia Library Electronic Text Center.</name>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt>  
<extent>ca. <num type="kilobytes">22</num> kilobytes</extent>  
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>University of Virginia Library</publisher>
<pubPlace>Charlottesville, Virginia</pubPlace>  
<idno type="ETC">Law1Rex</idno>  
<date value="1997">1997</date>
<availability status="public">
<p n="copyright">Copyright &copy; 1997 by the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia</p>
<p n="access">Publicly accessible</p>
</availability>
<idno type="uva-pid">uva-lib:476147</idno>
</publicationStmt>
<seriesStmt>
<title>University of Virginia Library, Text collection</title>
<idno type="uva-set">UVA-LIB-Text</idno>
</seriesStmt>  
<sourceDesc>
<biblFull>
<titleStmt>
<title type="main">Rex</title>
<title level="j">The Dial, vol. 70</title>
<title type="sort">rex</title>
<author>D. H. Lawrence</author>
</titleStmt>  
<extent>pp 169-176</extent>  
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>The Dial Publishing Company, Inc.</publisher>  
<pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>  
<date value="1921-01">January-June, 1921</date>  
<idno type="callNo">Print copy consulted: Uva Library AP2.D48</idno>
</publicationStmt>  
</biblFull>
</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc>  
<encodingDesc>
<projectDesc>
<p>Prepared for the University of Virginia Library Electronic Text Center.</p>
</projectDesc>  
<editorialDecl>
<p>All quotation marks retained as data.</p>  
<p>All unambiguous end-of-line hyphens have been removed, and the trailing part of a word has been joined to the preceding line.</p>  
<p>The images exist as archived TIFF images, one or more JPEG versions for general use, and thumbnail GIFs.</p>  
<p>Keywords in the header are a local Electronic Text Center scheme to aid in establishing analytical groupings.</p>
</editorialDecl>  
</encodingDesc>  
<profileDesc>
<creation>
<date value="1921">1921</date>
</creation>  
<langUsage>
<language id="eng" usage="main">English</language>
</langUsage>  
<textClass>
<keywords>
<term>prose; fiction</term>
</keywords>  
</textClass>
</profileDesc>  
<revisionDesc>
<change>
<date value="1997-05">May, 1997</date>  
<respStmt>
<resp>corrector</resp>  
<name>Christine Ruotolo</name>
</respStmt>  
<item>Added TEI header and tags.</item>
</change>  
<change>
<date value="2005-07">July 2005</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>Corrector</resp>
<name>John Ivor Carlson</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Converted SGML to XML and/or corrected tagging.</item>
</change>
<change>
<date value="2007-09">September 2007</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>Migration</resp>
<name>Ethan Gruber, University of Virginia Library</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Converted XML markup from TEI Lite to uva-dl-tei (TEI P4 with local customizations).</item>
</change>
<change>
<date value="2008-01">January 2008</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>Migration</resp>
<name>Greg Murray, University of Virginia Library</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Programmatically updated TEI header markup (but not header content) for minimal compliance with current QA requirements.</item>
</change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>  
 
<text id="d1">  
<body id="d2"> 

<div1 type="story" id="d3">  <pb n="169"/>   
<head> 
R E X<lb/> 
BY D. H. LAWRENCE<lb/> 
</head> 
 
<p>SINCE every family has its black sheep, it almost follows that 
every man must have a sooty uncle.  Lucky if he hasn't two. 
However, it is only with my mother's brother that we are concerned. 
She had loved him dearly when he was a little blond boy.  When 
he grew up black, she was always vowing she would never speak to 
him again.  Yet when he put in an appearance, after years of absence,  
she invariably received him in a festive mood, and was even 
flirty with him. 
 
</p><p>He rolled up one day in a dog-cart, when I was a small boy.  He 
was large and bullet-headed and blustering, and this time, sporty. 
Sometimes he was rather literary, sometimes coloured with business. 
But this time he was in checks, and was sporty.  We viewed him 
from a distance. 
 
</p><p>The upshot was, would we rear a pup for him.  Now my mother 
detested animals about the house.  She could not bear the mix-up 
of human with animal life.  Yet she consented to bring up the pup. 
 
</p><p>My uncle had taken a large, vulgar public-house in a large and 
vulgar town.  It came to pass that I must fetch the pup.  Strange 
for me, a member of the Band of Hope, to enter the big, noisy, 
smelly plate-glass and mahogany public-house.  It was called The 
Good Omen.  Strange to have my uncle towering over me in the 
passage, shouting "Hello Johnny, what d'yer want?"  He didn't 
know me.  Strange to think he was my mother's brother, and that 
he had his bouts when he read Browning aloud with emotion and 
<hi rend="italic">&eacute;clat</hi>. 
 
</p><p>I was given tea in a narrow, uncomfortable sort of living-room, 
half kitchen.  Curious that such a palatial pub should show such 
miserable private accomodations, but so it was.  There was I, unhappy,  
and glad to escape with the soft fat pup.  It was winter-time,  
and I wore a big-flapped black overcoat, half cloak.  Under 
the cloak-sleeves I hid the puppy, who trembled.  It was Saturday, 
and the train was crowded, and he whimpered under my coat.  I 
sat in mortal fear of being hauled out for travelling without a dog-ticket.  
   <pb n="170"/>   
However, we arrived, and my torments were for nothing. 
 
</p><p>The others were wildly excited over the puppy.  He was small 
and fat and white, with a brown-and-black head: a fox terrier. 
My father said he had a lemon head&mdash;some such mysterious technical  
phraseology.  It wasn't lemon at all, but coloured like a field 
bee.  And he had a black spot at the root of his spine. 
 
</p><p>It was Saturday night&mdash;bath-night.  He crawled on the hearth-rug  
like a fat white tea-cup, and licked the bare toes that had just 
been bathed. 
 
</p><p>"He ought to be called Spot," said one.  But that was too ordinary.   
It was a great question, what to call him. 
 
</p><p>"Call him Rex&mdash;the King," said my mother, looking down on 
the fat, animated little tea-cup, who was chewing my sister's little 
toe and making her squeal with joy and tickles.  We took the name 
in all seriousness. 
 
</p><p>"Rex&mdash;the King!"  We thought it was just right.  Not for 
years did I realize that is was a sarcasm on my mother's part.  She 
must have wasted some twenty years or more of irony, on our incurable  
na&iuml;vet&eacute;. 
 
</p><p>It wasn't a successful name, really.  Because my father, and all 
the people in the street failed completely to pronounce the mono-syllable  
Rex.  They all said Rax.  And it always distressed me. 
It always suggested to me seaweed, and rack-and-ruin.  Poor Rex! 
 
</p><p>We loved him dearly.  The first night we woke to hear him 
weeping and whinneying in loneliness at the foot of the stairs. 
When it could be borne no more, I slipped down for him, and he 
slept under the sheets. 
 
</p><p>"I won't have that little beast in the beds.  Beds are not for 
dogs," declared my mother callously. 
 
</p><p>"He's as good as we are "' we cried, injured. 
 
</p><p>"Whether he is or not, he's not going in the beds." 
 
</p><p>I think now, my mother scorned us for our lack of pride.  We 
were a little infra dig., we children. 
 
</p><p>The second night, however, Rex wept the same and in the same 
way was comforted.  The third night we heard our father plod 
downstairs, heard several slaps administered to the yelping, dismayed  
puppy, and heard the amiable, but to us heartless voice 
saying "Shut it then!  Shut thy noise, 'st hear?  Stop in thy basket, 
stop there!" 
 
</p><p>"It's a shame!" we shouted, in muffled rebellion, from the sheets.</p> 
 
   <pb n="171"/>   
<p>"I'll give you shame, if you don't hold your noise and go to 
sleep," called our mother from her room.  Whereupon we shed 
angry tears and went to sleep.  But there was a tension. 
 
</p><p>"Such a houseful of idiots would make me detest the little beast, 
even if he was better than he is," said my mother. 
 
</p><p>But as a matter of fact, she did not detest Rexie at all.  She 
only had to pretend to do so, to balance our adoration.  And in 
truth, she did not care for close contact with animals.  She was 
too fastidious.  My father, however, would take on a real dog's 
voice, talking to the puppy: a funny, high, sing-song falsetto which 
he seemed to produce at the top of his head.  "'S a pretty little dog! 
's a pretty little doggy!&mdash;ay!&mdash;yes!&mdash;he is, yes!&mdash;Wag thy strunt, 
then!  Wag thy strunt, Raxie!&mdash;Ha-ha!  Nay, tha munna&mdash;" 
This last as the puppy, wild with excitement at the strange falsetto 
voice, licked my father's nostrils and bit my father's nose with his 
sharp little teeth. 
 
</p><p>"'E makes blood come," said my father. 
 
</p><p>"Serves you right for being so silly with him," said my mother. 
It was odd to see her as she watched the man, my father, crouching 
and talking to the little dog and laughing strangely when the little 
creature bit his nose and toused his beard.  What does a woman 
think of her husband at such a moment? 
 
</p><p>My mother amused herself over the names we called him. 
 
</p><p>"He's an angel&mdash;he's a little butterfly&mdash;Rexie, my sweet!" 
 
</p><p>"Sweet!  A dirty little object!" interpolated my mother.  She 
and he had a feud from the first.  Of course he chewed boots and 
worried our stockings and swallowed our garters.  The moment 
we took off our stockings he would dart away with one, we after 
him.  Then as he hung, growling vociferously, at one end of the 
stocking, we at the other, we would cry: 
 
</p><p>"Look at him, mother!  He'll make holes in it again."  Whereupon  
my mother darted at him and spanked him sharply. 
 
</p><p>"Let go, Sir, you destructive little fiend." 
 
</p><p>But he didn't let go.  He began to growl with real rage, and 
hung on viciously.  Mite as he was, he defied her with a manly 
fury.  He did not hate her, nor she him.  But they had one long 
battle with one another. 
 
</p><p>"I'll teach you, my Jockey!  Do you think I'm going to spend 
my life darning after your destructive little teeth!  I'll show you 
if I will!"</p> 
 
   <pb n="172"/>   
<p>But Rexie only growled more viciously.  They both became 
really angry, whilst we children expostulated earnestly with both. 
He would not let her take the stocking from him. 
 
</p><p>"You should tell him properly, mother.  He won't be driven," 
we said. 
 
</p><p>"I'll drive him further than he bargains for.  I'll drive him out 
of my sight for ever, that I will," declared my mother, truly angry. 
He would put her into a real temper, with his tiny, growling defiance. 
 
</p><p>"He's sweet!  A Rexie, a little Rexie!" 
 
</p><p>"A filthy little nuisance!  Don't think I'll put up with him." 
 
</p><p>And to tell the truth, he was dirty at first.  How could he be 
otherwise, so young!  But my mother hated him for it.  And perhaps  
this was the real start of their hostility.  For he lived in the 
house with us.  He would wrinkle his nose and show his tiny dagger-teeth  
in fury when he was thwarted, and his growls of real 
battle-rage against my mother rejoiced us as much as they angered 
her.  But at last she caught him <hi rend="italic">in flagrante</hi>.  She pounced on him, 
rubbed his nose in the mess, and flung him out into the yard.  He 
yelped with shame and disgust and indignation.  I shall never forget  
the sight of him as he rolled over, then tried to turn his head 
away from the disgust of his own muzzle, shaking his little snout 
with a sort of horror, and trying to sneeze it off.  My sister gave 
a yell of despair, and dashed out with a rag and a pan of water, 
weeping wildly.  She sat in the middle of the yard with the befouled  
puppy, and shedding bitter tears she wiped him and washed 
him clean.  Loudly she reproached my mother.  "Look how much 
bigger you are than he is.  It's a shame, it's a shame!" 
 
</p><p>"You ridiculous little lunatic, you've undone all the good it 
would do him, with your soft ways.  Why is my life made a curse 
with animals!  Haven't I enough as it is&mdash;" 
 
</p><p>There was a subdued tension afterwards.  Rex was a little white 
chasm between us and our parent. 
 
</p><p>He became clean.  But then another tragedy loomed.  He must 
be docked.  His floating puppy-tail must be docked short.  This 
time my father was the enemy.  My mother agreed with us that 
it was an unnecessary cruelty.  But my father was adamant.  "The 
dog'll look a fool all his life, if he's not docked."  And there was 
no getting away from it.  To add to the horror, poor Rex's tail  
   <pb n="173"/>   
must be <hi rend="italic">bitten</hi> off.  Why bitten? we asked aghast.  We were assured  
that biting was the only way.  A man would take the little 
tail and just nip it through with his teeth, at a certain joint.  My 
father lifted his lips and bared his incisors, to suit the description. 
We shuddered.  But we were in the hands of fate. 
 
</p><p>Rex was carried away, and a man called Rowbotham bit off the 
superfluity of his tail in the Nags Head, for a quart of best and 
bitter.  We lamented our poor diminished puppy, but agreed to find 
him more manly and <hi rend="italic">comme il faut</hi>.  We should always have 
been ashamed of his little whip of a tail, if it had not been shortened.   
My father said it had made a man of him. 
 
</p><p>Perhaps it had.  For now his true nature came out.  And his 
true nature, like so much else, was dual.  First he was a fierce, 
canine little beast, a beast of rapine and blood.  He longed to hunt, 
savagely.  He lusted to set his teeth in his prey.  It was no joke 
with him.  The old canine Adam stood first in him, the dog with 
fangs and glaring eyes.  He flew at us when we annoyed him.  He 
flew at all intruders, particularly the postman.  He was almost a 
peril to the neighbourhood.  But not quite.  Because close second 
in his nature stood that fatal need to love, the <hi rend="italic">besoin d'aimer</hi> which 
at last makes an end of liberty.  He had a terrible, terrible necessity  
to love, and this trammelled the native, savage hunting beast 
which he was.  He was torn between two great impulses: the native 
impulse to hunt and kill, and the strange, secondary, supervening 
impulse to love and obey.  If he had been left to my father and 
mother, he would have run wild and got himself shot.  As it was, 
he loved us children with a fierce, joyous love.  And we loved him. 
 
</p><p>When we came home from school we would see him standing at 
the end of the entry, cocking his head wistfully at the open country 
in front of him, and meditating whether to be off or not: a white, 
inquiring little figure, with green savage freedom in front of him. 
A cry from a far distance from one of us, and like a bullet he hurled 
himself down the road, in a mad game.  Seeing him coming, my 
sister invariably turned and fled, shrieking with delighted terror. 
And he would leap straight up her back, and bite her and tear her 
clothes.  But it was only an ecstasy of savage love, and she knew it. 
She didn't care if he tore her pinafores.  But my mother did. 
 
</p><p>My mother was maddened by him.  He was a little demon.  At 
the least provocation, he flew.  You had only to sweep the floor,  
   <pb n="174"/>   
and he bristled and sprang at the broom.  Nor would he let go. 
With his scruff erect and his nostrils snorting rage, he would turn 
up the whites of his eyes at my mother, as she wrestled at the other 
end of the broom.  "Leave go, Sir, leave go!"  She wrestled and 
stamped her foot, and he answered with horrid growls.  In the end 
it was she who had to let go.  Then she flew at him, and he flew at 
her.  All the time we had him, he was within a hair's-breadth of 
savagely biting her.  And she knew it.  Yet he always kept sufficient  
self-control. 
 
</p><p>We children loved his temper.  We would drag the bones from 
his mouth, and put him into such paroxysms of rage that he would 
twist his head right over and lay it on the ground upside-down, because  
he didn't know what to do with himself, the savage was so 
strong in him and he must fly at us.  "He'll fly at your throat one 
of these days," said my father.  Neither he nor my mother dared 
have touched Rex's bone.  It was enough to see him bristle and roll 
the whites of his eyes when they came near.  How near he must 
have been to driving his teeth right into us, cannot be told.  He 
was a horrid sight snarling and crouching at us.  But we only 
laughed and rebuked him.  And he would whimper in the sheer 
torment of his need to attack us. 
 
</p><p>He never did hurt us.  He never hurt anybody, though the 
neighbourhood was terrified of him.  But he took to hunting.  To 
my mother's disgust, he would bring large dead bleeding rats and 
lay them on the hearth-rug, and she had to take them up on a shovel. 
For he would not remove them.  Occasionally he brought a mangled 
rabbit, and sometimes, alas, fragmentary poultry.  We were in terror  
of prosecution.  Once he came home bloody and feathery and 
rather sheepish-looking.  We cleaned him and questioned him and 
abused him.  Next day we heard of six dead ducks.  Thank 
heaven no one had seen him. 
 
</p><p>But he was disobedient.  If he saw a hen he was off, and calling 
would not bring him back.  He was worst of all with my father, 
who would take him walks on Sunday morning.  My mother would 
not walk a yard with him.  Once, walking with my father, he 
rushed off at some sheep in a field.  My father yelled in vain.  The 
dog was at the sheep, and meant business.  My father crawled 
through the hedge, and was upon him in time.  And now the man 
was in a paroxysm of rage.  He dragged the little beast into the 
road and thrashed him with a walking stick.</p> 
 
   <pb n="175"/>   
<p>"Do you know you're thrashing that dog unmercifully?" said a 
passer-by. 
 
</p><p>"Ay, an' mean to," shouted my father. 
 
</p><p>The curious thing was that Rex did not respect my father any 
the more, for the beatings he had from him.  He took much more 
heed of us children, always. 
 
</p><p>But he let us down also.  One fatal Saturday he disappeared. 
We hunted and called, but no Rex.  We were bathed, and it was 
bed-time, but we would not go to bed.  Instead we sat in a row in 
our night-dresses on the sofa, and wept without stopping.  This 
drove our mother mad. 
 
</p><p>"Am I going to put up with it?  Am I?  And all for that hateful  
little beast of a dog!  He shall go!  If he's not gone now, he 
shall go." 
 
</p><p>Our father came in late, looking rather queer, with his hat over 
his eye.  But in his staccato tippled fashion he tried to be consoling. 
 
</p><p>"Never mind, my duckie, I s'll look for him in the morning." 
 
</p><p>Sunday came&mdash;Oh, such a Sunday.  We cried, and didn't eat. 
We scoured the land, and for the first time realized how empty and 
wide the earth is, when you're looking for something.  My father 
walked for many miles&mdash;all in vain.  Sunday dinner, with rhubarb  
pudding, I remember, and an atmosphere of abject misery 
that was unbearable. 
 
</p><p>"Never," said my mother, "never shall an animal set foot in this 
house again, while I live.  I knew what it would be!  I knew." 
 
</p><p>The day wore on, and it was the black gloom of bed-time, when 
we heard a scratch and an impudent little whine at the door.  In 
trotted Rex, mud-black, disreputable, and impudent.  His air of 
off-hand "how d'ye do!" was indescribable.  He trotted round with 
<hi rend="italic">suffisance</hi>, wagging his tail as if to say "Yes, I've come back.  But 
I didn't need to.  I can carry on remarkably well by myself." 
Then he walked to his water, and drank noisily and ostentatiously. 
It was rather a slap in the eye for us. 
 
</p><p>He disappeared once or twice in this fashion.  We never knew 
where he went.  And we began to feel that his heart was not so 
golden as we had imagined it. 
 
</p><p>But one fatal day re-appeared my uncle and the dog-cart.  He 
whistled to Rex, and Rex trotted up.  But when he wanted to 
examine the lusty, sturdy dog, Rex became suddenly still, then 
sprang free.  Quite jauntily he trotted round&mdash;but out of reach of 
   <pb n="176"/>   
my uncle.  He leaped up, licking our faces, and trying to make us 
play. 
 
</p><p>"Why what ha' you done wi' the dog&mdash;You've made a fool of 
him.  He's softer than grease.  You've ruined him.  You've 
made a damned fool of him," shouted my uncle. 
 
</p><p>Rex was captured and hauled off to the dog-cart and tied to the 
seat.  He was in a frenzy.  He yelped and shrieked and struggled, 
and was hit on the head, hard, with the butt-end of my uncle's whip, 
which only made him struggle more frantically.  So we saw him 
driven away, our beloved Rex, frantically, madly fighting to get 
to us from the high dog-cart, and being knocked down, whilst we 
stood in the street in mute despair. 
 
</p><p>After which, black tears, and a little wound which is still alive 
in our hearts. 
 
</p><p>I saw Rex only once again, when I had to call just once at The 
Good Omen.  He must have heard my voice, for he was upon me in 
the passage before I knew where I was.  And in the instant I knew 
how he loved us.  He really loved us.  And in the same instant 
there was my uncle with a whip, beating and kicking him back, and 
Rex cowering, bristling, snarling. 
 
</p><p>My uncle swore many oaths, how we had ruined the dog for ever, 
made him vicious, spoiled him for showing purposes, and been altogether  
a pack of mard-soft fools not fit to be trusted with any dog 
but a gutter-mongrel. 
 
</p><p>Poor Rex!  We heard his temper was incurably vicious, and he 
had to be shot. 
 
</p><p>And it was our fault.  We had loved him too much, and he had 
loved us too much.  We never had another pet. 
 
</p><p>It is a strange thing, love.  Nothing but love has made the dog 
lose his wild freedom, to become the servant of man.  And this 
very servility or completeness of love makes him a term of deepest 
contempt.&mdash;"You dog!" 
 
</p><p>We should not have loved Rex so much, and he should not have 
loved us.  There should have been a measure.  We tended, all of 
us, to overstep the limits of our own natures.  He should have 
stayed outside human limits, we should have stayed outside canine 
limits.  Nothing is more fatal than the disaster of too much love. 
My uncle was right, we had ruined the dog. 
 
</p><p>My uncle was a fool, for all that.</p> 
 
   
</div1> 
</body> 
</text> 
</TEI.2> 
 
