<?xml version="1.0"?>

<?dlps id="LesSmit"?>
<?dlps page-images="none" figure-images="no"?>
<?dlps transcription="other"?>

<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/tei-p4/tei2.dtd" [
<!ENTITY % POSTKB "INCLUDE">
<!ENTITY % TEI.extensions.ent SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.ent">
<!ENTITY % TEI.extensions.dtd SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.dtd">
<!ENTITY % ISOnum SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/charent/iso-num.ent"> %ISOnum;
<!ENTITY % ISOlat1 SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/charent/iso-lat1.ent"> %ISOlat1;
 
]> 
<TEI.2 id="LesSmit"> 
<teiHeader type="migrated" creator="Etext">
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title type="main">The Political Economy of Adam Smith</title>
<title type="sort">political economy of adam smith</title>
<author>Leslie, T.E. Cliffe, 1826-1882</author>
<respStmt> 
<resp>Creation of machine-readable version:</resp> 
<name>McMaster University Archive for the History of Economic Thought</name> 
<resp>Conversion to TEI.2-conformant markup:</resp> 
<name>University of Virginia Library Electronic Text Center.</name>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt> 
<extent>ca. <num type="kilobytes">47</num> kilobytes</extent> 
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>University of Virginia Library</publisher>
<pubPlace>Charlottesville, Virginia</pubPlace> 
<idno type="ETC">LesSmit</idno> 
<date value="2001">2001</date>
<availability status="public">
<p n="copyright">Copyright &copy; 2001 by the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia</p>
<p n="access">Publicly accessible</p>
</availability>
<idno type="uva-pid">uva-lib:476150</idno>
</publicationStmt>
<seriesStmt>
<title>University of Virginia Library, Text collection</title>
<idno type="uva-set">UVA-LIB-Text</idno>
</seriesStmt> 
<sourceDesc>
<biblFull>
<titleStmt>
<title type="main">The Political Economy of Adam Smith</title>
<title level="m">The Fornightly Review, November 1, 1870</title>
<title type="sort">political economy of adam smith</title>
<author>T.E. Cliffe Leslie</author>
</titleStmt> 
<publicationStmt> 
<idno type="callNo">Source copy consulted: None Available</idno>
</publicationStmt> 
<notesStmt>
<note>
<p>Corrector could not obtain a copy of the printed original text</p>
</note>
</notesStmt>
</biblFull>
</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc> 
<encodingDesc>
<projectDesc>
<p>Prepared for the University of Virginia Library Electronic Text Center.</p>
</projectDesc> 
<editorialDecl>
<p>All unambiguous end-of-line hyphens have been removed, and the  trailing part of a word has been joined to the preceding line.</p> 
<p id="ETC">Some keywords in the header are a local Electronic Text Center scheme  to aid in establishing analytical groupings.</p>
</editorialDecl> 
</encodingDesc> 
<profileDesc>
<creation>
<date value="1870">1870</date>
</creation> 
<langUsage>
<language id="eng" usage="main">English</language>
</langUsage> 
<textClass>
<keywords>
<term>nonfiction</term> 
<term>prose</term> 
<term>masculine</term> 
</keywords> 
</textClass>
</profileDesc> 
<revisionDesc>
<change>
<date value="2002-07">July, 2002</date> 
<respStmt>
<resp>corrector</resp> 
<name>Wilson Brissett, Electronic Text Center</name>
</respStmt> 
<item>Added TEI header and tags.</item>
</change> 
<change>
<date value="2005-07">July 2005</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>Corrector</resp>
<name>John Ivor Carlson</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Converted SGML to XML and/or corrected tagging.</item>
</change>
<change>
<date value="2007-09">September 2007</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>Migration</resp>
<name>Ethan Gruber, University of Virginia Library</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Converted XML markup from TEI Lite to uva-dl-tei (TEI P4 with local customizations).</item>
</change>
<change>
<date value="2008-01">January 2008</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>Migration</resp>
<name>Greg Murray, University of Virginia Library</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Programmatically updated TEI header markup (but not header content) for minimal compliance with current QA requirements.</item>
</change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader> 
 
<text id="d1"> 
<body id="d2"> 
 
<div1 type="essay" id="d3"> 
<div2 type="text" id="d4"><head>THE POLITICAL ECONOMY OF ADAM SMITH</head> 
 
<p>`Political Economy belongs to no nation; it is of no country: it is the science of the rules for the production, the 
accumulation, the distribution, and the consumption of wealth. It will assert itself whether you wish it or not. It is founded 
on the attributes of the human mind, and no power can change it.'<ref target="n1">(1)</ref> In these wordsaccompanying an admission that the 
Irish Land Bill, which he nevertheless defended on other grounds, `offended against the principles of political economy`Mr. 
Lowe gave expression last session to the conception of one school of the followers of Adam Smith, that Political Economy 
is, not what Adam Smith called his own treatise, `An Inquiry into the Nature and Causes of the Wealth of Nations,' but a 
final answer to the inquirya body of necessary and universal truth, founded on invariable laws of nature, and deduced from 
the constitution of the human mind. </p> 
 
<p>I venture to maintain, to the contrary, that political economy is not a body of natural laws in the true sense, or of universal 
and immutable truths, but an assemblage of speculations and doctrines which are the result of a particular history, coloured 
even by the history and character of its chief writers; that, so far from being of no country, and unchangeable from age to 
age, it has varied much in different ages and countries, and even with different expositors in the same age and country; that, 
in fact, its expositors, since the time of Adam Smith, are substantially divisible into two schools, following opposite 
methods; and that the method of one of them, of which the fundamental conception is, that their political economy is an 
ascertained body of laws of nature, is an offshoot of the ancient fiction of a Code of Nature and a natural order of things, in 
a form given to that fiction in modem times, by theology on one hand, and a revolt against the tyranny of the folly and 
inequality of such human codes as the world had known on the other. </p> 
 
<p>No branch of philosophical doctrine, indeed, can be fairly investigated or apprehended apart from its history. All our systems 
of politics, morals, and metaphysics would be different if we knew exactly how they grew up, and what transformations they 
have undergone; if we knew, in short, the true history of human ideas. And the history of political economy, at any rate, is 
not lost. It would not be difficult to trace the connection between every extant treatise prior to the `Wealth of Nations,' and 
conditions of thought at the epoch at which it appeared. But there is the less occasion, for the purpose of these pages, or of 
ascertaining the origin and foundation of the economic doctrines of our own day, to go behind the epoch of Adam Smith, 
that he has himself traced the systems of political economy antecedent to his own to a particular course of history, to `the 
different progress of opulence in different ages and nations,' and `the private interests and prejudices of particular orders of 
men.' What he did not see was, that his own system, in its turn, was the product of a particular history; that what he 
regarded as the System of Nature was a descendant of the System of Nat-are as conceived by the ancients, in a form 
fashioned by the ideas and circumstances of his own time, and. coloured by his own disposition and course of life. Still less 
could he see how, after his time, `the progress of opulence' would govern the interpretation of his doctrines, or how the 
system he promulgated as the system of liberty, justice, and divine benevolence, would be moulded into a system of 
selfishness by `the private interests and prejudices of particular orders of men.' </p> 
 
<p>`The Wealth of Nations,' says Mr. Buckle, `is entirely deductive. Smith generalizes the laws of wealth, not from the 
phenomena of wealth, but from the phenomena of selfishness. He makes men naturally selfish; he represents them as 
pursuing wealth for sordid objects, and for the narrowest personal pleasures.<ref target="n2">(2)</ref> This description is not misapplied to a 
political economy of later days, which has guided Mr. Buckle's interpretation of the system of Adam Smith; but with respect 
to that system itself, it involves two fundamental misconceptions. Selfishness was not the fundamental principle of Adam 
Smith's theory; and his method, though combining throughout a vein of unsound a priori speculation, was in a large measure 
inductive. The investigation which establishes this will be found also to exhibit the connection between his economic system 
and the chief problems pressing for solution in his time; the methods which the philosophy of the age provided for their 
solution; and the history and phenomena of the economic world in which he lived, and from which his ideas, his inductions, 
and his verifications were drawn. </p> 
 
<p>One consideration to be carried in mind in the interpretation of the `Wealth of Nations' is that its author's system of 
philosophy ought to be studied as a whole; his economic system was part of a complete system of social, or, as he called it, 
moral philosophy. Mr. Buckle, who on other points has much misconceived the `Wealth of Nations,' properly says of it, and 
the `Theory of Moral Sentiments,' that the two must be taken together and considered as one, both forming part of the 
scheme embraced in his course of moral philosophy at Glasgowa course which, it is important to observe, began with 
Natural Theology, and included, along with Ethics and Political Economy, the Philosophy of Law. Again, as his social 
philosophy should be considered as a whole, so the whole should be considered in connection with the philosophical systems 
or methods of investigation of his time. Two `essentially opposite systems of reasoning respecting the fundamental laws of 
human society were before the world at that epoch, which may be respectively designated as the theory of a Code of Nature, 
and the inductive system of  Montesquieuthe former speculating a priori about `Nature,' and seeking to develop from a  
particular hypothesis the `Natural' order of things; the latter investigating in history and the  phenomena of the actual world 
the different states of society and their antecedents or causesor,  in short, the real, as contrasted with an ideal, order of 
things. The peculiarity of Adam Smith's  philosophy is, that it combines these two opposite methods, and hence it is that we 
have two  systems of political economy claiming descent from himone, of which Mr. Ricardo was the  founder, reasoning 
entirely from hypothetical laws or principles of nature, and discarding  induction not only for the ascertainment of its 
premises, but even for the verification of its  deductive conclusions; the otherof which Malthus in the - generation after 
Adam Smith, and Mr.  Mill in our own, may be taken as the representativescombining, like Adam Smith himself, the  a  
priori  and the inductive methods, reasoning sometimes, it is true, from pure hypotheses, but also  from experience, and 
shrinking from no corrections which the test of experience may require in  deductions. Of the two schools, distinguished by 
their methods, the first finds in assumptions  respecting the nature of man, and the course of conduct it prompts, a complete 
`natural'  organization of the economic world, and aims at the discovery of `natural prices,' `natural wages,'  and `natural 
profits.' </p> 
 
<p>  An examination of Adam Smith's philosophy enables us to trace to its foundation the t theory upon which the school in 
question has built its whole superstructure. We shall see that the  original foundation is in fact no other than that theory of 
Nature which, descending through Roman jural philosophy from the speculations of Greece, taught that there is a simple 
Code of Nature which human institutions have disturbed, though its principles are distinctly visible though them, and a 
beneficial and harmonious natural order of things which appears wherever Nature is left to itself. In the last century this 
theory assumed a variety of forms and disguises, all of them, however, involving one fundamental fallacy of reasoning a 
priori from assumptions obtained, not by the interrogation but by the anticipation of Nature; what is assumed as Nature 
being at bottom a mere conjecture respecting its constitution and arrangements. The political philosophy flowing from this 
ideal source presents to us sometimes an assumed state of nature or of society in its natural simplicity; sometimes an 
assumed natural tendency or order of events, and sometimes a law or principle of human nature; and these different aspects 
greatly thicken the confusion perpetually arising between the real and the ideal, between that which by the assumption ought 
to be and that which actually is. The philosophy of Adam Smith, though combining an inductive investigation of the real 
order of things, is pervaded throughout by this theory of Nature, in a form given to it by theology, by political history, and 
by the cast of his own mind. `The great and leading object of his speculations,' says Dugald Stewart, by no means intending a 
criticism, for Mr. Maine had not then explored the fallacies lurking in the terms Nature and Natural Law, `is to illustrate the 
provisions made by Nature in the principles of the human mind, and in the circumstances of man's external situation, for a 
gradual and progressive augmentation in the means of national wealth, and to demonstrate that the most effectual  means of 
advancing a people to greatness is to maintain that order of things which Nature has pointed out.' At the end of Book IV. of 
the `Wealth of Nations' we find the Code of Nature and its institutions definitely marked out: `All systems either of 
preference or restraint being completely taken away, the obvious and simple system of natural liberty establishes itself of its 
own accord. According to the system of natural liberty, the State has only three duties to attend to:' namely, to protect the 
nation from foreign aggressions, to administer justice, and to maintain certain great institutions beyond the reach of 
individual enterprisea supposed natural limitation of the province of law and government which has been the cause of 
infinite error in both theoretical political economy and practical legislation. </p> 
 
<p>The same fundamental conception pervades both Smith's system of ethics and his philosophy of law. Investigating the 
character of virtue, he treats first of `the order in which Nature recommends objects to the care of individuals' for their own 
personal happiness; next, of `the order which Nature has traced out for the direction of our powers of beneficence: first, 
towards other individuals; and, secondly, towards societies.' So, in the description given by himself of his proposed history 
of jurisprudence, he states that `every system of positive law may be regarded as a more or less imperfect attempt towards a 
system of natural jurisprudence;' and that the main end of jural inquiry is to ascertain `what were the natural rules of justice, 
independent of all positive institutions `a description, perfectly coinciding with Mr. Maine's, of the place which the law of 
Nature filled in the conception of the Roman jurist. `After  Nature had become a household word, the belief gradually 
prevailed among the Roman lawyers that the old Jus Gentium was in fact the lost Code of Nature. The Roman conceived 
that, by careful observation of existing institutions, parts of them could be singled out which either exhibited already, or 
could by judicious purification be made to exhibit, the vestiges of the reign of Nature.'<ref target="n3">(3)</ref> </p> 
 
<p>But abstraction would never have played so great a part in Adam Smith's philosophy, would never have resulted in such 
sweeping generalizations respecting the beneficent and equitable economy resulting from the play of the natural inclinations 
and individual interests of men, had not the classical conception of Nature's harmonious code become blended with the 
theological conception of `that great, benevolent, and all-wise Being, who directs all the movements of Nature, and who is 
determined to maintain in it at all times the greatest possible quantity of happiness.' Ideas thus derived from early philosophy 
became converted into the plans of Providence. Mr. Buckle displays less than his customary erudition when he states that 
theology had been finally separated from morals in the seventeenth centuryfrom politics before the middle of the eighteenth. 
</p> 
 
<p>Natural theology makes the first part of Adam Smith's course of moral philosophy, and its principles pervade every other 
part. The law of Nature becomes with him an article of religious belief; the principles of human nature, in accordance with 
the nature of their Divine Author, necessarily tend to the most beneficial employments of man's faculties and resources. And 
as the classical conception of Nature supposed simplicity, harmony, order, and equality in the moral as in the physical world, 
in Adam Smith's philosophy it becomes associated with divine equity and equal benevolence towards all mankind, and by 
consequence with a substantially equal distribution of wealth, as the means of material happiness. Nothing, therefore, is 
needed from human legislationand this conclusion was powerfully fortified, as we shall afterwards see, by the political ideas 
of the agebeyond the maintenance of equal justice and security for every man to pursue his own interest in his own way. In 
the `Wealth of Nations,' after laying it down that every individual endeavours as much as he can both to employ his capital in 
the support of domestic industry, and so to direct that industry that its produce may be of the greatest value, and Therefore 
necessarily labours to render the annual revenue of his own nation as great as he can, Adam Smith adds: `He generally, 
indeed, neither intends to promote the public interest, nor knows how much he is promoting it. By preferring the support of 
domestic to that of foreign industry, he intends only his own security; and by directing that industry that its freedom may be 
of the greatest value, he intends only his own gain, and he is in this, as in many other cases, led by an invisible hand to 
promote an end which was no part of his intention.' </p> 
 
<p>So in the `Theory of Moral Sentiments:<ref target="n4">(4)</ref> `The produce of the soil maintains at all times nearly that number of inhabitants 
which it is capable of maintaining. The rich only select from the heap what is most precious and agreeable. They consume 
little more than the poor, and, in spite of their natural selfishness and rapacity, though they mean only their own 
conveniency, though the sole end which they propose from the labours of all the thousands whom they employ be the 
gratification of their own vain and insatiable desires, they divide with the poor the produce of all their improvements. They 
are led by an invisible hand to make nearly the same distribution of the necessaries of life which would have been made had 
the earth been divided into equal portions among all its inhabitants; and thus without intending it, without knowing it, 
advance the interest of the society, and afford means to the multiplication of the species. When Providence divided the earth 
among a few lordly masters, it neither forgot nor abandoned those who seemed to have been left out in the partition.' </p> 
 
<p>The mischief done in political economy by this assumption respecting the beneficent constitution of Nature, and therefore of 
all human inclinations and desires, has been incalculable. It became an axiom of science with many economists, and with all 
English statesmen, that by a natural law the interests of individuals harmonize with the interests of the public; and one 
pernicious consequence is, that the important department of the consumption of wealth hasthough Mr. Lowe properly 
includes it in his definition of political economybeen in reality either altogether set aside, as lying beyond the pale of 
economic investigation, or passed over with a general assumption, after the manner of Mandeville, that private vices are 
public benefits. The real interests which determine the production, and subsequently, in the course of consumption, in a great 
degree the distribution, of wealth, are the interests of consumers; although the truth is veiled by the division of labour, the 
process of exchange, and the intervention of money, which makes wealth in the abstract, or pecuniary interest, seem the 
motive of producers. If every man produced for himself what he desires to consume or use, it would be patent how diverse 
are the interests summed up in one vague general term, self-interestinterests which vary in different individuals, different 
classes, different nations, and different states of civilization. And economic investigation would long since have penetrated 
beneath the surface of pecuniary interest to the widely different character of the real aims determining the nature and uses of 
wealth, but for that assumption of an identity between public and private interest which Adam Smith's authority converted 
into an axiom. Under its influence we find him assuming that the great landowners of the sixteenth century, in enclosing their 
`manors and dismissing tenants, retainers, and labourers, to purchase luxuries for themselves, employed no less national 
labour than before; although the land fed sheep instead of men, and the wool of the sheep, in place of clothing labourers at 
home, went from the country to foreigners in exchange for wines, silks, velvets, and trinkets, for the personal consumption 
of the lord of the manor. When William the Conqueror afforested at once some three-score parishes, he did only what 
landowners have done from the fifteenth century to the present time. To take the children's food and give it unto dogs is, by 
this reasoning, to give it back to the children! </p> 
 
<p>The Nature hypothesis had, however, with Adam Smith another powerful ally besides theology in the idea of liberty. The 
idea of civil and religious liberty, of resistance to arbitrary government and unequal laws, of confidence in individual reason 
and private judgment as opposed to the dictates of external authority, had begun even in the seventeenth century to spread 
from the world of religion and politics to the daily business of life. At the beginning of the second half of the eighteenth 
century the predominant form which this idea took was the liberation of individual effort in the world of industry and trade 
from oppressive restrictions and arbitrary and unequal imposts; and it found in the Code of Nature a quasi-philosophical 
basis on which to build a complete economic `system of natural liberty.' The French Revolution, of which the seeds were 
then being sown by the Economistes (or Physiocrates, as they were afterwards called, from the name they gave to their 
system, a name denoting the government of society by nature or natural laws), was, in its origin, an economic revolution, a 
`rebellion of the belly,' stirred up  ab initio  by the Economistes, who saw in the fetters and insecurity of industry the cause of 
the poverty of France, and in the superior freedom and security of its cultivators and tradespeople the secret of the superior 
prosperity of Great Britain. Living in such a world of human misgovernment and suffering toil, beholding, as the 
Physiocrates did, all the natural sources of wealth locked up by human laws, it is not surprising that the doctrine of a Code 
of Nature, of natural rights of liberty and property, of a natural organization of society for the increase of human prosperity 
and a just distribution of the fruits of the earth and of industry, came upon them like a new revelation, and carried the 
authority of one. Thus, like Adam Smith, on whom their doctrines had no small influence, the Physiocrates invested the ideal 
Code of Nature, which had come to them through the lawyers of their country from the jurisprudence of Rome, with a 
divine origin, and found in it a complete circumscription and definition of the province of human sovereignty. The three 
same fundamental conceptions derived from the three same sourcesfrom Graeco-Roman speculation, from Christian 
theology, and from the revolt of the age against arbitrary interference with private industry and unequal imposts on the fruits 
of labour, formed the groundwork of the political economy of Adam Smith and the Physiocrates: the sole difference in this 
respect is, that the latter gave the name political economy to the whole of social philosophy, while Adam Smith limits the 
particular name to a department of social philosophy relating to wealth, and that they enunciated these doctrines as laws of 
Nature and God with more passionate emphasis. Adam Smith had not derived any of the three fundamental ideas of his 
political economy from the Physiocrates for those ideas came to both from the history and philosophy of the past, and from 
the circumstances of the agebut he was strongly confirmed in them by his visits to France, his personal intercourse with 
them, and his study of their writings; he caught from them, moreover, not only particular propositions and expressions, but 
something of the form which his doctrine of natural distribution has taken, and also the precise limitation which he gives to 
the functions of the State. </p> 
 
<p>Smith was himself so sensible of his debt to the Physiocrates, that he not only speaks of Quesnay's system as `the nearest 
approximation to the truth that had been published upon the subject of political economy,' but was prevented only by 
Quesnay's death from dedicating to him his own great treatise. He was, however, under a much more solid obligation to a 
much greater Frenchman, the illustrious Montesquieu. Mr. Buckle, who in his excellent chapters on the `Intellectual History 
of France' justly traces to England the origination of the spirit of liberty which in the eighteenth century took possession of 
French philosophy, nevertheless does injustice at once to France and to Great Britain in overlooking the influence of 
ontesquieu over Scotch philosophy in Adam Smith's age. And the same oversight, coupled with a view of political 
economy which Mr. Buckle himself adopted from Ricardo and his school, leads him to describe Adam Smith's method as 
entirely deductive. The philosophy of Great Britain, Mr. Buckle affirms, owes nothing to France; and he represents the 
intellect of Scotland as having~ under clerical guidance, become wholly deductive, referring as a crucial example to Adam 
Smith, Scotland's most eminent political philosopher. The clerical system of deductive reasoning certainly runs through and 
warps the whole philosophy of Adam Smith. Nevertheless, his philosophical love of truth, and of interrogating nature itself 
in its real phenomena, and the inductive method of doing so which Scotch philosophy in his age had adopted from 
ontesquieu, preserved him from many errors into which the method of deduction from assumptions respecting Nature and 
its laws has led one school of his followers, which at the present day is not backward in claiming the clerical prerogative of 
orthodoxy. It has already been observed that two opposite systems of reasoning were before the world in Adam Smith's age, 
and that he combined them boththe system of reasoning from a theoretical law of Nature, and the historical inductive 
method of Montesquieu, which traces the real order of things, and seeks in the circumstances and history of society the 
explanation of its different states in different ages and countries. The latter method had a powerful attraction for a new 
school of political and jural philosophy in Scotland to which Adam Smith belonged. Lord Kaimes, his literary patron, and 
illar, his own pupil, alike followed Montesquieu's method. Dalrymple, also a disciple of Lord Kaimes, states in the 
dedication of his `History of Feudal Property`a work which seems to have afforded Adam Smith not a few important 
suggestionsthat much of his manuscript had actually been `revised by the greatest genius of the age, President 
ontesquieu.' And Millar expressly states that in his lectures on the Philosophy of Law, his great master `followed the plan 
which seems to have been suggested by Montesquieu; endeavouring to trace the gradual progress of jurisprudence from the 
earliest to the most refined ages, and to point out the effect of those arts which contribute to subsistence and to the 
accumulation of property in producing corresponding improvements in law and government.' But, as Mr. Buckle himself 
says, Adam Smith's political economy and the rest of his philosophy were `part of a single scheme.' And a comparison of 
Books iii., iv., and v. (chapter i.) of the `Wealth of Nations' with Adam Smith's own description, on the one hand, of the 
work he had previously contemplated on the History of Law, and Millar's account of his lectures, on the other, shows how 
closely connected were his economic and his jural researches. So closely indeed were they so, that internal evidence 
confirms the statement of Dugald Stewart, that he actually published in the `Wealth of Nations' a valuable part of the work 
he had long before announced on the jural history of mankind; and we have in this fact a probable explanation of the story 
that he destroyed a few days before his death the manuscript of his lectures on jurisprudence. He preserved in the `Wealth of 
Nations' what he probably thought their most valuable results.<ref target="n5">(5)</ref> </p> 
 
<p>The problem which Adam Smith proposed to himself was by no means only the illusive one, What is a priori the order of 
Nature, or `the natural progress of opulence?' He inquired further' What had been the actual order of things, the actual 
progress of opulence, and its causes?' What had occasioned the slow progress of Europe from the time of the barbarian 
conquests down to modern times? What the more rapid advance of Great Britain than of France and other parts of the 
continent? To answer these inquiries he subjected the phenomena of history and the existing state of the world to a searching 
investigation, traced the actual economic progress of different countries, the influences of laws of succession, and of the 
political distribution of property, the action and reaction of legal and industrial changes, and the real movements of wages 
and profits so far as they could be ascertained. Nor was he content with the inductions of the closet from written 
evidencethough necessarily the most important field of inductive investigation in social philosophyhe compared all the 
phenomena which careful personal observation, both in his own country and in France, had brought under his view. In short, 
he added to the experience of mankind a large personal experience for inductive investigation. Even the Physiocrates, 
although their study of actual phenomena was much less comprehensive and minute, though they were far more given to 
accepting at once their own unverified ideas as laws of nature, yet by no means neglected experience entirely. They had 
studied the economic condition of their own country, and compared it with what they knew of Great Britain; and they 
believed their theories of the natural order of things founded on the evidence of the results of interference with industry and 
spoliation of its fruits on the one hand, and of individual liberty and security of property on the other. The extent to which 
observation guided their doctrines is remarkably illustrated by their division substantially into two schools, whose 
conclusions, though converging in the main, were reached by different paths of personal experience, and moulded by it. 
Quesnay, the son of a small farmer, reared in the country amid the sufferings of the peasantry and the stagnation of 
agriculture under despotic restriction and ruinous imposts, and knowing of what imprisoned riches the soil was possessed, 
taught that land was the sole original source of wealth, agriculture the sole really productive employment, to whose fruits 
other industries gave only changes of form or place. Gournay, on the other hand, a merchant himself, and of a line of 
merchants, made the freedom of trade his staple doctrine, and summed up in the maxim, Laissez faire et passer, the duties of 
government.<ref target="n6">(6)</ref> The distinction exemplifies, moreover, that influence of personal history on the forms of political economy to 
which reference has been made. </p> 
 
<p>There ran thus through the political economy of both Adam Smith and the Physiocrates, though much more extensively and 
systematically in the former, a combination of the experience philosophy, of inductive investigation, with  a priori  speculation 
derived from the Nature hypothesis. Hence, while on one hand the inductive method preserved the great Scotchman from 
grave errors into which not a few of his English followers in the mother-country of inductive philosophy have been led by 
the  a priori  method, on the other hand the bias given by preconceived ideas was so strong in the case of Smith himself, as to 
cause him to see in all his inductions proofs of a complete code of nature of a beneficent order of nature flowing from 
individual liberty and the natural desires and dispositions of men. Like the Physiocrates, he blended the so-called `evidence,' 
or self-evidence, of the law of nature in itself, with the evidence of phenomena carefully collated and sifted. The truth is, that 
Smith wrote before the physical sciences had developed canons of induction, and he thought an induction complete when he 
had obtained an immense number of instances, and a theory proved when it seemed to fit every observed case. Throughout 
history, and over Europe, he saw nothing but disorder and misery from such human legislation as the world had known, 
wherever it went beyond protecting personal liberty and property; he saw on all sides a mass of poverty traceable to State 
interference; the only sources of whatever wealth and prosperity existed were the natural motives to industry, and the natural 
powers of production of individual men, and he leaped to the conclusion that nothing was requisite but to leave Nature to 
itself, that complete harmony existed between individual and public interests, and that the natural conduct of mankind 
secured not only the greatest abundance, but an equal distribution of wealth. He thought he found in phenomena positive 
proof of the Law of Nature, and of the character of its enactments. We find here the explanation of the seeming 
contradiction which Adam Smith's combination of the theory of natural Law with the inductive historical method gives to 
r. Maine's proposition `that the book of Montesquieu, with all its defects, still proceeded on that Historical Method, before 
which the Law of Nature has never maintained its footing for an instant.' It is incontrovertible that historical investigation 
convicts the Nature hypothesis of reproducing a mere fiction of ancient philosophy; nevertheless Adam Smith, partly under 
the bias given by the theory itself, partly because the method of interrogating Nature itself was new, and the canons of 
induction unsettled, conceived that the method of Montesquieu proved the truth of the theory of Nature; in short, that 
nature, when interrogated, confirmed his anticipations of Nature. </p> 
 
<p>One cause of the misconception that Adam Smith's economic method was one of mere a priori deduction is the arrangement 
he has adopted in the order of the five books of the `Wealth of Nations.' In the order of logic the third and fourth books 
come before the first and second. They contain the induction on which is based the conclusion that the State has only to 
protect individual liberty, and the natural effort of every individual to better his own conditionor, in one word (with which 
his first book begins), labourwill supply in the most ample manner all the necessaries and conveniences of life, will divide its 
functions spontaneously in the best manner, and will distribute its produce in a natural order, and with the utmost equality. It 
has already been suggested that no such complete organization for the distribution of wealth is made by individual action, or 
what Adam Smith called Nature. Mr. Mill has shown the fallacy of defining political economy as the science of exchanges; a 
definition which, besides omitting some of the most important conditions determining the production of wealth, overlooks 
the truth that human institutions, laws of property and succession, are necessarily chief agencies in determining its 
distribution. And it affords an instructive exemplification of the two methods which Adam Smith combined,  a priori  
deduction from supposed principles of Nature, and inductive investigation of facts, that when the order of Nature is present 
to his mind, he finds a complete natural organization for the distribution of wealth, and no function for the State in the 
matter; but when he traces the actual progress of opulence, his readers are confronted at once with laws of succession, to 
which he traces the slow and irregular course of European progress after the barbarian conquests;. laws founded on those 
conquests, and designed to perpetuate the unequal distribution of wealth they effected; laws which are potent agencies in the 
distribution of wealth in England to this day, and in the determination of its whole social and industrial economy. </p> 
 
<p>But even while tracing in his first book the `natural' distribution of wealth by exchange, or as he expresses it, `the order 
according to which the produce of labour is naturally distributed among the different ranks of the people,' Adam Smith has 
been preserved by the inductive method which he combined with a priori deduction from enormous fallacies into which the 
school of Ricardo has since been betrayed by their method of pure deduction. The ancient theory of natural law involved the 
idea of uniformity and equality; and this idea in Adam Smith's case was powerfully reinforced both by that of an ideal order 
deducible from the equity and equal benevolence towards mankind of the Author of Nature, and by the love of system, 
symmetry, and harmonious arrangement which plays a conspicuous part in the `Theory of Moral Sentiments,' because it did 
so in the author's own mind. With all these conceptions the theory of a complete equality of the advantages and 
disadvantages of different human occupations, and an equality, in that sense, of wages and profits, had obviously a powerful 
attraction for Smith. It affords surprising evidence of his true philosophical spirit of inquiry into facts that he should 
nevertheless have denied the actual equality of wages and profits, traced the great actual inequalities to their causes, and 
defined the conditions of equality and inequality, and the actual effect of industrial progress on these movements, in such a 
manner as to indicate the very progressive divergence which can be shown to have since taken place, and which a school of 
modern economists not only ignores, but sometimes angrily denies, as inconsistent with its a priori deductions. Adam Smith, 
for his own part, not only limited ab initio the tendency to equality to what was practically the same neighbourhood, but 
pointed out that the kingdom was in fact divided into a number of different neighbourhoods with very different rates. 
Secondly, he traced many of the actual inequalities to pernicious institutions, a class of causes of inequality which later 
economists have done much to perpetuate by affirming a substantial equality. Thirdly, in place of insisting that competition 
alone determines the rate of wages, and gives the labourer the utmost value of what he produces, Adam Smith maintained 
that combination on one hand, tacit or open, on the part of employers, was the normal condition of things; while, on the 
other, the necessitous position of the labourer exposed him to the exaction of very unequal terms. Fourthly, he expressly 
confined the tendency to equality in the case of both wages and profits, even where competition was in full and free activity, 
to a stationary and simple condition of the industrial world. Fifthly, he showed that in place of equalizing wages, industrial 
progress had already produced great inequalities in England, and was beginning to do so in Scotland. </p> 
 
<p>After observing that the price of labour varied much more in England than in Scotland, he adds: `In the last century the most 
usual day wages of common labour through the greater part of Scotland were sixpence in summer and fivepence in winter. 
Three shillings a-week, the same price very nearly, still continues to be paid in some parts of the Highlands. Through the 
greater part of the low country the most usual wages of common labour are now eightpence a-day; tenpence, and sometimes 
a shilling about Edinburgh, in the counties which border upon England, and in a few other places where there has lately been 
a considerable rise in the demand for labour, about Glasgow, Carron, Ayrshire, &amp;c. In England the improvements of 
agriculture, manufactures, and commerce began much earlier than in Scotland. The demand for labour, and consequently its 
price, must necessarily have increased with those improvements.' </p> 
 
<p>Manufactures and trade on a great scale were only beginning in Scotland; the steam-engine had not yet been brought to bear 
on the mine or the loom when the `Wealth of Nations' was composed; and the great inequalities in the local demand for 
labour throughout the kingdom, which have followed in the wake of steam, were yet to appear. Adam Smith, in truth, lived 
in a very early industrial world; the only steam-engine he refers to is Newcomen's; the word `manufacture' had not lost its 
true meaning and become as inappropriate as hideous. In the clothing manufacture, he expressly says, the division of labour 
was nearly the same as it had been for a century, and the machines employed were the same; adding that only three 
improvements in them of any importance had taken place since the reign of Edward IV. In place of the infinite diversities of 
complexity and difficulty in the different employments of capital which have followed the progress of mechanics and 
chemistry, all modes of employing capital were, he says, about equally easy. The foreign trade of the kingdom was so small 
that he computed the annual importation of corn at only 23,000 quarters, and concluded that the freest importation never 
could sensibly affect. prices in the home market. </p> 
 
<p>In short, he applied the doctrine of equality only to a simple and almost stationary condition of industry and neighbourhood 
trade, in which few changes in the mode of production or the channels of trade took place from one century to another, and 
in which the inhabitants of each neighbourhood might comparatively easily estimate the profits and prospects of each 
different employment; and even to such a world, only with many modifications and exceptions. To such a world, in positive 
terms, he limited the tendency to equality which has been made by his successors, not only an unconditional assumption, but 
the basis of finance. The truth is, that the doctrine of a tendency to equality is a mere theorem in political economy; and a 
theorem which imports the tendency only under special conditions well enunciated by Adam Smithconditions the opposites 
of those which prevail in the present industrial world. </p> 
 
<p>A state of the industrial world which was exceptional in Adam Smith's time is the normal state in our own; and it is  certain, 
both from his positive doctrine and from his close attention to the realities of life, that had he lived even two generations 
later, his general theory of the organization of the economic world and the results of the competition for economic life 
would have been cast in a very different mould. Alike in the theory of Nature which pervades his entire philosophy of 
society, and in his general conceptions of the industrial world, we trace the influence of the early world in which he lived. 
One striking example of this is that one-half of society has been almost entirely overlooked in his philosophy. His language 
appears at first sight to point to unrestricted liberty as the unconditional principle of a true political economy, and the 
-indispensable requisite of the full development of the economic resources of nature; but on closer inspection it will be found 
that where he speaks of `the natural effort of every individual to better his own condition, when suffered to exert itself with  
freedom and security,' as the cause of national wealth and prosperity, he had only the half of the nation denoted by the 
masculine pronoun in his mind; he meant only what he elsewhere says, `the natural effort of every man.' He seems to have 
been perfectly contentthough it involves an inconsistency which is fatal to his whole theorywith the existing restraints on 
the energies of women; and the only effort on the part of a woman to better her own condition which he has in view is `to 
become the mistress of a family.' In the only passage m the `Wealth of Nations' in which women are referred to, we discover 
at once how far was he from having developed universal laws of industry and wealth, how far he was from escaping from 
the ideas of a primitive world. `There are,' he said, `no public institutions for the education of women, and there is 
accordingly nothing useless, absurd, or fantastical, in the common course of their education. They are taught what their 
parents or guardians judge it necessary or useful for them to learn, and they are taught nothing else. Every part of their 
education tends evidently to some useful purposeeither to improve the natural attractions of their person, or to form their 
minds to reserve, to modesty, to chastity, and to economy; to render them both likely to become the mistresses of a family, 
and to behave properly when they have become such. In every part of her life a woman feels same convenience or advantage 
from every part of her education.' </p> 
 
<p>Although `the obvious and simple system of natural liberty' is the foundation of Smith's whole system, though he regarded it 
as the law of the beneficent Author of Nature, it turns out that he applied it only to one-half of mankind. The reason is that 
the law and the exception alike came to him from the age in which he lived, and the ideas of a yet earlier state of society. 
The insurrection against the oppressive and unequal economic regime of the past was as yet only on the part of men; and the 
very theory of the Law of Nature which men invoked for their own emancipation, as it was the offspring of the speculation 
of the ancient world, so it bore the impress of its narrowness and injustice.   </p> 
</div2> 
 
<div2 type="notes" id="d5"><head>NOTES</head> 
 
<note id="n1"><seg type="note-symbol">1.</seg> <p>Speech on the Irish Land Bill, April 4th, 1870.</p></note> 
<note id="n2"><seg type="note-symbol">2.</seg> <p>History of Civilization in England, i. 228; ii. 449.</p></note> 
<note id="n3"><seg type="note-symbol">3.</seg> <p>Ancient Law, pp. 56, 88.</p></note> 
<note id="n4"><seg type="note-symbol">4.</seg> <p>Theory of Moral Sentiments. Part iv., chap. i.</p></note> 
<note id="n5"><seg type="note-symbol">5.</seg> <p>An eminent Scotch philosopher of the present day, Mr. Alexander Bain, has expressed to me a doubt that Adam Smith 
destroyed anything which he considered valuable; adding, that be was little disposed to consider anything to which he had 
given research and thought of small value. The preservation of the chief results of his jural studies in the Wealth of Nations 
reconciles Mr. Bain's opinion on this point with the destruction of the manuscripts, of which there seems to me conclusive 
evidence.</p></note> 
<note id="n6"><seg type="note-symbol">6.</seg> <p>Les &Eacute;conomistes Fran&ccedil;ais du XVIIIme Si&egrave;cle, by M. L&eacute;once de Lavergne, pp. 173-6.</p></note> 
</div2> 
</div1> 
</body> 
</text> 
</TEI.2> 
