<?xml version="1.0"?>

<?dlps id="LevFnor"?>
<?dlps page-images="none" figure-images="no"?>
<?dlps transcription="other"?>

<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/tei-p4/tei2.dtd" [
<!ENTITY % POSTKB "INCLUDE">
<!ENTITY % TEI.extensions.ent SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.ent">
<!ENTITY % TEI.extensions.dtd SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.dtd">
<!ENTITY % ISOnum SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/charent/iso-num.ent"> %ISOnum;
<!ENTITY % ISOpub SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/charent/iso-pub.ent"> %ISOpub;
]> 
 
<TEI.2 id="LevFnor"> 
<teiHeader type="migrated" creator="Etext">
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title type="main">Frank Norris</title>
<title type="sort">frank norris</title>
<author>Levick, Milne B.</author>
<respStmt>
<resp>Creation of machine-readable version:</resp> 
<name>Judy Boss</name> 
<resp>Conversion to TEI.2-conformant markup:</resp>  
<name>University of Virginia Library Electronic Text Center.</name>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt> 
<extent>ca. <num type="kilobytes">22</num> kilobytes</extent> 
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>University of Virginia Library</publisher>
<pubPlace>Charlottesville, Virginia</pubPlace> 
<idno type="ETC">LevFnor</idno> 
<date value="1996">1996</date>
<availability status="public">
<p n="copyright">Copyright &copy; 1996 by the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia</p>
<p n="access">Publicly accessible</p>
</availability>
<idno type="uva-pid">uva-lib:476151</idno>
</publicationStmt>
<seriesStmt>
<title>University of Virginia Library, Text collection</title>
<idno type="uva-set">UVA-LIB-Text</idno>
</seriesStmt> 
<sourceDesc>
<biblFull>
<titleStmt>
<title type="main">Frank Norris</title>
<title level="j">Overland Monthly</title>
<title type="sort">frank norris</title>
<author>Milne B. Levick</author>
</titleStmt> 
<editionStmt>
<p>n. s. 45</p>
</editionStmt> 
<extent>504-508.</extent> 
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>California Pub. Co.</publisher> 
<pubPlace>San Francisco</pubPlace> 
<date value="1905-06">June 1905</date>
</publicationStmt> 
</biblFull>
</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc> 
<encodingDesc>
<projectDesc>
<p>Prepared for the University of Virginia Library Electronic Text Center.</p>
</projectDesc> 
<editorialDecl>
<p>All quotation marks retained as data.</p> 
<p>Spell-check and verification made 
against printed text using WordPerfect spell checker.</p> 
<p>All unambiguous end-of-line hyphens have been removed, and the 
trailing part of a word has been joined to the preceding line.</p> 
<p>The images exist as archived TIFF images, one or more JPEG versions 
for general use, and thumbnail GIFs.</p> 
<p id="ETC">Keywords in the header are a local Electronic Text Center scheme  
to aid in establishing analytical groupings.</p>
</editorialDecl> 
<refsDecl>
<p>ID elements are given for each page element and are composed of the text's 
unique cryptogram and the given page number, as in AusEmma1 for page one of  
Jane Austen's Emma.</p>
</refsDecl> 
</encodingDesc> 
<profileDesc>
<creation>
<date value="1905">1905</date>
</creation> 
<langUsage>
<language id="eng" usage="main">English</language>
</langUsage> 
<textClass>
<keywords>
<term>non-fiction; prose</term>
</keywords> 
</textClass>
</profileDesc> 
<revisionDesc>
<change>
<date value="1996-05">May 1996</date> 
<respStmt>
<resp>corrector</resp> 
<name>Judy Boss</name>
</respStmt> 
<item>page 505 para. 1 line 5  Varamee] Vanamee; 
page 506 para. 7 line 2  immeasureably] immeasurably; 
page 507 para. 2 line 4  Annixeter] Annixter; 
page 507 para. 5 line 1  animaculae] animalculae; 
page 507 para. 5 line 3  Varamee] Vanamee.</item>
</change> 
<change>
<date value="1996-05">May 1996</date> 
<respStmt>
<resp>corrector</resp> 
<name>Catherine Tousignant</name>
</respStmt> 
<item>Added TEI header and tags</item>
</change> 
<change>
<date value="2005-07">July 2005</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>Corrector</resp>
<name>John Ivor Carlson</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Converted SGML to XML and/or corrected tagging.</item>
</change>
<change>
<date value="2007-09">September 2007</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>Migration</resp>
<name>Ethan Gruber, University of Virginia Library</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Converted XML markup from TEI Lite to uva-dl-tei (TEI P4 with local customizations).</item>
</change>
<change>
<date value="2008-01">January 2008</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>Migration</resp>
<name>Greg Murray, University of Virginia Library</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Programmatically updated TEI header markup (but not header content) for minimal compliance with current QA requirements.</item>
</change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader> 
 
<text id="d1">  

<body id="d2"> 
<div1 type="essay" id="d3">  <pb n="504"/>   
<head><hi rend="bold">Frank Norris</hi><lb/> 
BY MILNE B. LEVICK</head> 
 
<p>FRANK NORRIS has been dead over two years.  The rush of faddists, of 
readers of new books only, has passed.  Norris has been honored with a 
limited, and, alas! complete edition.  But his books are still in 
demand, and if, as he thought, in the end the people are always right, 
Norris will not soon be forgotten. 
 
</p><p>To understand his work, it is necessary for one to remember from 
what standpoint he himself regarded it. 
 
</p><p>The key-note of his point of view is that "life is better than 
literature."  "Novel-writing, of all the arts, is the most virile; of 
all the arts it will not flourish indoors.  Dependent solely on 
fidelity to life for existence, it must be practiced in the very 
heart's heart of life, on the street corner, in the market place, not 
in the studios." 
 
</p><p>Realism, brutality, Zola and Norris are often spoken of 
together.  To deny brutality would have been ludicrous, even had 
Norris cared to do so.  But realism, as he understood it, he did deny, 
and proclaimed his master of the period of "McTeague" to be, indeed, 
"the very head of the romanticists." 
 
</p><p>"Romance is the kind of fiction that takes cognizance of 
variations from the type of normal life," he says.  "Realism is the 
kind of fiction that confines itself to the type of normal life." 
According to this definition, then, romance may even treat of the 
sordid, the unlovely&mdash;as, for instance, the novels of Zola.  Zola has 
been dubbed a realist, but he is, on the contrary, the very head of 
the romanticists. 
 
</p><p>"Also, realism, used as it sometimes is, as a term of reproach, 
need not be in the remotest sense or degree offensive, but on the other 
hand, respectable as a church and proper as a deacon&mdash;as, for instance, 
the novels of Mr. Howells. 
 
</p><p>"To romance belongs the wide world for range and the unplumbed 
depths of the human heart, and the mystery of sex, and the problems of 
life, and the black, unsearched penetralia of the human soul." 
 
</p><p>It is equally important for one to remember this: "The men and 
women of the story-teller's world are not apt to be, to him, so 
important in themselves as the whirl of things in which he chooses to 
involve them." 
 
</p><p>Frank Norris does not write of farmers and capitalists and 
outcasts&mdash;it is the wheat, the railroad, the terror of the city.  He 
saw the epic value of forces, and in this lies the originality of his 
literary outlook. 
 
</p><p>It is typical of this man, who lived and saw so much that "he 
followed many masters."  The influences of Kipling, Stevenson, Zola and 
Hugo are most evident in his work.  Harding Davis was a power in the 
early days, and in "The Ship That Saw a Ghost," there is a suggestion 
of Poe's "Narrative of A. Gordon Pym."  Although Condy Rivers, Norris' 
picture of himself in the early part of his career, was affected by De 
Maupassant, for one not thoroughly familiar with the Frenchman's work, 
it is difficult to find any trace of his power over Norris. 
 
</p><p>Of Stevenson's influence, no one that has read "Moran of the 
Lady Letty" need be reminded. 
 
</p><p>It may be that such minor slips as "the balance of the crew," 
"only two alternatives," and the like, which are to be found all 
through Norris' works, are due to the Scotchman's 
 
   <pb n="505"/>   
 
example, though they might be expected in a writer of Norris' 
temperament. 
 
</p><p>Naturally, Kipling's influence is most clearly seen in the short 
stories.  One effect of his hold on Norris is the inclination toward 
mysticism found in all the latter's works&mdash;the warning sense of the 
pursued McTeague, the enemy of Lloyd Searight, the character of 
Vanamee.  But "the little, spectacled colonial, to whose song we must 
all listen, and to whose pipe we must all dance," may be held partly 
responsible for a fault the direct opposite of this&mdash;excessive 
realism, or, adopting Norris' own terms, realism.  The description of 
the dental operation in "McTeague," for instance, is quite as tiresome 
as some of the technicalities of the engine room indulged in by 
Kipling. 
 
</p><p>"The Octopus," Norris' greatest work, is distinctly Hugoesque. 
By imitating his masters, Stevenson, when at last he found himself, 
became "the greatest of the stylists."  Norris followed the same plan 
intentionally, if one can judge by "The Mechanics of Fiction."  His own 
individuality was developing rapidly, however, all the while he was 
following his preceptors. 
 
</p><p>Throughout all his works, from the curiosity that caused the 
hero of "Moran" to speak to the man in the sweater to the end of "The 
Pit," we find him more interested in the whirl of things, in forces, 
than in men. 
 
</p><p>But perhaps the most noticeable characteristic of his style is 
his point of view that life is better than literature, that striving 
for "sincerity, sincerity, and again sincerity." 
 
</p><p>Norris' climaxes often strike one like blows, yet if we examine 
them, we can find nothing unnatural in the abruptness. 
 
</p><p>For him everything had a particular odor&mdash;"aroma" and "redolent" 
are favorite words, a peculiarity which has a specially pleasing 
effect in his description of women.  A more mechanical characteristic 
is his habit of repeating certain phrases again and again, though at 
times the insistence is not so happy as in others.  The local color in 
his books and tales is faultless.  One can still have tea in the 
identical room where Blix and Condy agreed to be chums; Luna's is 
flourishing, and who can pass Polk street without looking for the big 
gold tooth?  In a great measure the local color for "The Octopus" was 
gotten upon a large ranch near Tres Pinos, although in the book Los 
Muertes is located near "Bonneville" (Tulare.)  Annixter is drawn 
largely from the owner of this ranch, whose wife served to some extent 
as a model for Mrs. Derrick. 
 
</p><p>From his essays, however, it is evident that Norris never 
regarded local color as other than a means to an end.  But his 
fidelity to life does not stop even at actual names and incidents. 
 
</p><p>"There was the inevitable Studebaker" wagon; in "Moran" the 
ambergris was to go to Langley &amp; Michaels; McTeague gave up Yale 
Mixture for Mastiff tobacco.  The incident in "The Octopus" of the 
plows which, coming from the East, had to pass Bonneville, go to San 
Francisco, and then be returned to the farmers at the short haul rate, 
is founded on fact.  The very climax of this, his masterpiece, is but 
an account of the Mussel Slough affair, which occurred in Tulare 
County, California, in 1878. 
 
</p><p>By some, "Moran," Norris' first novel, is ranked among his best 
work.  Despite its faults, it certainly has "all the roll and plunge of 
action."  Even here we find traces of his later style; for instance: 
the habit of repeating, and the sudden climax, and his sense of smell. 
 
</p><p>The forces in "McTeague" are much more clearly defined than 
those in "Moran."  Trina's avarice had its source centuries before her 
birth in the Swiss mountains, among    <pb n="506"/>   the race that 
saved they knew not why&mdash;saved merely to save.  With the dentist, too, 
heredity is a power, though his fall is more of a reversion to his 
former life than a deterioration. 
 
</p><p>That wonderful picture of the growth of miserliness in Trina 
proves Norris to have been a sincere student of what he describes as 
"The Mechanics of Fiction."  A sentence suffices for the first mention 
of her niggardliness, next it occupies a paragraph, then a page, and 
finally, working its way into the details, permeates the entire 
story.  No less powerful is the description of the effects of alcohol 
on the ex-car boy. 
 
</p><p>Although the brutalities of "McTeague" exceed those of "Moran," 
and the impression the book leaves is far from pleasant, it has, like 
all Norris wrote, much humor, often coarse, often over-drawn, like the 
character work, but still enough to relieve the general gloomy tone at 
the time of reading, at least.  And despite Boston, in that story of 
the Polk street dentist, among the coarseness and cruelty and 
melodrama, Norris found romance. 
 
</p><p>Despite Norris' gift, that of the born story-teller, of knowing 
what points to omit and what ideas to inject, the character of Condy 
Rivers in "Blix" is the best picture of the early Frank Norris we can 
have.  Realism leads him to introduce many ideas into the Love Idyl, 
in one way or another, that he actually "worked up" into stories, 
among them his first mention of the wheat. 
 
</p><p>Even here there is another force than love&mdash;the force of the 
swinging cycle of fate, the whirl of things. 
 
</p><p>"There, in that room, high above the city, a little climax had 
come swiftly to a head, a crisis in two lives had suddenly developed. 
The moment that had been in preparation for the last few months, the 
last few years, the last few centuries, behold! it had arrived." 
 
</p><p>In "A Man's Woman," also, love is not the only power.  Each of 
the two main characters has an antagonistic force, the Arctic region 
for Bennett and the enemy for Lloyd.  Here, too, we have glimpses of 
the machine of the gods. 
 
</p><p>"For an instant Lloyd saw deep down into the black, mysterious 
gulf of sex&mdash;down, down, down, where, immeasurably below the world of 
little things, the changeless, dreadful machinery of life itself 
worked, clashing and resistless in its grooves.  It was a glimpse 
fortunately brief, a vision that does not come too often, lest reason, 
brought to the edge of the abyss, grow giddy at the sight, and 
reeling, topple head-long." 
 
</p><p>The keynote of the story, however, lies in this: 
 
</p><p>"God, Man and the Work&mdash;the three elements of our entire system, 
the universal epitomized in the tremendous trinity." 
 
</p><p>It is curious that Norris, who had so much individuality, should 
have held the idea, brought forward in the essay, "Novelists to 
Order," in "The Responsibilities of the Novelist," that "every child 
contains in himself the elements of every profession, every 
occupation, every art, every industry," and that the developing of a 
novelist or soldier or business-man is a mere matter of 
specialization.  Perhaps he was led to this belief by his professional 
view that characters are subservient to "the whirl of things in which 
the author chooses to involve them," and by the fact that he used 
himself for two of his principal characters&mdash;Condy and Presley. 
 
</p><p>The article published in the S. F. Argonaut, "In Defense of Dr. 
Lawlor," shows what a friend Norris was&mdash;a friend stanch enough to 
stand by a man when he was down, and more, to fight for him against 
every daily paper in San Francisco.  Some of Norris' best short 
stories are in the book called "A Deal in Wheat," though that from 
which the  
 
   <pb n="507"/>    
 
collection takes its name is inferior to most of the others.  Of the 
tales of the "Three Black Crows," undoubtedly the best is "The Dual 
Personality of Slick Dick Nickerson."  Though good, these stories are 
obviously too reminiscent of Kipling's trio to be ranked among Norris' 
distinctive work.  Some of the others are not as good, perhaps, as many 
that have not found permanent homes.  But the best thing in the book, 
and probably the best of all Norris' short work, is "A Memorandum of 
Sudden Death."  So artfully written that one almost doubts it is 
fiction; it has for its subject a gradually contracting power, an idea 
we find in all of Norris' best work, reduced to an actual physical 
force. 
 
</p><p>Theoretically and practically, Norris defended the novel with a 
purpose.  The purpose of "The Octopus" is found in Cedarquinst's speech 
when he first meets Magnus Derrick: "We are both of us fighters, it 
seems, Mr. Derrick * * each with his particular enemy.  We are well 
met, indeed, the farmer and the monied adventurer, both in the same 
grist between the two mill-stones of the lethargy of the public and the 
aggression of the trust; the two great evils of America."  And he adds: 
"Presley, my boy, there is your epic poem to hand." 
 
</p><p>The influence of Hugo was at its greatest when "The Octopus" was 
written.  Vanamee's dream realized Annixter's coming to himself, and 
the rise of the wheat, all on the same night, is Hugoesque.  That Dyke 
should rob the train carrying Hilma and Annixter on their wedding 
trip, is Hugoesque.  S. Behrman's escape from bomb and revolver, his 
death in the Wheat, and Presley's passage on the ship carrying his 
body, is Hugoesque.  The very complexity of the plot reflects the 
Frenchman's hold on the young Westerner. 
 
</p><p>Like nearly all Norris' work, "The Octopus" is episodical, and 
the interests are diverse.  In Vanamee, we have mysticism.  We have a 
problem in Minna Hooven's fate.  We have delicate suggestiveness in the 
story of Angele; we have brutality in Dyke's fight.  We have satire in 
the picture of society and its fakers, and the literature of the 
"little toy magazines."  There is the broad humor and tragedy of the 
Epic of the West in the dance at Annixter's barn, and above all are 
the two conflicting forces, the railroad and the wheat. 
 
</p><p>Nowhere are forces more apparent than in Norris' chef d'oeuvre; 
even Presley was compelled to recognize in his interview with Shelgrim, 
that the conflict in "The Octopus" is between forces, not men. 
 
</p><p>"Men were nothings, mere animalculae, mere ephemerides that 
fluttered and fell and were forgotten between dawn and dusk.  Vanamee 
had said there was no death.  But for one second Presley could go one 
step further.  Men were nought, death was nought, life was nought. 
Force only existed&mdash;Force that brought men into the world&mdash;Force that 
crowded them out of it to make way for the succeeding generation&mdash;Force 
that made the wheat grow&mdash;Force that garnered it from the soil to give 
place to the succeeding crop." 
 
</p><p>The engine&mdash;"the galloping monster, the terror of steel and 
steam, with its single eye, cyclopean, red, shooting from horizon to 
horizon * * * the symbol of a vast power, huge, terrible, flinging the 
echo of its thunder over all the ranches of the valley, leaving blood 
and destruction in its path; the leviathan, with tentacles of steel 
clutching into the soil, the soulless Force, the iron-hearted power, 
the monster, the colossus, the Octopus." 
 
</p><p>"Men&mdash;motes in the sunshine&mdash;perished, were shot down in the 
very noon of life; hearts were broken; little children started in life 
lamentably handicapped; young girls    <pb n="508"/>   were brought 
to a life of shame; old women died in the heart of life for lack of 
food.  In that little isolated group of human insects, misery, death, 
and anguish spun like a wheel of fire. 
 
</p><p>"But the Wheat remained, untouched, unassailable, that mighty 
world force, that nourisher of nations, wrapped in Nirvanic calm, 
indifferent to the human swarm, gigantic, resistless, moved onward in 
its appointed grooves.  Through the welter of blood at the irrigation 
ditch, through the sham charity and shallow philanthropy of famine 
relief committees, the great harvest of Los Muertos rolled like a flood 
from the Sierras to the Himalayas to feed thousands of starving 
scare-crowd on the barren plains of India." 
 
</p><p>Not till the time of "The Pit" was Norris freed from his 
masters.  Here there is but one coincidence that shows the influence 
of even Hugo&mdash;the crash of the market coming on Laura's birthday.  In 
spite of his emancipation, and the book's greater popular success, 
"The Pit" is inferior to "The Octopus."  This is due, not to the 
handling of the subject, but to the subject itself. 
 
</p><p>Norris' style and temperament are better adapted to an Epic of 
the West than to a story of a nerve center like Chicago, a style that 
treats of forces as Norris' does, loses its power the farther it 
enters the artificiality of our so-called civilization.  We have only 
to consider Norris' books individually to see this.  And the forces of 
"The Pit" are the farthest from the soil of any he writes of.  The 
principal force of the book is the conflict between the wheat and the 
man who would control it, obviously less powerful than such a Titanic 
struggle as the conflict in "The Octopus."  And while the actual grain 
is a living force all through "The Octopus," in the later book it is, 
for the most part, merely an excuse for gambling, until the climax, 
when it crushes Jadwin. 
 
</p><p>"All those millions and millions of bushels of wheat were gone 
now.  The wheat that had killed Cressler, that had engulfed Jadwin's 
fortune and all but unseated reason itself, the wheat that had 
intervened like a great torrent to drag Laura's husband from her side 
and drown him in the roaring vortex of the Pit, had passed on, 
resistless, along its ordered and pre-determined courses, from West to 
East, like a vast Titanic flood; had passed, leaving death and ruin in 
its wake, but bearing life and prosperity to the crowded cities and 
centers of Europe." 
 
</p><p>"This huge, resistless nourisher of nations&mdash;why was it that 
it could 
not reach the people, could not fulfill its destiny, unmarred by 
all this 
suffering, unattended by all this misery?" 
 
</p><p>Frank Norris developed rapidly.  At the time of his death, in 
his thirty-third year, he had written six books, all with exceptional 
vigor and power.  One of them has been called great.  He saw his 
responsibilities and fulfilled them with such sincerity, originality, 
broadness of view, and depth as could only lead him to heights not 
often attained. 
 
</p><p>As it is, the name of Norris is an important one in American 
letters.  Who can say what it might have been?  </p> 
</div1> 
   
</body> 
</text> 
</TEI.2> 
 
