<?xml version="1.0"?>

<?dlps id="LipOpen"?>
<?dlps page-images="none" figure-images="no"?>
<?dlps transcription="other"?>

<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/tei-p4/tei2.dtd" [
<!ENTITY % POSTKB "INCLUDE">
<!ENTITY % TEI.extensions.ent SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.ent">
<!ENTITY % TEI.extensions.dtd SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.dtd">
<!ENTITY % ISOnum SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/charent/iso-num.ent"> %ISOnum;
<!ENTITY % ISOpub SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/charent/iso-pub.ent"> %ISOpub;
 
]> 
<TEI.2 id="LipOpen"> 
<teiHeader type="migrated" creator="Etext">
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title type="main">An Open Mind: William James</title>
<title type="sort">open mind william james</title>
<author>Lippmann, Walter</author>
<respStmt>
<resp>Creation of machine-readable version:</resp>  
<name>Charles Keller</name>  
<resp>Creation of digital images:</resp>  
<name/>  
<resp>Conversion to TEI.2-conformant markup:</resp>  
<name>University of Virginia Library Electronic Text Center.</name>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt>  
<extent>ca. <num type="kilobytes">12</num> kilobytes</extent>  
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>University of Virginia Library</publisher>
<pubPlace>Charlottesville, Virginia</pubPlace>  
<idno type="ETC">LipOpen</idno>  
<date value="1997">1997</date>
<availability status="public">
<p n="copyright">Copyright &copy; 1997 by the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia</p>
<p n="access">Publicly accessible</p>
</availability>
<idno type="uva-pid">uva-lib:476154</idno>
</publicationStmt>
<seriesStmt>
<title>University of Virginia Library, Text collection</title>
<idno type="uva-set">UVA-LIB-Text</idno>
</seriesStmt>  
<sourceDesc>
<biblFull>
<titleStmt>
<title type="main">An Open Mind: William James</title>
<title level="j">Everybody's Magazine, vol. XXIII, no. 6</title>
<title type="sort">open mind william james</title>
<author>Walter Lippmann</author>
<respStmt>
<resp>Editor</resp>  
<name>John O'Hara Cosgrave</name>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt>  
<extent>pages 800-801</extent>  
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>The Ridgway Company Publishers</publisher>  
<pubPlace>New York City, Spring and Macdougal Streets</pubPlace>  
<date value="1910-12">December 1910</date>  
<idno type="callNo">Print copy consulted: UVa library, call no.: AP 2.E9</idno>
</publicationStmt>  
</biblFull>
</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc>  
<encodingDesc>
<projectDesc>
<p>Prepared for the University of Virginia Library Electronic Text Center.</p>
</projectDesc>  
<editorialDecl>
<p>All quotation marks retained as data.</p>  
<p>All unambiguous end-of-line hyphens have been removed, and the trailing part of a word has been joined to the preceding line.</p>  
<p>The images exist as archived TIFF images, one or more JPEG versions for general use, and thumbnail GIFs.</p>  
<p>Keywords in the header are a local Electronic Text Center scheme to aid in establishing analytical groupings.</p>
</editorialDecl>  
</encodingDesc>  
<profileDesc>
<creation>
<date value="1910">1910</date>
</creation>  
<langUsage>
<language id="eng" usage="main">English</language>
</langUsage>  
<textClass>
<keywords>
<term>non-fiction; prose</term>
</keywords>  
</textClass>
</profileDesc>  
<revisionDesc>
<change>
<date value="1997-08">August 1997</date>  
<respStmt>
<resp>corrector</resp>  
<name>Gregory Murray, Electronic Text Center</name>
</respStmt>  
<item>Added TEI header and tags.</item>
</change>  
<change>
<date value="2005-07">July 2005</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>Corrector</resp>
<name>John Ivor Carlson</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Converted SGML to XML and/or corrected tagging.</item>
</change>
<change>
<date value="2007-09">September 2007</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>Migration</resp>
<name>Ethan Gruber, University of Virginia Library</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Converted XML markup from TEI Lite to uva-dl-tei (TEI P4 with local customizations).</item>
</change>
<change>
<date value="2008-01">January 2008</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>Migration</resp>
<name>Greg Murray, University of Virginia Library</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Programmatically updated TEI header markup (but not header content) for minimal compliance with current QA requirements.</item>
</change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>  
 
 
<text id="d1">  
<body id="d2"> 
 
 
 
<div1 type="essay" id="d3">  <pb n="800"/>  
<head> 
AN OPEN MIND: WILLIAM JAMES<lb/> 
<lb/> 
<hi rend="italic">By</hi><lb/> 
<lb/> 
WALTER LIPPMANN 
</head> 
 
<p>WITHIN a week of the death of 
Professor William James of Harvard 
University, the newspapers 
had it that Mr. M. S. Ayer of Boston 
had received a message from his spirit. 
This news item provoked the ridicule of 
the people who don't believe in ghosts, 
but the joke was on Mr. Ayer of Boston. 
When, however, it was reported that 
Professor James himself had agreed to 
communicate with this world, if he could, 
and, in order to test the reports, had left 
a sealed message to be opened at a certain 
definite time after his death, the incredulous 
gasped at the professor's amazing "credulity." 
 
</p><p>William James wasn't "credulous." He 
was simply open-minded. Maybe the soul 
of man <hi rend="italic">is</hi> immortal. The professors couldn't 
prove it wasn't, so James was willing to open 
his mind to evidence. He was willing to hunt 
for evidence, and to be convinced by it. 
 
</p><p>And in that he was simply keeping 
America's promise: he was actually doing 
what we, as a nation, proclaimed that we 
would do. He was tolerant; he was willing 
to listen to what seems preposterous, and 
to consider what might, though queer, be 
true. And he showed that this democratic 
attitude of mind is every bit as 
fruitful as the aristocratic determination 
to ignore new and strange-looking ideas. 
James was a democrat. He gave all men 
and all creeds, any idea, any theory, any 
superstition, a respectful hearing. 
 
</p><p>His interest in spiritualism is merely 
one illustration in a thousand. The hard 
scientists knew it was a hoax because they 
couldn't explain it, and the sentimentalists 
knew it was the truth because they wished 
it to be: but James wanted to know the 
facts. So he went to Mrs. Piper, and heard 
her out. Nay, he listened to Palladino and 
to Munsterberg. They pretended to know, 
and maybe they did. 
 
</p><p>And last year, when Frank Harris 
published his book on Shakespeare, to show 
that the "unknown" life and character of 
the poet could be drawn from his works, 
the other professors laughed the theory out 
of court. James went to Shakespeare and 
read the plays all over again to test the 
Harris theory. Maybe the poet <hi rend="italic">could</hi> be 
known by his works. The fact that the 
theory was revolutionary did not alter the 
possibility that it might be true. 
 
</p><p>So with religion. A scientist, living in 
an age when science is dogmatically irreligious, 
he turned from its cocksure reasoning 
to ask for the facts. He went to the 
lives of the saints! Not to Herbert Spencer, 
you see. When he wanted to study the 
religious experience he went to the people 
who had had it, to Santa Theresa and Mrs. 
Eddy. They might know something the 
professors didn't know. 
 
</p><p>And again: at the age of sixty-five, 
with the whole of New England's 
individualism behind him, he asked about 
socialism. When he met H. G. Wells, he 
listened to the socialist, and, as it happens, 
was converted. So he said so. James was 
no more afraid of a new political theory than 
he was of ghosts, and he was no more 
afraid of proclaiming a new theory, or an 
old one, than he was of being a ghost. 
I think he would have listened with an 
open mind to the devil's account of heaven, 
and I'm sure he would have heard him 
out on hell. 
 
</p><p>James knew that he didn't know. He 
never acted upon the notion that the 
truth was his store of wisdom. Perhaps 
that is why he kept on rummaging about 
in other people's stores, and commending 
their goods. He seemed to take a delight 
in writing introductions, and appreciations 
of new books, and in going out of his way 
to listen to a young doctor of philosophy, 
or an undergraduate discussion of pragmatism, 
or the poetry of an obscure mystic. 
And, optimist that he was, by virtue of 
his unceasing freshness of interest, there 
is nothing more open-minded in our 
 
   <pb n="801"/>   
 
literature than his chivalrous respect for 
the pessimism of Francis Thompson.</p> 
 
<lg type="poem"> 
<l>"Speak not of comfort where no comfort is,</l> 
<l>Speak not at all: can words make foul things fair?</l> 
<l>Our life's a cheat, our death a black abyss:</l> 
<l>Hush and be mute, envisaging despair."</l> 
</lg> 
 
<p>He felt with all sorts of men. He 
understood their demand for immediate 
answers to the great speculative questions 
of life. God, freedom, immortality, nature 
as moral or non-moral&mdash;these were for him 
not matters of idle scientific wonder, but 
of urgent need: The scientific demand 
that men should wait "till doomsday, or 
till such time as our senses and intellect 
working together may have raked in evidence 
enough" for answers to these questions, 
is, says James, "the queerest idol 
ever manufactured in the philosophic cave." 
We cannot wait for a final solution. Our 
daily life is full of choices that we cannot 
dodge, and some guide we simply must 
have. There can be no loitering at the 
crossroads. We are busy. We must choose, 
whether we will it or not, and where all is 
doubt, who shall refuse us the right to 
believe what seems most adapted to our needs? 
Not know, you understand, but believe. 
 
</p><p>That is the famous position taken in 
"The Will to Believe." As James has 
once pointed out, its real title should have 
been "The Right to Believe." No doctrine 
in James's thinking has been more 
persistently misunderstood. Yet it rests 
on the simplest of insights: that atheism 
and theism are both dogmas, for there is 
scientific evidence for neither; that to 
withhold judgment is really to make a 
judgment, and act as if God didn't exist; 
that until the evidence is complete men have 
a right to believe what they most need. 
 
</p><p>James has acted upon that right. He has made a picture compounded 
of the insights of feeling, the elaborations of reason, and the daily 
requirements of men. It is a huge guess, if you like, to be verified 
only at the end of the world.  But it has made many men at home in the 
universe. And this democrat understood the need of feeling at home in 
the world, and he understood also that the aristocrats are not at home 
here. (Perhaps that's why they are aristocrats.) "The luxurious 
classes," he says, "are blind to man's real relation to the globe he 
lives on, and to the permanently hard and solid foundations of his 
higher life." And he prescribed for them&mdash;for their culture, I 
mean&mdash;this treatment: "To coal and iron mines, to freight trains, to 
fishing fleets in December, to dishwashing, clotheswashing and 
windowwashing, to road-building and tunnel-making, to foundries and 
stoke-holes, and to the frames of skyscrapers, would our gilded youths 
be drafted off according to their choice, to get the childishness 
knocked out of them, and to come back into society with healthier 
sympathies and soberer ideas." 
 
</p><p>This, and thoughts like this, and kindnesses like this, put James 
not alone among the democrats of this uncertain world, but among the 
poets also; among the poetic philosophers who, like Goethe, 
Schopenhauer, and Whitman, have a sense of the pace of things. Sunlight 
and storm-cloud, the subdued busyness of outdoors, the rumble of cities, 
the mud of life's beginning and the heaven of its hopes, stain his pages 
with the glad, sweaty sense of life itself. 
 
</p><p>It is an encouraging thought that America 
should have produced perhaps the most 
tolerant man of our generation. It is a 
stimulating thought that he was a man 
whose tolerance never meant the kind of 
timidity which refuses to take a stand 
"because there is so much to be said on 
both sides." As every one knows, he 
fought hard for his ideas, because he 
believed in them, and because he wanted 
others to believe in them. The propagandist 
was strong in William James. 
He wished to give as well as receive. 
And he listened for truth from anybody, 
and from anywhere, and in any form. He 
listened for it from Emma Goldman, the 
pope, or a sophomore; preached from a 
pulpit, a throne, or a soap-box; in the 
language of science, in slang, in fine rhetoric, 
or in the talk of a ward boss. 
 
</p><p>And he told his conclusions. He told them, too, without the 
expert's arrogance toward the man in the street, and without the dainty 
and finicky horror of being popular and journalistic. He would quote Mr. 
Dooley on God to make himself understood among men. He would have heard 
God gladly in the overalls of a carpenter, even though He came to preach 
that the soul of man is immortal. So open-minded was he; so very much of 
a democrat.</p> 
 
   
</div1> 
</body> 
</text> 
</TEI.2> 
 
