<?xml version="1.0"?>

<?dlps id="LonScab"?>
<?dlps page-images="none" figure-images="no"?>
<?dlps transcription="other"?>

<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/tei-p4/tei2.dtd" [
<!ENTITY % POSTKB "INCLUDE">
<!ENTITY % TEI.extensions.ent SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.ent">
<!ENTITY % TEI.extensions.dtd SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.dtd">
<!ENTITY % ISOnum SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/charent/iso-num.ent"> %ISOnum;
<!ENTITY % ISOlat1 SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/charent/iso-lat1.ent"> %ISOlat1;
<!ENTITY % ISOpub SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/charent/iso-pub.ent"> %ISOpub;
 
]> 
<TEI.2 id="LonScab"> 
<teiHeader type="migrated" creator="Etext">
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title type="main">The Scab</title>
<title type="sort">scab</title>
<author>London, Jack</author>
<respStmt>
<resp>Creation of machine-readable version:</resp>  
<name>Charles Keller</name>  
<resp>Creation of digital images:</resp>  
<name/>  
<resp>Conversion to TEI.2-conformant markup:</resp>  
<name>University of Virginia Library Electronic Text Center.</name>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt>  
<extent>ca. <num type="kilobytes">39</num> kilobytes</extent>  
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>University of Virginia Library</publisher>
<pubPlace>Charlottesville, Virginia</pubPlace>  
<idno type="ETC">LonScab</idno>  
<date value="1997">1997</date>
<availability status="public">
<p n="copyright">Copyright &copy; 1997 by the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia</p>
<p n="access">Publicly accessible</p>
</availability>
<idno type="uva-pid">uva-lib:476159</idno>
</publicationStmt>
<seriesStmt>
<title>University of Virginia Library, Text collection</title>
<idno type="uva-set">UVA-LIB-Text</idno>
</seriesStmt>  
<sourceDesc>
<biblFull>
<titleStmt>
<title type="main">The Scab</title>
<title level="j">The Atlantic Monthly: A Magazine of Literature, Science, Art, and Politics. Vol. 93, no. 555.</title>
<title type="sort">scab</title>
<author>Jack London</author>
</titleStmt>  
<extent>pages 54-63</extent>  
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>Houghton, Mifflin and Company. | The Riverside Press.</publisher>  
<pubPlace>Boston and New York. | Cambridge, Mass.</pubPlace>  
<date value="1904">1904</date>  
<idno type="callNo">Print copy consulted: UVa library, call no.: AP2.A8</idno>
</publicationStmt>  
</biblFull>
</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc>  
<encodingDesc>
<projectDesc>
<p>Prepared for the University of Virginia Library Electronic Text Center.</p>
</projectDesc>  
<editorialDecl>
<p>All unambiguous end-of-line hyphens have been removed, and the trailing part of a word has been joined to the preceding line.</p>  
<p>The images exist as archived TIFF images, one or more JPEG versions for general use, and thumbnail GIFs.</p>  
<p>Some keywords in the header are a local Electronic Text Center scheme to aid in establishing analytical groupings.</p>
</editorialDecl>  
</encodingDesc>  
<profileDesc>
<creation>
<date value="1904">1904</date>
</creation>  
<langUsage>
<language id="eng" usage="main">English</language>
</langUsage>  
<textClass>
<keywords>
<term>prose; non-fiction</term>
</keywords>  
</textClass>
</profileDesc>  
<revisionDesc>
<change>
<date value="1997-10">October 1997</date>  
<respStmt>
<resp>corrector</resp>  
<name>Greg Murray, Electronic Text Center</name>
</respStmt>  
<item>Added TEI header and tags.</item>
</change>  
<change>
<date value="2005-07">July 2005</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>Corrector</resp>
<name>John Ivor Carlson</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Converted SGML to XML and/or corrected tagging.</item>
</change>
<change>
<date value="2007-09">September 2007</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>Migration</resp>
<name>Ethan Gruber, University of Virginia Library</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Converted XML markup from TEI Lite to uva-dl-tei (TEI P4 with local customizations).</item>
</change>
<change>
<date value="2008-01">January 2008</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>Migration</resp>
<name>Greg Murray, University of Virginia Library</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Programmatically updated TEI header markup (but not header content) for minimal compliance with current QA requirements.</item>
</change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>  
 
<text id="d1">  
 

 
<front id="d2"> 
 
<div1 type="note" id="d3">  <pb n="54"/>   
<p> 
[Although the author of this paper has been chiefly known to the readers 
of the ATLANTIC as a writer of stories of the Klondike, he has given 
many years to the study of social problems.  The People of the Abyss is 
one of his latest productions in this field. The present article is an 
interesting contribution, from a radical point of view, to the 
ATLANTIC'S series of papers on the Ethics of Business. It is to be 
followed in February by an article, Is Commercialism in Disgrace?  by 
John Graham Brooks.&mdash;THE EDITORS.] 
</p> 
</div1> 
 
</front> 
<body id="d4"> 
 
<div1 type="essay" id="d5"> 
<head>THE SCAB.</head> 
 
<p>IN a competitive society, where men 
struggle with one another for food and 
shelter, what is more natural than that 
generosity, when it diminishes the food 
and shelter of men other than he who 
is generous, should be held an accursed 
thing? Wise old saws to the contrary, 
he who takes from a man's purse takes 
from his existence. To strike at a man's 
food and shelter is to strike at his life, 
and in a society organized on a tooth-and-nail basis, such an act, performed 
though it may be under the guise of 
generosity, is none the less menacing 
and terrible. 
</p><p>It is for this reason that a laborer is 
so fiercely hostile to another laborer who 
offers to work for less pay or longer 
<milestone unit="column"/> 
hours. To hold his place (which is to 
live), he must offset this offer by another 
equally liberal, which is equivalent to 
giving away somewhat from the food 
and shelter he enjoys. To sell his day's 
work for two dollars instead of two dollars 
and a half means that he, his wife, 
and his children will not have so good a 
roof over their heads, such warm clothes 
on their backs, such substantial food in 
their stomachs. Meat will be bought 
less frequently, and it will be tougher 
and less nutritious; stout new shoes will 
go less often on the children's feet; and 
disease and death will be more imminent 
in a cheaper house and neighborhood. 
</p><p>Thus, the generous laborer, giving 
more of a day's work for less return 
   <pb n="55"/>   
(measured in terms of food and shelter), 
threatens the life of his less generous 
brother laborer, and, at the best, if he 
does not destroy that life, he diminishes 
it. Whereupon the less generous laborer 
looks upon him as an enemy, and, as 
men are inclined to do in a tooth-and-nail society, he tries to kill the man who 
is trying to kill him. 
</p><p>When a striker kills with a brick the 
man who has taken his place, he has no 
sense of wrong-doing. In the deepest 
holds of his being, though he does not 
reason the impulse, he has an ethical 
sanction. He feels dimly that he has 
justification, just as the home-defending 
Boer felt, though more sharply, with 
each bullet he fired at the invading English. 
Behind every brick thrown by a 
striker is the selfish "will to live" of 
himself and the slightly altruistic will 
to live of his family. The family-group 
came into the world before the state-group, and society being still on the 
primitive basis of tooth and nail, the 
will to live of the state is not so compelling 
to the striker as the will to live 
of his family and himself. 
</p><p>In addition to the use of bricks, clubs, 
and bullets, the selfish laborer finds it 
necessary to express his feelings in 
speech. Just as the peaceful country-dweller calls the sea-rover a "pirate," 
and the stout burgher calls the man who 
breaks into his strong-box a "robber," 
so the selfish laborer applies the opprobrious 
epithet "scab" to the laborer who 
takes from him food and shelter by being 
more generous in the disposal of his labor-power. The sentimental connotation 
of scab is as terrific as that of "traitor" 
or "Judas," and a sentimental definition 
would be as deep and varied as 
the human heart. It is far easier to arrive 
at what may be called a technical 
definition, worded in commercial terms, 
as, for instance, that <hi rend="italic">a scab is one who 
gives more value for the same price 
than another</hi>. 
</p><p>The laborer who gives more time, or 
<milestone unit="column"/> 
strength, or skill, for the same wage, than 
another, or equal time, or strength, or 
skill, for a less wage, is a scab. This 
generousness on his part is hurtful to his 
fellow laborers, for it compels them to 
an equal generousness which is not to 
their liking, and which gives them less 
of food and shelter. But a word may 
be said for the scab. Just as his act 
makes his rivals compulsorily generous, 
so do they, by fortune of birth and training, 
make compulsory his act of generousness. 
He does not scab because he 
wants to scab. No whim of the spirit, 
no burgeoning of the heart, leads him to 
give more of his labor-power than they 
for a certain sum. 
</p><p>It is because he cannot get work on 
the same terms as they that he is a scab. 
There is less work than there are men 
to do work. This is patent, else the scab 
would not loom so large on the labor-market horizon. Because they are 
stronger than he, or more skilled, or more 
fortunate, or more energetic, it is impossible 
for him to take their places at the 
same wage. To take their places he 
must give more value, must work longer 
hours, or receive a smaller wage. He 
does so, and he cannot help it, for his 
will to live is driving him on as well 
as they are being driven on by theirs, 
and to live he must win food and shelter, 
which he can do only by receiving 
permission to work from some man who 
owns a bit of land or piece of machinery. 
And to receive permission from this man, 
he must make the transaction profitable 
for him. 
</p><p>Viewed in this light, the scab who 
gives more labor-power for a certain 
price than his fellows is not so generous 
after all. He is no more generous with 
his energy than the chattel slave and the 
convict laborer, who, by the way, are 
the almost perfect scabs. They give 
their labor-power for about the minimum 
possible price. But, within limits, they 
may loaf and malinger, and, as scabs, 
are exceeded by the machine, which 
   <pb n="56"/>   
never loafs and malingers, and which is 
the ideally perfect scab. 
</p><p>It is not nice to be a scab. Not only is it 
not in good social taste and comradeship, 
but, from the standpoint of food and 
shelter, it is bad business policy. Nobody 
desires to scab, to give most for 
least. The ambition of every individual 
is quite the opposite,&mdash;to give least for 
most; and as a result, living in a tooth-and-nail society, battle royal is waged 
by the ambitious individuals. But in its 
most salient aspect, that of the struggle 
over the division of a joint-product, it is 
no longer a battle between individuals, 
but between groups of individuals. Capital 
and labor apply themselves to raw 
material, make something useful out of 
it, add to its value, and then proceed to 
quarrel over the division of the added 
value. Neither cares to give most for 
least. Each is intent on giving less than 
the other and on receiving more. 
</p><p>Labor combines into its unions; capital 
into partnerships, associations, corporations, 
and trusts. A group-struggle 
is the result, in which the individuals, as 
individuals, play no part. The Brotherhood 
of Carpenters and Joiners, for instance, 
serves notice on the Master Builders' 
Association that it demands an increase 
of the wage of its members from 
$3.50 a day to $4.00, and a Saturday 
half-holiday without pay. This means 
that the carpenters are trying to give less 
for more. Where they received $21.00 
for six full days, they are endeavoring to 
get $22.00 for five days and a half,&mdash;that is, they will work half a day less 
each week and receive a dollar more. 
</p><p>Also, they expect the Saturday half-holiday to give work to one additional 
man for each eleven previously employed. 
This last affords a splendid example of 
the development of the group idea. In 
this particular struggle the individual 
has no chance at all for life. The individual 
carpenter would be crushed like 
a mote by the Master Builders' Association, 
and like a mote the individual master 
<milestone unit="column"/> 
builder would be crushed by the 
Brotherhood of Carpenters and Joiners. 
</p><p>In the group-struggle over the division 
of the joint-product, labor utilizes the 
union with its two great weapons,&mdash;the 
strike and boycott; while capital utilizes 
the trust and the association, the weapons 
of which are the blacklist, the lockout, 
and the scab. The scab is by far the 
most formidable weapon of the three. 
He is the man who breaks strikes and 
causes all the trouble. Without him 
there would be no trouble, for the strikers 
are willing to remain out peacefully 
and indefinitely so long as other men 
are not in their places, and so long as 
the particular aggregation of capital with 
which they are fighting is eating its head 
off in enforced idleness. 
</p><p>But both warring groups have reserve 
weapons up their sleeves. Were it not 
for the scab, these weapons would not be 
brought into play. But the scab takes 
the places of the strikers, who begin at 
once to wield a most powerful weapon,&mdash;terrorism. The will to live of the scab 
recoils from the menace of broken bones 
and violent death. With all due respect 
to the labor leaders, who are not 
to be blamed for volubly asseverating 
otherwise, terrorism is a well-defined and 
eminently successful policy of the labor 
unions. It has probably won them more 
strikes than all the rest of the weapons 
in their arsenal. This terrorism, however, 
must be clearly understood. It is 
directed solely against the scab, placing 
him in such fear for life and limb as to 
drive him out of the contest. But when 
terrorism gets out of hand and inoffensive 
non-combatants are injured, law and 
order threatened, and property destroyed, 
it becomes an edged tool that cuts both 
ways. This sort of terrorism is sincerely 
deplored by the labor leaders, for it has 
probably lost them as many strikes as 
have been lost by any other single cause. 
</p><p>The scab is powerless under terrorism. 
As a rule he is not so good or gritty a 
man as the men he is displacing, and he 
   <pb n="57"/>   
lacks their fighting organization. He 
stands in dire need of stiffening and 
backing. His employers, the capitalists, 
draw their two remaining weapons, the 
ownership of which is debatable, but 
which they for the time being happen to 
control. These two weapons may be 
called the political and judicial machinery 
of society. When the scab crumples 
up and is ready to go down before the 
fists, bricks, and bullets of the labor-group, 
the capitalist-group puts the police and 
soldiers into the field, and begins a general 
bombardment of injunctions. Victory 
usually follows, for the labor-group 
cannot withstand the combined assault of 
galling guns and injunctions. 
</p><p>But it has been noted that the ownership 
of the political and judicial machinery 
of society is debatable. In the Titanic 
struggle over the division of the 
joint-product, each group reaches out for 
every available weapon. Nor are they 
blinded by the smoke of conflict. They 
fight their battles as coolly and collectedly 
as ever battles were fought on paper. 
The capitalist-group has long since realized 
the immense importance of controlling 
the political and judicial machinery 
of society. Taught by gatlings and 
injunctions, which have smashed many 
an otherwise successful strike, the labor-group is beginning to realize that it all depends 
upon who is behind and who is before 
those weapons. And he who knows 
the labor-movement knows that there is 
slowly growing up and being formulated 
a clear, definite policy for the capture of 
the political and judicial machinery. 
</p><p>This is the terrible spectre which Mr. 
John Graham Brooks sees looming 
portentously over the twentieth-century 
world. No man may boast a more intimate 
knowledge of the labor-movement than 
he, and he reiterates again and again the 
dangerous likelihood of the whole labor-group capturing the political machinery 
of society. As he gays in his recent book:<ref target="n1">[1]</ref> 
<milestone unit="column"/> 
"It is not probable that employers can 
destroy unionism in the United States. 
Adroit and desperate attempts will, however, 
be made, if we mean by unionism 
the undisciplined and aggressive fact of 
vigorous and determined organizations. 
If capital should prove too strong in this 
struggle, the result is easy to predict. 
The employers have only to convince 
organized labor that it cannot hold its 
own against the capitalist manager, and 
the whole energy that now goes to the 
union will turn to an aggressive political 
socialism. It will not be the harmless 
sympathy with increased city and state 
functions which trade unions already 
feel; it will become a turbulent political 
force bent upon using every weapon of 
taxation against the rich." 
</p><p>This struggle not to be a scab, to avoid 
giving more for less, and to succeed in 
giving less for more, is more vital than 
it would appear on the surface. The 
capitalist and labor groups are locked 
together in desperate battle, and neither 
side is swayed by moral considerations 
more than skin-deep. The labor-group 
hires business agents, lawyers, and 
organizers; and is beginning to intimidate 
legislators by the strength of its solid 
vote, and more directly, in the near 
future, it will attempt to control legislation 
by capturing it bodily through the 
ballot-box. On the other hand, the capitalist-group, numerically weaker, hires 
newspapers, universities, and legislatures, 
and strives to bend to its need all 
the forces which go to mould public 
opinion. 
</p><p>The only honest morality displayed by 
either side is white-hot indignation at 
the iniquities of the other side. The 
striking teamster complacently takes a 
scab driver into an alley and with an iron 
bar breaks his arms so that he can drive 
no more, but cries out to high heaven 
for justice when the capitalist breaks his 
skull by means of a club in the hands of 
a policeman. Nay, the members of a 
union will declaim in impassioned rhetoric 
   <pb n="58"/>   
for the God-given right of an eight-hour day, and at the time be working 
their own business agent seventeen hours 
out of the twenty-four. 
</p><p>A capitalist, such as the late Collis P. 
Huntington, and his name is Legion, after 
a long life spent in buying the aid of 
countless legislatures, will wax virtuously 
wrathful and condemn in unmeasured 
terms "the dangerous tendency of crying 
out to the government for aid" in 
the way of labor legislation. Without a 
quiver, a member of the capitalist-group 
will run tens of thousands of pitiful child-laborers through his life-destroying cotton 
factories, and weep maudlin and 
Constitutional tears over one scab hit in 
the back with a brick. He will drive 
a "compulsory" free contract with an 
unorganized laborer on the basis of a 
starvation wage, saying, "Take it or 
leave it," knowing that to leave it means 
to die of hunger; and in the next breath, 
when the organizer entices that laborer 
into a union, will storm patriotically 
about the inalienable rights of all men 
to work. In short, the chief moral concern 
of either side is with the morals of 
the other side. They are not in the business 
for their moral welfare, but to 
achieve the enviable position of the non-scab who gets more than he gives. 
</p><p>Rut there is more to the question than 
has yet been discussed. The labor scab 
is no more detestable to his brother 
laborers than is the capitalist scab to his 
brother capitalists. A capitalist may 
get most for least in dealing with his 
laborers, and in so far be a non-scab; but 
at the same time, in his dealings with his 
fellow capitalists, he may give most for 
least and be the very worst kind of scab. 
The most heinous crime an employer 
of labor can commit is to scab on his 
fellow employers of labor. Just as the 
individual laborers have organized into 
groups to protect themselves from the 
peril of the scab laborer, so have the 
employers organized into groups to protect 
themselves from the peril of the scab 
<milestone unit="column"/> 
employer. The employers' federations, 
associations, and trusts are nothing more 
or less than unions. They are organized 
to destroy scabbing amongst themselves 
and to encourage scabbing amongst 
others. For this reason they pool interests, 
determine prices, and present an 
unbroken and aggressive front to the 
labor-group. 
</p><p>As has been said before, nobody likes 
to play the compulsorily generous r&ocirc;le 
of scab. It is a bad business proposition 
on the face of it. And it is patent that 
there would be no capitalist scabs if there 
were not more capital than there is work 
for capital to do. When there are enough 
factories in existence to supply, with occasional 
stoppages, a certain commodity, 
the building of new factories, by a rival 
concern, for the production of that commodity, 
is plain advertisement that that 
capital is out of a job. The first act of 
this new aggregation of capital will be to 
cut prices, to give more for less; in short, 
to scab, to strike at the very existence of 
the less generous aggregation of capital, 
the work of which it is trying to do. 
</p><p>No scab capitalist strives to give more 
for less for any other reason than that he 
hopes, by undercutting a competitor and 
driving that competitor out of the market, 
to get that market and its profits for 
himself. His ambition is to achieve the 
day when he shall stand alone in the field 
both as buyer and seller, when he will 
be the royal non-scab, buying most for 
least, selling least for most, and reducing 
all about him, the small buyers and sellers 
(the consumers and the laborers), to 
a general condition of scabdom. This, 
for example, has been the history of Mr. 
Rockefeller and the Standard Oil Company. 
Through all the sordid economies 
of scabdom he has passed until to-day he 
is a most regal non-scab. However, to 
continue in this enviable position, he 
must be prepared at a moment's notice 
to go scabbing again. And he is prepared. 
Whenever a competitor arises, 
Mr. Rockefeller changes about from giving 
   <pb n="59"/>   
least for most, and gives most for 
least with such a vengeance as to drive 
the competitor out of existence. 
</p><p>The banded capitalists discriminate 
against a scab capitalist by refusing him 
trade advantages, and by combining 
against him in most relentless fashion. 
The banded laborers, discriminating 
against a scab laborer in more primitive 
fashion, with a club, are no more merciless 
than the banded capitalists. 
</p><p>Mr. Casson tells of a New York 
capitalist, who withdrew from the Sugar 
Union several years ago and became a 
scab. He was worth something like 
twenty millions of dollars. But the 
Sugar Union, standing shoulder to 
shoulder with the Railroad Union and 
several others, beat him to his knees till 
he cried enough. So frightfully did they 
beat him that he was obliged to turn over 
to his creditors his home, his chickens, 
and his gold watch. In point of fact, he 
was as thoroughly bludgeoned by the 
Federation of Capitalist Unions as ever 
scab workman was bludgeoned by a labor 
union. The intent in either case is the 
same, to destroy the scab's producing 
power. The labor scab with concussion 
of the brain is put out of business, and 
so is the capitalist scab who has lost all 
his dollars down to his chickens and his 
watch. 
</p><p>But the r&ocirc;le of scab passes beyond the 
individual. Just as individuals scab on 
other individuals, so do groups scab on 
other groups. And the principle involved 
is precisely the same as in the 
case of the simple labor scab. A group, 
in the nature of its organization, is often 
compelled to give most for least, and, so 
doing, to strike at the life of another 
group. At the present moment all Europe 
is appalled by that colossal scab, 
the United States. And Europe is clamorous 
with agitation for a Federation of 
National Unions to protect her from the 
United States. It may be noted, in 
passing, that in its prime essentials this 
agitation in no wise differs from the 
<milestone unit="column"/> 
trade union agitation among workmen in 
any industry. The trouble is caused by 
the scab who is giving most for least. 
The result of the American Scab's nefarious 
actions will be to strike at the 
food and shelter of Europe. The way 
for Europe to protect herself is to quit 
bickering among her parts and to form 
a union against the Scab. And if the 
union is formed, armies and navies may 
be expected to be brought into play in 
fashion similar to the bricks and clubs 
in ordinary labor struggles. 
</p><p>In this connection, and as one of 
many walking delegates for the nations, 
M. Leroy-Beaulieu, the noted French 
economist, may well be quoted. In a 
letter to the Vienna Tageblatt, he advocates 
an economic alliance among the 
Continental nations for the purpose of 
barring out American goods, an economic 
alliance, in his own language, <hi rend="italic">"which 
may possibly and desirably develop into 
a political alliance</hi>." 
</p><p>It will be noted in the utterances of 
the Continental walking delegates that, 
one and all, they leave England out of 
the proposed union. And in England 
herself the feeling is growing that her 
days are numbered if she cannot unite 
for offense and defense with the great 
American Scab. As Andrew Carnegie 
said some time ago, "The only course 
for Great Britain seems to be reunion 
with her grandchild, or sure decline to a 
secondary place, and then to comparative 
insignificance in the future annals of the 
English-speaking race." 
</p><p>Cecil Rhodes, speaking of what would 
have obtained but for the pig-headedness 
of George III., and of what will obtain 
when England and the United States are 
united, said, <hi rend="italic">"No cannon would . . . 
be fired on either hemisphere but by 
permission of the English race</hi>." It 
would seem that England, fronted by 
the hostile Continental Union and flanked 
by the great American Scab, has nothing 
left but to join with the Scab and play the 
historic labor-r&ocirc;le of armed Pinkerton. 
   <pb n="60"/>   
Granting the words of Cecil Rhodes, the 
United States would be enabled to scab 
without let or hindrance on Europe, while 
England, as professional strike-breaker 
and policeman, destroyed the unions and 
kept order. 
</p><p>All this may appear fantastic and 
erroneous, but there is in it a soul of 
truth vastly more significant than it may 
seem. Civilization may be expressed 
to-day in terms of trade unionism. 
Individual struggles have largely passed 
away, but group struggles increase 
prodigiously. And the things for which 
the groups struggle are the same as of 
old. Shorn of all subtleties and complexities, 
the chief struggle of men, and 
of groups of men, is for food and shelter. 
And, as of old they struggled with tooth 
and nail, so to-day they struggle, with 
teeth and nails elongated into armies 
and navies, machines, and economic 
advantages. 
</p><p>Under the definition that a scab is 
<hi rend="italic">one who gives more value for the same 
price than another</hi>, it would seem that 
society can be generally divided into the 
two classes of the scabs and the nonscabs. 
But on closer investigation, however, 
it will be seen that the non-scab is 
almost a vanishing quantity. In the 
social jungle everybody is preying upon 
everybody else. As in the case of Mr. 
Rockefeller, he who was a scab yesterday 
is a non-scab to-day, and to-morrow 
may be a scab again. 
</p><p>The woman stenographer or bookkeeper 
who receives forty dollars per 
month where a man was receiving 
seventy-five is a scab. So is the woman 
who does a man's work at a weaving 
machine, and the child who goes into the 
mill or factory. And the father, who is 
scabbed out of work by the wives and 
children of other men, sends his own 
wife and children to scab in order to 
save himself. 
</p><p>When a publisher offers an author 
better royalties than other publishers 
have been paying him, he is scabbing 
<milestone unit="column"/> 
on those other publishers. The reporter 
on a newspaper who feels he should be 
receiving a larger salary for his work, 
says so, and is shown the door, is 
replaced by a reporter who is a scab; 
whereupon, when the belly-need presses, 
the displaced reporter goes to another 
paper and scabs himself. The minister 
who hardens his heart to a call, and waits 
for a certain congregation to offer him 
say five hundred a year more, often 
finds himself scabbed upon by another 
and more impecunious minister; and the 
next time it is <hi rend="italic">his</hi> turn to scab while a 
brother minister is hardening his heart 
to a call. The scab is everywhere. The 
professional strike-breakers, who, as a 
class, receive large wages, will scab on 
one another, while scab unions are even 
formed to prevent scabbing upon scabs. 
</p><p>There are non-scabs, but they are 
usually born so, and are protected by the 
whole might of society in the possession 
of their food and shelter. King Edward 
is such a type, as are all individuals 
who receive hereditary food-and-shelter 
privileges, such as the present Duke of 
Bedford, for instance, who yearly receives 
$75,000 from the good people of 
London because some former king gave 
some former ancestor of his the market 
privileges of Covent Garden. The irresponsible 
rich are likewise non-scabs, and 
by them is meant that coupon-clipping 
class which hires its managers and brains 
to invest the money usually left it by its 
ancestors. 
</p><p>Outside these lucky creatures, all the 
rest, at one time or another in their lives, 
are scabs, at one time or another are engaged 
in giving more for a certain price 
than any one else. The meek professor 
in some endowed institution, by his meek 
suppression of his convictions, is giving 
more for his salary than the other more 
outspoken professor gave, whose chair 
he occupies. And when a political party 
dangles a full dinner-pail in the eyes of 
the toiling masses, it is offering more for 
a vote than the dubious dollar of the opposing 
   <pb n="61"/>   
party. Even a money-lender is 
not above taking a slightly lower rate of 
interest and saying nothing about it. 
</p><p>Such is the tangle of conflicting interests 
in a tooth-and-nail society that people 
cannot avoid being scabs, are often 
made so against their desires, and 
unconsciously. When several trades in a 
certain locality demand and receive an 
advance in wages, they are unwittingly 
making scabs of their fellow laborers in 
that district who have received no advance 
in wages. In San Francisco the barbers, 
laundry workers, and milk-wagon 
drivers received such an advance in 
wages. Their employers promptly added 
the amount of this advance to the 
selling price of their wares. The price 
of shaves, of washing, and of milk went 
up. This reduced the purchasing power 
of the unorganized laborers, and, in point 
of fact, reduced their wages and made 
them greater scabs. 
</p><p>Because the British laborer is disinclined 
to scab, that is, because he restricts 
his output in order to give less for the 
wage he receives, it is to a certain extent 
made possible for the American capitalist, 
who receives a less restricted output 
from his laborers, to play the scab on the 
English capitalist. As a result of this 
(of course, combined with other causes), 
the American capitalist and the American 
laborer are striking at the food and 
shelter of the English capitalist and laborer. 
</p><p>The English laborer is starving to-day 
because, among other things, he is not a 
scab. He practices the policy of "Ca' 
Canny," which may be defined as "go 
easy." In order to get most for least, in 
many trades he performs but from one 
fourth to one sixth of the labor he is well 
able to perform. An instance of this is 
found in the building of the Westinghouse 
Electric Works at Manchester. 
The British limit per man was 400 bricks 
per day. The Westinghouse Company 
imported a "driving" American contractor 
aided by half-a-dozen "driving" 
<milestone unit="column"/> 
American foremen, and the British bricklayer 
swiftly attained an average of 1800 
bricks per day, with a maximum of 2500 
bricks for the plainest work. 
</p><p>But the British laborer's policy of 
Ca' Canny, which is the very honorable 
one of giving least for most, and 
which is likewise the policy of the English 
capitalist, is nevertheless frowned 
upon by the English capitalist whose 
business existence is threatened by the 
great American Scab. From the rise of 
the factory system, the English capitalist 
gladly embraced the opportunity, wherever 
he found it, of giving least for most. 
He did it all over the world wherever he 
enjoyed a market monopoly, and he did 
it at home, with the laborers employed 
in his mills, destroying them like flies till 
prevented, within limits, by the passage 
of the Factory Acts. Some of the proudest 
fortunes of England to-day may trace 
their origin to the giving of least for 
most to the miserable slaves of the factory 
towns. But at the present time 
the English capitalist is outraged because 
his laborers are employing against him 
precisely the same policy he employed 
against them, and which he would employ 
again did the chance present itself. 
</p><p>Yet Ca' Canny is a disastrous thing 
to the British laborer. It has driven 
ship-building from England to Scotland, 
bottle-making from Scotland to Belgium, 
flint-glass-making from England to Germany, 
and to-day it is steadily driving 
industry after industry to other countries. 
A correspondent from Northampton 
wrote not long ago: "Factories are 
working half and third time.... There 
is no strike, there is no real labor trouble, 
but the masters and men are alike suffering 
from sheer lack of employment. 
Markets which were once theirs are now 
American." It would seem that the unfortunate 
British laborer is 'twixt the 
devil and the deep sea. If he gives most 
for least, he faces a frightful slavery such 
as marked the beginning of the factory 
system. If he gives least for most, he 
   <pb n="62"/>   
drives industry away to other countries, 
and has no work at all. 
</p><p>But the union laborers of the United 
States have nothing to boast of, while, 
according to their trade-union ethics, they 
have a great deal of which to be ashamed. 
They passionately preach short hours and 
big wages, the shorter the hours and the 
bigger the wages the better. Their hatred 
for a scab is as terrible as the hatred 
of a patriot for a traitor, of a Christian 
for a Judas. And in the face of all this 
they are as colossal scabs as the United 
States is a colossal scab. For all of their 
boasted unions and high labor-ideals, they 
are about the most thorough-going scabs 
on the planet. 
</p><p>Receiving $4.50 per day, because of 
his proficiency and immense working 
power, the American laborer has been 
known to scab upon scabs (so called) who 
took his place and received only $.90 per 
day for a longer day. In this particular 
instance, five Chinese coolies, working 
longer hours, gave less value for the price 
received from their employer than did 
one American laborer. 
</p><p>It is upon his brother laborers 
overseas that the American laborer most 
outrageously scabs. As Mr. Casson has 
shown, an English nailmaker gets $3.00 
per week, while an American nailmaker 
gets $30.00. But the English worker 
turns out 200 pounds of nails per week, 
while the American turns out 5500 
pounds. If he were as "fair" as his 
English brother, other things being equal, 
he would be receiving, at the English 
worker's rate of pay, $82.50. As it is, 
he is scabbing upon his English brother 
to the tune of $79.50 per week. Dr. 
Schultze-Gaevernitz has shown that a 
German weaver produces 466 yards of 
cotton a week at a cost of .303 per yard, 
while an American weaver produces 1200 
yards at a cost of .02 per yard. 
</p><p>But, it may be objected, a great part 
of this is due to the more improved 
American machinery. Very true; but, 
none the less, a great part is still due to 
<milestone unit="column"/> 
the superior energy, skill, and willingness 
of the American laborer. The English 
laborer is faithful to the policy of 
Ca' Canny. He refuses point blank to 
get the work out of a machine that the 
New World scab gets out of a machine. 
Mr. Maxim, observing a wasteful hand-labor process in his English factory, 
invented a machine which he proved 
capable of displacing several men. But 
workman after workman was put at the 
machine, and without exception they 
turned out neither more nor less than 
a workman turned out by hand. They 
obeyed the mandate of the union and 
went easy, while Mr. Maxim gave up in 
despair. Nor will the British workman 
run machines at as high speed as the 
American, nor will he run so many. An 
American workman will "give equal attention 
simultaneously to three, four, or 
six machines or tools, while the British 
workman is compelled by his trade union 
to limit his attention to one, so that 
employment may be given to half-a-dozen 
men." 
</p><p>But to scabbing, no blame attaches itself 
anywhere. All the world is a scab, 
and, with rare exceptions, all the people 
in it are scabs. The strong, capable 
workman gets a job and holds it because 
of his strength and capacity. And he 
holds it because out of his strength and 
capacity he gives a better value for his 
wage than does the weaker and less capable 
workman. Therefore he is scabbing 
upon his weaker and less capable 
brother workman. This is incontrovertible. 
He is giving more value for the 
price paid by the employer. 
</p><p>The superior workman scabs upon the 
inferior workman because he is so constituted 
and cannot help it. The one, by 
fortune of birth and upbringing, is strong 
and capable; the other, by fortune of 
birth and upbringing, is not so strong or 
capable. It is for the same reason that 
one country scabs upon another. That 
country which has the good fortune to 
possess great natural resources, a finer 
   <pb n="63"/>   
sun and soil, unhampering institutions, 
and a deft and intelligent labor class and 
capitalist class, is bound to scab upon a 
country less fortunately situated. It is 
the good fortune of the United States 
that is making her the colossal scab, just 
as it is the good fortune of one man to 
be born with a straight back while his 
brother is born with a hump. 
</p><p>It is not good to give most for least, 
not good to be a scab. The word has 
gained universal opprobrium. On the 
other hand, to be a non-scab, to give 
least for most, is universally branded as 
stingy, selfish, and unchristian-like. So 
all the world, like the British workman, 
is 'twixt the devil and the deep sea. It 
is treason to one's fellows to scab, it is 
treason to God and unchristian-like not 
to scab. 
</p><p>Since to give least for most and to 
give most for least are universally bad, 
<milestone unit="column"/> 
what remains? Equity remains, which 
is to give like for like, the same for the 
same, neither more nor less. But this 
equity, society, as at present constituted, 
cannot give. It is not in the nature of 
present-day society for men to give like 
for like, the same for the same. And as 
long as men continue to live in this competitive 
society, struggling tooth and nail 
with one another for food and shelter, 
(which is to struggle tooth and nail with 
one another for life), that long will the 
scab continue to exist. His will to live 
will force him to exist. He may be flouted 
and jeered by his brothers, he may be 
beaten with bricks and clubs by the men 
who by superior strength and capacity 
scab upon him as he scabs upon them 
by longer hours and smaller wages, but 
through it all he will persist, going them 
one better, and giving a bit more of most 
for least than they are giving. 
</p><p><hi rend="italic">Jack London</hi>. 
</p> 
 
<note id="n1"><seg type="note-symbol">[1]</seg> <p><hi rend="italic">The Social Unrest</hi>. New York: The Macmillan Co. 
1903.</p></note> 
 
</div1> 
</body> 
</text> 
</TEI.2> 
 
