<?xml version="1.0"?>

<?dlps id="MarFits"?>
<?dlps page-images="none" figure-images="no"?>
<?dlps transcription="other"?>

<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/tei-p4/tei2.dtd" [
<!ENTITY % POSTKB "INCLUDE">
<!ENTITY % TEI.extensions.ent SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.ent">
<!ENTITY % TEI.extensions.dtd SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.dtd">
<!ENTITY % ISOnum SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/charent/iso-num.ent"> %ISOnum;
<!ENTITY % ISOpub SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/charent/iso-pub.ent"> %ISOpub;

]>
<TEI.2 id="MarFits">
<teiHeader type="migrated" creator="Etext">
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title type="main">Fits and Starts</title>
<title type="sort">fits and starts</title>
<author>Marquis, Don</author>
<respStmt>
<resp>Creation of machine-readable version:</resp>
<name>Judy Boss</name>
<resp>Conversion to TEI.2-conformant markup:</resp>
<name>University of Virginia Library Electronic Text Center.</name>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt>
<extent>ca. <num type="kilobytes">10</num> kilobytes</extent>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>University of Virginia Library</publisher>
<pubPlace>Charlottesville, Virginia</pubPlace>
<idno type="ETC">MarFits</idno>
<date value="1999">1999</date>
<availability status="public">
<p n="copyright">Copyright &copy; 1999 by the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia</p>
<p n="access">Publicly accessible</p>
</availability>
<idno type="uva-pid">uva-lib:476170</idno>
</publicationStmt>
<seriesStmt>
<title>University of Virginia Library, Text collection</title>
<idno type="uva-set">UVA-LIB-Text</idno>
</seriesStmt>
<sourceDesc>
<biblFull>
<titleStmt>
<title type="main">Fits and Starts</title>
<title level="j">Harper`s Magazine</title>
<title type="sort">fits and starts</title>
<author>Don Marquis</author>
</titleStmt>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>Harper &amp; Bros.</publisher>
<pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
<date value="1919">c1912-1976</date>
<idno type="callNo">Source copy consulted:  Uva Library AP2.H3</idno>
</publicationStmt>
<notesStmt>
<note>
<p>The article appeared in v. 139, Part One (June-August 1919), p. 277-279.</p>
</note>
</notesStmt>
</biblFull>
</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc>
<encodingDesc>
<projectDesc>
<p>Prepared for the University of Virginia Library Electronic Text Center.</p>
</projectDesc>
<editorialDecl>
<p>All unambiguous end-of-line hyphens have been removed, and the  trailing part of a word has been joined to the preceding line.</p>
<p id="ETC">Some keywords in the header are a local Electronic Text Center scheme  to aid in establishing analytical groupings.</p>
</editorialDecl>
</encodingDesc>
<profileDesc>
<creation>
<date value="1919">1919</date>
</creation>
<langUsage>
<language id="eng" usage="main">English</language>
</langUsage>
<textClass>
<keywords>
<term>nonfiction</term>
<term>prose</term>
<term>masculine</term>
</keywords>
</textClass>
</profileDesc>
<revisionDesc>
<change>
<date value="1999-01">January 1999</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>corrector</resp>
<name>Matthew Gibson, University of Virginia Electronic Text Center</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Added TEI header and tags; closed hyphenated spaces between words.</item>
</change>
<change>
<date value="2005-07">July 2005</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>Corrector</resp>
<name>John Ivor Carlson</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Converted to XML and/or checked tags.</item>
</change>
<change>
<date value="2007-09">September 2007</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>Migration</resp>
<name>Ethan Gruber, University of Virginia Library</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Converted XML markup from TEI Lite to uva-dl-tei (TEI P4 with local customizations).</item>
</change>
<change>
<date value="2008-01">January 2008</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>Migration</resp>
<name>Greg Murray, University of Virginia Library</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Programmatically updated TEI header markup (but not header content) for minimal compliance with current QA requirements.</item>
</change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text id="d1">
<body id="d2">
<div1 type="essay" id="d3">
<head>FITS AND STARTS<lb/>

By Don Marquis</head>

<p>I WENT into the new Broadway Subway, near City Hall, the other day,
and asked the pensive lady at the money-window:</p>
<p>"How long does it take to go up to Times Square?"</p>
<p>She haled back her ego from its dream; with difficulty she
compelled herself to look at me.  After she had looked at me a
moment, she seemed to pity me.</p>
<p>"I dunno'," she said.</p>
<p>But I persisted.  I had never ridden in that Subway, and I really
wanted to know.  I was already ten minutes late for an engagement.  I
wished to know whether I was going to be forty minutes late or twenty.
A man who is late for an engagement owes the engagee a lie which is
not only plausible, but entertaining.  But the story that goes with being
forty minutes late will not do at all when you are twenty minutes late.
I wished to know in advance the sort of story I should have to tell.  I
wished to rehearse it to myself and perfect it on the way up-town.  And
I did not wish to spend the time perfecting one sort of story, only to
find it useless upon arrival.  I have something of a reputation to keep
up in the matter of tardiness: if I am ten minutes late, I am on time; it
is a pose, an affectation, with me; and it is, in the long run and in a
small way, profitable: people ask me to lunch frequently just to hear
what I will say when I arrive late.</p>
<p>     So I really wanted to know, and I asked the lady at the ticket-window once more.  She had taken up a comb and

<pb n="278"/>

was rubbing it through her hair, and attracting with the electrified
celluloid certain little bits of paper spread before her.  Somehow
she made me feel, when she answered, that I was of less importance
in her scheme of things than one of the bits of paper.</p>
<p>     "It doesn't take so very long," said she.</p>
<p>     "But <hi rend="italic">how</hi> long?" I insisted.</p>
<p> "How long would you say yourself?" said she.</p>
<p>     It was perhaps fortunate for her that she had not to deal with a
person with an idea on the subject of catching a train.  As it was, I
tried to suggest mild rebuke by my manner.</p>
<p> "I have never ridden on this line," I said.</p>
<p>     "You go and ride on it, then," said she, "and then come
back here and tell me how long it takes."</p>
<p>     It struck me, on reflection, that her attitude was quite
right.  She was a specialist.  She made change; it was her business
to give out the nickels that the public dropped into the hopper,
and she refused to burden her mind with any further responsibility.</p>
<p>     But beneath this and behind it and more important, I
thought that I could discern a fine scorn for that mania for rushing
hither and thither which characterizes the populations of large
towns.  So much of that rushing is entirely aimless and unnecessary.
I have seen people in New York race down the street as if the
very devil burnt their heels behind them, flinging weaker
pedestrians to one side, skipping perilously in front of auto-trucks
and eluding traffic cops, and then stand for twenty minutes
watching an office safe being lowered from the tenth story of a
building.  They weren't really in a hurry; they weren't even going
anywhere in particular, most of them.</p>
<p>     They were merely being like their era.  I do not pretend
to say, especially since the war, where the world is going, but it
gets sudden urgent impulses to be rapidly on its way; it has spasms
of the most disconcerting speed, and then it stops, puts its hands
in its pockets, sits down on a park bench, and stares at the
toes of its shoes.</p>
<p>     It hasn't been long since certain persons said this country
was going to the demnition bow-wows; it was hell-bent and
iniquitously happy, what with simian dances and&mdash;and&mdash;oh, you
know, Immoral Stuff generally.  And now these same persons
insist that it is dashing madly toward redemption&mdash;Prohibition,
you know, and Moral Stuff generally.</p>
<p>     But it always stops and rests awhile and forgets where
it was going.  It has time, after all, to be charmed by the
demonstrator's alluring pantomime in the show-window; it
allows itself to become possessed of long and placid thoughts
as it watches the skilful gentleman in the white cap tossing
buckwheat cakes in the white-tiled food-mausoleum.  Perhaps,
in these quarter-hours of rest between dashes lies a certain
safety.  For none of its rushes ever carries through; it always
saves itself from logical arrival at a logical terminus; it turns
with a kind of horror from any possible partnership with the
absolute; when it dashes again, it will dash in some other
direction, and its new dash will bear no perceptible relation
to its former dash and no relation to what it was supposed to
be thinking about in the interval between the dashes.</p>
<p>     These remarks concerning the illogical rushes of human
beings are uttered in no hateful spirit.  After all, I am one of
them.  I prefer them, on the whole, to any other sort of animal;
I always feel a clannish instinct to defend them; as between
human beings and, let us say, camels, or even gazelles, I do
not hesitate an instant.</p>
<p>     I know that it is fashionable to criticize the universe
which contains humanity, but I have never been able to remain
angry with it for very long at a time.  I incline toward lenience
with regard to its mistakes.  It has come a long way.  It has a long
way to go.  It is, at times, no doubt, tired.  And it can neither
strike nor resign.  It cannot even go crazy, for its insanity would
immediately become the standard of normality.  It must keep on
being the universe.  Often, when we contemplate the universe,
we burst into tears of sheer pity.  It did not ask to be.  It cannot
help but be.  It does the best it can.  And thrice ten thousand
<hi rend="italic">vers libre</hi> bards and philosophers, every year, gibe at it
with bitterness and contumely.  It never answers.  Sometimes
we think its dull and


<pb n="279"/>


plodding patience is almost grand.  It is probably discouraged a
great deal of the time at not being able to please G. B. Shaw, or
keep up with H. G. Wells, but it chokes back the sobs and keeps
on trying.</p><lb/>

<p>    These fits and starts of humanity, these rushings and
stoppings, may, for all I know, correspond to some vast internal
rhythm of the cosmos; the pulse jumps, and the corpuscles shoot
ahead.  Personally, I prefer the dreamy, more stationary moments
between pulsebeats; I don't want to go anywhere in particular
badly enough to hurry; effort is loathsome.</p>
<p>     The lady at the Subway window is of my way of thinking.</p>
<p>     "Can't you," I said to her, consciously impersonating the
bustling person I am not&mdash;"can't you at least give me some
approximate idea of how long it takes to get up to Forty-second
Street?  Does it take about ten minutes, or does it take about
thirty minutes?"</p>
<p>     "It takes shorter than a horse," said she, "and longer than
an airyoplane.  The time some people waste standin' around
here, askin' questions, they'd get there quicker if they walked."</p>
</div1>
</body>
</text>
</TEI.2>

