<?xml version="1.0"?>

<?dlps id="MayPudd"?>
<?dlps page-images="none" figure-images="no"?>
<?dlps transcription="other"?>

<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/tei-p4/tei2.dtd" [
<!ENTITY % POSTKB "INCLUDE">
<!ENTITY % TEI.extensions.ent SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.ent">
<!ENTITY % TEI.extensions.dtd SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.dtd">
<!ENTITY % ISOnum SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/charent/iso-num.ent"> %ISOnum;
<!ENTITY % ISOpub SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/charent/iso-pub.ent"> %ISOpub;

]>
<TEI.2 id="MayPudd">
<teiHeader type="migrated" creator="Etext">
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title type="main">Pudd'nhead Wilson (Review)</title>
<title type="sort">puddnhead wilson review</title>
<author>Mayo, Frank</author>
<respStmt>
<resp>Creation of machine-readable version:</resp>
<name>Stephen Railton</name>
<resp>Creation of digital images:</resp>
<name/>
<resp>Conversion to TEI.2-conformant markup:</resp>
<name>University of Virginia Library Electronic Text Center.</name>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt>
<extent>ca. <num type="kilobytes">8</num> kilobytes</extent>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>University of Virginia Library</publisher>
<pubPlace>Charlottesville, Virginia</pubPlace>
<idno type="ETC">MayPudd</idno>
<date value="1997">1997</date>
<availability status="public">
<p n="copyright">Copyright &copy; 1997 by the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia</p>
<p n="access">Publicly accessible</p>
</availability>
<idno type="uva-pid">uva-lib:476176</idno>
</publicationStmt>
<seriesStmt>
<title>University of Virginia Library, Text collection</title>
<idno type="uva-set">UVA-LIB-Text</idno>
</seriesStmt>
<sourceDesc>
<biblFull>
<titleStmt>
<title type="main">"Pudd'nhead Wilson"</title>
<title level="j">Harper's Weekly, Vol. XXXIX, No. 2009: 594</title>
<title type="sort">puddnhead wilson</title>
<author>Frank Mayo</author>
</titleStmt>
<extent>p. 594</extent>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>Harper &amp; Brothers</publisher>
<pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
<date value="1895-06-22">June 22, 1895</date>
<idno type="callNo">Print copy consulted: UVA Library call number AP 2 .H32 v.39 1895</idno>
</publicationStmt>
</biblFull>
</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc>
<encodingDesc>
<projectDesc>
<p>Prepared for the University of Virginia Library Electronic Text Center.</p>
</projectDesc>
<editorialDecl>
<p>All quotation marks retained as data.</p>
<p>All unambiguous end-of-line hyphens have been removed, and the trailing part of a word has been joined to the preceding line.</p>
<p>The images exist as archived TIFF images, one or more JPEG versions for general use, and thumbnail GIFs.</p>
<p>Keywords in the header are a local Electronic Text Center scheme to aid in establishing analytical groupings.</p>
</editorialDecl>
</encodingDesc>
<profileDesc>
<creation>
<date value="1895">1895</date>
</creation>
<langUsage>
<language id="eng" usage="main">English</language>
</langUsage>
<textClass>
<keywords>
<term>prose; non-fiction</term>
</keywords>
</textClass>
</profileDesc>
<revisionDesc>
<change>
<date value="1997-06">June 1997</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>corrector</resp>
<name>Carol Osborne, Electronic Text Center</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Added TEI header and tags</item>
</change>
<change>
<date value="2005-07">July 2005</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>Corrector</resp>
<name>John Ivor Carlson</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Converted to XML and/or checked tags.</item>
</change>
<change>
<date value="2007-09">September 2007</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>Migration</resp>
<name>Ethan Gruber, University of Virginia Library</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Converted XML markup from TEI Lite to uva-dl-tei (TEI P4 with local customizations).</item>
</change>
<change>
<date value="2008-01">January 2008</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>Migration</resp>
<name>Greg Murray, University of Virginia Library</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Programmatically updated TEI header markup (but not header content) for minimal compliance with current QA requirements.</item>
</change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text id="d1">
<body id="d2">


<div1 type="article" id="d3"> <pb n="594" id="MayPudd594"/><head>"Pudd'nhead Wilson"<lb/>
[by Frank Mayo]</head>
<p>Harper's Weekly<lb/>
<hi rend="italic">June 22, 1895</hi><lb/></p>
<p>Why did I make a drama of Mark Twain's story of "Pudd'nhead Wilson"?</p>
<p>Ah! that question unlocks the doors of memory and awakens a thousand recollections.  I am
back in the early sixties, in that great mining-camp of Virginia City, in the "Comstock days."</p>
<p>At that time I was the "leading" man of Maguire's Opera-house of San Francisco, the stock
company of which embraced the names of Julia Dean Hayne, Agnes Booth, Charles Thorne,
Louis Aldrich, and J.B. Booth.  This company was sent up to Virginia City to open the new
opera-house which had just been built there.</p>
<p>Here I first made the acquaintance of Samuel L. Clemens, who was then beginning to earn
fame for his <hi rend="italic">nom de guerre</hi> of Mark Twain as a writer on the staff of the <hi rend="italic">Territorial
Enterprise</hi>, of which Joseph T. Goodman was the editor.</p>
<p>It was through Goodman, between whom and Twain there existed a deep and sincere
affection, and which since that time it has been my fortune to share, that I met Twain.  This
meeting was epoch-making in my life and professional career.  I was then twenty-four years old,
the impressionable time of life, when friendships are founded to endure.  Ah! that country was
young, too, and beginning.  Think of it: John Mackay, a miner, earning his living with his pick and
shovel; Flood &amp; O'Brien, keepers of a second class bar-room in Frisco, where the best drinks
could be got for a "bit," the smallest coin in use; Sharon, a teller in a bank; James G. Fair, a
lawyer of few briefs; "Lucky" Baldwin, the owner of a livery-stable; Francis Bret Harte, a writer
on a weekly paper!  At Sacramento, the great railroad group of Huntington, Crocker, Stanford,
and Hopkins were then dealing in hardware, provisions, and other commodities, and not even
dreaming of across-continent rails.  The events in the lives of these men in their rise to wealth,
fame, and power form a greater drama than was ever written.</p>
<p>It was in these days that my friendship for Mark Twain was founded &mdash; a friendship which has
not faltered until this time.  And as well for "Joe" Goodman.  And so closely were these two men
associated that I have never been able to think of one without the presence of the other.</p>
<p>Ten years later I produced <hi rend="italic">Davy Crockett</hi> in the East, and all that is sweet,
wholesome, and lovable &mdash; the happy, frank, open nature in the title role &mdash; is based on my
conception of the nature and character of Joe Goodman; and all that is quaint and humorous was
taken from that other friend of the trio, Mark Twain.  And during all the years of my playing
<hi rend="italic">Davy Crockett</hi> there was not a night that these men were not present with me.</p>
<p>A strong desire had always possessed me to play something written by Mark Twain.  On a
cold drizzly day in February, 1894, late in the afternoon, I was making my way toward the Players
Club, when I saw, crossing toward me on Fourth Avenue, the familiar face of Mark Twain.
Greeting him, I said, "Step into this doorway, Sam."</p>
<p>Looking up at the face of the house, the doorway of which I had indicated, with his inimitable
drawl Twain replied: "Frank, haven't you made a mistake?  They don't sell it in here!"</p>
<p>"I shan't detain you long, Sam, for you must be going somewhere, since you are out in this
weather," I said.  "I want to take one of your stories and write a play around it."</p>
<p>"Which one?" he asked.</p>
<p>"What is the matter with 'Pudd'nhead Wilson'?" I asked in turn, and then added, "I have read
two numbers."</p>
<p>"Well," said Sam, "go ahead.  I am going to a supper, and must hurry away.  But you can
have 'Pudd'nhead.""</p>
<p>"But about the terms?" I asked.</p>
<p>"Oh, we'll settle that later.  Come down to the club any time between eleven and midnight,
and we'll talk it over."  He moved away, and turned to say, "You write the play, Frank &mdash; write
anything you like; you needn't submit it.  I know it'll be good.  I'll arrange that you shall have the
advance sheets."</p>
<p>In a moment more he was lost in the mist, and that is all that was said between us on the
subject.</p>
<p>Very shortly after this conversation I began the labor of turning his story into a play.  Just
when the character of Pudd'nhead Wilson and Mark Twain became to me one and inseparable I
cannot now tell.  Perhaps it was on the first reading, but now as I look upon it I doubt if there
ever was a moment in my mind when they were two separate individuals.  And in it &mdash; I mean the
writing &mdash; I lost my own identity, and seemed to become the hand and instrument of Mark
Twain.</p>
<p>The result is before the world, and New York has passed judgment upon it.  This is how and
why I dramatized "Pudd'nhead Wilson."</p>

</div1>

</body>
</text>
</TEI.2>

