<?xml version="1.0"?>

<?dlps id="MonFami"?>
<?dlps page-images="none" figure-images="no"?>
<?dlps transcription="other"?>

<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/tei-p4/tei2.dtd" [
<!ENTITY % POSTKB "INCLUDE">
<!ENTITY % TEI.extensions.ent SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.ent">
<!ENTITY % TEI.extensions.dtd SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.dtd">
<!ENTITY % ISOnum SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/charent/iso-num.ent"> %ISOnum;
]><TEI.2 id="MonFami">
<teiHeader type="migrated" creator="Etext">
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title type="main">Family Stories from the Trail of Tears (taken from the Indian-Pioneer History
Collection, Grant Foreman, editor)</title>
<title type="sort">family stories from the trail of tears taken from the indian pioneer history collection, grant foreman editor</title>
<author>Montiero, Lorrie</author>
<respStmt>
<resp>Editor</resp>
<name>Montiero, Lorrie</name>
<resp>Creation of machine-readable version:</resp>
<name>Thompson, Carolyn</name>
<resp>Creation of digital images:</resp>
<name>Thompson, Carolyn</name>
<resp>Conversion to TEI.2-conformant markup:</resp>
<name>American Native Press Archives and Sequoyah Research Center, University of Arkansas at Little Rock (http://www.anpa.ualr.edu)</name>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt>
<extent>ca. <num type="kilobytes">100</num> kilobytes</extent>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>University of Virginia Library</publisher>
<pubPlace>Charlottesville, Virginia</pubPlace>
<idno type="ETC">MonFami</idno>
<date value="2004-07-22">July 22, 2004</date>
<availability status="public">
<p n="copyright">Copyright &copy; 2004 by the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia</p>
<p n="access">Publicly accessible</p>
</availability>
<idno type="uva-pid">uva-lib:476238</idno>
</publicationStmt>
<seriesStmt>
<title>University of Virginia Library, Text collection</title>
<idno type="uva-set">UVA-LIB-Text</idno>
</seriesStmt>
<sourceDesc>
<biblFull>
<titleStmt>
<title type="main">Family Stories from the Trail of Tears (taken from the Indian-Pioneer
History Collection, Grant Foreman, editor)</title>
<title type="sort">family stories from the trail of tears taken from the indian pioneer history collection, grant foreman editor</title>
<author>Lorrie Montiero</author>
<respStmt>
<resp>Editor</resp>
<name>Lorrie Montiero</name>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt>
<editionStmt>
<p>1st Edition. <date value="2004-07-22">July 22, 2004</date>
</p>
</editionStmt>
<publicationStmt>
<pubPlace>Little Rock, Ar.</pubPlace>
<date value="2004-07-22">July 22, 2004</date>
</publicationStmt>
</biblFull>
</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc>
<encodingDesc>
<projectDesc>
<p>Prepared for the UALR American Native Press Archives and Sequoyah Research Center.</p>
</projectDesc>
<editorialDecl>
<p>Spell-check made against printed text using Microsoft Word spell checker.</p>
<p>All unambiguous end-of-line hyphens have been removed, and the trailing part of a
word has been joined to the preceding line.</p>
</editorialDecl>
<refsDecl>
<p>ID elements are given for each page element and are composed of the text's unique
cryptogram and the given page number, as in AusEmma1 for page one of Jane
Austen's Emma.</p>
</refsDecl>
</encodingDesc>
<profileDesc>
<langUsage>
<language id="eng" usage="main">English</language>
</langUsage>
<textClass>
<keywords>
<term>Indians of North America--biography, Indian Territory, Indian
Territory--in literature, Indian Territory (Okla.)--biography, American
literature--Indian authors</term>
</keywords>
</textClass>
</profileDesc>
<revisionDesc>
<change>
<date value="2005-07">July 2005</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>Corrector</resp>
<name>John Ivor Carlson</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Converted to XML and/or checked tags.</item>
</change>
<change>
<date value="2007-09">September 2007</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>Migration</resp>
<name>Ethan Gruber, University of Virginia Library</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Converted XML markup from TEI Lite to uva-dl-tei (TEI P4 with local customizations).</item>
</change>
<change>
<date value="2008-01">January 2008</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>Migration</resp>
<name>Greg Murray, University of Virginia Library</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Programmatically updated TEI header markup (but not header content) for minimal compliance with current QA requirements.</item>
</change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>
<text id="d1">
<body id="d2">
<div1 type="text" id="d3">
<head>Family Stories from the Trail of Tears </head>
<byline>Edited by Lorrie Montiero</byline>
<div2 type="part" id="d4" n="1">
<head>Agnew, Mary Cobb</head>
<p>May 25, 1937<lb/> L. W. Wilson<lb/>Field Worker<lb/>An Interview with Mary
Cobb Agnew; 917 North M Street; Muskogee, Oklahoma</p>
<p>My name was Mary Cobb and I was married to Walter S. Agnew before the Civil War.</p>
<p>I was born in Georgia on May 19, 1840. My mother was a Cherokee woman and my
father was a white man. I was only four years old when my parents came to
the Indian Territory and I am now ninety-three years old.</p>
<p>My mother and father died when I was but seven years old and I was raised by
an aunt, my mother's sister. I never attended school and my education is
practical except what I was taught by my husband.</p>
										<p>My parents did not come to the Territory on the "Trail of Tears" but my
grandparents on my mother's side did. I have heard them say that the
United States Government drove them out of Georgia. The Cherokees had
protested to the bitter end. Finally the Cherokees knew that they had to
go some place because the white men would kill their cattle and hogs and
would even burn their houses in Georgia. The Cherokees came a group at a
time until all got to the Territory. They brought only a few things with
them traveling by wagon train. Old men and women, sick men and women
would ride but most of them walked and the men in charge drove them like
cattle and many died enroute and many other Cherokees died in Tennessee
waiting to cross the Mississippi River. Dysentery broke out in their
camp by the river and many died, and many died on the journey but my
grandparents got through all right.</p>
<p>I have heard my grandparents say that after they got out of the camp, and
even before they left Georgia, many Cherokees were taken sick and later died.</p>
<p>The Cherokees came through Tennessee, Kentucky, part of Missouri and then
down to Indian Territory on the "Trail of Tears".</p>
<p>Some Cherokees were already in the country around Evansville, Arkansas,
before my grandparents came. They called them Western Cherokees. It was
in 1838 when my grandparents came and I heard them say it was in the
winter time and all suffered with cold and hunger.</p>
<p>My mother and father remained in Georgia about six years after Mother's
folk's came on the "Trail of Tears" and Mother worried continually about
her parents. Then when I was four years old, I with my parents and other
kin, came west to join my grandparents. I don't know why the Government
let Mother stay longer than the rest of the Cherokees in Georgia unless
it was because she married a white man. We came by wagons to Memphis,
Tennessee. At Memphis we took a steamboat and finally landed at Fort
Gibson, Indian Territory, in June, 1844. I don't know how long it took
us to come from Memphis nor do I remember the names of the towns we came
through but I have heard my folks say that we had to change boats two or
three times because the rivers became shallow and we had to change to
smaller boats.</p>
<p>After our arrival at Fort Gibson, Indian Territory, we met our kinspeople
in the Flint District and settled in the Territory a short way from
Evansville, Arkansas. It was in the Flint District and around Fort
Gibson that I grew to be a young lady.</p>
</div2>
<div2 type="part" id="d5" n="2">
<head>Alexander, Jobe</head>
<p>May 3, 1938<lb/>Jesse S. Bell-Investigator<lb/>Indian-Pioneer History,
S-149<lb/> Interview with Jobe Alexander<lb/>Proctor, Oklahoma</p>
<p>I am a full blood Cherokee Indian born in Going-Lake District, Indian
Territory, Cherokee Nation, March 10, 1854, and raised there. My father,
Dun-Ev-Nall Alexander was born in Georgia and was driven West during the
immigration. All the Indians were gathered up or rounded up by Federal
soldiers and put in pens and guarded until ready for the move; they were
gathered up by the "Clans" and left their gardens and crops, and some of the
old homes of the Cherokee are still standing in Georgia.</p>
<p>The last group that was rounded up revolted; the leader gave the signal to
revolt and all turned on the guards and took their guns away and murdered
the guards and they made for hide aways in the mountains. That is why the
Indians are back in North Carolina, Tennessee, and Georgia. They never were
found or hunted much.</p>
</div2>
<div2 type="part" id="d6" n="3">
<head>Anderson, Lilian</head>
<p>August 20, 1837</p>
<p>Margaret McGurie</p>
<p>Field Worker</p>
<p>An Interview with Lilian Anderson</p>
<p>Eufaula, Oklahoma</p>
										<p>In 1838, my grandfather, Washington Lee, came to the Territory and
stopped at Westville. He was driven from his home in Georgia over the
Trail of Tears with all the other Cherokee Indians and while on the
trail somewhere he lost his father and mother and sister, and never saw
them any more. He did not know whether they died or got lost.</p>
<p>The Cherokees had to walk; all the old people who were too weak to walk
could ride in the Government wagons that hauled the food and the
blankets which they allowed to have. The food was most always cornbread
or roasted green corn. Some times the men who had charge of the Indians
would kill a buffalo and would let the Indians cut some of it and roast it.</p>
<p>The food on the Trail of Tears was very bad and very scarce and the
Indians would go for two of three days without water, which they would
get just when they came to a creek or river as there were no wells to
get water from. There were no roads to travel over, as the country was
just a wilderness. The men and women would go ahead of the wagons and
cut the timber out of the way with axes.</p>
<p>This trail started in Georgia and went across Kentucky, Tennessee and
through Missouri into the Territory and ended at Westville, where old
Fort Payne was. Old Fort Wayne was built to shelter the Indians until
some houses could be built.</p>
<p>Aunt Chin Deanawash was my grandmother's sister and she came from Georgia
on the Trail of Tears. Her husband died shortly after they got out of
Georgia and left her to battle her way through with three small
children, one who could not walk. Aunt Chin tied the little one on her
back with an old shawl, she took one child in her arms and led the other
by the hand; the two larger children died before they had gone so very
far and the little one died and Aunt Chin took a broken case knife and
dug a grave and buried the little body by the side of the Trail of Tears.</p>
<p>The Indians did not have food of the right kind to eat and Aunt Chin came
on alone and lived for years after this.</p>
</div2>
<div2 type="part" id="d7" n="4">
<head>Carnes, Solomon</head>
<p>August 20, 1837</p>
<p>Joe Southern, Interviewer</p>
<p>Indian-Pioneer History</p>
<p>An interview with Solomon Carnes of Bentley, Oklahoma, a full blood Choctaw
Indian, as to the disposition of the shipment or removal of Mississippi
Choctaws at Atoka, Indian Territory. Age 57 years of age.</p>
<p>Solomon Carnes, a native full blood Choctaw Indian, who lives near Bentley,
Oklahoma, born December 27, 1880, states: In 1898 Congress, under the Treaty
made with the Choctaw and the Chickasaws, passed an act allowing all
Mississippi Choctaw Indians that remained in all other states to move into
the Choctaw-Chickasaw country and reside for one year. Under this agreement
they were allowed to allot and have equal rights as to the allotment of
lands as to the Choctaw and Chickasaw Nation.</p>
<p>In 1903 there were about 450 Choctaws under the supervision of the United
States Indian Agency established at Muskogee. The Mississippi Choctaws were
loaded into box cars in the state of Mississippi and shipped to and unloaded
at Atoka, under the supervision of W. H. Angel as Supervisor, Leon Harkins
as Field Superintendent and Peter Maytubby as Choctaw Indian Police. These
Mississippi Choctaws were unloaded and established in camps three miles
southwest of Atoka, near what is known as the Mary Ann Brown spring.</p>
<p>This camp was established in August, 1903, for the purpose of locating these
Mississippi Indians on their homestead allotment in and around what is now
Atoka County. The expense for food at this camp and other expenses were
defrayed by the United States Indian Department located at Muskogee, Oklahoma.</p>
<p>Leon Harkins, as Field Supervisor, would take heads of these families and
drive out over the country and show them different lands that were
unallotted, for the purpose of helping them make decisions from among the
different locations as to their homestead allotment.</p>
<p>The camp was kept intact for four months as those different heads of families
made decisions of where they want to allot. They were supplied with a tent,
crosscut saw, ax, wedges, hoes, and other tools, also thirty days of
groceries, and they moved out on their homestead allotments near some spring
or live stream of water, where they could undertake to clear or fence and
build houses on these lands for the purpose of establishing permanent homes there.</p>
</div2>
<div2 type="part" id="d8" n="5">
<head>Chambers, Jennie McCoy</head>
<p>Mary D. Dorward,</p>
<p>Field Worker</p>
<p>Jennie McCoy Chambers</p>
<p>A Biographical Sketch</p>
<p>From a personal Interview with the Subject.</p>
<p>(1530 East 14th Street; Tulsa, Okla.)</p>
<p>(The subject of this sketch was very difficult to interview, for, while she
was very willing to talk, she is very deaf, is eighty-three years old, and
her mind seems to wander.)</p>
<p>Jennie McCoy Chambers was born April 24, 1854, in the Koo-wee-skoo-wee (her
spelling) district of the Cherokee Nation, near the town of now Claremore.
The house, a log cabin, still stands. It is at the north end of Claremore
Lake on Dog Creek, has two large rooms and a small room downstairs and a
room upstairs. Has clapboard doors.</p>
<p>Mrs. McCoy is about half Cherokee (which she calls Cher o 'kee, just as she
says Tahl ee 'quah), her mother, Mary Hicks, coming over the Trail of Tears
from Alabama when a child. Her father, Joseph McCoy, was a rancher and the
family lived on the place near Claremore until the Civil War when they went
over near Saline, and "refugeed" in the Cherokee Nation until the close of
the War. Evidently they did not remain at Saline because she said that she
and her sister many times walked from Tahlequah to Fort Smith and back for
supplies from the Government, and many times they almost starved. Her people
sympathized with the Union.</p>
								<p>Mrs. Chambers' grandfather and grandmother Hicks, together with her own
mother, came in the emigrant train over the Trail. On the way they
picked up to children who were lost. One, a boy whose people had all
died of smallpox, came to them when they were encamped along a creek. He
was known as S. S. Stevens and never knew but what he was an Indian. The
other child was a little girl who knew no name but Polly. When she grew
older she married and was known as Aunt Polly Myers.</p>
 		</div2>
<div2 type="part" id="d9" n="6">
<head>Cook, Wallace</head>
<p>March 17, 1937</p>
<p>Cook, Wallace</p>
<p>Grace Kelley, Field Worker</p>
<p>When my grandfather, Emeithle Harjo, was twenty-five or thirty years old, he
was removed to the Indian Territory, from Alabama. The boat that he was to
cross the Mississippi in was a dilapidated affair and sank in the
Mississippi River. He swam pretty near all night saving the women and
children. They were all brought here and turned loose like something wild.
He had to walk from here to the Fort Gibson to get the axe and gun that the
Government promised and gave to him. He built his home across the highway
from here. There are some house there but they are not the ones he built,
they burned, and rotted down.</p>
</div2>
<div2 type="part" id="d10" n="7">
<head>Davis, Susanna Adair</head>
<p>March 18, 1937</p>
<p>Wm. T. Holland, Field Worker</p>
<p>Interview with Mrs. Susanna Adair Davis</p>
<p>106 s. Quannah; Tulsa, Oklahoma</p>
<p>My first husband was William Penn Adair, known as a full-blood Cherokee
Indian. He was born in the Indian Territory, Cherokee Nation, in Flint Dist.
near Stilwell, Oklahoma on November 13, 1857.</p>
<p>His father was Red Squirrel Adair and his mother was Sallie Sunday Adair.
They were born in the "old" country, Georgia, and came west before general
transfer of the Indians. I have heard them tell of their journey. Red
Squirrel Adair met his future wife, and also a full blood, on this trip.
They were allowed to bring their herds so Grandpa Red Squirrel walked the
entire distance and drove his father's sheep. That was about 1810 and he was
16 years of age at that time. They would camp together and in this way Red
Squirrel and Sallie Sunday met. They had similar jobs. Sallie however, got
to ride a pony but her job was to drive the sheep and cattle. At night time
her herds would often get mixed and this, of course, resulted in confusion
and arguments, many of these between Red Squirrel Adair, 16 years of age and
Sallie Sunday, 11 years of age. However, this did not keep them from being
friends. Their families settled in the Cherokee Nation, Red Squirrel's near
Stilwell, Oklahoma, and the Sunday's further north and east of them.</p>
</div2>
<div2 type="part" id="d11" n="8">
<head>Dodge, Rachel</head>
<p>May 14, 1937</p>
<p>Field Worker: Grace Kelley</p>
<p>Interview with Rachel Dodge; Born 1886</p>
<p>11 miles SE of Henryetta</p>
<p>Father: Christopher Columbus Clay</p>
<p>Born in the I. T. Cherokee Nation</p>
<p>Mother: Polly Silk</p>
<p>Born, I. T. Cherokee Nation</p>
<p>Trail of Tears by Rachel Dodge </p>
<p>Aggie Silk was my grandmother and she has told me of the many hardships of
the trip to this country. Many had chills and fever from the exposure,
change of country and they didn't have too much to eat. When they would get
too sick to walk or ride, they were put in the wagons and taken along until
they died. The Indian doctors couldn't find the herbs they were used to and
didn't know the ones they did find, so they couldn't doctor them as they
would have at home. Some rode in wagons, some rode horses and some had to
walk. There was a large bunch when she came; she was sixteen years old. They
were Cherokees and stopped close to Muldrow where they built log houses or
cabins but they didn't like this country at first as everything was so
strange. She married at twenty years of age.</p>
</div2>
<div2 type="part" id="d12" n="9">
<head>Doublehead, Bird</head>
<p>I. W. Wilson, Field Worker</p>
<p>Father-Bird Doublehead. Born in Georgia, and first settled in Arkansas. I
don't know the date of his birth or death.</p>
<p>Mother-First name unknown, last name Timson, was born in Georgia and first
settled in Arkansas.</p>
								<p>The information that I have as to the migration of my parents, who came
west from Georgia, came on their own free will, paid their own expenses
and settled around the present town of Coal Hill, south and east of the
present town of Fort Smith, Arkansas. This removal from Georgia to
Arkansas was about the year of 1815. They remained there about thirteen
years thus and moved to the Indian Territory in 1828, and settled in the
Saline District at which place I was born. My aunt has told me that
later these Western Cherokees like my parents were increased with the
Eastern Cherokees who came by various methods and ways to the Indian Territory.</p>
</div2>
<div2 type="part" id="d13" n="10">
<head>Dowson, Lucy</head>
<div3 type="section" id="d14" n="1">
<head>Removal</head>
<p>Melissa Bird, an old woman of the Eufaula tomi ( tulwa) has often talked
of the life and incidents occurring in the Muskogee-Creek Indian removal
from the old country of Alabama to the Indian Territory.</p>
<p>Prior to the beginning of the move, the Indians had already begun the
holding of religious services at night. They were told of old Jerusalem.</p>
<p>When the move was finally begun a group of the Muskogee-Creek Indians
arrived at the Mississippi River. There was a log building on the banks
of the river wherein some Indians were holding religious meetings. The
inside of the log house was covered with red clay and the Indians of the
vicinity wore kerchiefs around their heads, long shirts and leggings.</p>
<p>It was in the Mississippi River, known as the Wewogufkee Thakko (Big
Muddy Water) in the Muskogee Creek language, that one of the ships with
a load of the Muskogee-Creek Indians was wrecked. Although many
perished, a few were saved or swam to shore. Many of the dead bodies
were taken from the river and given burial on the west banks of the
great river. Search was carried on for several days for other lost
bodies yet a number were never found or recovered.</p>
</div3>
</div2>
<div2 type="part" id="d15" n="11">
<head>Fleming, Effie Oakes</head>
<p>June 12, 1937</p>
<p>Field Worker: Hazel B. Greene</p>
<p>Interview with Mrs. Effie Oakes Fleming</p>
<p>Hugo, Oklahoma</p>
<p>Born: 3 1/2 miles northeast of Hugo</p>
<p>Parents: Joel E. Oakes, father, born near Old Goodwater. Choctaw Nation, on
Red River, about 15 miles S. E. Hugo; Josephine Cronk, mother, born Grand
Rapids, Michigan.</p>
<p>Mrs. Effie Oakes Fleming, forty-nine years old, one-sixteenth Choctaw Indian,
daughter of Joel E. and Josephine Cronk Oakes, was born at the present home
of her father, 3 1/2 miles northeast of Hugo, Oklahoma. I guess it was then
Kiamichi County. She was raised there and got all of her schooling just a
mile from home, at Nook Hill school. Started at the age of seven and
finished U. S. History, Geography, Arithmetic, Spelling, Rhetoric, Algebra
and elocution. The last year they had her study Texas history to keep her
busy. Hers would probably equal the present day high school education. The
schools weren't graded then. She finished school at fifteen years of age.
Aunt Mary Oakes Hibbins died in 1928, and is buried at Oakes Cemetery. Three
other children died young and are buried there of course.</p>
<p>About ten or fifteen years ago George Oakes bought out the other heirs of the
old place but stipulated that the cemetery should still belong to all of the
Oakes family.</p>
<p>After grandpa died, grandmother, made her home in the winter with the Tom
Hibbins, at the home that she and grandfather settled. In summer she visited
around, sometimes she would stay with us till late in the fall. I knew she
was there a lot after I would start to school in the fall, and when I was
studying history, she would tell us of the history of the Indian Territory,
and of their coming to this "wilderness" over the "Trail of Tears". She was
old and had nothing much to do but sit in the corner and live her life over
and tell us about it. She said that everybody who was able to, had to walk,
but if babies gave out of the parents could not carry them the drivers of
the ox wagons would just take then and swing them against a tree and knock
their brains out and leave them by the road side like a dog or a cat and not
bury them. Her baby brother, Joel (who later became supreme court judge of
the Choctaw Nation) was four years old and very fat. She was just eight
years old, but she took her turn at carrying him because he could not walk
much, and she said that she would get so tired she'd think she was going to
die but she would hang on to him. She was so afraid they would kill him. She
said she saw them kill babies who were too big to be carried and would give
out walking. Nobody rode. Occasionally a woman was confined. She was
permitted to ride for a few days.</p>
<p>There were ox wagons and they hauled necessities only; food, clothes,
bedding, and garden seed. Those drivers were employed by the government just
like grandpa was when he was sent out here.</p>
</div2>
<div2 type="part" id="d16" n="12">
<head>Geboe, Dave</head>
<p>May 4, 1937</p>
<p>By, Nannie Lee Burns, Field Worker,</p>
<p>Indian-Pioneer History Project S-149</p>
<p>Interview with Dave Geboe-1/2 Ottawa, 1/4 Miami</p>
<p>Miami, Oklahoma</p>
								<p>My father, Frank Geboe, was Eel River Miami Indian, disbanded at Peru,
Ind. He was Indian and French and spoke both languages. He died in 1871
and was 35 years old then and he is buried at Ottawa Cemetery in this county.</p>
<p>My mother, Pa-tes-noquah Geboe, was a full blood Ottawa. They lived near
Ottawa, Franklin Co., Kansas, where they were married and my sister and
myself were born. I was born November 24, 1861, and my sister, Emma, was
born in 1865.</p>
<p>My parents came in the fall of 1866 and located 2 miles north, one mile
east and three-fourths mile back south of Ottawa. The place is now Clay
Stevens' place. They came in two wagons and brought with them, cattle
and all the furniture, stoves and things that they could load in the two
wagons. My mother's nephew, Joe Holmes, came with them and drove one of
the wagons.</p>
<p>They were thirty days on the road. Whenever they wanted to, they would
stop and let the stock graze and rest, they camped at night, wagons all
drawn up close together. Built fires and sat round them after supper,
the men talking.</p>
<p>When they reached the land bought for the Ottawas, they went around over
it and each selected the place where he wanted to settle. We had a big
spring and were not far from Spring River, though not in the woods. Our
home was a double low house with clapboards for a roof. The men helped
each other and went to the timber and cut and prepared the logs and when
they had enough, then they were hauled to the place where the building
was to be, and the men all came and had a log-rolling. Our house and
stable were both built this was so by the cold days we had a home for
the winter. We had a fireplace in one room for heat but cooked on a
stove. We had coal-oil lights and sometimes used tallow candles. The
Indians of our tribes in this county have had plenty of money and so
have not had to live like some. They are all from the northeast, and
lived like white folks even before they came to Kansas and there we had
nice farms, nice homes, good furniture and lots of good stock.</p>
<p>There was a fort here then. Where was it? You know where Sunnyside School
is, Yes. It was on the first hill north of there on right hand side of
the road. It is about six miles south of Baxter Springs. What was it
called? I don't know the name but the name of the hill was Hunt Hill.
Now it is called the Abrams Hill, as they took the land. The old earth
works may still be there. There were stationed at the fort then one
company of Calvary and a company of Infantry. Col. Toe, I think was in
command. Several buildings, two commissaries, soldiers quarters, etc.</p>
<p>Why was this fort established? It was to keep the white settlers out of
Indian lands. There was a strip 2 1/2 miles wide from the Missouri Line
on the east, west along the Kansas Line to the Neosho River. Sometimes
referred to as the Neutral Strip-along the north end of the Quapaws.
White settlers kept coming over the line and trying to settle here. When
these soldiers looked after the Nez Perces while they were camped near
the fort. They gave them rations and kept them together. They were
northern Indians, I think, anyway they did not stay long. They were soon moved.</p>
<p>In 1873, I think the Modocs were brought to Baxter from Oregon on troop
trains in charge of soldiers. I remember seeing them. They were hideous.
They wore rings in their noses and ears, had flat heads. They bound
boards to the children's heads over forehead, and shaved the hair high
over the ears leaving the hair through the center of the head. This was
placed and hung down the back. They wore feather headdress. They wore
blankets, the men wore moccasins, leggins and breechclout. They were not
friendly and gave the soldiers lots of trouble. They were settled on a
tract 2 1/2 mile square in the northeast corner of the Shawnee
Reservation just west of Seneca, Mo.</p>
<p>They came from a different climate and they died like sheep. It did not
agree with them here and then they were not satisfied. I remember
Steamboat Frank. He was a fine looking young man about a half-breed I
should think. He wore citizen's clothes and nice ones, acted as
interpreter and talked English well. He died here and is buried in the
Modoc Cemetery. So is Scar-Face Charlie.</p>
</div2>
<div2 type="part" id="d17" n="13">
<head>Guernsey, Charles</head>
<p>April 17, 1937</p>
<p>Field Worker: Don Whistler</p>
<p>Biography of : Chas. e. Guernsey</p>
<p>1951 N. W. 12th Street</p>
<p>Oklahoma City, Oklahoma</p>
<p>Born: 1849, in Niles, Michigan</p>
<p>I was born in Niles, Michigan in 1849 and while I was still a boy we moved to
Illinois and later to Iowa. I was living in Iowa when I heard that the
government needed men to help move the Indians out of Kansas, so I sent in
my application, and was accepted. I went to Lincoln County and went to work
in 1869 when I was twenty-one years old.</p>
<p>I went to the new Sac and Fox Agency in the Indian Territory in March of
1870. The Sac and Foxes had been moved to their new reservation in the fall
of 1869. Through a mistake, they had located too far east and were really in
the Creek country. The Creeks protested and asked for a new survey, in the
spring of 1870.</p>
<p>The Sac and Foxes moved further west and the agency was located in a big
horse-shoe bend of the Deep Fork River about six miles south of the present
town of Stroud.</p>
<p>Miller, who was the Indian agent and Dr. Cook, the government doctor for the
Indians, and I lived in a long log house and kept "batch" that first year.</p>
<p>One time while we were eating, an Indian by the name of Chuck-a-ho
(Shack-a-ho) came along. I had learned enough Sauk to talk a little with the
Indian, and Miller told me to invite him to eat with us. While we were
eating Miller asked Chuck-a-ho why he didn't wear pants? I did the
interpreting. Chuck-a-ho asked Miller if he would give him some pants, and
Miller said that he would. So Miller told me to go down to John Whistler's
store and buy a pair of pants for Chuck-a-ho. The next time we saw him, he
was wearing the pants, but he had cut the seat and the crotch out and was
wearing then like leggins. When asked why he had done that, he said that
they choked his seat.</p>
<p>That first year the Government provided the Sac and Foxes with rations which
were issued every other day. They were given Salt Pork, Flour, Lard, green
coffee, and tobacco. I remember being a dinner guest at an Indian camp one
time, and as a special delicacy they melted a cup of Lard and gave it to me
to drink.</p>
<p>There was a company of soldiers stationed at the Sac and Fox Agency, about
one hundred, I believe. They were given rations every other day, but on the
alternate days for the Indians.</p>
<p>When I first went to the Agency we hauled supplies from Kansas City. We had a
great big wagon with six mules to the wagon. I remember one time we went
after potatoes. The weather was cold. We took some hay with us but that
didn't last so after that we cut down cottonwood trees and let the mules eat
the tiny branches. However, we did have grain for them. We loaded up six
wagons with potatoes and started toward home. When we were near Ottawa,
Kansas, the weather turned extremely cold and all of the potatoes froze. We
hauled them along and they began to rot. When we got to Honey Falls we
dumped them the whole load.</p>
<p>Sometimes we would be six weeks making a trip. Later the Government made an
arrangement to buy supplies by contract in Arkansas and they were delivered
by the seller.</p>
<p>There was a great deal of sickness among the Sac and Foxes that first year. I
believe there was about seven hundred died between the first payment and the
second payment. Dr. Cook was the first doctor for the Sac and Foxes and was
succeeded by Dr. Williams.</p>
<p>One of my duties at the agency was to drive the Ambulance. It was not the
same as an ambulance these days. But was somewhat like an old stage coach or
a hack. the drivers' seat was raised above the others. The seats for
passengers were a long ways of the coach and faced each other. We usually
hitched four mules to it.</p>
</div2>
<div2 type="part" id="d18" n="14">
<head>Harnage, W. W.</head>
<p>March 19, 1937</p>
<p>Interview with</p>
<p>W. W. Harnage</p>
<p>L. W. Wilson, Field Worker; Historical-Indian Research Worker</p>
<p>Interview was secured March 19, 1937, and Mr. Harnage states as follows:</p>
<p>I am one-fourth Cherokee and was born in 1852 in Tyler, Texas, which makes me
eighty-five years of age, last January.</p>
<p>My Father's name was George W. Harnage, born in Georgia, date unknown. Died
at the age of seventy and was buried at Chapel Hill, Texas, near the present
town of Tyler, Texas.</p>
<p>Mother's name was Nancy Mayfield, born in Tennessee, date unknown, and was
buried at Overton, Texas.</p>
<p>Grandfather, Jesse Mayfield, on my mother's side, was born in North Carolina
at date unknown to me. He died in 1847. He was buried at Belleview, Texas on
the old home place. The Mayfield Plantation.</p>
<p>Grandmother, Sally Starr-Mayfield, on my mother's side was born in Tennessee,
at a date unknown to me. She died in the early part of 1860 and was buried
at Belleview, Texas, alongside her husband. Grandmother, when about twelve
years of age, went to the river to see the party, under Chief Bowls, who was
Chief of a band of Cherokee Indians, leaving in canoes seeking a new land in
which to live.</p>
<p>Chief Bowls and his party left in canoes and drifted down the Tennessee
River, until they came to the Mississippi River. When they reached the mouth
of Red River they ascended Red River to the mouth of the Sabine River,
thence up the Sabine, to the headwaters of the Neches and here he
established a village.</p>
<p>He remained there until the Mexican War. At the beginning of the Mexican War,
with the solicitation of Sam Houston, and agreement was made, whereby Chief
Bowls would protect their rear from attack from wild Indians. The reason
that they solicited Chief Bowls was because he lived among the Indians, and
knew their traits, character, and tactics. For his services as such, he was
promised a concession of land, which embraced about three counties, the
names of the counties were Rusk, Smith, and Cherokee County, Texas. The
result of the Mexican War was that the United States whipped them. "Chief
Bowls never did receive for his reward, the three counties promised."</p>
<p>The line was run and started at the head-waters of the Neches River and went
with the wind of the Naches to some point on the Angelina River, thence,
down the Angelina to a certain point, thence due north to the Sabine,
embracing about three counties. Houston went to Bowls camp or village. He
told Bowls that he would give him that land and would make him a title as
soon as it could be done.</p>
<p>After the war, Houston became the first Governor of Texas. Later he was
elected United States Senator, which was after the annexation of the state
of Texas. While he was in the Senate, Governor Lamar became Governor. He was
the first Governor after the annexation.</p>
<p>Bowls was in his little village in the Neches and the people began to
encroach on him. He thought that he had a promised reservation. Bowls went
to Lamar and told him that the people were encroaching on his reservation.
Lamar did not give him any encouragement. The third time Lamar just answered
him: "The boundary of Texas is marked by the sword." Bowls understood it and
he left. He went back to his reservation and began a removal. He crossed the
Neches and camped off his reservation. He was pursued by the Texas Rangers,
and Bowls was killed and the larger part of his tribe slaughtered. Some of
them, however, got away. The Rangers pursued them, and they were captured.
They took them, as prisoners, to Fort Towson, in the Indian Territory and
turned them over to the Government. They were then moved to Fort Smith and
turned over to the Cherokee Nation.</p>
<p>My father was an old settler. He settled within about four miles of the
present town of Evansville, Arkansas, in about 1825 and remained there until
a treaty was signed back east by John Ridge and Elias Boudinot for the
removal of the entire Cherokee tribe from Georgia, North Carolina, Florida,
and other states, and he then moved to the Indian Territory and settled in
the Going Snake District.</p>
<p>My mother came through at the instigation of the treaty made as above
mentioned and known to all as the "Trail of Tears". They traveled in
caravans and wagons and were pushed along by the United States troops. Many
of the Cherokees did not care to leave their lands, that were so productive
and also to leave behind the burial grounds, where their loved ones were
buried, to come to this Western country. It was forced upon them and
consequently a great deal of dissatisfaction reigned among them, causing a
faction known as the Treaty Party and the Anti-Treaty Party.</p>
<p>My mother has told me that they came to the Mississippi River, that is was up
and that it was necessary for them to remain there six or seven weeks,
before they could cross the river, as they had no means, other than canoes
and flat boats to put them across. This put them on the west bank of the
Mississippi River, in Arkansas, and they continued to travel, often wading
streams with little food and practically no medical attention and hundreds
of them died enroute, caused by exposure and unsanitary conditions. Even
while they were waiting for the river to recede, while in Tennessee,
hundreds of them died on the banks of the river from dysentery. As they died
along the route they were buried in unmarked graves. My mother was one of
the fortunates that made it through and it is useless to say that she
endured many hardships, was grief stricken and sorrowful. She weathered the
storm, while others, even after arriving, soon died of sorrow and grief.</p>
<p>In this removal my grandfather had thirty teams and was employed by the
government to assist in removing them, so I guess my folks really fared well
to what some of the rest of them did, because, they brought with them enough
stuff to start building cabins, clearing the ground and making ready for crops.</p>
<p>My father and mother married in the Cherokee Nation and remained there until
what they called the "Star War", between parties of Treaty and Anti-Treaty.
My parents, along with Judge Adair, George Starr, Judge Wiley, Franklin D.
Thompson, two or three of my uncles and my grandmother, Sally Mayfield, all
went to Texas, before the Civil War, and lived as one big family and located
near the present town of Tyler, and Kilgore, Texas, and it was at this place
that I was born.</p>
</div2>
<div2 type="part" id="d19" n="15">
<head>Harris, C. B.</head>
<p>Interview with C. B. Harris, age 63, lives on Route 3, Muskogee, Okla. Just
north of the present Bacone College.</p>
<p>Mr. Harris was born and reared on the place which he now lives. He is a full
blood Cherokee Indian.</p>
<p>Father's name was Red Bird Harris born near Atlanta, Ga. Date unknown. Died
in 1903. Buried at family cemetery at his home. Mother's name was Ellen
Rogers Harris, born in Georgia, date unknown. Was a distant relative of the
late Will Rogers, the humorist. Died in 1910. Buried near the town of
Coweta, Oklahoma.</p>
<p>Grandfather-Father's side. Bill Harris born and died in Georgia. Dates
unknown. Full blood Cherokee.</p>
<p>Grandmother-Father's side. Savannah Collins Harris and died in Georgia. Dates
unknown. Full blood Cherokee.</p>
<p>Grandfather-Mother's side. Dr. Robert Rogers born and died in Georgia. Dates
unknown. Was full blood Cherokee.</p>
<p>Grandmother-Mother's side. First name unknown, last name Pateish. Born and
died in Georgia. Dates unknown. Full blood Cherokee.</p>
								<p>Number of the Cherokee tribe as early as 1828 left Georgia and came west
as far as Arkansas. About 1836 my great-uncle, Henry Harris, was
instrumental in perfecting as agreement with the officials in Washington
for the moving of the Cherokees in Georgia to the Indian Territory. The
move westward started about the same year and continued on through 1839
and probably as late as 1840. Some came on foot and their conveyances
were ox-carts, wagon trains, caravans, etc. The government moved those
who agreed with the treaty and those who did not want to leave their
rich fertile soil was driven out by the soldiers and came along as
history has already mentioned the "Trail of Tears". My mother Ellen
Rogers was one of the ones on this trail. My father Red Bird came from
Georgia to New Orleans, La., and thence from there by boat up the
Mississippi and Arkansas rivers and unloaded at the present town of
Webbers Falls, Okla. The Western Cherokees who settled first in Arkansas
joined the Eastern Cherokees in Indian Territory about the time my
father came which was in 1839. He and mother were married and settled on
the place I now live long before the Civil War. They fought, lived and
died on this place.</p>
</div2>
<div2 type="part" id="d20" n="16">
<head>Hicks, Herbert Worchester</head>
<p>March 30, 1937</p>
<p>Chauncey C. Moore, Supervisor</p>
<p>Indian-Pioneer History, S-149</p>
<p>James R. Carselowey</p>
<p>Field Worker</p>
<p>Interview: Herbert W. Hicks</p>
<p>Vinita, Okla.</p>
<p>Father: Herbert Worcester Hicks, born at Pork Hill, Indian Territory, May 14,
1861 and was married to Rachel Cardwell at Fayetteville, Arkansas, December
23, 1886. Rachel Cardwell was the daughter of James and Sarah Cardwell and
was born July 20, 1869, in Washington County, Arkansas. To this union the
following children were born: Ethel Inez, Homer Wilton, Clifton A., Vern
Clara, Ralph Conner, Herbert Morris</p>
<p>Vera Clara died November 20, 1900.</p>
<p>Father's Name: Abijah Hicks, born March 2, 1819, married January 30, 1852 to
Hanna Worcester and she was born January 29, 1834, at New Echota, Georgia.</p>
<p>My father and mother came with the Cherokees from Georgia and Tennessee in
1838. My mother was a daughter of Reverend Samuel A. Worcester, one of the
first missionaries to the Cherokees back in Georgia and my father was a
descendent of Charles Hicks, a Cherokee chief in the old Cherokee Nation in Georgia.</p>
<p>In 1835, after serving a term in the Georgia penitentiary, because of his
firm fidelity to the tribe, my grandfather, Rev. Worcester, was forced to
leave Georgia. His notice to evacuate follows:</p>
								<p>It becomes my duty to give you notice to evacuate the lot of land No.
125, in the 14th District, of the third section, and to give the house
now occupied by you to Col. William Handen, or whoever he may put
forward to take possession of the same and that you may have ample time
to prepare for the same, I will allow you until the 28th day of this
month to do the same.</p>
</div2>
<div2 type="part" id="d21" n="17">
<head>Hill, Mary</head>
<p>April 19, 1937</p>
<p>Billie Byrd</p>
<p>Research Field Worker S-149</p>
<p>Interview with Mary Hill, Age 47,</p>
<p>Muskogee Tribe</p>
<p>Okfuskee Town (tulwa), Okemah, Oklahoma</p>
								<p>Many years ago, my grandmother, Sallie Farney, who was among those, that
made the trip to the West from Alabama, often told of the trip as follows:</p>
<p>"In every way we were abundantly blessed in our every day life in the old
country. We had our hunting grounds and all the things that are dear to
the heart or interest of an Indian.</p>
<p>A council meeting was mostly composed of men, but there were times when
every member of a town (tulwa) was requested to attend the meetings.</p>
<p>Many of the leaders, when unrest was felt in the homes, visited the
different homes and gave encouragement to believe that Alabama was to be
the permanent home of the Muskogee tribe. But many different rumors of a
removal to the far west was often heard.</p>
<p>The command for a removal came unexpectedly upon most of us. There was
the time that we noticed that several overloaded wagons were passing our
home, yet we did not grasp the meaning. However, it was not long until
we found out the reason. Wagons stopped at our home and the men in
charge commanded us to gather what few belongings could be crowded into
the wagons. We were to be taken away and leave our homes never to
return. This was just the beginning of much weeping and heartaches.</p>
<p>We were taken to a crudely built stockade and joined others of our tribe.
We were kept penned up until everything was ready before we started on
the march. Even here, there was the awful silence that showed the
heartaches and sorrow at being taken from the homes and even separation
from loved ones.</p>
<p>Most of us had not foreseen such a move in this fashion or at this time.
We were not prepared, but times became more horrible after the real
journey was begun.</p>
<p>Many fell by the wayside, too faint with hunger or too weak to keep up
with the rest. The aged, feeble, and sick were left to perish by the
wayside. A crude bed was quickly prepared for these sick and weary
people. Only a bowl of water was left within reach, thus they were left
to suffer and die alone.</p>
<p>The little children piteously cried day after day from weariness, hunger,
and illness. Many of the men, women, and even the children were forced
to walk. They were once happy children - left without mother and father
- crying could not bring consolation to those children.</p>
<p>The sick and the births required attention, yet there was no time or no
one was prepared. Death stalked at all hours, but there was no time for
proper burying of ceremonies. My grandfather died on this trip. A
hastily cut piece of cotton wood contained his body. The open ends were
closed up and this was placed along a creek. This was not the only time
this manner of burying was held nor the only way. Some of the dead were
placed between two logs and quickly covered with shrubs, some were
shoved under the thickets, and some were not even buried but left by the wayside.</p>
<p>There were several men carrying reeds with eagle feathers attached to the
end. These men continually circled around the wagon trains or during the
night around the camps. These men said the reeds with feathers had been
treated by the medicine men. Their purpose was to encourage the Indians
not to be heavy hearted nor to think of the homes that had been left.</p>
<p>Some of the older women sang songs that meant, "We are going to our homes
and land; there is One who is above and ever watches over us; He will
care for us." This song was to encourage the ever downhearted Muskogees.</p>
<p>Many a family was forced to abandon their few possessions and necessities
when their horses died or were too weary to pull the heavy wagons any further.</p>
</div2>
<div2 type="part" id="d22" n="18">
<head>James, Rhoda</head>
<p>May 15, 1937</p>
<p>Interview with Rhoda James</p>
<p>Field Worker Gomer Gomer</p>
<p>Mrs. Rhoda James was born near Shady Point, Sugar Loaf County, in the Choctaw
Nation, some time in the year 1869, and now resides within eight miles of
where she was born. Her mother, Emily Tobley, came to the Indian Territory
at the time of the Removal of the Indians from Mississippi and settled near
Shady Point. She does not know whether or not her father accompanied her, as
he died when Mrs. James was a small child. She attended school at Shady
Point-then called Double Springs - where for a time John Payne was a
teacher. Later the school was taught by Jacob Jackson. The terms of school
usually run from September to March each year.</p>
<p>She cannot recall the year in which she was married but assumes it was at an
early age. At the time of her marriage, both she and her husband were very
poor. They erected a small cabin on the ground where she now lives. Her
husband worked around in the community wherever work could be found. He
found considerable work making fence rails, for which he received
seventy-five cents per hundred. This was usually paid in trade, such as
bacon, lard, flour, sugar and dry goods...........</p>
<p>She recalls hearing her mother relate her experiences both before and after
the removal. Her mother said that there was considerable opposition among
the Indians to being removed from their Mississippi homes to the Indian
Territory. This opposition was so strong that quite a number refused to
leave their homes, with the result that only a part of the Choctaw people
were removed. The oppositionists warned those who consented to the removal
that the land then offered them would again be taken from them just as it
had been done in Mississippi. According to the mother of Mrs. James, the
Choctaws were not accorded the best of treatment while in Mississippi. They
were not permitted to hunt on any land owned by Whites, and if any game was
killed on such land by the Indians, they would be subject to severe
punishment. The Indians were restricted in many other ways and were far from
being happy under such restrictions. After removing to the Indian Territory
the Indians had not fully recovered from the effects of the trip from
Mississippi, before the Civil War with its devastating effects overtook
them. The families of such Choctaws as entered the war were left helpless.</p>
</div2>
<div2 type="part" id="d23" n="19">
<head>Jones, Joanna nee McGhee</head>
<p>July 15, 1937</p>
<p>Interview with Mrs. Joanna Jones nee McGhee</p>
<p>128 K, N. E.</p>
<p>Mrs. Thos. Walker</p>
<p>Miami, Oklahoma</p>
<p>Mannie Lee Burns, Interviewer</p>
<p>Indian-Pioneer History S-149</p>
<p>Grant Foreman, Director</p>
<p>My mother was Susie Beck, a Cherokee and the daughter of Charlotte Downing
and Ellis Beck and she was born in Georgia. My father was Albert McGhee. I
do not remember the dates of their births.</p>
								<p>My mother was about twelve years old when they were forced to leave
Georgia and I have heard her say that before they left their homes there
that the white people would come into their houses and look things over
and when they found something that they liked, they would say, "This is
mine, I am going to have it", etc. When they were gathering their things
to start they were driven from their homes and collected together like
so many cattle. Some would try to take along something which they loved,
but were forced to leave it, if it was of any size. The trip was made in
covered wagons and this made many of the women sick, but they were
forced along just the same. When they reached streams and rivers, they
did not want to cross and they were dragged on the boats.</p>
<p>Grandmother always remembered it and I have often heard her say, "Some
day you will be taxed out of your homes here just as we were."</p>
</div2>
<div2 type="part" id="d24" n="20">
<head>Lattimer, Josephine Usray</head>
<p>October 13, 1937</p>
<p>Interview with Josephine Usray Lattimer</p>
<p>Interviewer - Amelia Harris</p>
<p>Indian-Pioneer History, S-149</p>
<p>My father was James Usray. Mother was Maylinda Roebuck. My maternal
grandfather was William Roebuck, three-fourths Choctaw.</p>
<p>My maternal grandmother was Felayah Polayah Homer, one-half blood Choctaw,
daughter of John Homer of the Shacchi Homer Nation, the name, Sig-Red
Crawfish. John Homer's wife was Chief Natastachi's daughter.</p>
<p>My paternal grandfather was Phillip Usray, one-half Cherokee. My paternal
grandmother (name forgotten) was sister to Chief Bowl of East Texas, who
held a Spanish grant to lands before Texas independence. He aided General
Houston in the battle of San Jacinto.</p>
<p>Josephine Usray Lattimer's grandparents came to the Indian Territory over the
Trail of Tears.</p>
<p>The Choctaws in Mississippi were a law abiding and cultured farming people.
They had good homes, churches....</p>
<p>All of the Indians in this District gathered at Memphis, Tennessee, in 1832
and were transported across the Mississippi in the steamboats, the Reindeer,
the Cleopatra, the Talma and the Sir Walter Scott. In crossing over the
Choctaws sang this song:</p>
<p>Fare thee well to Nunialchwayah (meaning to the land we love so dear).
Nunialchwayah was in memory of the leaning Pole "Fabuasa", the legend of
which may be found at the close of history of the Choctaws. When the
Choctaws reached Arkansas, the Government had wagons and teams there ready
for them. The Indians were loaded into the wagons and they started for the
Government post, near Little Rock, Arkansas.</p>
<p>In loading my people got separated from each other for there were hundreds of
wagons on this journey. When they reached the Ouachita (meaning 4th River)
River, it was on a rampage and out of banks. The roads were almost
impassable. It was raining and cold. Even for all the well and strong, the
journey was almost beyond human endurance. Many were weak and
broken-hearted, and as night came there were new graces dug beside the way.
Many of the Indians contracted pneumonia fever and the cholera. They camped
a mile from the Ouachita, waiting for the water to recede so they could
cross. While they were camped here, Ezekiel Roebuck, father of my
grandfather, William Roebuck, became ill but said nothing. When the river
was low enough to cross, everyone got in the wagons and started on the
journey but Ezekiel was so sick he became unconscious and fell over. Some
one told the driver and he said, "I will have to stop and put him out as we
can't afford to have any one with the Cholera along." So they stopped by the
road side and put him out. My great grandmother said, "You can put the
children and me out too," and the driver replied, "All right, but he will
soon be dead and you and your three children will have to walk the balance
of the way." Each child had a small blanket. My great-grandmother had a
paisley shawl she had brought along a bucket of honey and some cold flour
from their home. This flour is made by parching corn and grinding it in a
coffee mill until pulverized. This food she carried along for her six months
old baby. She begged the driver for food and a blanket for
Great-grandfather, and he grudgingly gave the blanket and one days supply of food.</p>
<p>Great-grandfather was conscious at times. He had dubbed Great-grandmother
"Little Blue Hen" and when he became conscious of their plight, he would
say, "Dear Little Blue Hen, why didn't you take the children and go on, I
can't last much longer, and my Soul will rest much easier if I knew you were
safe. My body is just dust and will be all right any place." She replied,
"As long as you live I'll be with you, Dear." Then the Little Blue Hen and
two boys, aged ten and twelve, set about fixing a bed.</p>
</div2>
<div2 type="part" id="d25" n="21">
<head>Lewis, D. B.</head>
<p>Thomas and Lewis Stories</p>
<p>An interview of D. B. Lewis, age 36, of Eufaula town, Henryetta, Oklahoma.</p>
<p>The story of a singing river was told by an old man by the name of Holly
Thomas who use to live three or four miles southeast of Eufaula, but he has
been dead for some years. His father and mother had come over to the new
country from the eastern home during the removal and so the story had been
told to Holly of the sorrows at the time of the removal and what the
conditions were at that time. He was a small child during that time but he
was told all stories about the times when he had become a young man. Those
old folks never could cease from talking about and telling of the hardships
they experienced along their trip often known as the Trail of Tears.</p>
<p>This story of the singing river was told to Holly by his father. It is not
exactly known whether the incident connected with this story happened in the
Mississippi River or the Tennessee River but it was the Creek Indians that
it was told about. This was told as it actually happened but it was a very
strange incident. As some of the Indians had been brought to the river to be
put aboard the ships that were to carry them part of the way by a water
route, some began to form ideas that they did not fully want to leave their
old homes and further, some resolved never to set foot on the ships so that
they couldn't be forced to suffer any more hardships.</p>
<p>They thought it would be best to end all relations with their superior
officers so that they began to fight them. In the attempts to check the
rebellion the officers had to use weapons and some of the Indians were
killed as they tried to run off into the woods. Seeing the rebellious
attitude of the Indians the white officers grabbed any Indian and pushed or
forced them into the ships. The officers readily killed any Indian on board
the ships that seemed to be in a rebellious attitude, but there were some
Indians who did not take part in the uprising but they were the eye
witnesses to those Indians who were killed on board the ships and thrown
overboard into the waters of the river. Some of them that were left unharmed
said, "Even we will die here but not by guns." With this, they took hold of
one another's hands and stepped off into a large suck hole that was in the
river and went to their deaths singing a song. It is told that many years
later, the words of the song which had been sung by those Indians could be
heard at certain times so that many people from foreign countries and people
from different places in this country have made trips to this vicinity in
attempts to record the tune and words of the song, but no one has ever been successful.</p>
</div2>
<div2 type="part" id="d26" n="22">
<head>Lewis, S. R.</head>
<p>Chauncey O. Moore, Supervisor</p>
<p>Indian-Pioneer History S-14</p>
<p>Lawrence D. Hibbs</p>
<p>Field Worker</p>
<p>Interview: S. R. Lewis</p>
								<p>Major Ridge, a full blood Cherokee Indian, who married a white woman and
his son, John Ridge, who also married a white woman, came to what is now
Delaware County, Indian Territory, from Georgia in the year of 1835.
John Ridge, the son, had a college education and both men were
considered rich men.</p>
<p>They opened a trading post near the Arkansas State line. (This store may
have been called Ridge's Store.) They employed one, William Childers, as
a clerk in this trading post. Later they gave William Childers $8,000.00
to go to New Orleans to buy supplies for this store. He made the trip by
way of the Arkansas and Mississippi Rivers, buying the supplies and
returning to the trading post.</p>
<p>The Ridges, father and son, were signers of the Treaty of 1835, and
which, later, was the cause of their deaths.</p>
<p>After the general removal of the Cherokees to Indian Territory in 1838,
the two Ridges (Major and John) were assassinated by their own tribe,
the reason being that because these two men signed the treaty disposing
of the Cherokee country east of the Mississippi River for land in Indian
Territory, the tribe thought they had been betrayed and sold out by
their supposed friends. They were killed in different sections, but on
the same day. Major Ridge was killed somewhere near the Arkansas State
line, on the same day a relative of theirs was killed near Parkhill,
which is about six miles south of Tahlequah.</p>
<p>The wives of the two Ridges, being white women, feared for their lives
after the death of their husbands and they moved to Arkansas, remaining
there until their deaths.</p>
<p>John Ridge had a son, John Rollins Ridge, who later came back to that
country to see after his father's and grandfather's land and business.
On reaching their old homes, he found that there was a black stallion
missing and he started out in search of this horse. After some time of
searching he rode into the farm yard of a man by the name of Kell. He
asked him if he had seen a black stallion and Kell told him he had and
pointed to where the horse was standing. They had some words about the
horse and the outcome was that Ridge killed Kell, after which he escaped
into Missouri and later joined a party of Indians that was migrating to
California. He later made a trip or two back to this country and to
Washington D. C. but ended his days in California. While in California,
he became a newspaper man and a writer, later being known as the "Poet
of the Sierras of California".</p>
</div2>
<div2 type="part" id="d27" n="23">
<head>Mann, Richard</head>
<p>RICHARD C. MANN</p>
<p>by</p>
<p>O. C. Davidson</p>
<p>I was born Jan. 20, 1872 in the Going Snake District of the Cherokee Nation,
at Oaks, one of the two oldest towns in the Cherokee Nation. I am a full
blood Cherokee; my mother, Elizabeth Miller came from Georgia in the Trail
of Tears in 1832, when the Indians were driven out of Georgia at the point
of bayonet and brought here like live-stock.</p>
<p>They came here by boats, landed at the mouth of the Verdigris River. A rock
with the date of their landing carved on it still marks the spot of their landing.</p>
<p>Upon their arrival here the Creek and Cherokee tribes separated. The Creeks
going west of Grand River and the Cherokees settling east of the Grand River.</p>
<p>Upon coming here the Cherokees were permitted to take claims at the land they
wanted, anywhere east of Grand River. The stipulations of the treaty were
that this land was to be theirs as long as grass grew and the waters run.
But later, the white mans greed for this beautiful and valuable country
became so strong that, they went to work and legislated laws in Washington
where by this country might be surveyed and divided up, allowing each Indian
just so much land as a homestead and certain allotment of surplus other than
their homesteads.</p>
<p>The full blood Indians never did agree to this allotment system but were
forced to accept it.</p>
</div2>
<div2 type="part" id="d28" n="24">
<head>McGirt, Dick</head>
<p>March 30, 1937</p>
<p>Billie Byrd, Field Worker</p>
<p>Indian-Pioneer S-149</p>
<p>An interview with Dick McGirt, age 65, Tuckabatchee town (tulwa), 21 miles
southwest of Okeach, Oklahoma.</p>
<p>The government orders for the removal of the Seminole Indians in the old
country to the new Indian Territory was under way. The Seminoles did not
want to come to the country, west of the Mississippi River.</p>
<p>They resisted the move. The Indians were victorious in battle, killing many
of the whites, but more forces were sent by the government, and the
Seminoles were overpowered and they surrendered.</p>
<p>There were four of us men who had always caused trouble and caused the tribe
to move in a disobedient manner.</p>
<p>The rest of the members of our tribe was quickly mobilized while the four of
us off on a hunting trip. Our wives and children taken by the white men
along with the rest of the Seminoles. Because our families were in the hands
of the government authorities so we thought it best to surrender. We were
bound and made prisoners.</p>
<p>The four of us were constantly guarded. The guards would often ask us if we
had the courage to be killed and if we were ready to die. The guards talked
as if we were to be killed after we had crossed the river. Still, we never
said anything.</p>
<p>As we were going along a trail to the river and just before we reached the
river, one of the prisoner's saw a crow feather on the ground which he
picked up. We hadn't gone much further when another one of the prisoner's
saw a blue jay feather which he also picked up. After they had picked up the
feathers they stuck them in their hats and then we gave our tribal war
whoop. We then told our guards that we were ready and unafraid to die.</p>
<p>When we reached the river, we were put on the boat with the rest of the
members of our people and tribe. The four of us that were held prisoners
were placed in a separate small room from the rest of our people. One of the
prisoners took sick while we were being held in this room.</p>
<p>The guards were in the same room with the prisoners, but they were asleep
when the following incident took place. I said to the other, "Let's make an
escape. I am going to make a dash for the door and break the door down and
when I do that the rest of you follow me and do whatever I do on the boat."</p>
<p>The sick man said, "I will stay in here and carry out the will of God to die."</p>
<p>So two men stayed while another man and I dashed through the door.</p>
<p>Just as we went out the door, shots rang; out in the room that we had just
left--the room where the sick man and the other had stayed. We knew that
those shots had taken the lives of our comrades.</p>
<p>We concealed ourselves in the lower part of the boat. Everything was in
confusion on board the big boat and several smaller boats were lowered into
the water while a search was made on the boat as well as in the water. We
were never found.</p>
<p>After things had quieted down, we dared to swim the mighty river. We hung on
to a log that happened to be floating in the water. Once we saw a large
snake that had a head shaped like the head of a cow, but we safely reached shore.</p>
<p>This is a story by an old Seminole man who was one of the prisoners that made
the escape and as he told it to Dick McGirt.</p>
</div2>
<div2 type="part" id="d29" n="25">
<head>Payne, Mary</head>
<p>May 10, 1937</p>
<p>Miss Ella Robinson</p>
<p>Research Field Worker</p>
<p>Mrs. Mary Payne</p>
<p>521 South Third</p>
<p>Muskogee, Oklahoma</p>
								<p>My father was David Israel, a full-blood Cherokee and my mother was
Martha Jane Miller Israel, a quarter Cherokee. They were born in
Georgia. My mother in 1836 and my father in 1837. They were brought to
Indian Territory by their parents over the "Trail of Tears" when the
Indians were driven from their eastern homes by the United States
Troops. They were too young to know of the tragedies and sorrows of that
terrible event. My aunt, who was 15 years old at the time, told me of
the awful suffering along the journey. Almost everyone had to walk as
the conveyance they had were inadequate for transporting what few
possessions they had and their meager supply of food. Only the old
people and little children were allowed to ride. They died by the
hundreds and were buried by the roadside. As they were not allowed to
remove any of their household goods, they arrived at their destination
with nothing with which to start housekeeping.</p>
</div2>
<div2 type="part" id="d30" n="26">
<head>Pennington, Josephine</head>
<p>October 12, 1937</p>
<p>D. W. Wilson</p>
<p>Investigator</p>
<p>Interview with Mrs. Josephine Pennington</p>
<p>Hulbert, Oklahoma</p>
<p>The scene of this story as given by Mrs. Pennington starts far back in the
dawn of Cherokee history. It deals with her forefathers before wrongs were
done to these proud Cherokee back in Tennessee and Georgia; with their weary
journey westward over the Trail of Tears. The Cherokees' first constitution
according to the Cherokee laws; the Cherokees' first Principal Chief, John
Ross; stirring events of the Civil War; the coming of the wild bands of
painted Indians from other parts of the United States brought by the
Government into the Indian Territory to occupy a part of the Cherokee lands
that they were compelled by the Government to sell for this purpose.</p>
<p>Progress is to be noted in Mrs. Pennington's recital, for they builded
schools and churches, towns and cities, from savagery among the wild Indians
to our present great state we have today.</p>
<p>Every individual has back of him things of which they are justly proud and
Mrs. Pennington is proud to know that she is a direct descendant of the
principal characters of the Cherokees.</p>
<p>After the Ridges made this treaty and those who favored it moved west. Chief
Ross and his band of 12,000 still refused to move and they met abuse and
troubles indescribable and finally the United States Soldiers were sent to
move Chief Ross and his people.</p>
								<p>After the soldiers appeared, they began to build stockades to house the
Cherokees until they could get them moving. All over the Cherokee
country they went, bringing in all of them, old and young, male and
female and their babes, the sick, the lame and the halt. They hunted
them down like hunting wild beasts and when they found them, they drove
them under threats and blows like cattle to these stockades. These
stockades were over crowded, disease broke out among them and many of
them died with dysentery. Poor food and poor water, no doctors and no medicine.</p>
<p>In due time parties were started west, under the charge of soldiers.
These parties were driven through like cattle. The sick and weak walked
until they fell exhausted and then were loaded in wagons or left behind
to die. When streams were to be crossed if not too deep all were
compelled to wade. The water often times was to the chins of the men and
women, and the little children were carried high over their heads. If
the water was over their heads they would build rafts and cross on them.</p>
<p>Chief Ross and the Council begged the Government to let them take over
the moving after a few parties had been moved by the soldiers and this
was agreed upon. They began to establish camps and their health got
better. It was only a short time until Chief Ross had worked out the
details for the removal and he moved his people in groups through
Kentucky, Illinois, Missouri, Arkansas, and then into the Indian
Territory. This journey was called the "Trail of Tears".</p>
<p>Unlike the moving by the army, arrangements were made whereby the old,
sick and afflicted and the babies rode on the wagons hauling provisions
and household goods. The others walked or rode horseback. These wagons
hauling provisions were Government property.</p>
<p>Even with these arrangements many died on account of cold and hunger
enroute and were buried in unmarked graves.</p>
<p>One of those who died on the Trail of Tears was Jim Ross Jr., the son of
Jim Ross who was the son of Chief John Ross as aforementioned.</p>
<p>Jim Ross Jr. was buried in an unmarked grave somewhere near the present
town of Aurora, Missouri.</p>
<p>Those who survived the hardships of the long trek, finally came to meet
the Cherokees west. After they arrived here all that they possessed were
a saw, an axe, a very little bedding and a big-eyed hoe and a small
amount of corn, enough possibly to plant an acre of ground.</p>
<p>Having located in the Ozarks of the eastern part of the Indian Territory,
many of them dug caves or dugouts in the hillsides in which to live
until with their axe and saw, they built a little log cabin. They lived
on wild fruits and berries. They made themselves bows and arrows to kill
their game.</p>
<p>Some were a little more fortunate for they had a horse and with a deer
tongue of wood and the big-eyed hoe they planted their corn in little clearings.</p>
<p>Chief John Ross and his family settled and builded their first home near
the west bank of the Illinois.</p>
<p/>
</div2>
<div2 type="part" id="d31" n="26">
<head>Pierce, Nannie Buchanan</head>
<p>February 24, 1937</p>
<p>Mrs. Nannie Pierce, Informant</p>
<p>Jas. S. Buchanan</p>
<p>Interview with Nannie Buchanan Pierce</p>
<p>My grandfather on my father's side of the family was an Irish emigrant to
this country in 1820 when he was only seventeen years of age and was living
among the Cherokees in Tennessee where he was married to my grandmother,
Eliza Heldebrand in 1829. To that union were born ten children, William,
Nancy, Rachel, Marguret, Elias, John J. (my father), Washington, Polly,
Lucy, and Mikel.</p>
<p>As grandmother was Cherokee, she and grandfather and the children that were
born up to that time were driven out of that country with the removal of the
Cherokees to this country in 1837 with the general exodus of the Indians
over what has been referred to in history as the "trail of tears", the
darkest blot on American history. According to the stories told to me by my
grandmother when I was a small girl it would be impossible for anyone to
graphically portray the horrors and suffering endured by the Cherokees on
that journey. The hardships were many all along the trail, rough country,
bad roads and all kinds of weather. A seeming endless march of weary,
struggling mass of humanity, driven from a country they knew and loved as
their home, deprived of most of their individual possessions, to the
wilderness of a new country. A procession miles in length of wagons,
two-wheel carts, vehicles of every description drawn by horses, mules and ox
teams, long troops of pedestrians of all ages and conditions, mothers
walking and carrying their babes on their back. Many walking and driving
their small herds of cattle and other stock. After a few days out on the
trail you could see them scattered along the roadside falling out of line of
march from exhaustion and illness, and so the long journey from east of the
Mississippi to the Indian Territory was made after several months of
hardships and sorrow and the cost of many lives of the Cherokees. I have
read of the "Trail of Tears " by different writers but none portray the
horrors of it all in detail as grandmother related to us when we could
persuade her to talk of it, as she would often tell us it was too horrible
to talk about and it only brought back sad memories.</p>
<p>Soon after the arrival in the territory my grandfather taken up a claim in
what was afterwards known as the Whiteoak Hills in the Illinois district of
the Cherokee nation about seventeen miles east of where the town of Bragg
now stands. He built a large two room log house with a railway between the
rooms and a stone fireplace at each end of the house. At this place they
reared their family of ten children and resided the remainder of their
active lives. Their last few years were spent among the children who were
all married and living at different places in the Territory. Grandfather
died at the home of his son Washington Patrick near Braggs in 1887.
Grandmother died at the home of another son at Vann, Oklahoma in 1903,</p>
</div2>
<div2 type="part" id="d32" n="28">
<head>Purcell, Joe</head>
<p>August 16, 1837</p>
<p>Billie Byrd, Field Worker</p>
<p>Indian-Pioneer History</p>
<p>Cheyennes</p>
<p>An Interview with Joe Purcell, age 38,</p>
<p>Cheyenne Tribe, Anadarko, Okla.</p>
<p>I have heard talk among and from the older Indians that when the Cheyennes
were moved from their older homes in Wyoming that they had as great and much
trouble, hardships, sickness and death in their travels to what is now Oklahoma.</p>
<p>Some of the Indians were loyal to the government and wanted to do what was
ordered of them. They were willing to move and settle in the new country but
some of the others didn't want to leave their homes. Some of them, while on
the way to the new country, escaped and returned to their old homes. It was
often the case that these fleeing Indians would be overtaken and shot down.
This seemed to cause a lot of trouble for the white men who had to make a
return trip to the old country and bring the Indians back to the new country.</p>
<p>While the escaped Cheyennes were causing all the trouble, battles and deaths,
those that were obedient to orders had willingly taken the new country as
their homes where they had selected their camping sites and located their
favorite hunting grounds. They had already become used to the new lands.
This was among the more peace loving Cheyennes.</p>
<p>It was while in their weakness and while seeking safety from the winter snow
and cold that fathers, mothers, brothers, sisters and children were
massacred in the Washita Valley in their country by General Custer and his
troops who swooped down on them and wiped the camp out. This was caused by
some of the disobedient Cheyennes and by their rebellious acts.</p>
<p>As a revenge, the Cheyennes were successful in Wyoming in surrounding Custer
and his troops where he had gone to return the escaped Cheyennes.</p>
<p>Note: This manuscript has not been edited for phraseology since it appears a
part of its value lies in the field worker's interpretation of the Indian
manner of speech.</p>
</div2>
<div2 type="part" id="d33" n="29">
<head>Rackleff, Kate</head>
<p>August 31, 1937</p>
<p>Nannie Lee Burns,</p>
<p>Interviewer</p>
<p>Interview with Mrs. Kate Rackleff</p>
<p>Fairland, Oklahoma</p>
<p>My mother, Rebecca Neugin nee Ketcher, was the daughter of John Ketcher. I do
not know the name of his wife. Both were full bloods. My mother was born in
Georgia about 1829.</p>
								<p>My mother, said to be the last survivor of those who came over the Trail
of Tears, was about ten years old when they left Georgia.</p>
<p>They came in rude wagons drawn by oxen, each family furnishing its own
transportation or at least my grandfather did and he loaded his wagon
with provisions for his family for the trip. This left little room as he
had a wife and six children of whom my mother was next to the youngest.
They were compelled to have a little bedding. They left Georgia in the
summer and did not reach this state till the next summer.</p>
<p>These people were brought through Tennessee and Southern Missouri, under
soldiers commanded by General Winfield Scott. General Scott left these
people under command of his assistant about the middle of the trip that
he might attend the National Whig Convention, which was at that the
contesting the nominations of Henry Clay and William Henry Harrison for
President of the United States.</p>
<p>Mother started with a little pig that she named "Toby". When they started
he was no larger than a large rat and each day at noon and at night
mother would let him run around and watched him and she kept him till he
was a large hog and he disappeared one day at the noon hour and she was
never able to find him.</p>
<p>In those days there were no roads and few trails and very few bridges.
Progress of travelers was slow and often times they would have to wait
many days for the streams to run down before they could cross. Each
family did its own cooking on the road. People then had no matches and
they started a fire by rubbing two flint rocks together and catching the
spark on a piece of dry spunk held directly underneath the rocks.
Sometimes, they would have to rake away the snow and clear a place to
build the fire. Travelers carried dry wood in the wagons to build their
fires. The wagons were so heavily loaded and had traveled so many days
that when they came to a hill the persons in the wagons would have to
get out and walk up the hill. They did not ride much of the time but
walked a good deal, not only to rest themselves but to save their teams.</p>
<p>Often, teams would give out and could go no farther and then those who
were with that wagon would be divided up among the other wagons and
hurried along. One day mother saw a team of oxen fall dead, hitched to
their wagon. The party she was with were in a severe snowstorm on the
way which caused much suffering. Many died from exposure on the trip and
mother said that she thought that a third of those who started died on
the way, although all of her family lived to reach the new country.
Those who came over the Trail of Tears would not stop for sickness and
would stop only long enough to dig a rude grave when any one died and
then the bereaved family was forced to move right along.</p>
<p>Mother said that their food lasted them till they reached the Indian
Territory but towards the last of the trip that they had little to eat
and had to plan to make it last. It was indeed a pitiful band that
finally reached the new home promised them for they had been a year on
the road, food had become scarce, their clothes which were homemade were
wearing out, many had died on the trail, some had lost their teams and
wagons and had been placed with other families and there were small
children in the band who had lost their parents.</p>
</div2>
<div2 type="part" id="d34" n="30">
<head>Stephens, J. W.</head>
<p>March 22, 1938</p>
<p>D. W. Wilson</p>
<p>Journalist</p>
<p>Interview with Mr. J. W. Stephens; Tallahassee, Oklahoma</p>
<p>J. W. Stephens is of Negro and Creek Indian blood and was born near the
present town of Eufaula, Oklahoma, on the Canadian River, about the year
1858. His father and mother, John and Theba Stephens, were born in the Creek
Nation of old Indian Territory, but their parents, his grandparents, came
from Georgia at the time of the removal of the Creeks, out of the states of
Georgia and Alabama, about the year 1833.</p>
								<p>Of course I do not know personally but my grandparents have told me of
their removal to the Indian Territory, and I can only tell you as it has
been handed down to me.</p>
<p>This removal was nothing more than greed and injustice on the part of the
Whites and suffering and hardship for the Creeks.</p>
<p>The Creek Indians held large tracts of land located partly in Georgia,
partly in Alabama and partly in Mississippi. They at one time had owned
considerable land but by treaties with the United States, at and before
their removal, they had left only what they considered enough for their
own needs.</p>
<p>The whites continued to encroach on the Creeks and insisted they move
west, but they stood with a firm determination not to give up their
lands. The entire tribe held council and at that meeting it was decided
that they would not give up a single acre of their land or leave the
home of their fathers they loved so well.</p>
<p>After this council meeting, a fellow named Colonel William McIntosh
called another meeting for he favored removal. Only a few attended this
meeting. McIntosh signed a treaty with the United States, saying at the
council meeting they had decided to trade their land in the east, acre
for acre, for land in the Indian Territory. Another council was held by
the majority protesting, saying it was made by the minority and not the
majority and they would die first.</p>
<p>The Creeks then began to shout Colonel McIntosh had sold out, accused him
of treason and at last burned his home and shot him. The men of the
McIntosh following were also killed.</p>
<p>The white people called the Creeks savages on account of this and all
manner of ill things were said of them, but, in reality the ones killed
were slain according to tribal laws.</p>
<p>A few years later the Government made a treaty with the majority to
remove them west, giving them land in the Indian Territory along and
between the Arkansas and Canadian Rivers. They were to move them and
furnish them with food during the first year, allowing them to clear
land and establish themselves.</p>
<p>Some of the Creeks left on this occasion: many, however, still refused to
move and my grandparents were among those who were driven out like
cattle and came to the Indian country by wagon trains and on foot. They
suffered many hardships, were footsore and weary, tattered and torn.
Sickness was among them and many died along the route.</p>
<p>My grandfather told me, he made the trip barefoot and often left bloody
footprints in the snow. He carried a little bundle of clothing and an
old flintlock rifle.</p>
</div2>
<div2 type="part" id="d35" n="31">
<head>Vann, E. F.</head>
<p>March 20, 1938</p>
<p>D. T. Wilson</p>
<p>Journalist</p>
<p>An interview with Mr. E. F. Vann; Muskogee, Oklahoma</p>
<p>I am the son of Turnip and Martha Vann and I was born in the Flint District
of the Cherokee Nation of the Indian Territory, June 20, 1870. The present
location of my birthplace would be in Adair County near the present town of
Stilwell. I am a full blood Cherokee Indian and am now the day jailer at the
Muskogee County jail in Muskogee.</p>
<p>My father was born in North Carolina about 1825, and my mother's name was
Martha Hood before her marriage and she was born in Georgia, September 14,
1835. My father is now dead and is buried some few miles south of Stilwell.
My mother is also dead and is buried in McIntosh County, near Chocotah.</p>
<p>In 1890 I married a white woman of the name of Alice McTheney who was born in
Crawford County, Arkansas, June 6, 1874.</p>
<p>My father and grandfather moved to Georgia before the removal of the
Cherokees to the Indian Territory from North Carolina and my mother's
parents lived in Georgia. There has been much told to me by my parents and
grandparents as to the way in which the Cherokees were treated and were
driven from their homes in Georgia, all of which history has recorded;
however I feel that I should say my parents were of two different clans or
factions. My mother's parents were favorable to the Treaty or the Ridge
Party and on account of a treaty made with the United States Government, my
mother's people were moved west by the Government, by steamboat and wagons
and settled in Western Arkansas, north of the present town of Fort Smith, in
1835. Mother was but a baby two years old at this time. These Cherokees were
called emigrants or the Western Cherokees.</p>
<p>My father's people would not abide by the treaty and were known as members of
the Anti-treaty or Ross Party who refused to leave their homes back in
Georgia, because the land was fertile and had many improvements and
furthermore because their loved ones were buried there. In all, the members
of the Ross or Anti-treaty party were satisfied and content in Georgia and
did not care to take up new homes in a country of which they knew nothing.
All the story of their sufferings in Georgia and across the Trail of Tears
has already been written. My father while only thirteen years old came on
the Trail of Tears with his parents and while on this trail, he lost one of
his brothers. Father's people settled in the Flint District where I was
born. It was in 1838 that this removal occurred and it was only a few years
until my mother's people who had settled in Arkansas were again compelled to
move into the confines of the Indian Territory. They settled in the Flint
District where Father and Mother grew up and were married.</p>
<p>I have heard my grandparents and parents say, that after the troublesome
times of enforced migration and settlement in their new lands in Indian
Territory, there followed at last a period of peace and prosperity among the
Cherokees. The younger Indians such as Father and Mother became reconciled
to the change but my grandfather never did.</p>
</div2>
<div2 type="part" id="d36" n="32">
<head>Walker, Henry J.</head>
<p>Interview with Henry J. Walker</p>
<p>Welch, Oklahoma, Star Route</p>
<p>James R. Carseloway, Field Worker</p>
<p>My name is Henry J. Walker, and I live at Welch, Oklahoma, Star Route. I live
on the farm my father settled on, when the Kansas line was re-established,
located on Big Cabin Creek.</p>
<p>My father's name was George Washington Walker. My mother's name was Mary Jane
(Harlow) Walker.</p>
<p>My grandfather was Timothy Migs Walker, and my grandmother was Elizabeth
Neely (Adair) Walker.</p>
<p>My father was born in Tennessee in 1823 and came to the Indian Territory when
a boy 12 years old with his parents, brothers and sisters, along with the
eastern emigrants, from Georgia about 1838.</p>
<p>My father told me that all the men and boys walked all the way from
Georgia, and the women and children were allowed to ride in the ox
wagons. It was a long hard journey and many took sick and died on the
road. It took so long to make the trip, longer than the government had
figured, that about all the money the Cherokees were given to live on
after they arrived was used up on the way.</p>
<p>My father said each head of a family was given $100.00 in money to live
on until they could get started up in their new homes, and that the
soldiers in charge of the movement were given feed and food enough to
carry them through. It ran out long before the journey's end was reached
and the government officers had to borrow from the Indians to buy food
and feed to continue the trip. By the time the Territory was reached
about all the Indians money was used up, many of their families were
reduced by death, and they were here without a thing to live on.</p>
<p>My father said the Government men in charge of the "Trail of Tears"
promised to turn in their claims and pay back the money they borrowed
from the Cherokees on the way over here, but they never did. I am told
that the Cherokees now have in a claim against the government for this
money with 5 per cent interest from 1838.</p>
<p>My grandfather, Timothy Walker, was a full blood Cherokee and settled
with his family near Tahlequah in 1868, where he lived until his death
several years later.</p>
<p>My father, George W. Walker, was almost a full blood Cherokee, and spoke
languages fluently.</p>
</div2>
<div2 type="part" id="d37" n="33">
<head>Interview with Mr. Ellis Waterkiller</head>
<p>Mr. Waterkiller was born in the Cookson Hills of Eastern Oklahoma, near
White Oak School, in Cherokee County, Oklahoma and now lives six miles
east of Fort Gibson, Oklahoma, near the present Perkins School in
Muskogee County, Oklahoma, on highway #62.</p>
<p>He is a full blood Cherokee Indian and 73 years old.</p>
<p>All of his known relatives were buried in the Cookson Hills of eastern
Oklahoma, near the White Oak School. No markers mark their graves.</p>
<p>Father - Waterkiller - Born North Carolina (year unknown) Died 1870.</p>
<p>Mother - Nancy Parsons Waterkiller, born Cookson Hills 1873 and died 1890.</p>
<p>Grandfather - (First name unknown) last name, Parsons. Born North
Carolina, (date unknown) Died 1840.</p>
<p>Grandmother - Sallie Parsons, born North Carolina (date unknown) Died 1885.</p>
<p>Don't know much about Father's people. Grandma (Parsons) tell me lot,
like I tell you.</p>
<p>Grandpa and Grandma leave North Carolina, in old country, come Georgia,
that old country too, stay there year. . . . 1837, soldiers drive um
West. . . . Grandpa and Grandma no want come. Soldiers say go or kill
you. Stick bayonet in you. They get things one night, skillet, pot,
dishes, clothes, bedclothes too. . . . got dish grandma bring. I eat
beans out em, I boy. It was an old piece of pottery, highly polished.
Bowl was fashioned with handles, handles broken off, but designs on it
were beautiful. See bowl, is over hundred years old. Next day soldiers
drive um out. Easy first day. Make soldiers feel good. Every day worse.
Just drive um like cattle. Grandma say she walk, grandpa walk too or
soldiers run bayonets through um. They walk, wade creeks to chin, lots
mud some places. Cross rivers in canoes. Soldiers save canoes, sometimes
hollow logs, made um boats, go cross river. Yuh, soldiers have wagons.
Feed um two times some days, sometimes feed um one time. Soldiers eat
all time, take care horses better than my grandma-grandpa. Yuh-they
bring skillet some things grandma had. Yuh - lots die, lots sick, lots
die, two week walk, they die, bury em where they die, any place. Yuh -
clothes bad, tore em, dirty too, clothes all gone when get here. Throw
lot way on road, no good.</p>
<p>They get here, lots timber, land no good in hills, all right in valley
Yuh - Grandma hate white man. Give all land, good land, in old country
meaning North Carolina and Georgia. . . . white man say "Trail Tears",
she say: "Trail Death". . . . grandpa die next year, mother born.
(meaning his grandmother died one year after the birth of his mother.)</p>
<p>Grandma say, her and grandpa come in hills. Soldiers say live, work, die.</p>
<p>Soldiers give em, ax, saw, big eye hoe, flint makin firs, corn, cotton,
beans, mellon seed. Some soldiers give em nothin. (He had in his mind
that some of the emigrants received nothing after their arrival, but was
promised they would get theirs later). My folks lucky. Others never get
nothin. .......</p>
</div2>
<div2 type="part" id="d38" n="34">
<head>Watts, Elizabeth</head>
<p>April 27, 1937</p>
<p>Mrs. Elizabeth Watts</p>
<p>A Biographic Sketch</p>
<p>Route #2, Box 168, Muskogee, Oklahoma</p>
<p>By L. D. Wilson, Field Worker</p>
<p>Indian-Pioneer History</p>
<p>Mrs. Watt's maiden name was Elizabeth Miller. She was born in 1859, in
the Canadian District of the Cherokee Nation and is a full-blood
Cherokee Indian. Her first marriage was to a Mr. Whitewater, now
deceased, and in 1894, she was married to Mr. Watts. Each marriage was
consummated under the Cherokee Laws.</p>
<p>Her mother was Mrs. Nancy Tony - Miller and she was born on the East bank
of the Mississippi River near Memphis, Tennessee, in 1837. Her
grandparents were enroute from Georgia on the "Trail of Tears". They
camped at the river several weeks waiting for the river to recede.
Disease broke out among them and many died, but Nancy was born and she,
at least replaced one of those who died.</p>
<p>Mrs. Miller died in 1876, and is buried in Goose-Neck Band neighborhood,
east of Muskogee, Oklahoma.</p>
<p>Her father, Wilson Miller, was born in the Cherokee Nation. Was an
orphan. He was reared by Uncle Joe Robertson, who was the father of Miss
Alice Robertson, late Congress-woman from Oklahoma. His home was with
the Robertson's at the old Tallahassee Mission, in the Creek Nation at
the present town of Tallahassee, Oklahoma. He knew little of his
parents, and likewise, Mrs. Watts knew nothing of her grand-parents on
her father's side. He is buried three miles south of Broken Arrow, Oklahoma.</p>
<p>Grandparents on Mrs. Watts' mother's side were named Richard and Nellie
Tony and they came to the Indian Territory in 1837, due to the removal
of all Cherokees west of the Mississippi River.</p>
<p>The Cherokees owned a large acreage in Georgia. After Jefferson was
elected President by the United States, he had agents to come to the
different Tribes to induce them to come west. Their inducement was much
more land than they had there. They had lived there in Georgia for years
and years. They had good land, that was left, for already the white
people had encroached and taken much of their land. Naturally, most of
them did not want to leave and go out into the wilderness and start life
anew. To do so, was like spending a nickel these days for a grab bag, or
like the saying, "Buying a cat in a sack". They did not willingly want
to do this. Time passed. The War of 1812 came, and removal was delayed.
A new President, Madison, was elected and he traded land in Arkansas,
north of Fort Smith, for their land and agreed to move them and give
them supplies, guns, clothing, ammunition, and utensils. A few of them
agreed and came. The most of them still refused. This greatly separated
the Cherokees. Those that came to Arkansas, had trouble there. The
Government then moved them to what we call the Strip Country.</p>
<p>Those left in Georgia began building larger homes, put in larger crops,
planted orchards, and advanced by leaps and bounds. It was during this
period the Cherokees adopted the Sequoyah alphabet in Georgia. Sequoyah
also came west to the ones in the Strip country and taught it there.</p>
<p>The white people used all means to get the Indians out of Georgia.
Claimed they were barbarians, and they, the Cherokees, made new laws,
just like the ones we had here in the Nation. John Ross was elected
Chief of all the Tribes of Cherokees. Ross did all he could to get to
stay there, but the Georgia white man passed laws and more laws, and law
or no law, they destroyed the Indian's fences, and crops, and killed
their cattle, burned their homes and made life a torment to them.</p>
<p>The Cherokees began to think of joining the West Cherokees. They simply
could endure no longer. Like everything, it took a leader, and Major
Ridge, his son, John Ridge, and two nephews, Elias Boudinot and Stan
Natie became leaders. Of course, John Ross was the Chief and they all
got to squabbling. Ross did not want to move his people, but by some
hook or crook, Boudinot and Ridge signed a treaty to move, and claimed
it was the will of the majority, but it was not, and the Government
united a little while and sent Gen. Scott and two or three thousand
soldiers. The soldiers gathered them up, all up, and put them in camps.
They hunted them and run them down until they got all of them. Even
before they were loaded in wagons, many of them got sick and died. They
were all grief stricken. They lost all on earth they had. White men even
robbed their dead's graves to get their jewelry and other little trinkets.</p>
<p>They saw to stay was impossible and the Cherokees told Gen. Scott they
would go without further trouble and the long journey started. They did
not all come at once. First one batch and then another. The sick, old,
and babies rode on the grub and household wagons. The rest rode a horse,
if they had one. Most of them walked. Many of them died along the way.
They buried them where they died, in unmarked graves. It was a bitter
dose and lingered in the mind of Mrs. Watts Grand-parents and parents
until death took them. The road they traveled, History calls the "Trail
of Tears". This trail was more than tears. It was death, sorrow, hunger,
exposure, and humiliation to a civilized people as were the Cherokees.
Today, our greatest politicians, lawyers, doctors, and many of worthy
mention are Cherokees. Holding high places, in spite of all the
humiliation brought on their forefathers.</p>
<p>Yes, they reached their Western friends and started all over again.</p>
<p>Lands promised, money promised, never materialized only with a paltry
sum, too small to recall, for what they parted with and the treatment received.</p>
</div2>
<div2 type="part" id="d39" n="35">
<head>Whitmire, Eliza</head>
<p>February 14, 1938</p>
<p>Interview with Eliza Whitmire (Ex-slave woman), Estella, Oklahoma</p>
<p>Giving her experience on the removal of the Cherokees from Georgia and other
experience of Pre-War Days.</p>
<p>My name is Eliza Whitmire. I live on a farm, near Estella. Where I settled
shortly after the Civil War and where I have lived ever since. I was born in
slavery in the state of Georgia, my parents having belonged to a Cherokee
Indian of the name of George Sanders, who owned a large plantation in the
old Cherokee Nation in Georgia. He also owned a large number of slaves but I
was to young to remember how many he owned.</p>
<p>I do not know the exact date of my birth, although my mother told me I was
about five years old when President Andrew Jackson ordered General Scott to
proceed to the Cherokee country, in Georgia with two thousand troops and
remove the Cherokees by force to the Indian Territory. This bunch of Indians
were called the Eastern Emigrants. The Old Settler Cherokees had moved
themselves in 1835 when the order was first given to the Cherokees to move out.</p>
<p>The weeks that followed General Scott's order to remove the Cherokees
were filled horror and suffering for the unfortunate Cherokees and their
slaves. The women and children were driven from their homes, sometimes
with blows and close on the heels of the retreating Indians came greedy
whites to pillage the Indians' homes, drive off their cattle, horses and
hogs, and they even rifled the graves for any jewelry, or other
ornaments that might have been buried with the dead.</p>
<p>The Cherokees, after being driven from their homes, were divided into
detachments of nearly equal size and late in October 1838, the first
detachment started, the others following one by one. The aged, sick and
the young children rode in the wagons, which carried the provisions and
bedding, while others went on foot. The trip was made in the dead of
winter and many died from exposure from sleet and snow, and all who
lived to make this trip, or had parents who made it, will long remember
it as a bitter memory.</p>
</div2>
<div2 type="part" id="d40" n="36">
<head>Woodall, Bettie</head>
<p>September 20, 1937</p>
<p>James R. Carselowey</p>
<p>Interviewer</p>
<p>An Interview with Bettie Perdue Woodall</p>
<p>Welch, Oklahoma</p>
<p>My name is Elizabeth Perdue Woodall, but I have always been called
"Bettie". I was born near Westville, Indian Territory, December 6, 1851.
My father's name was James Perdue, a half-breed Cherokee Indian. My
other, Dollie Thornton Perdue, was a white woman. Both were born in
Georgia. They were married in 1838, and came immediately with the
eastern emigrants over the Trail of Tears to their new home west of the
Mississippi, settling in Going Snake District, in the new Cherokee Nation.</p>
<p>Some histories say that on the Trail of Tears all the women and children
were allowed to ride; but my mother told me that not a single woman rode
unless she was sick and not able to walk. My mother walked every step of
the way over here.</p>
<p>The Government furnished green coffee in the grain for the Indians along
the route. Many of them had never seen coffee and did not know how to
make it. Some of them put the coffee in a pot with meat and were trying
to cook it like beans when my mother came along and some Indian woman
said, "Ask her, She white woman." My mother said she just had to laugh
the way they were trying to cook that coffee. She took some of the green
coffee, roasted it in a pan over their fire, put the parched grains in a
cloth and pounded it up, and made them a pot of coffee. They all liked
it and said she was a smart white woman.</p>
<p>She also showed them how to cook their rice. It seems they all thought
everything had to be cooked with meat, but in this way the young white
woman became very popular and much loved by her newly made friends.</p>
<p>My mother told me about many of the hardships and privations she and the
rest of the women suffered while on their way from Georgia. Some of them
were almost unbelievable, yet I know they are true, for my mother would
have had no motive in telling it if it had not been so.</p>
<p>On one occasion she told of an officer in charge of one of the wagons,
who killed a little baby because it cried all the time. It was only four
days old and the mother was forced to walk and carry it, and because it
cried all of the time and the young mother could not quiet it, the
officer took it away from her and dashed its little head against a tree
and killed it.</p>
</div2>
<div2 type="part" id="d41" n="37">
<head>Wynn, Lizzie</head>
<p>November 29, 1937</p>
<p>Grace Kelley, Investigator</p>
<p>An Interview with Lizzie Wynn; Dustin, Oklahoma</p>
<p>Uncle Willie Benson used to tell me about how they came to this country.
When they started out they were afoot and were driven like cattle. At
first they had something to eat but that gave out and they were
starving. If they had had guns or string they could have gotten game or
fish but were not allowed to have them. They came to a slippery elm tree
and ate the bark of that until they could get something else. When they
would give out they would camp for two or three days to rest up a very
little bit, then come on again. Lots took sick and died, so there were
not so many when they got here. Big boats were used to haul them across
the streams and lakes. When they got to Arkansas they were unable to
walk farther so wagons were provided for the rest of the trip. I don't
know just where they located first but they were Muskogee Indians under
Opuithli Yahola.</p>
</div2>
</div1>
</body>
</text>
</TEI.2>
