<?xml version="1.0"?>

<?dlps id="MuiAmer"?>
<?dlps page-images="none" figure-images="no"?>
<?dlps transcription="other"?>

<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/tei-p4/tei2.dtd" [
<!ENTITY % POSTKB "INCLUDE">
<!ENTITY % TEI.extensions.ent SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.ent">
<!ENTITY % TEI.extensions.dtd SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.dtd">
<!ENTITY % ISOnum SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/charent/iso-num.ent"> %ISOnum;
<!ENTITY % ISOpub SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/charent/iso-pub.ent"> %ISOpub;

]>


<TEI.2 id="MuiAmer">
<teiHeader type="migrated" creator="Etext">
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title type="main">American Forests</title>
<title type="sort">american forests</title>
<author>Muir, John</author>
<respStmt>
<resp>Creation of machine-readable version:</resp>
<name>Judy Boss</name>
<resp>Conversion to TEI.2-conformant markup:</resp>
<name>University of Virginia Library Electronic Text Center</name>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt>
<extent>ca. <num type="kilobytes">50</num> kilobytes</extent>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>University of Virginia Library</publisher>
<pubPlace>Charlottesville, Virginia</pubPlace>
<idno type="ETC">MuiAmer</idno>
<date value="1995">1995</date>
<availability status="public">
<p n="copyright">Copyright &copy; 1995 by the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia</p>
<p n="access">Publicly accessible</p>
</availability>
<idno type="uva-pid">uva-lib:476242</idno>
</publicationStmt>
<seriesStmt>
<title>University of Virginia Library, Text collection</title>
<idno type="uva-set">UVA-LIB-Text</idno>
</seriesStmt>
<sourceDesc>
<biblFull>
<titleStmt>
<title type="main">American Forests</title>
<title type="sort">american forests</title>
<author>John Muir</author>
</titleStmt>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>Atlantic Monthly no. 80</publisher>
<pubPlace>Boston, Mass.</pubPlace>
<date value="1897-08">August 1897</date>
</publicationStmt>
<seriesStmt>
<p>80</p>
</seriesStmt>
<notesStmt>
<note>
<p>Atlantic Monthly no. 80, August 1897</p>
</note>
</notesStmt>
</biblFull>
</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc>
<encodingDesc>
<projectDesc>
<p>Prepared for the University of Virginia Library Electronic Text Center</p>
</projectDesc>
<editorialDecl>
<p>All quotation marks retained as data</p>
<p>All unambiguous end-of-line hyphens have been removed, and the
trailing part of a word has been joined to the preceding line.</p>
<p id="ETC">Keywords in the header are a local Electronic Text Center scheme
to aid in establishing analytical groupings</p>
</editorialDecl>
<refsDecl>
<p>ID elements are given for each page element and are composed of the text's
unique cryptogram and the given page number, as in AusEmma1 for page one of
Jane Austen's Emma.</p>
</refsDecl>
</encodingDesc>
<profileDesc>
<creation>
<date value="1897">1897</date>
</creation>
<langUsage>
<language id="eng" usage="main">English</language>
</langUsage>
<textClass>
<keywords>
<term>non-fiction; prose</term>
</keywords>
</textClass>
</profileDesc>
<revisionDesc>
<change>
<date value="1995-08">August 1995</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>corrector</resp>
<name>Jamie L Spriggs, Electronic Text Center, University of Virginia</name>
<name>Deirdre A Johnson, Electronic Text Center, University of Virginia</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Added header, Tagged with TEI.2-compatible SGML, Parsed against "teilite" dtd</item>
</change>
<change>
<date value="2005-07">July 2005</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>Corrector</resp>
<name>John Ivor Carlson</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Converted to XML and/or checked tags.</item>
</change>
<change>
<date value="2007-09">September 2007</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>Migration</resp>
<name>Ethan Gruber, University of Virginia Library</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Converted XML markup from TEI Lite to uva-dl-tei (TEI P4 with local customizations).</item>
</change>
<change>
<date value="2008-01">January 2008</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>Migration</resp>
<name>Greg Murray, University of Virginia Library</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Programmatically updated TEI header markup (but not header content) for minimal compliance with current QA requirements.</item>
</change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text id="d1">
<body id="d2">

<div1 type="essay" id="d3"><pb n="145"/>
<head>                       THE AMERICAN FORESTS.</head>

<p>     THE forests of America, however slighted by man, must have
been a great delight to God; for they were the best he ever
planted.  The whole continent was a garden, and from the beginning
it seemed to be favored above all the other wild parks and gardens
of the globe.  To prepare the ground, it was rolled and sifted in
seas with infinite loving deliberation and forethought, lifted into
the light, submerged and warmed over and over again, pressed and
crumpled into folds and ridges, mountains and hills, subsoiled with
heaving volcanic fires, ploughed and ground and sculptured into
scenery and soil with glaciers and rivers,&mdash;every feature growing
and changing from beauty to beauty, higher and higher.  And in the
fullness of time it was planted in groves, and belts, and broad,
exuberant, mantling forests, with the largest, most varied, most
fruitful, and most beautiful trees in the world.  Bright seas made
its border with wave embroidery and icebergs; gray deserts were
outspread in the middle of it, mossy tundras on the north, savannas
on the south, and blooming prairies and plains; while lakes and
rivers shone through all the vast forests and openings, and happy
birds and beasts gave delightful animation.  Everywhere, everywhere
over all the blessed continent, there were beauty, and melody, and
kindly, wholesome, foodful abundance.</p>
<p>     These forests were composed of about five hundred species of
trees, all of them in some way useful to man, ranging in size from
twenty-five feet in height and less than one foot in diameter at
the ground to four hundred feet in height and more than twenty feet
in diameter,&mdash;lordly monarchs proclaiming the gospel of beauty like
apostles.  For many a century after the ice-ploughs were melted,
nature fed them and dressed them every day; working like a man, a
loving, devoted, painstaking gardener; fingering every leaf and
flower and mossy furrowed bole; bending, trimming, modeling,
balancing, painting them with the loveliest colors; bringing over
them now clouds with cooling shadows and showers, now sunshine;
fanning them with gentle winds and rustling their leaves;
exercising them in every fibre with storms, and pruning them;
loading them with flowers and fruit, loading them with snow, and
ever making them more beautiful as the years rolled by.  Wide-branching oak and elm in endless variety, walnut and maple,
chestnut and beech, ilex and locust, touching limb to limb, spread
a leafy translucent canopy along the coast of the Atlantic over the
wrinkled folds and ridges of the Alleghanies,&mdash;a green billowy sea
in summer, golden and purple in autumn, pearly gray like a
steadfast frozen mist of interlacing branches and sprays in
leafless, restful winter.</p>
<p>     To the southward stretched dark, level-topped cypresses in
knobby, tangled swamps, grassy savannas in the midst of them like
lakes of light, groves of gay sparkling spice-trees, magnolias and
palms, glossy-leaved and blooming and <pb n="146"/>  shining continually.
To the northward, over Maine and the Ottawa, rose hosts of spiry,
rosiny evergreens,&mdash;white pine and spruce, hemlock and cedar,
shoulder to shoulder, laden with purple cones, their myriad needles
sparkling and shimmering, covering hills and swamps, rocky
headlands and domes, ever bravely aspiring and seeking the sky; the
ground in their shade now snow-clad and frozen, now mossy and
flowery; beaver meadows here and there, full of lilies and grass;
lakes gleaming like eyes, and a silvery embroidery of rivers and
creeks watering and brightening all the vast glad wilderness.</p>
<p>     Thence westward were oak and elm, hickory and tupelo, gum and
liriodendron, sassafras and ash, linden and laurel, spreading on
ever wider in glorious exuberance over the great fertile basin of
the Mississippi, over damp level bottoms, low dimpling hollows, and
round dotting hills, embosoming sunny prairies and cheery park
openings, half sunshine, half shade; while a dark wilderness of
pines covered the region around the Great Lakes.  Thence still
westward swept the forests to right and left around grassy plains
and deserts a thousand miles wide: irrepressible hosts of spruce
and pine, aspen and willow, nut-pine and juniper, cactus and yucca,
caring nothing for drought, extending undaunted from mountain to
mountain, over mesa and desert, to join the darkening multitudes of
pines that covered the high Rocky ranges and the glorious forests
along the coast of the moist and balmy Pacific, where new species
of pine, giant cedars and spruces, silver firs and sequoias, kings
of their race, growing close together like grass in a meadow,
poised their brave domes and spires in the sky three hundred feet
above the ferns and the lilies that enameled the ground; towering
serene through the long centuries, preaching God's forestry fresh
from heaven.</p>
<p>     Here the forests reached their highest development.  Hence
they went wavering northward over icy Alaska, brave spruce and fir,
poplar and birch, by the coasts and the rivers, to within sight of
the Arctic Ocean.  American forests! the glory of the world!
Surveyed thus from the east to the west, from the north to the
south, they are rich beyond thought, immortal, immeasurable, enough
and to spare for every feeding, sheltering beast and bird, insect
and son of Adam; and nobody need have cared had there been no pines
in Norway, no cedars and deodars on Lebanon and the Himalayas, no
vine-clad selvas in the basin of the Amazon.  With such variety,
harmony, and triumphant exuberance, even nature, it would seem,
might have rested content with the forests of North America, and
planted no more.</p>
<p>     So they appeared a few centuries ago when they were rejoicing
in wildness.  The Indians with stone axes could do them no more
harm than could gnawing beavers and browsing moose.  Even the fires
of the Indians and the fierce shattering lightning seemed to work
together only for good in clearing spots here and there for smooth
garden prairies, and openings for sunflowers seeking the light.
But when the steel axe of the white man rang out in the startled
air their doom was sealed.  Every tree heard the bodeful sound, and
pillars of smoke gave the sign in the sky.</p>
<p>     I suppose we need not go mourning the buffaloes.  In the
nature of things they had to give place to better cattle, though
the change might have been made without barbarous wickedness.
Likewise many of nature's five hundred kinds of wild trees had to
make way for orchards and cornfields.  In the settlement and
civilization of the country, bread more than timber or beauty was
wanted; and in the blindness of hunger, the early settlers,
claiming Heaven as their guide, regarded God's trees as only a
larger kind of pernicious weeds, extremely hard to get rid of.
Accordingly, with no eye <pb n="147"/>  to the future, these pious
destroyers waged interminable forest wars; chips flew thick and
fast; trees in their beauty fell crashing by millions, smashed to
confusion, and the smoke of their burning has been rising to heaven
more than two hundred years.  After the Atlantic coast from Maine
to Georgia had been mostly cleared and scorched into melancholy
ruins, the overflowing multitude of bread and money seekers poured
over the Alleghanies into the fertile middle West, spreading
ruthless devastation ever wider and farther over the rich valley of
the Mississippi and the vast shadowy pine region about the Great
Lakes.  Thence still westward the invading horde of destroyers
called settlers made its fiery way over the broad Rocky Mountains,
felling and burning more fiercely than ever, until at last it has
reached the wild side of the continent, and entered the last of the
great aboriginal forests on the shores of the Pacific.</p>
<p>     Surely, then, it should not be wondered at that lovers of
their country, bewailing its baldness, are now crying aloud, "Save
what is left of the forests!"  Clearing has surely now gone far
enough; soon timber will be scarce, and not a grove will be left to
rest in or pray in.  The remnant protected will yield plenty of
timber, a perennial harvest for every right use, without further
diminution of its area, and will continue to cover the springs of
the rivers that rise in the mountains and give irrigating waters to
the dry valleys at their feet, prevent wasting floods and be a
blessing to everybody forever.</p>
<p>     Every other civilized nation in the world has been compelled
to care for its forests, and so must we if waste and destruction
are not to go on to the bitter end, leaving America as barren as
Palestine or Spain.  In its calmer moments in the midst of
bewildering hunger and war and restless over-industry, Prussia has
learned that the forest plays an important part in human progress,
and that the advance in civilization only makes it more
indispensable.  It has, therefore, as shown by Mr. Pinchot, refused
to deliver its forests to more or less speedy destruction by
permitting them to pass into private ownership.  But the state
woodlands are not allowed to lie idle.  On the contrary, they are
made to produce as much timber as is possible without spoiling
them.  In the administration of its forests, the state righteously
considers itself bound to treat them as a trust for the nation as
a whole, and to keep in view the common good of the people for all
time.</p>
<p>     In France no government forests have been sold since 1870.  On
the other hand, about one half of the fifty million francs spent on
forestry has been given to engineering works, to make the
replanting of denuded areas possible.  The disappearance of the
forests in the first place, it is claimed, may be traced in most
cases directly to mountain pasturage.  The provisions of the code
concerning private woodlands are substantially these: No private
owner may clear his woodlands without giving notice to the
government at least four months in advance, and the forest service
may forbid the clearing on the following grounds: to maintain the
soil on mountains, to defend the soil against erosion and flooding
by rivers or torrents, to insure the existence of springs and
watercourses, to protect the dunes and seashore, etc.  A proprietor
who has cleared his forest without permission is subject to heavy
fine, and in addition may be made to replant the cleared area.</p>
<p>     In Switzerland, after many laws like our own had been found
wanting, the Swiss forest school was established in 1865, and soon
after the Federal Forest Law was enacted, which is binding over
nearly two thirds of the country.  Under its provisions, the
cantons must appoint and pay the number of suitably educated
foresters required for the fulfillment of the forest law; and in
the organization <pb n="148"/>  of a normally stocked forest, the object
of first importance must be the cutting each year of an amount of
timber equal to the total annual increase, and no more.</p>
<p>     The Russian government passed a law in 1888, declaring that
clearing is forbidden in protection forests, and is allowed in
others "only when its effects will not be to disturb the suitable
relations which should exist between forest and agricultural
lands."</p>
<p>     Even Japan is ahead of us in the management of her forests.
They cover an area of about 29,000,000 acres.  The feudal lords
valued the woodlands, and enacted vigorous protective laws; and
when, in the latest civil war, the Mikado government destroyed the
feudal system, it declared the forests that had belonged to the
feudal lords to be the property of the state, promulgated a forest
law binding on the whole kingdom, and founded a school of forestry
in Tokio.  The forest service does not rest satisfied with the
present proportion of woodland, but looks to planting the best
forest trees it can find in any country, if likely to be useful and
to thrive in Japan.</p>
<p>     In India systematic forest management was begun about forty
years ago, under difficulties&mdash;presented by the character of the
country, the prevalence of running fires, opposition from
lumbermen, settlers, etc.&mdash;not unlike those which confront us now.
Of the total area of government forests, perhaps 70,000,000 acres,
55,000,000 acres have been brought under the control of the
forestry department,&mdash;a larger area than that of all our national
parks and reservations.  The chief aims of the administration are
effective protection of the forests from fire, an efficient system
of regeneration, and cheap transportation of the forest products;
the results so far have been most beneficial and encouraging.</p>
<p>     It seems, therefore, that almost every civilized nation can
give us a lesson on the management and care of forests.  So far our
government has done nothing effective with its forests, though the
best in the world, but is like a rich and foolish spendthrift who
has inherited a magnificent estate in perfect order, and then has
left his rich fields and meadows, forests and parks, to be sold and
plundered and wasted at will, depending on their inexhaustible
abundance.  Now it is plain that the forests are not inexhaustible,
and that quick measures must be taken if ruin is to be avoided.
Year by year the remnant is growing smaller before the axe and
fire, while the laws in existence provide neither for the
protection of the timber from destruction nor for its use where it
is most needed.</p>
<p>     As is shown by Mr. E. A. Bowers, formerly Inspector of the
Public Land Service, the foundation of our protective policy, which
has never protected, is an act passed March 1, 1817, which
authorized the Secretary of the Navy to reserve lands producing
live-oak and cedar, for the sole purpose of supplying timber for
the navy of the United States.  An extension of this law by the
passage of the act of March 2, 1831, provided that if any person
should cut live-oak or red cedar trees or <hi rend="italic">other timber</hi> from the
lands of the United States for any other purpose than the
construction of the navy, such person should pay a fine not less
than triple the value of the timber cut, and be imprisoned for a
period not exceeding twelve months.  Upon this old law, as Mr.
Bowers points out, having the construction of a wooden navy in
view, the United States government has to-day chiefly to rely in
protecting its timber throughout the arid regions of the West,
where none of the naval timber which the law had in mind is to be
found.</p>
<p>     By the act of June 3, 1878, timber can be taken from public
lands not subject to entry under any existing laws except for
minerals, by <hi rend="italic">bona fide</hi> residents of the Rocky Mountain States
and Terri-<pb n="149"/> tories and the Dakotas.  Under the timber and
stone act, of the same date, land in the Pacific States and Nevada,
valuable mainly for timber, and unfit for cultivation if the timber
is removed, can be purchased for two dollars and a half an acre,
under certain restrictions.  By the act of March 3, 1875, all land-grant and right-of-way railroads are authorized to take timber from
the public lands adjacent to their lines for construction purposes;
and they have taken it with a vengeance, destroying a hundred times
more than they have used, mostly by allowing fires to run into the
woods.  The settlement laws, under which a settler may enter lands
valuable for timber as well as for agriculture, furnish another
means of obtaining title to public timber.</p>
<p>     With the exception of the timber culture act, under which, in
consideration of planting a few acres of seedlings, settlers on the
treeless plains got 160 acres each, the above is the only
legislation aiming to protect and promote the planting of forests.
In no other way than under some one of these laws can a citizen of
the United States make any use of the public forests.  To show the
results of the timber-planting act, it need only be stated that of
the 38,000,000 acres entered under it, less than 1,000,000 acres
have been patented.  This means that less than 50,000 acres have
been planted with stunted, woebegone, almost hopeless sprouts of
trees, while at the same time the government has allowed millions
of acres of the grandest forest trees to be stolen, or destroyed,
or sold for nothing.  Under the act of June 3, 1878, settlers in
Colorado and the Territories were allowed to cut timber for mining
and agricultural purposes from mineral land, which in the practical
West means both cutting and burning anywhere and everywhere, for
any purpose, on any sort of public land.  Thus, the prospector, the
miner, and mining and railroad companies are allowed by law to take
all the timber they like for their mines and roads, and the
forbidden settler, if there are no mineral lands near his farm or
stock-ranch, or none that he knows of, can hardly be expected to
forbear taking what he needs wherever he can find it.  Timber is as
necessary as bread, and no scheme of management failing to
recognize and properly provide for this want can possibly be
maintained.  In any case, it will be hard to teach the pioneers
that it is wrong to steal government timber.  Taking from the
government is with them the same as taking from nature, and their
consciences flinch no more in cutting timber from the wild forests
than in drawing water from a lake or river.  As for reservation and
protection of forests, it seems as silly and needless to them as
protection and reservation of the ocean would be; both appearing to
be boundless and inexhaustible.</p>
<p>     The special land agents employed by the General Land Office to
protect the public domain from timber depredations are supposed to
collect testimony to sustain prosecution, and to superintend such
prosecution on behalf of the government, which is represented by
the district attorneys.  But timber-thieves of the Western class
are seldom convicted, for the good reason that most of the jurors
who try such cases are themselves as guilty as those on trial.  The
effect of the present confused, discriminating, and unjust system
has been to place almost the whole population in opposition to the
government; and as conclusive of its futility, as shown by Mr.
Bowers, we need only state that during the seven years from 1881 to
1887 inclusive the value of the timber reported stolen from the
government lands was $36,719,935, and the amount recovered was
$478,073, while the cost of the services of special agents alone
was $455,000, to which must be added the expense of the trials.
Thus for nearly thirty-seven million dollars' worth of timber<pb n="150"/>
the government got less than nothing; and the value of that
consumed by running fires during the same period, without benefit
even to thieves, was probably over two hundred millions of dollars.
Land commissioners and Secretaries of the Interior have repeatedly
called attention to this ruinous state of affairs, and asked
Congress to enact the requisite legislation for reasonable reform.
But, busied with tariffs, etc., Congress has given no heed to these
or other appeals, and our forests, the most valuable and the most
destructible of all the natural resources of the country, are being
robbed and burned more rapidly than ever.  The annual appropriation
for so-called "protection service" is hardly sufficient to keep
twenty-five timber agents in the field, and as far as any efficient
protection of timber is concerned these agents themselves might as
well be timber.</p>
<p>     That a change from robbery and ruin to a permanent rational
policy is urgently needed nobody with the slightest knowledge of
American forests will deny.  In the East and along the northern
Pacific coast, where the rainfall is abundant, comparatively few
care keenly what becomes of the trees as long as fuel and lumber
are not noticeably dear.  But in the Rocky Mountains and California
and Arizona, where the forests are inflammable, and where the
fertility of the lowlands depends upon irrigation, public opinion
is growing stronger every year in favor of permanent protection by
the federal government of all the forests that cover the sources of
the streams.  Even lumbermen in these regions, long accustomed to
steal, are now willing and anxious to buy lumber for their mills
under cover of law: some possibly from a late second growth of
honesty, but most, especially the small mill-owners, simply because
it no longer pays to steal where all may not only steal, but also
destroy, and in particular because it costs about as much to steal
timber for one mill as for ten, and therefore the ordinary
lumberman can no longer compete with the large corporations.  Many
of the miners find that timber is already becoming scarce and dear
on the denuded hills around their mills, and they too are asking
for protection of forests, at least against fire.  The slow-going,
un-thrifty farmers, also, are beginning to realize that when the
timber is stripped from the mountains the irrigating streams dry up
in summer, and are destructive in winter; that soil, scenery, and
everything slips off with the trees: so of course they are coming
into the ranks of tree-friends.</p>
<p>     Of all the magnificent coniferous forests around the Great
Lakes, once the property of the United States, scarcely any belong
to it now.  They have disappeared in lumber and smoke, mostly
smoke, and the government got not one cent for them; only the land
they were growing on was considered valuable, and two and a half
dollars an acre was charged for it.  Here and there in the Southern
States there are still considerable areas of timbered government
land, but these are comparatively unimportant.  Only the forests of
the West are significant in size and value, and these, although
still great, are rapidly vanishing.  Last summer, of the unrivaled
redwood forests of the Pacific Coast Range the United States
Forestry Commission could not find a single quarter-section that
remained in the hands of the government.</p>
<p>     Under the timber and stone act of 1878, which might well have
been called the "dust and ashes act," any citizen of the United
States could take up one hundred and sixty acres of timber land,
and by paying two dollars and a half an acre for it obtain title.
There was some virtuous effort made with a view to limit the
operations of the act by requiring that the purchaser should make
affidavit that he was entering the land exclusively for his own
use, and by not allowing any <pb n="151"/>  association to enter more than
one hundred and sixty acres.  Nevertheless, under this act wealthy
corporations have fraudulently obtained title to from ten thousand
to twenty thousand acres or more.  The plan was usually as follows:
A mill company desirous of getting title to a large body of redwood
or sugar-pine land first blurred the eyes and ears of the land
agents, and then hired men to enter the land they wanted, and
immediately deed it to the company after a nominal compliance with
the law; false swearing in the wilderness against the government
being held of no account.  In one case which came under the
observation of Mr. Bowers, it was the practice of a lumber company
to hire the entire crew of every vessel which might happen to touch
at any port in the redwood belt, to enter one hundred and sixty
acres each and immediately deed the land to the company, in
consideration of the company's paying all expenses and giving the
jolly sailors fifty dollars apiece for their trouble.</p>
<p>     By such methods have our magnificent redwoods and much of the
sugar-pine forests of the Sierra Nevada been absorbed by foreign
and resident capitalists.  Uncle Sam is not often called a fool is
business matters, yet he had sold millions of acres of timber land
at two dollars and a half an acre on which a single tree was worth
more than a hundred dollars.  But this priceless land has been
patented, and nothing can be done now about the crazy bargain.
According to the everlasting laws of righteousness, even the
fraudful buyers at less than one per cent of its value are making
little or nothing, on account of fierce competition.  The trees are
felled, and about half of each giant is left on the ground to be
converted into smoke and ashes; the better half is sawed into
choice lumber and sold to citizens of the United States or to
foreigners: thus robbing the country of its glory and impoverishing
it without right benefit to anybody,&mdash;a bad, black business from
beginning to end.</p>
<p>     The redwood is one of the few conifers that sprout from the
stump and roots, and it declares itself willing to begin
immediately to repair the damage of the lumberman and also that of
the forest-burner.  As soon as a redwood is cut down or burned it
sends up a crowd of eager, hopeful shoots, which, if allowed to
grow, would in a few decades attain a height of a hundred feet, and
the strongest of them would finally become giants as great as the
original tree.  Gigantic second and third growth trees are found in
the redwoods, forming magnificent temple-like circles around
charred ruins more than a thousand years old.  But not one denuded
acre in a hundred is allowed to raise a new forest growth.  On the
contrary, all the brains, religion, and superstition of the
neighborhood are brought into play to prevent a new growth.  The
sprouts from the roots and stumps are cut off again and again, with
zealous concern as to the best time and method of making death
sure.  In the clearings of one of the largest mills on the coast we
found thirty men at work, last summer, cutting off redwood shoots
"in the dark of the moon," claiming that all the stumps and roots
cleared at this auspicious time would send up no more shoots.
Anyhow, these vigorous, almost immortal trees are killed at last,
and black stumps are now their only monuments over most of the
chopped and burned areas.</p>
<p>     The redwood is the glory of the Coast Range.  It extends along
the western slope, in a nearly continuous belt about ten miles
wide, from beyond the Oregon boundary to the south of Santa Cruz,
a distance of nearly four hundred miles, and in massive, sustained
grandeur and closeness of growth surpasses all the other timber
woods of the world.  Trees from ten to fifteen feet in diameter and
three hundred feet high are not uncommon, and a few attain a height
of three <pb n="152"/>  hundred and fifty feet, or even four hundred, with
a diameter at the base of fifteen to twenty feet or more, while the
ground beneath them is a garden of fresh, exuberant ferns, lilies,
gaultheria, and rhododendron.  This grand tree, <hi rend="italic">Sequoia
sempervirens</hi>, is surpassed in size only by its near relative, <hi rend="italic">
Sequoia gigantea</hi>, or big tree, of the Sierra Nevada, if indeed it
is surpassed.  The sempervirens is certainly the taller of the two.
The gigantea attains a greater girth, and is heavier, more noble in
port, and more sublimely beautiful.  These two sequoias are all
that are known to exist in the world, though in former geological
times the genus was common and had many species.  The redwood is
restricted to the Coast Range, and the big tree to the Sierra.</p>
<p>     As timber the redwood is too good to live.  The largest
sawmills ever built are busy along its seaward border, "with all
the modern improvements," but so immense is the yield per acre it
will be long ere the supply is exhausted.  The big tree is also to
come extent being made into lumber.  Though far less abundant than
the redwood, it is, fortunately, less accessible, extending along
the western flank of the Sierra in a partially interrupted belt
about two hundred and fifty miles long, at a height of from four to
eight thousand feet above the sea.  The enormous logs, too heavy to
handle, are blasted into manageable dimensions with gunpowder.  A
large portion of the best timber is thus shattered and destroyed,
and, with the huge knotty tops, is left in ruins for tremendous
fires that kill every tree within their range, great and small.
Still, the species is not in danger of extinction.  It has been
planted and is flourishing over a great part of Europe, and
magnificent sections of the aboriginal forests have been reserved
as national and state parks,&mdash;the Mariposa Sequoia Grove, near
Yosemite, managed by the State of California, and the General Grant
and Sequoia national parks on the King's, the Kaweah, and Tule
rivers, efficiently guarded by a small troop of United States
cavalry under the direction of the Secretary of the Interior.  But
there is not a single specimen of the redwood in any national park.
Only by gift or purchase, so far as I know, can the government get
back into its possession a single acre of this wonderful forest.</p>
<p>     The legitimate demands on the forests that have passed into
private ownership, as well as those in the hands of the government,
are increasing every year with the rapid settlement and upbuilding
of the country, but the methods of lumbering are as yet grossly
wasteful.  In most mills only the best portions of the best trees
are used, while the ruins are left on the ground to feed great
fires which kill much of what is left of the less desirable timber,
together with the seedlings on which the permanence of the forest
depends.  Thus every mill is a centre of destruction far more
severe from waste and fire than from use.  The same thing is true
of the mines, which consume and destroy indirectly immense
quantities of timber with their innumerable fires, accidental or
set to make open ways, and often without regard to how far they
run.  The prospector deliberately sets fires to clear off the woods
just where they are densest, to lay the rocks bare and make the
discovery of mines easier.  Sheep-owners and their shepherds also
set fires everywhere through the woods in the fall to facilitate
the march of their countless flocks the next summer, and perhaps in
some places to improve the pasturage.  The axe is not yet at the
root of every tree, but the sheep is, or was before the national
parks were established and guarded by the military, the only
effective and reliable arm of the government free from the blight
of politics.  Not only do the shepherds, at the driest time of the
year, set fire to everything that will burn, but the sheep consume
every green leaf, not sparing even the young conifers when they are
in a starving condition from <pb n="153"/>  crowding, and they rake and
dibble the loose soil of the mountain sides for the spring floods
to wash away, and thus at last leave the ground barren.</p>
<p>     Of all the destroyers that infest the woods the shake-maker
seems the happiest.  Twenty or thirty years ago, shakes, a kind of
long boardlike shingles split with a mallet and a frow, were in
great demand for covering barns and sheds, and many are used still
in preference to common shingles, especially those made from the
sugar-pine, which do not warp or crack in the hottest sunshine.
Drifting adventurers in California, after harvest and threshing are
over, oftentimes meet to discuss their plans for the winter, and
their talk is interesting.  Once, in a company of this kind, I
heard a man say, as he peacefully smoked his pipe: "Boys, as soon
as this job's done I'm goin' into the duck business.  There's big
money in it, and your grub costs nothing.  Tule Joe made five
hundred dollars last winter on mallard and teal.  Shot 'em on the
Joaquin, tied 'em in dozens by the neck, and shipped 'em to San
Francisco.  And when he was tired wading in the sloughs and touched
with rheumatiz, he just knocked off on ducks, and went to the
Contra Costa hills for dove and quail.  It's a mighty good
business, and you're your own boss, and the whole thing's fun."</p>
<p>     Another of the company, a bushy-bearded fellow, with a trace
of brag in his voice, drawled out: "Bird business is well enough
for some, but bear is my game, with a deer and a California lion
thrown in now and then for change.  There's always a market for
bear grease, and sometimes you can sell the hams.  They're good as
hog hams any day.  And you are your own boss in my business, too,
if the bears ain't too big and too many for you.  Old grizzlies I
despise,&mdash;they want cannon to kill 'em; but the blacks and browns
are beauties for grease, and when I get 'em just right, and draw a
bead on 'em, I fetch 'em every time."  Another said he was going to
catch up a lot of mustangs as soon as the rains set in, hitch them
to a gang-plough, and go to farming on the San Joaquin plains for
wheat.  But most preferred the shake business, until something more
profitable and as sure could be found, with equal comfort and
independence.</p>
<p>     With a cheap mustang or mule to carry a pair of blankets, a
sack of flour, a few pounds of coffee, and an axe, a frow, and a
cross-cut saw, the shake-maker ascends the mountains to the pine
belt where it is most accessible, usually by some mine or mill
road.  Then he strikes off into the virgin woods, where the sugar-pine, king of all the hundred species of pines in the world in size
and beauty, towers on the open sunny slopes of the Sierra in the
fullness of its glory.  Selecting a favorable spot for a cabin near
a meadow with a stream, he unpacks his animal and stakes it out on
the meadow.  Then he chops into one after another of the pines,
until he finds one that he feels sure will split freely, cuts this
down, saws off a section four feet long, splits it, and from this
first cut, perhaps seven feet in diameter, he gets shakes enough
for a cabin and its furniture,&mdash;walls, roof, door, bedstead, table,
and stool.  Besides his labor, only a few pounds of nails are
required.  Sapling poles form the frame of the airy building,
usually about six feet by eight in size, on which the shakes are
nailed, with the edges overlapping.  A few bolts from the same
section that the shakes were made from are split into square sticks
and built up to form a chimney, the inside and interspaces being
plastered and filled in with mud.  Thus, with abundance of fuel,
shelter and comfort by his own fireside are secured.  Then he goes
to work sawing and splitting for the market, tying the shakes in
bundles of fifty or a hundred.  They are four feet long, four
inches wide, and about one fourth of an inch thick.  The first few
<pb n="154"/>  thousands he sells or trades at the nearest mill or store,
getting provisions in exchange.  Then he advertises, in whatever
way he can, that he has excellent sugar-pine shakes for sale, easy
of access and cheap.</p>
<p>     Only the lower, perfectly clear, free-splitting portions of
the giant pines are used,&mdash;perhaps ten to twenty feet from a tree
two hundred and fifty in height; all the rest is left a mass of
ruins, to rot or to feed the forest fires, while thousands are
hacked deeply and rejected in proving the grain.  Over nearly all
of the more accessible slopes of the Sierra and Cascade mountains
in southern Oregon, at a height of from three to six thousand feet
above the sea, and for a distance of about six hundred miles, this
waste and confusion extends.  Happy robbers! dwelling in the most
beautiful woods, in the most salubrious climate, breathing
delightful doors* both day and night, drinking cool living water,&mdash;
roses and lilies at their feet in the spring, shedding fragrance
and ringing bells as if cheering them on in their desolating work.
There is none to say them nay.  They buy no land, pay no taxes,
dwell in a paradise with no forbidding angel either from Washington
or from heaven.  Every one of the frail shake shanties is a centre
of destruction, and the extent of the ravages wrought in this quiet
way is in the aggregate enormous.</p>
<p>     It is not generally known that, notwithstanding the immense
quantities of timber cut every year for foreign and home markets
and mines, from five to ten times as much is destroyed as is used,
chiefly by running forest fires that only the federal government
can stop.  Travelers through the West in summer are not likely to
forget the fire-work displayed along the various railway tracks.
Thoreau, when contemplating the destruction of the forests on the
east side of the continent, said that soon the country would be so
bald that every man would have to grow whiskers to hide its
nakedness, but he thanked God that at least the sky was safe.  Had
he gone West he would have found out that the sky was not safe; for
all through the summer months, over most of the mountain regions,
the smoke of mill and forest fires is so thick and black that no
sunbeam can pierce it.  The whole sky, with clouds, sun, moon, and
stars, is simply blotted out.  There is no real sky and no scenery.
Not a mountain is left in the landscape.  At least none is in sight
from the lowlands, and they all might as well be on the moon, as
far as scenery is concerned.</p>
<p>     The half dozen transcontinental railroad companies advertise
the beauties of their lines in gorgeous many-colored folders, each
claiming its as the "scenic route."  "The route of superior
desolation"&mdash;the smoke, dust, and ashes route&mdash;would be a more
truthful description.  Every train rolls on through dismal smoke
and barbarous melancholy ruins; and the companies might well cry in
their advertisements: "Come! travel our way.  Ours is the blackest.
It is the only genuine Erebus route.  The sky is black and the
ground is black, and on either side there is a continuous border of
black stumps and logs and blasted trees appealing to heaven for
help as if still half alive, and their mute eloquence is most
interestingly touching.  The blackness is perfect.  On account of
the superior skill of our workmen, advantages of climate, and the
kind of trees, the charring is generally deeper along our line, and
the ashes are deeper, and the confusion and desolation displayed
can never be rivaled.  No other route on this continent so fully
illustrates the abomination of desolation."  Such a claim would be
reasonable, as each seems the worst, whatever route you chance to
take.</p>
<p>     Of course a way had to be cleared through the woods.  But the
felled timber is not worked up into firewood for the engines and
into lumber for the <pb n="155"/>  company's use; it is left lying in
vulgar confusion, and is fired from time to time by sparks from
locomotives or by the workmen camping along the line.  The fires,
whether accidental or set, are allowed to run into the woods as far
as they may, thus assuring comprehensive destruction.  The
directors of a line that guarded against fires, and cleared a clean
gap edged with living trees, and fringed and mantled with the grass
and flowers and beautiful seedlings that are ever ready and willing
to spring up, might justly boast of the beauty of their road; for
nature is always ready to heal every scar.  But there is no such
road on the western side of the continent.  Last summer, in the
Rocky Mountains, I saw six fires started by sparks from a
locomotive within a distance of three miles, and nobody was in
sight to prevent them from spreading.  They might run into the
adjacent forests and burn the timber from hundreds of square miles;
not a man in the State would care to spend an hour in fighting
them, as long as his own fences and buildings were not threatened.</p>
<p>     Notwithstanding all the waste and use which have been going on
unchecked like a storm for more than two centuries, it is not yet
too late, though it is high time, for the government to begin a
rational administration of its forests.  About seventy million
acres it still owns,&mdash;enough for all the country, if wisely used.
These residual forests are generally on mountain slopes, just where
they are doing the most good, and where their removal would be
followed by the greatest number of evils; the lands they cover are
too rocky and high for agriculture, and can never be made as
valuable for any other crop as for the present crop of trees.  It
has been shown over and over again that if these mountains were to
be stripped of their trees and underbrush, and kept bare and
sodless by hordes of sheep and the innumerable fires the shepherds
set, besides those of the millmen, prospectors, shake-makers, and
all sorts of adventurers, both lowlands and mountains would
speedily become little better than deserts, compared with their
present beneficent [sic] fertility.  During heavy rainfalls and
while the winter accumulations of snow were melting, the larger
streams would swell into destructive torrents; cutting deep,
rugged-edged gullies, carrying away the fertile humus and soil as
well as sand and rocks, filling up and overflowing their lower
channels, and covering the lowland fields with raw detritus.
Drought and barrenness would follow.</p>
<p>     In their natural condition, or under wise management, keeping
out destructive sheep, preventing fires, selecting the trees that
should be cut for lumber, and preserving the young ones and the
shrubs and sod of herbaceous vegetation, these forests would be a
never failing fountain of wealth and beauty.  The cool shades of
the forest give rise to moist beds and currents of air, and the sod
of grasses and the various flowering plants and shrubs thus
fostered, together with the network and sponge of tree roots,
absorb and hold back the rain and the waters from melting snow,
compelling them to ooze and percolate and flow gently through the
soil in streams that never dry.  All the pine needles and rootlets
and blades of grass, and the fallen decaying trunks of trees, are
dams, storing the bounty of the clouds and dispensing it in
perennial life-giving streams, instead of allowing it to gather
suddenly and rush headlong in short-lived devastating floods.
Everybody on the dry side of the continent is beginning to find
this out, and, in view of the waste going on, is growing more and
more anxious for government protection.  The outcries we hear
against forest reservations come mostly from thieves who are
wealthy and steal timber by wholesale.  They have so long been
allowed to steal and destroy in peace that any impediment to forest
robbery is denounced as <pb n="156"/>  a cruel and irreligious
interference with "vested rights," likely to endanger the repose of
all ungodly welfare.</p>
<p>Gold, gold, gold!  How strong a voice that metal has!

<q><lg type="fragment"><l>"O wae for the siller, it is sae
preva'lin'."</l></lg></q>

Even in Congress, a sizable chunk of gold, carefully concealed,
will outtalk and outfight all the nation on a subject like
forestry, well smothered in ignorance, and in which the money
interests of only a few are conspicuously involved.  Under these
circumstances, the bawling, blethering oratorical stuff drowns the
voice of God himself.  Yet the dawn of a new day in forestry is
breaking.  Honest citizens see that only the rights of the
government are being trampled, not those of the settlers.  Merely
what belongs to all alike is reserved, and every acre that is left
should be held together under the federal government as a basis for
a general policy of administration for the public good.  The people
will not always be deceived by selfish opposition, whether from
lumber and mining corporations or from sheepmen and prospectors,
however cunningly brought forward underneath fables and gold.</p>
<p>     Emerson says that things refuse to be mismanaged long.  An
exception would seem to be found in the case of our forests, which
have been mismanaged rather long, and now come desperately near
being like smashed eggs and spilt milk.  Still, in the long run the
world does not move backward.  The wonderful advance made in the
last few years, in creating four national parks in the West, and
thirty forest reservations, embracing nearly forty million acres;
and in the planting of the borders of streets and highways and
spacious parks in all the great cities, to satisfy the natural
taste and hunger for landscape beauty and righteousness that God
has put, in some measure, into every human being and animal, shows
the trend of awakening public opinion.  The making of the far-famed
New York Central Park was opposed by even good men, with misguided
pluck, perseverance, and ingenuity; but straight right won its way,
and now that park is appreciated.  So we confidently believe it
will be with our great national parks and forest reservations.
There will be a period of indifference on the part of the rich,
sleepy with wealth, and of the toiling millions, sleepy with
poverty, most of whom never saw a forest; a period of screaming
protest and objection from the plunderers, who are as
unconscionable and enterprising as Satan.  But light is surely
coming, and the friends of destruction will preach and bewail in
vain.</p>
<p>     The United States government has always been proud of the
welcome it has extended to good men of every nation, seeking
freedom and homes and bread.  Let them be welcomed still as nature
welcomes them, to the woods as well as to the prairies and plains.
No place is too good for good men, and still there is room.  They
are invited to heaven, and may well be allowed in America.  Every
place is made better by them.  Let them be as free to pick gold and
gems from the hills, to cut and hew, dig and plant, for homes and
bread, as the birds are to pick berries from the wild bushes, and
moss and leaves for nests.  The ground will be glad to feed them,
and the pines will come down from the mountains for their homes as
willingly as the cedars came from Lebanon for Solomon's temple.
Nor will the woods be the worse for this use, or their benign
influences be diminished any more than the sun is diminished by
shining.  Mere destroyers, however, tree-killers, spreading death
and confusion in the fairest groves and gardens ever planted, let
the government hasten to cast them out and make an end of them.
For it must be told again and again, and be burningly borne in
mind, that just now, while protective measures are being
deliberated languidly, destruction and use are speeding on faster
<pb n="157"/>  and farther every day.  The axe and saw are insanely busy,
chips are flying thick as snowflakes, and every summer thousands of
acres of priceless forests, with their underbrush, soil, springs,
climate, scenery, and religion, are vanishing away in clouds of
smoke, while, except in the national parks, not one forest guard is
employed.</p>
<p>     All sorts of local laws and regulations have been tried and
found wanting, and the costly lessons of our own experience, as
well as that of every civilized nation, show conclusively that the
fate of the remnant of our forests is in the hands of the federal
government, and that if the remnant is to be saved at all, it must
be saved quickly.</p>
<p>     Any fool can destroy trees.  They cannot run away; and if they
could, they would still be destroyed,&mdash;chased and hunted down as
long as fun or a dollar could be got out of their bark hides,
branching horns, or magnificent bole backbones.  Few that fell
trees plant them; nor would planting avail much towards getting
back anything like the noble primeval forests.  During a man's life
only saplings can be grown, in the place of the old trees&mdash;tens of
centuries old&mdash;that have been destroyed.  It took more than three
thousand years to make some of the trees in these Western woods,&mdash;
trees that are still standing in perfect strength and beauty,
waving and singing in the mighty forests of the Sierra.  Through
all the wonderful, eventful centuries since Christ's time&mdash;and long
before that&mdash;God has cared for these trees, saved them from
drought, disease, avalanches, and a thousand straining, leveling
tempests and floods; but he cannot save them from fools,&mdash;only
Uncle Sam can do that.</p>
                                  <signed><hi rend="italic">John Muir.</hi></signed>





</div1>
</body>
</text>
</TEI.2>
