<?xml version="1.0"?>

<?dlps id="NeiAlie"?>
<?dlps page-images="none" figure-images="no"?>
<?dlps transcription="other"?>

<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/tei-p4/tei2.dtd" [
<!ENTITY % POSTKB "INCLUDE">
<!ENTITY % TEI.extensions.ent SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.ent">
<!ENTITY % TEI.extensions.dtd SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.dtd">
<!ENTITY % ISOnum SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/charent/iso-num.ent"> %ISOnum;
<!ENTITY % ISOpub SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/charent/iso-pub.ent"> %ISOpub;

]>
<TEI.2 id="NeiAlie">
<teiHeader type="migrated" creator="Etext">
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title type="main">"The Alien" / By John G. Neihardt</title>
<title type="sort">the alien by john g neihardt</title>
<author>Neihardt, John G.</author>
<respStmt>
<resp>Creation of machine-readable version:</resp>
<name>Judy Boss</name>
<resp>Conversion to TEI.2-conformant markup:</resp>
<name>University of Virginia Library Electronic Text Center.</name>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt>
<extent>ca. <num type="kilobytes">31</num> kilobytes</extent>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>University of Virginia Library</publisher>
<pubPlace>Charlottesville, Virginia</pubPlace>
<idno type="ETC">NeiAlie</idno>
<date value="2000">2000</date>
<availability status="public">
<p n="copyright">Copyright &copy; 2000 by the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia</p>
<p n="access">Publicly accessible</p>
</availability>
<idno type="uva-pid">uva-lib:476247</idno>
</publicationStmt>
<seriesStmt>
<title>University of Virginia Library, Text collection</title>
<idno type="uva-set">UVA-LIB-Text</idno>
</seriesStmt>
<sourceDesc>
<biblFull>
<titleStmt>
<title type="main">"The Alien"</title>
<title level="j">Munsey`s Magazine</title>
<title type="sort">the alien</title>
<author>John G. Neihardt</author>
</titleStmt>
<extent>6 pages</extent>
<publicationStmt>
<pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
<date value="1907-03">March 1907</date>
<idno type="callNo">Source copy consulted: Alderman Library, University of Virginia AP2 .M8 v.36 1906-07</idno>
</publicationStmt>
</biblFull>
</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc>
<encodingDesc>
<projectDesc>
<p>Prepared for the University of Virginia Library Electronic Text Center.</p>
</projectDesc>
<editorialDecl>
<p>All unambiguous end-of-line hyphens have been removed, and the  trailing part of a word has been joined to the preceding line.</p>
<p id="ETC">Some keywords in the header are a local Electronic Text Center scheme  to aid in establishing analytical groupings.</p>
</editorialDecl>
</encodingDesc>
<profileDesc>
<creation>
<date value="1907-03">March 1907</date>
</creation>
<langUsage>
<language id="eng" usage="main">English</language>
</langUsage>
<textClass>
<keywords>
<term>fiction</term>
<term>prose</term>
<term>masculine</term>
</keywords>
</textClass>
</profileDesc>
<revisionDesc>
<change>
<date value="2000-01">January 2000</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>corrector</resp>
<name>Jeffrey Feldman, Electronic Text Center</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Added TEI header and tags</item>
</change>
<change>
<date value="2005-07">July 2005</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>Corrector</resp>
<name>John Ivor Carlson</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Converted to XML and/or checked tags.</item>
</change>
<change>
<date value="2007-09">September 2007</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>Migration</resp>
<name>Ethan Gruber, University of Virginia Library</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Converted XML markup from TEI Lite to uva-dl-tei (TEI P4 with local customizations).</item>
</change>
<change>
<date value="2008-01">January 2008</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>Migration</resp>
<name>Greg Murray, University of Virginia Library</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Programmatically updated TEI header markup (but not header content) for minimal compliance with current QA requirements.</item>
</change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>
<text id="d1">
<body id="d2">
<div1 type="story" id="d3">
<head><hi rend="bold">THE ALIEN</hi><lb/>
<hi rend="italic">BY JOHN G. NEIHARDT</hi><lb/>
<hi rend="italic">AUTHOR OF "THE LOOK IN THE FACE"</hi></head>
<div2 type="part" n="1" id="d4">
<pb n="706"/>
<p>THROUGH the quiet night, crystalline
with the pervading spirit of
the frost, under prairie skies of mystic
purple pierced with the glasslike glitter
of the stars, fled Antoine.
</p><p>Huge, and hollow-sounding with the
clatter of the pinto's hoofs, hung the
night above and about, lonesome, empty,
bitter as the soul of him who fled.
</p><p>A weary age of flight since sunset!
And now the coming of midnight saw
the thin-limbed, long-haired pony slowly
losing its nerve, rasping in the throat,
tottering.
</p><p>With pitiless, spike-spurred heels the
rider hurled the beast on into the empty
night.
</p><p>"G'wan, you blasted cayuse, you over-grown wolf-dog, you pot-bellied shonga!
Keep up that tune; I'm goin' somewheres!
What'd I steal you fer?
Pleasure?  Ho, ho, ho!  I reckon!
Pleasure for the half-breed!  G'wan!"
</p><p>Suddenly rounding a bank of sand,
the pinto sighted the broad, ice-bound
river, a stream of glinting silver under
the stars.  Sniffing and crouching upon
its haunches at the sudden glow that
dwindled a gleaming thread into the
further dusk, the jaded beast received a
series of vicious jabs from the spike-spurred heels.  It groaned and lunged
forward again, taking with uncertain
feet the glaring path ahead, and awakening
a dull, snarling thunder in the under
regions of the ice.
</p><p>Slipping, struggling, doing its brute
best to overcome fatigue, the pinto covered the ice.
</p><p>"Doin' a war-dance, eh?" growled
the man with bitter mirth; and gouging
the foaming, bloody flanks of the animal:
"G'wan!  Set up that tune; I want fast
music, 'cause I'm goin' somewheres &mdash;
don't know where &mdash; out there in the
shadders.  Come here, will you?  Take
<hi rend="italic">that</hi> and <hi rend="italic">that</hi> and <hi rend="italic">that!</hi>  Now, will
you kick the scen'ry back'ards?  By
the &mdash;"
</p><p>The cries of the man were cut short
as he shot far over the pommel, lunging
headlong past the pinto's head, and
striking with head and shoulders upon
the ice.
</p><p>When he stopped sliding, he lay very
still for a few moments.  Then he
groaned, sat up, and found that the
bluffs and the river and the stars and the
universe in general were whirling giddily &mdash;
himself the dizzy center.
</p><p>With uncertain arms he reached out,
endeavoring to check the sickening motion
of things by sheer force of his powerful
hands.  He was thrown down like
a weakling wrestling with a giant.  Then
he lay still, cursing in a whisper, trying
to balance the disturbed universe, until
the motion passed.
</p><p>With great care, Antoine raised himself
upon his elbows and gazed about
with a foolish grin.
</p><p>Then he remembered &mdash; remembered
that he was hunted; that he was an outcast,
a man of no race; remembered dimly, and with
a leer, a portion of a long
series of crimes; remembered that the
last was horse-stealing, and that some of
the others concerned blood.
</p><p>And as he remembered, he felt with
horrible distinctness the lariat tightening
about his neck &mdash; the lariat that the
men of Cabanne's trading-post were
bringing on fleet horses, nearer, nearer,
nearer through the silent night.
</p><p>Antoine shuddered and got to his feet,
looming huge against the star-sprinkled
surface of the ice as he turned a malevolent
face down trail and listened for the
beat of hoofs.
</p><p>There was only the dim, hollow murmur

<pb n="707"/>

that has its habitation at the heart
of silence.
</p><p>"Got a long start," he observed with
the chuckle of a man whom desperation
has made careless.  <hi rend="italic">"Hello!"</hi>
</p><p>A pale, semicircular glow, like the
flare of a burning straw-stack a half a
night's journey over the hills, had grown
up at the horizon of the east.  And as the
man stared, still in a maze from his recent
fall, the moon heaved an arc of
tarnished silver above the mystic rim of
sky, flooding with new light the river
and the bluffs.  The man stood illumined
&mdash; a big brute of a man; heavy-limbed,
massive-shouldered, with the slouching
stoop and alert air of the habitual
skulker.
</p><p>The refugee moved uneasily, as though
he had suddenly become visible to a lurking
foe.  He glanced nervously about
him, fumbled at the butt of a six-shooter at his belt, then catching sight of
the blotch of huddled dusk that was the
fallen pinto, the meaning of his situation
flashed upon him.
</p><p>"That cussed cayuse!  Gone and
done hisself, like as not!  The whole
creation's agin me!"
</p><p>He made for the pinto, snarling
viciously, as though its exhausted, lacerated
body were the visible self of the
inimical universe.  He grasped the reins
and jerked them.  The brute groaned
and let its weary head fall heavily upon
the ice.
</p><p><hi rend="italic">"Get up!"</hi>
</p><p>Antoine began kicking the pinto in the
ribs, bringing forth groans of pain.
</p><p>"Oh, you won't get up, eh?  Agin me,
too, eh?  Take that and that and <hi rend="italic">that!</hi>
I wished you was everybody in the world
and hell to wunst; I'd make you beller,
now I got you down!  Take <hi rend="italic">that,</hi> and
pass in!"
</p><p>With a roar of anger, he fell upon
the pinto, swearing, striking, kicking.
But the pony only groaned faintly.  Its
outworn limbs could no longer support
its body.
</p></div2>

<div2 type="part" n="2" id="d5"><head>II</head>

<p>WHEN Antoine had exhausted his
rage, he got up, gave the pony a farewell
kick upon the nose, and started off at a
dog-trot across the ice toward the bluffs
beyond.
</p><p>Ever and anon he stopped and whirled
about with hand at ear.  He heard only
the sullen murmur of the silence, broken
occasionally by the whine and pop of
the ice and the plaintive, bitter wail of
coyotes somewhere in the hills, like the
heart-broken cry of the lonesome prairie
yearning for the summer.
</p><p>"Oh, I wouldn't howl if I was you!"
muttered Antoine, apostrophizing the
coyotes.  "I wished I was a coyote or
a gray wolf, knowin' what I do.  I'd be
a man-killer and a cattle-eater, I would.
And then I'd have people of my own.
Wouldn't be no cussed half-breed, a
runnin' from his kind.  Oh, I wouldn't
howl if I was you!"
</p><p>He proceeded at a swinging trot across
the half-mile of ice and halted under
the bluffs.  He listened intently.  A
far sound had grown up in the hollow
night, as if from the bottom of a
deep well.
</p><p>It was the clatter of hoofs far away,
but clear in faintness, for the cold snap
had made the frozen prairie a vast
sounding-board.
</p><p>A light snow had fallen the night before,
and the moonlit trail of the refugee
stood out upon it as clear as a wagon-track.
</p><p>Antoine felt the pitiless pinch of the
approaching lariat as he listened.  Then
his accustomed bitter weariness of life
came upon him.
</p><p>"What's the use in me runnin'?  What
am I runnin' to?  Nothin' &mdash; only more of
the same I'm runnin' from; lonesomeness
and hunger and the like of that.  Gettin'
awake, stiff and cold and half-starved,
and cussin' the daylight 'cause it's agin
me like everything else, and gives me
away.  Sneakin' around till dark, eatin'
when I can, like a dern gray wolf; then
goin' to bed agin a snow-drift, like as
not, hopin' it'll never get day.  But it
always does!
</p><p>"It's all night somewheres, I reckon,
spite of what the missionaries says.
That's fer me &mdash; night always!  No
comin' day, no gettin' up; some place to
hide in always."
</p><p>He walked on with head dropped
forward upon his breast, skirting the
base of the bluffs, now seemingly
oblivious of the sound of hoofs that grew
momently more distinct.


<pb n="708"/>

</p><p>As he walked he was dimly conscious
of passing within a foot of the dark
mouth of a hole running back into the
clay of a bluff.  He proceeded until he
found himself again at the edge of the
river, staring down into a broad black
fissure in the ice, caused, doubtless, by
the dash of the current crossing from
the other side.
</p><p>A terrible, dark, alluring thought
seized him.  Here was the place &mdash; the
doorway to that place where it was
always night!
</p><p><hi rend="italic">Why not go in?</hi>
</p><p>There would be no more running
away, no more hiding, no more hatred of
men, no more lonesomeness and hunger.
Here was the place!  He stepped
forward, and stooped to gaze down into
the door of night.
</p><p>The rushing waters made a dismal,
moaning sound.  He stared, transfixed.
Yes, he would go!
</p><p>Suddenly a shudder ran through his
whole body.  He gave a quick exclamation
of terror.
</p><p>"No! <hi rend="italic">No!  Not there!"</hi>
</p><p>He leaped back and raised his face to
the skies.  How kind and good to look
upon was the sky!  He gazed about &mdash; it
was so fair a world!  How good it was
to breathe!  He longed to throw his
great brute arms about creation and
clutch it to him, and hold it, hold it,
hold it!
</p><p><hi rend="italic">The hoofs!</hi>
</p><p>The distant and muffled confusion of
sound had grown into a series of sharp,
distinct, staccato notes.  The outlaw's
pursuers were now no farther than a
mile away.  They would soon reach the
river.
</p><p>With the quick instinct of the hunted
beast, Antoine grasped the means of
safety.  He remembered the hole in the
bluff.  His footprints led to the ice-fissure.  He decided that none should
lead away.  He could not be pursued
under ice.
</p><p>Stooping, so that he could look
between his legs, he began retracing his
steps backward, placing his feet with
infinite care where they had fallen before.
Thus he came again to the hole in the
clay bluff, and disappeared.  A jutting
point of sandstone had kept the quiet
snow from falling at the mouth of the
hole.  The man left no trail as he entered
on hands and knees.
</p><p>When he had entered, he stopped and
listened.  He could now hear distinctly
the sharp crack of hoofs upon the ice and
the pop and thunder of the shaken surface.
</p><p>"Here's <hi rend="italic">some</hi> luck for me, anyhow,"
mused Antoine.
</p></div2>

<div2 type="part" n="3" id="d6"><head>III</head>

<p>HE crawled on into the nether
darkness of the hole, which grew more
spacious as he proceeded.
</p><p>As he crawled, the sound of pursuing
hoofs grew dimmer.  Antoine half forgot
them.  His keen sense had caught the
peculiar musty odor of animal life.  He
felt a stuffy warmth in his nostrils as he
breathed.
</p><p>Suddenly out of the dark ahead there
grew up two points of phosphorescent
light.  Antoine fell back upon his
haunches with a low growl of surprise.
Years of wild, lonesome life had made
him more beast than man.
</p><p>The lights slowly came closer,
growing more brilliant.  There was a harsh,
rasping growl and a sound of sniffing.
</p><p>Antoine waited until the contracting
pupils of his eyes could grasp the
situation with more distinctness.
</p><p>"Can't run," he muttered.  "Lariat
behind; somethin' growlin' in front.  It's
one more fight, and here goes fer my
damnedest.  Rather die mad and fightin'
than jump into cold water or stick my
head through a leather necktie."
</p><p>Then, of a sudden, came a sharp,
savage yelp, and Antoine's cheek was
ripped open with a stroke of gnashing
teeth!
</p><p>He felt for an instant the hot breath
of the beast, the trickle of hot blood on
his cheek; and then the last of the human
in him passed.  He growled and hurled
the body of his enemy from him with
a swing of his bearlike paw.
</p><p>The dark hole echoed a muffled howl
of anger, and in an instant the two rolled
together in the darkness.  The man had
forgotten his six-shooter.  It was a
primitive struggle &mdash; the snapping of
jaws, the grating of hoarse throats that
labored with angry breath, snarls,
growls, whines!
</p><p>At last the man knew it was a wolf


<pb n="709"/>

he fought.  He reached for its throat,
but felt his hand caught in a hot, wet,
powerful trap of teeth.  He grasped the
under jaw with a grip that made his
antagonist howl with pain.  With his
other hand he felt about in the darkness,
groping for the throat.
</p><p>He found it; seized it with a viselike
clutch; shut his teeth and threw all the
power of his massive frame into the
struggle.
</p><p>Slowly, slowly, the struggles of the
wolf became weaker.  The lean, hairy
form fell limply, and the man laughed
with guttural mirth, for he was master.
</p><p>Then again he felt the trickle of blood
upon his cheek, the ache of his bitten
hand.  His anger returned with double
fury.  He kicked the limp body as he
lay panting beside it, never releasing his
grip.
</p><p>Suddenly he ceased kicking; he forgot
his conquered enemy for the moment.
There were sounds.
</p><p>He heard the thump, thump of hoofs
passing his place of refuge.  Then they
ceased.  A sound of confused voices
came dimly.  Then after a while the
hoofs passed again, and there was a
distinct voice that said: "Saved hangin',
anyway."  The hoofs grew dimmer, and
Antoine knew by the hollowness of the
sound that his pursuers had begun to
recross the river.
</p><p>He again gave his attention to the
wolf.  It lay very still; it seemed dead.
A feeling of supreme comfort came over
Antoine.  He had fought and conquered,
and now he was weary but safe.  He laid
his head upon the body for a pillow.
</p></div2>

<div2 type="part" n="4" id="d7"><head>IV</head>

<p>HE awoke, feeling a soft, warm
rasping on his wounded cheek.  A faint light
came in at the entrance of the place; it
was morning.  In his sleep Antoine had
moved his head near to the mouth of the
wolf.  And now, utterly conquered,
bruised, unable to rise, the brute was
feebly licking the blood from the man's
face.
</p><p>A sense of mastery made the man
inclined to be kind to a fellow being for
once.  He was safe, and something had
caressed him, although it was only a
beaten wolf.
</p><p>"You pore devil!" said Antoine, with
a sudden softness in his voice.  "I done
you up, didn't I?  But you hain't so bad,
I guess.  But if I hadn't done you, I'd
got done myself.  Hurt much, you pore
devil, eh?"
</p><p>He stroked the side of the animal,
making it cry out with pain.
</p><p>"Pretty sore, eh?  Well, as long as
I'm bigger'n you, I'll be good to you, I
will.  I ain't so bad, am I?  You treat me
square and you won't never get no bad
deals from the half-breed.  Mind that, I
tell you.
</p><p>"Let me hunt you up a name.
<hi rend="italic">Susette!</hi>  That's it &mdash; Susette!  You're
Susette now.  I hain't got no people, so
I'm a wolf, and my name's Antoine.
Antoine and Susette &mdash; sounds good,
don't it?
</p><p>"Say, I know as much about bein' a
gray wolf as you do!  Can't show me
nothin' about sneakin' and hidin' and
fightin'!  Say, old girl, <hi rend="italic">hain't</hi> I a pretty
good fighter?  Oh, I know I am, all
right!  And when you need it ag'in
you're goin' to get it strong, Susie.  Mind
that!
</p><p>"Hain't got nothin' to eat about the
house, have you?  Then, bein' head of
the family, I'm goin' huntin'.  Don't
you let no other wolf come 'round here;
you know me!  I'll wear his hide when
I get back, if you don't mind!"
</p><p>And he went out.
</p><p>Before noon Antoine returned
bringing three jack-rabbits, having shot them
with his six-shooter.
</p><p>"Well, Susette," said he, "got any
appetite?"
</p><p>He passed his hand over the wolf's
snout caressingly.  The wolf flinched in
fear, but the man continued the caress
until she licked his hand.
</p><p>"Now we're friends, and we can live
together peaceable, can't we?  Took a
big family row, though.  Families needs
stirrin' up now and then, I guess."
</p><p>He skinned a rabbit and with his knife
cut off morsels of meat.
</p><p>"Here, Susette, I'm goin' to fill your
hide first, 'cause you've been so good
since the row.  There, that's it!  Eat!
Does me good to see you eat, pore, sick
Susette!"
</p><p>The wolf took the morsels from his
hand, and a look that was almost tame
came into her eyes.  When she had eaten


<pb n="710"/>

the better part of a rabbit, Antoine
skinned another and had a meal of raw
flesh.
</p><p>Then he sat down beside her and
stroked her nose and neck and flanks.
There was an air of home about the place.
He was safe and sheltered, had a full
stomach, and there was a creature near
that showed him kindness, although it
had been won by a beating.
</p><p>"Susette," he said in a soft voice, as
he stroked the wolf, "don't get mean
ag'in when you get well.  I want to
live quiet and like somethin' fer wunst.
If you'll be good, I'll see that you get
enough eatin'.  Oh, I'll get you rabbits
and antelope and birds, and you won't
need to hunt nor run about whinin' with
your belly flappin' together.
</p><p>"And I know how to make fire &mdash;
somethin' you don't know, wise as you
be &mdash; and I'll keep you warm, and pet
you lots.  Is it a bargain?  All you need
to do is be just good, keepin' your teeth
out'n my cheek.
</p><p>"I've been lonesome always.  I hain't
got no people.  Do you know who your
dad was?  Neither do I; we're in the
same boat there.  Some French trader
was mine, I guess.  My mother's an
Omaha.
</p><p><hi rend="italic">"Wagah peasha</hi> &mdash; bad white man &mdash;
that's what the Omahas called me ever
since I was a little feller.  And the white
men says, 'darned Injun.'  And where
am I?  Hangin' on the edge of things &mdash;
gettin' orn'ry and nasty and bad.  I've
stole horses and killed people and cussed
fer days, Susette.  And I want to rest.
I want to love somethin'!  I don't care
what; somethin' that'll just let me.
Cabanne's men down at the post would
laugh to hear Antoine sayin' that.  But
I do.  I want to love somethin'.
</p><p>"I tried to, wunst.  Her name was
Susette, same as your'n.  She was a
trader's daughter &mdash; a pretty French girl.
That was before I was very bad.  I
talked sweet to her, and she liked it.
But the old man Lecroix &mdash; that was her
dad &mdash; he showed me the trail, and he
says: 'Go that way, and go fast, you
damn Injun!'
</p><p>"I went, Susette, but I made him pay,
I did.  I saw him on his back, after that,
a grinnin' up at the stars.  And since
then I hain't cared much.  I killed
several in my time, and I called 'em all
Lecroix!
</p><p>"Be a good girl, Susette, and I'll stick
to you.  I'm a good fighter and a good
grub-hunter, too.  I learned all that
easy."
</p><p>He continued caressing the wolf, and
she licked his hand when he stroked her
muzzle.
</p></div2>

<div2 type="part" n="5" id="d8"><head>V</head>

<p>DAYS passed, the winter deepened, the
heavy snows came.  Antoine nursed his
bruised companion back to strength.
Through the bitter nights he kept a fire
burning in front of the hole.
</p><p>The depth of the snow made it
improbable that any would learn of his
whereabouts; and the news must have
spread from post to post that Antoine,
the outlaw half-breed, had drowned
himself in the ice-fissure in order to escape
hanging.
</p><p>The man had used all his ammunition,
and his six-shooter had become useless.
So, with the skill of an Indian, he
wrought a bow and arrows.  He made
snow-shoes, and continued to hunt, keeping
the wolf in meat until she grew
strong and fat with the unaccustomed
luxurious life.  Also, she became very
tame.  During her weakness, the man
had subdued her fierceness.  When the
snow crusted, the two went hunting
together, Susette trotting at Antoine's
heels like a dog.
</p><p>One evening in late December, when
the low moon threw a shaft of cold silver
into the mouth of the lair, Antoine lay
huddled in his furs, listening to the
dirgelike calls of the wolves, wandering
inward from the vast night.  Susette also
listened, sitting upon her haunches
beside the man, with her short ears pricked
forward.
</p><p>When the far-away cries of her
kinspeople arose into a compelling major
sound, dying away into the merest
shadow of a pitiful minor, she switched
her tail uneasily, shuffled about nervously,
sniffing and whining.
</p><p>Then she began pacing with an eager
swing up and down the place to the
opening and back, sending forth the long
cry of kinship whenever she reached the
mouth of the lair.
</p><p>"Night's cold, Susette," said Antoine;


<pb n="711"/>

"'tain't no time fer huntin'.  Hain't I
give you enough to eat?"
</p><p>He caught the wolf, and by main force
held her down beside him.  She snarled
savagely and snapped her jaws together,
struggling out of his arms and going to
the opening, where she cried into the
stillness; whereat the answer of her kind
floated back in doleful chorus.
</p><p>"Don't go!" begged the man;
"Susette, my pretty Susette!  I'd be so
lonesome."
</p><p>Finally, as the chorus died, the wolf
gave a loud yelp and rushed into the
pale night.
</p><p>A great passion seized Antoine.  He
leaped from his furs and ran out after
the wolf.  She fled with a rapid, swinging
trot over the scintillating snow
toward the concourse of her people.  The
man fled after, slipping, falling, getting
up, running, and ever the wolf widened
the glittering stretch of snow between
them.
</p><p>To Antoine, the ever-widening space
of glinting coldness vaguely typified the
barrier that seemed growing between him
and his last companion.
</p><p>"Susette, oh, Susette!" he cried at
last, breathless and exhausted.  His cry
was dirgelike, even as the wolves'; thin
and sharp &mdash; the voice of the old world-ache.
</p><p>She had disappeared in the dusk of a
ravine.  Antoine, huddled in the snow
with his face upon his knees, sobbed
unmanfully into the winter stillness.
</p></div2>

<div2 type="part" n="6" id="d9"><head>VI</head>

<p>AT last, with slow and faltering step,
he returned to his lair.  He threw himself
down upon the floor of the cave and
cursed the world &mdash; cursed everything in
it, individually and generally; and then
he cursed Susette.
</p><p>"It's some other wolf," he hissed;
"some other gray dog she's goin' to see!
Oh, darn him!  Darn his gray hide!
I'll kill her, if she ever gits back!"
</p><p>He took out his knife and began
whetting it viciously upon his boot.
</p><p>"I'll cut her into strips and eat 'em!
Wasn't I good to her?  Couldn't I have
killed her?  Oh, I'll cut her into strips, I
will!"
</p><p>He whetted his knife for an hour,
cursing through his teeth.  At last his
anger grew into a foolish madness.  He
hurled himself upon the bunch of furs
beside him and made himself imagine
that they were Susette.  He set his teeth
into them; he crushed them with his
hands.  Then, in the impotence of his
anger, he fell upon his face and sobbed
himself to sleep.
</p><p>Strange visions passed before him.
Again he killed Lecroix, and saw the
dead face grinning at the stars.  Again
he sat in his mother's lodge and wept
because he was a stranger.  Again he was
fleeing, fleeing, fleeing from a leather
noose that hung above him like a black
cloud, and circled and lowered and
raised and lowered, until it swooped
down upon him and closed about his
neck.
</p><p>With a yell of fright he awoke from
his nightmare.  His head throbbed, his
mouth was parched.
</p><p>At last day came in sneakingly through
the opening &mdash; a dull, melancholy light
and with it came Susette, sniffing, with
the bristles of her neck erect.
</p><p>"Susette!  Susette!" cried the man
joyfully.
</p><p>He no longer thought of killing her.
He seized her in his arms; he kissed her
frost-whitened muzzle.
</p><p>She received his caresses with disdain;
whereat he redoubled his acts of fondness.
He fed her and petted her as she
ate; then the bristles on her neck
dropped.  She nosed him half fondly.
And Antoine, manlike, was glad again.
He contented himself with touching the
frayed hem of the garment of Happiness.
</p><p>He ate nothing that day.  He said to
himself: "I won't hunt till it's all gone;
she can have it all."  He was afraid to
leave Susette; he was afraid to take her
with him again into the land of her
people.  Antoine was jealous.
</p><p>All day he was kind to her with pitiful
kindness.  He whispered softly into her
ear:
</p><p>"Susette, I hain't a goin' to be jealous
no more.  You've been a bad girl,
Susette; don't do it again.  I won't be
mean, less'n you let <hi rend="italic">him</hi> come skulkin'
around here."
</p><p>The next morning Antoine did not get
up.  He felt sore and exhausted.  By
evening his heart was beating like a


<pb n="712"/>

hammer.  His head ached and swam; his
burning eyes saw strange, uncertain
visions.
</p><p>"Susette," he called, "I ain't feelin'
right.  Come here and let me touch you
again."
</p></div2>

<div2 type="part" n="7" id="d10"><head>VII</head>

<p>NIGHT was falling, and Susette sat
sullenly apart, listening for the call of
her people.  She did not go to him.  All
night the man tossed and raved.
</p><p>After a lingering age of delirious
wanderings, dizzy flights from huge,
pitiless pursuers, he became conscious of the
daylight.  He raised his head feebly and
looked about the den.  Susette was
gone.
</p><p>A fury of jealousy came upon Antoine.
She had gone again to find that other
wolf; he felt certain of this.  He tried
to arise, but the fever had weakened him
so that he lay impotent, torn alternately
with anger and longing.
</p><p>Suddenly a frost-whitened snout was
thrust in at the opening.
</p><p>It was Susette.  The man gave a feeble
cry of joy, and his eyes were filled with
a soft light.  Susette entered, sniffing
strangely and switching her tail as she
came.  At her heels came another gray
wolf &mdash; a male &mdash; larger-boned, lanker,
with more powerful jaws.  He whined
and moved his tail nervously at sight of
the man.
</p><p>Antoine lay staring at the intruder.
</p><p>"So that's him!" thought the man.
"I wisht I could git up!"
</p><p>The gray intruder approached him
with a sinuous movement of the tail.  His
jaws grinned hideously with long, sharp
teeth displayed.  The rage of hunger was
in his eyes, fixed steadily upon the sick
man.
</p><p>Antoine stared into the eyes of his
enemy, already crouching for the spring.
On a sudden, a strange exhilaration
seized him.  He seemed to be drinking
in the essence of life from the pitiless
stare of his adversary.  His great limbs,
devitalized but a moment before, now
tingled to the extremities with a surging
of the wine of life.  His eyes, which the
fever had burned into the dulness of
ashes, flamed again with the eager lust
of fight.
</p><p>He raised himself upon his haunches,
and with the lifting of a sneering lip
that disclosed his grinding teeth, he
gave a cry that was both a snarl and a
sob.
</p><p>In that moment these many centuries
of artificial life were as a vanished
dream.  From the long-slumbering dust
of the prehistoric cave-man came a giant
spirit to steel the sinews of its far-removed
and weaker kin.
</p><p>Antoine met the impetuous spring of
the intruding wolf with a downward
blow of his fist, and sprang upon his
momentarily worsted foe.  Never before
in all his bitter, pariah life had he
fought as now he fought for the possession
of his last companion.  His antagonist,
bigger than Susette, was the survivor
of many moonlight battles to the
death in the frozen, foodless wilderness
of hills.
</p><p>Antoine struggled not as a man; he
was now merely the good, glorious fighting
beast &mdash; masterful, primitive, the taker
of his own.  Lacerated by the snapping
of powerful jaws, bleeding from his face
and hands, the man felt that he was
winning.  With a whining cry he succeeded
in fixing his left hand upon the
hairy throat, crushed the wolf down
upon his back, and, using prodigious
strength, began to press the fingers of his
right hand under the protruding lower
ribs.  He would tear them out!  He
would thrust his hand in among the
vitals of his foe!
</p><p>All the while Susette, whining and
wagging her tail nervously, watched the
struggle with glowing eyes, and waited
for the sign of the victor.  But at this
juncture she arose with a threatening
sway of the head, approached the two
cautiously, then hurled herself into the
encounter.  She leaped with a savage
yelp upon him who had long been her
master.
</p><p>The man's grip suddenly relaxed.  He
fell back and threw out his arms, into
which once more there came the weakness
of the fever.
</p><p>"Susette!" gasped Antoine; "I was
always good to you!  I &mdash;"
</p><p>His cry was choked into a wheeze.
Susette had gripped him by the throat,
and the two were upon him.
</p><p>She had gone back to the ways of her
kind, and the man was an alien.
</p></div2>

</div1>
</body>
</text>
</TEI.2>
