<?xml version="1.0"?>

<?dlps id="NeiPrai"?>
<?dlps page-images="none" figure-images="no"?>
<?dlps transcription="other"?>

<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/tei-p4/tei2.dtd" [
<!ENTITY % POSTKB "INCLUDE">
<!ENTITY % TEI.extensions.ent SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.ent">
<!ENTITY % TEI.extensions.dtd SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.dtd">
<!ENTITY % ISOpub SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/charent/iso-pub.ent"> %ISOpub;
]>
<TEI.2 id="NeiPrai">
<teiHeader type="migrated" creator="Etext">
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title type="main">A Prairie Borgia</title>
<title type="sort">prairie borgia</title>
<author>Neihardt, John G.</author>
<respStmt>
<resp>Creation of machine-readable version:</resp>
<name>Judy Boss</name>
<resp>Creation of digital images:</resp>
<name/>
<resp>Conversion to TEI.2-conformant markup:</resp>
<name>University of Virginia Library Electronic Text Center.</name>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt>
<extent>ca. <num type="kilobytes">40</num> kilobytes</extent>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>University of Virginia Library</publisher>
<pubPlace>Charlottesville, Virginia</pubPlace>
<idno type="ETC">NeiPrai</idno>
<date value="1997">1997</date>
<availability status="public">
<p n="copyright">Copyright &#xa9; 1997 by the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia</p>
<p n="access">Publicly accessible</p>
</availability>
<idno type="uva-pid">uva-lib:477217</idno>
</publicationStmt>
<seriesStmt>
<title>University of Virginia Library, Text collection</title>
<idno type="uva-set">UVA-LIB-Text</idno>
</seriesStmt>
<notesStmt>
<note>
<p>Images omitted due to poor image quality on the source text (microfilm).</p>
</note>
<note>
<p>Pages 52-53, 56-57, 60-61 are incorrectly numbered in the source text as 532-533, 536-537, 540-541 respectively. Judy Boss made the following emendations to this text: Page 49, para. 1, line 1: WAZHINGER ] WAZHINGA ; page 49, para. 1, line 1: Wazing
a ] Wazhinga ; page 533, para. 7 betrayel. ] betrayal. ; page 536, para. 11: kildeers ] killdeers ; page 541, para. 10: fangs; Pity ] fangs; pity</p>
</note>
</notesStmt>
<sourceDesc>
<biblFull>
<titleStmt>
<title type="main">A Prairie Borgia</title>
<title level="j">Overland Monthly</title>
<title type="sort">prairie borgia</title>
<author>John G. Neihardt</author>
</titleStmt>
<extent>pp. 49-62</extent>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>California Publishing Company</publisher>
<pubPlace>San Francisco</pubPlace>
<date value="1903">1903</date>
<idno type="callNo">Print copy consulted: Alderman Library, MicFilm S-147 Reel 43</idno>
</publicationStmt>
<notesStmt>
<note>
<p>Overland Monthly, Vol. 42, No. 1 (July 1903).</p>
</note>
</notesStmt>
</biblFull>
</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc>
<encodingDesc>
<projectDesc>
<p>Prepared for the University of Virginia Library Electronic Text Center.</p>
</projectDesc>
<editorialDecl>
<p>All quotation marks retained as data.</p>
<p>All unambiguous end-of-line hyphens have been removed, and the trailing part of a word has been joined to the preceding line.</p>
<p>Keywords in the header are a local Electronic Text Center scheme to aid in establishing analytical groupings.</p>
</editorialDecl>
</encodingDesc>
<profileDesc>
<creation>
<date value="1903">1903</date>
</creation>
<langUsage>
<language id="eng" usage="main">English</language>
</langUsage>
<textClass>
<keywords>
<term>nonfiction; prose</term>
<term>Native American</term>
</keywords>
</textClass>
</profileDesc>
<revisionDesc>
<change>
<date value="1997-01">January 1997</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>corrector</resp>
<name>Stephen Ramsay, Electronic Text Center</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Added Tei header and tags.</item>
</change>
<change>
<date value="2005-07">July 2005</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>Corrector</resp>
<name>John Ivor Carlson</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Converted to XML and/or checked tags.</item>
</change>
<change>
<date value="2007-09">September 2007</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>Migration</resp>
<name>Ethan Gruber, University of Virginia Library</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Converted XML markup from TEI Lite to uva-dl-tei (TEI P4 with local customizations).</item>
</change>
<change>
<date value="2008-01">January 2008</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>Migration</resp>
<name>Greg Murray, University of Virginia Library</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Programmatically updated TEI header markup (but not header content) for minimal compliance with current QA requirements.</item>
</change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>
<text id="d1">
<body id="d2">




<div1 type="essay" id="d3"><pb n="49"/>
<head>
<hi rend="bold">A Prairie Borgia</hi><lb/>

                          BY<lb/>
                   JOHN G. NEIHARDT


</head>
<p>
<figure rend="block"><figDesc>Drawn title with illustration of Medicine Man.
[omitted]</figDesc></figure>
</p>

<p>WAZHINGA Saba was a great Medicine Man.  An old Indian whose
original being has not been blasted by the doubt of the white man, will
tell you that he was a seer of strange things big in meaning; a dreamer of
dreams that glared with the light of dawns and days, sundowns and stars,
speaking with the ambiguous tongue of mystery!  To his credulous
subjects, Wazhinga Saba was a bronze Colossus, stretching a hard
metallic hand across his little world, and the little world groaned or
laughed according to the will of the many-mooded master; for such have
been the people since the creation, and such have been the masters.
</p><p>In the fall of the year 1812 the entire Omaha tribe, returning from a
buffalo hunt on the plains which now constitute Western Nebraska, built
its winter village at a distance of about 200 miles from Ne Shuga, the
Great River.
</p><p>The hunting had been poor, and the tribe, though originally
intending to winter among the protecting bluffs of the great stream,
where firewood was plentiful, discontinued its march in order to
conserve its strength.  Who toils must eat much; therefore the tribe
ceased toiling that the small stock of meat might endure the winter.
</p><p>The Omahas built comfortable mud lodges along the banks of a
creek, which would at once afford them water and a limited supply of
wood from the scattered plum thickets.
</p><p>The fall days passed and the Northwest breathed with snowy breath
upon the hills, and the tribe was locked in the desolate little valley as by a
hand of ice.  Confinement to the lodges and insufficiency of food
brought sickness.  Many a strong brave became less than the shadow of a
squaw.  Many a squaw tottered and fell beneath her load, and became
weaker than the child at her back.
</p><p>It was one of the numerous humble tragedies that history does not
see.
</p><p>But daily about the windswept village went a youth who entered the
lodges where the groans of suffering were loudest.  There was a strange
light in his eye, and he who from the bed of sickness saw the light trusted
in the youth and muttered to his kinsmen: "Did you not see the light in
the eye of this youth?  Wakunda smiles upon him&mdash;his power is great!"
</p><p>This the people did not guess.  The light was the glare of the life
that was being consumed within him, blown upon by the strong breath of
the winter and the hunger.  For wherever the youth went he brought not
only the mysterious drinks brewed from herbs, but he brought morsels of
meat which he himself should have eaten.
</p><p>And it happened that some of the stricken died and the greater part
lived.  Then a small noise of
<pb n="50"/>
voices with a big meaning spread
throughout the village.  A buzz of wonder, which was full of the doings
of the youth, whom the people learned to call Wazadi (Healer.)
</p><p>In all races have appeared these sacrificing men of genius.  Some
have been Christs in their small way; some have remained unappreciated
martyrs.  All have contributed to the upbuilding of belief in the
supernatural.  These are the incarnations of Pity, grotesque in a world of
cruelty and suffering.  Many have missed immortality but by the length of
Pilate's judgment.
</p><p>The noise of wondering voices spread and swelled into a cry that
beat into the lodge of the stern and selfish chief, Wazhinga Saba.  And as
he heard, the little warmth that hid in his heart died and the coldness
came; for jealousy is the northwest wind of the soul.
</p><p>Many days he sat alone in his lodge, speaking only with the
jealousy of his heart.  He said to himself: "Am I not the greatest of all
medicine men?  Shall a youth walk between Wazhinga Saba and the
belief of his people?"
</p><p>Then the coldness of his heart answered things that would have
been terrible upon a tongue.  And the Chief listened.
</p><p>So it happened one evening that a runner came to the lodge of the
youth called Wazadi, summoning him to go to the big chief's lodge.
Wazadi followed the runner to the big lodge.
</p><p>He pushed aside the buffalo hide that hung across the door and
entered.  The chief, dressed in his most elaborate garments, profusely
decorated with wolfs' teeth and hawks' beaks, sat alone by his fire.  As
the youth entered, the chief arose and stood in the glare of the flames that
gave an additional attraction to his regal figure.  For a moment Wazadi
stood awed into immobility at the sight, nor moved until Wazhinga Saba
smiled a pleasant smile.  The smile had its meaning.  The Chief had
wished to dazzle the youth, and it was accomplished.
</p><p>Wazhinga Saba motioned the youth to sit upon the opposite side of
the fire.  After a prolonged silence, during which each regarded the other
through the haze of flame-lit smoke, the Chief said:
</p><p>"The great heart of Wazhinga Saba is glad of the good words that
have been spoken among the lodges.  Does not the Chief love his people?
The little words of a chief are big.  Wazhinga Saba wishes to do great
honor to Wazadi."  At the name, the speaker paused and smiled again.
"This place is not good," he continued; "there is an evil spirit in this
place.  There is much sickness and groaning and dying.  It must not be.
Does not the Great Chief love his people?  We will take the sunrise trail;
we will leave the groaning and the sickness behind us.  We will go to the
banks of the great smoky water.  It is a good place; there are good spirits
there."
</p><p>The Chief paused and looked into the flames, thinking deeply.  "I
have a deed for a strong and brave man.  A good trail must be found that
the tribe may not go astray.  Is Wazadi strong?  Is he brave?  Then let him
seek a good trail to the great smoky water.  Let him go alone, that the
honor may not be divided like a big bison by many that are hungry!"
</p><p>As Wazhinga Saba ceased speaking, a great joy born of vanity
blazed in the blood of the youth, and he answered the question in the
chief's eyes with a glad voice.
</p><p>"I am strong and brave!  I will seek the trail!"
</p><p>When Wazadi withdrew from the lodge, Wazhinga Saba sat a long
time staring into the flame.  He was thinking.  The future was again
pleasant to look upon.  Ever since the noise of the strange youth's deeds
had beat into the lodge, striking discord in the song

<pb n="51"/>

<figure rend="block"><figDesc>Illustration with caption: "With his teeth set
and his face to the blast Wazadi led his people."
[omitted]</figDesc></figure>

<pb n="532"/>

that his vain heart sang, the future had been as the
horizon of the morning when a black cloud blinds the eyes of the
climbing sun.  But now the cloud had become but a thin, translucent
vapor, promising to vanish in the glare of day.
</p><p>As he gazed into the fire he was thinking of the long and cruel trail
which his rival would follow; of the keen and merciless storm winds,
mad with the zigzag flight of snow!  His reverie grew deeper.  In his
mind he followed the youth down the sunrise trail.  He saw him
wallowing through drifts, tumbling into hidden ravines; stumbling on
through the blinding, hissing snow that obliterated all landmarks!  He
saw the white ghost of a man thrown down with hunger and the cold, to
be the senseless impediment upon which the snow caught and drifted.
</p><p>The last thought came like the first far cry of an approaching
triumph.  The Chief leaped to his feet with a loud burst of laughter.
"Wazadi will not come back!" he muttered slowly as though to taste the
sweetness of the words: "Wazadi will not come hack!  Wazadi!"
</p><p>At the last word he chuckled with derision, and then lay down
beside his fire.  But he did not sleep.  Defeat can sleep, because there is
an element of death in it.  Triumph is wakeful, because it is life
new-born.
</p><p>Before the sunrise of the next day Wazadi had disappeared among
the frozen hills to the eastward.  Upon the lips of Wazhinga Saba sat a
smile beside a sneer.  He had vanquished his budding rival and his heart
held high festival.
</p><p>For many days he feasted the other chiefs of the tribe, who had
become puppets in his hands.  Haunches of the best bison meat were
wasted, until starvation stood between the tribe and the spring.  And the
people looked with wistful eyes upon the doings of their chief and
muttered syllables of discontent like the sound of underground waters,
for they dared not speak aloud.
</p><p>But one evening, after many days of storm had swept across the
sky, the figure of a man, frost-whitened, weakened, and blinded with the
snow, stumbled into the village.
</p><p>"Wazadi has come back!  Wazadi has come back!"
</p><p>The shout passed contagiously from lip to lip, and grew into a
clamor that found its way through the door of the lodge of Wazhinga
Saba.  The cry wrought a terrible anger in his heart.
</p><p>What!  Was this the way the great Wazhinga Saba took revenge?
No!  He would see the blood of this audacious Wazadi!  Yet it could not
be done with violence; for did not the people love the youth?  An
oppressed people is like a pack of wolves.  Both flee until the trail
ends, then they turn and their bites are terrible!  Would not the violent
death of Wazadi end the trail?
</p><p>At this thought the revenge of Wazhinga Saba became indefinite;
yet some time it would be.  He would wait.
</p><p>These turbulent thoughts were interrupted by the entrance of the
youth himself.  He stood at the door of the lodge, the white ghost of a
man.  His eyes were sunken and bleared.  The skin was drawn across his
cheek bones.  He tottered.  His voice was the ghost of a strong voice:
</p><p>"I have found the trail; the tribe will not go astray.  The trail is long
and there is death upon it.  The winds strike like the forefeet of a bear
and bite like the teeth of a wolf.  I was strong and I am here.  It is a bad
thing for the people to take the trail!"
</p><p>Wazhinga Saba smiled and answered: "Does the strong man make
his toil worthless with his groaning?  Wazhinga Saba speaks with the
spirits.  Wakunda (God) will put his hand upon the winds and
<pb n="533"/>
they will sleep; his hand upon their teeth and they will be dull.  The tribe
will take the trail."
</p><p>The words of the Chief flew through the village, and in their wake a
groan followed.  "If we take the trail we die!" muttered the people among
themselves; yet the work of preparing for the march began and
progressed rapidly.  The little word of a chief is big; and the people
feared Wazhinga Saba.
</p><p>To one who has some acquaintance with the prairie, the insanity of
moving an entire tribe, with its sickness and hunger, a distance of 200
miles in the dead of winter, is apparent.  On the prairie there is treachery
in the bluest winter sky.  The Southwind that whines so abjectly in the
morning, at noon may be crowned with a crown of ice in the silent North,
and return a terrible Conqueror in the evening.  The elemental Lackey
becomes the elemental Emperor.
</p><p>Wazhinga Saba, feeling that his rival was the product of the
people's praise, wished to retaliate upon the people.  He knew the
consequences of such a movement in the winter, but the idea pleased
him.  He would make the tribe suffer.  It would feel his power.
</p><p>Throughout the village was the activity of an imminent departure.
Drags were being fashioned, and upon these was packed the baggage of
the tribe.  There was no song among the toilers; but everywhere there was
muttering and much hopeless shaking of the head.  The people thought of
the long trail and shivered.
</p><p>One morning when the work was finished, through the pale and
shivering light of the early dawn, the tribe filed out of its desolate village,
and at its head walked Wazadi breaking the trail.
</p><p>The sick, the old, and the children were packed like baggage on the
drags.  In order that the trail might be easier for those who followed, the
tribe proceeded in single file, those who had extra ponies riding, and
those who had none walking.  So long was the column that the foremost
were lost from sight among the hills when the last left the village.
</p><p>By midday a heavy fall of snow began.  For three days and nights
the snow came, soft and gentle as a kiss that goes before betrayal.  Then
during the fourth night the Northwest shouted and shook the people from
their shivering sleep.  It was the battle cry that could not be answered.
</p><p>The poles of the hastily constructed tepees groaned with the blows
of the storm; many were thrown to the ground, while the blankets that
were wrapped about them flapped, tore and went with the wind.  The
light snow scurried along the ground with a hiss like the warning of a
snake, caught the madness of the storm, leaped into the air, writhing,
striking, biting!
</p><p>It is easy to imagine the many elemental phenomena as being
merely magnifications of human passions projected upon the universe.  A
cyclone is sudden anger; a southwind is feminine tenderness; a rainfall is
grief; the spring sunshine is love.  Madness is a conglomeration of all
passions.  A blizzard is the madness of the air!  It has the fury and
blindness of anger, the hiss of hate, the shout of joy, the dusk of
melancholy, the shiver of fear, the coldness of jealousy; and when its
force is spent, it folds its victims in a shroud of white, which may be the
act of love&mdash;a savage love!
</p><p>A blizzard transforms.  What it touches it leaves grotesque.  It
annihilates the boundary line of light and darkness.  In its breath the night
becomes merely a deepening of shadow upon the dim twilight of the day.
</p><p>God wished to demonstrate to mankind the awful tragedy of
unbridled passions, and his precept was the blizzard!
<pb n="54"/>
</p><p>A strange, one-sided battle had begun.  The Omahas, who would
have turned their faces to an onslaught of the Sioux, huddled together
with their backs to the storm like a herd of lost sheep surrounded by the
howl of wolves.  The bravest whimpered as they blew upon their
stiffened fingers.  In those rare places where some one had contrived to
coax a sickly fire with
<figure rend="block"><figDesc>Illustration with caption: "Wazadi raised the
earthen bowl to his lips." [omitted]</figDesc></figure>
scant fuel, there was a
jostling, fighting, crying mass of men, women and children struggling
toward the glow that fought a losing fight with the breath of the storm!
</p><p>At last the morning came without a sunrise.  A blizzard deals in
paradoxes.  It was not day: it was as if an evil spirit had travestied God's
sunlight!
</p><p>The storm grew stronger.  A blizzard has the impetuosity of youth
upon the first day, the strength of manhood upon the second, and upon
the third day it grows peevish with senility and dies in the evening.  In
the sense of time, it is little more than an ephemeron.  To its victims it is
thrice a centenarian!
</p><p>When the mockery of the day came, the people took heart and
began to reconstruct their places of shelter.  Yet scarcely had they cooked
and eaten their morning meal when an order to take the trail came from
Wazhinga Saba.  A part hesitated; a part, whose fear of the chief was
greater than the fear of the elements, prepared for the march; the
remainder followed.
</p><p>The long file disappeared into the swirling haze.  It is true that the
<pb n="55"/>
Chief also suffered; yet his selfishness was so great that to reach
its ends, it ignored self.  It was the apotheosis of egotism.  Selfishness
can become an inexorable god.
</p><p>The hundreds of stumbling hoofs and feet left no trail.  A foot-print
was momentary and served only to catch the drifting snow.  Many
wandered from the column into the terrible loneliness of the storm and
never re-appeared.  Many more tottered with weakness and the cold and
lay where they fell.  Those who followed stumbled across these
unfortunates, and felt no pity.  Despair crept icily through the blood of
the tribe.
</p><p>Despair is pitiless because it is the annihilation of all passion and
the exaltation of egotism.  It is that condition of the mind when the
democratic government of the passions is cast down and the ego seizes
the throne of reason, becoming dictatorial in defense of its realm.
</p><p>The tribe was desperate.  There is a terrible strength and power of
endurance in desperation.  Hope avails to goad the limbs only until that
moment when the limbs become feeble; then it vanishes in terror and
despair fights defeat.  More heroes have been made by the probability of
failure than by the possibility of success.  It is the difference between the
narcotic and the stimulant.
</p><p>With his teeth set and his face to the east, Wazadi led his people
into the storm.  Even he had forgotten the meaning of pity.  There was
rage in his heart; the rage of a brave man who is a fighter and faces great
odds.  The coward grows tender in the midst of danger.  The brave man
grows angry.
</p><p>Wazadi struck at the storm with his clenched fists!  He wished that
the wind would materialize into a bear that he might grapple with it and
die with his teeth set in its neck.
</p><p>But a storm is an anger without intelligence; a bodiless foe; an
enemy without nerves!  It knows not its strength of offense and feels no
blow of defense.  It is irresistible and invulnerable.
</p><p>The day lingered like a century, and when it had passed it was like a
dream.  The nights were terrible.  Inaction lessens courage and increases
suffering.  Thus the three days passed, and the wind died.  The white
prairie emerged from the terrible shadow and the sun went down
smiling like a cynic.
</p><p>Wazadi looked upon his people and his heart grew sick.  Hundreds
were missing, and the survivors were shadows of men.  Many of the
ponies had strayed into the storm, dragging with them the children, the
sick and the old.  And a great wail shook the frozen air.  It was the return
of conscious suffering after delirium.
</p><p>But upon the next morning the tribe again took up the trail, and
when the sun of the twelfth day reached the highest point in its brief arc,
a great shout went up from the foremost of the tribe, for the broad, frozen
river lay before them, and the trail was ended.
</p><p>Immediately the entire tribe began the difficult task of building
lodges from the frozen ground.  The young and old, the squaws and the
braves, threw their feeble efforts into the work and their hearts grew
warm again with the warmth that clings about a home.  They felt no
hatred against their chief for their past suffering; no more than the
sleeper feels against the night when awakened from a nightmare.  They
had not forgiven; they had forgotten.  Joy was gigantic and left no nook
for the dwelling place of hate.
</p><p>In a few days the village was complete, and the tribe again settled
down for the winter.  But Wazhinga Saba was not happy.  His heart was
dull with the tedium that follows a dead triumph.  The Chief wanted
diversion; he wanted feasting merriment.  Therefore he sent
<pb n="536"/>
runners about the village collecting a certain amount of meat from each
lodge; and the people groaned as they gave, for they could see starvation
stalking through the months of spring.
</p><p>Then, for many months Wazhinga Saba ate with his puppet chiefs;
and there was much laughter in the big lodge, much groaning without.
</p><p>But the feasting lost its flavor and Wazhinga Saba longed for new
pleasures.  He found no beauty in his old women; years and toil and
suffering had seamed their faces.  Again he sent runners about the
village, and this time they demanded the fairest of the maidens, whom he
smiled upon in the evening and frowned upon in the morning.
</p><p>To a primitive Indian, women were inviolate.  They might toil and
suffer, but they dared not be impure.  An impure woman would have
been stoned from the village.
</p><p>So a great murmur of anger grew among the lodges; and all this
indefinite muttering rage gathered and centralized in one voice.  That
voice was Wazadi.  He stood in the center of a growing crowd of his
tribesmen, and his voice was loud and fearless:
</p><p>"Does my cry reach the ears of badgers?  Are you brave but deaf?
Are you strong but blind?  Did Wakunda make the prairie and the people
for Wazhinga Saba?  Was it not enough that he gave us to be bitten by
the winds?  Are we wolves that we turn and flee not?  The love which I
gave to you at the summer's end, that love continues.  I made you well;
but Wazhinga Saba is worse sickness.  Let us put this sickness from us!"
</p><p>When the fearless youth had ceased speaking he became the center
of a great shouting.
</p><p>"Lead us!  Be our chief!" the people cried.
</p><p>"Wazadi will be your brother," he answered, "your brother and your
chief.  Let us build a village of our own where Wazhinga Saba will not
be."
</p><p>The last words went among the people and divided them.  Many
shouted with approval; many only scowled and shook their heads.  Their
fear was greater than their hate.
</p><p>That day Wazadi led his party carrying all its baggage out of the old
village into the hills to the north, and there a new village was built.  And
the people of his party changed the bold youth's name, calling him
Tawagaha (little village maker), and the name clung, and to this day it is
as a great noise in the ears of the Omahas.
</p><p>The winter grew old; the sun crept northward; the southwinds blew.
The great hoarse voice of the river with its booming ice went like a
herald before the approach of spring.  The snow faded from the hills.
The meadow-larks and the killdeers came back; the gophers chattered.
The days grew balmy and the frogs sang again.  The last ice of the winter
crashed past and the big muddy river exulted like a thing with a heart.
Greenness and warmth and sweet scents!
</p><p>In either village there was not a throat that could not sing, save one.
Wazhinga Saba still held the winter at his heart.  The shadow of his hate
preserved the snow of his soul.  While the broad sky and the vast prairie
relented, he thought only of revenge.
</p><p>Nothing can invent like a hate that lingers.  It is a diabolical genius.
It would burn away where love would wilt and weep.  This is because it
has nothing to lose; it has all to gain.  If Leander had taken the flood that
he might kill a sleeping rival, the Hellespont would have been narrower.
</p><p>Wazhinga Saba sat in his lodge and plotted.  He knew that the
people believed him to be a terrible medicine man, a doer of magic
things; yet he knew all his past successes to have depended merely
<pb n="537"/>  upon trickery.  Therefore he would not depend upon
magic for his
revenge, but merely as an appropriate setting for that revenge.
</p><p>Several years before, the steamboats of the white man had sailed up
the Missouri as far as the place where the Omahas were now camped, the
American Fur Company having established a trading post in 1810 at
Bellevue at a distance of about 150 miles down stream.
</p><p>Every spring and fall since then the company's boat, St. Ange, had
made a trip to the foot of Blackbird Hill, where the Omahas had their
winter village, in order to trade for the valuable furs which the Indians
disposed of very cheaply.
</p><p>Ever since Columbus first trod the American shore, the Indian has
looked upon the white man as a being of superior powers; and the Omaha
was no exception.  Did not the Wahgah (big knife or white man) know
the magic that made the talking stick and the sticks that walk?  Did he not
chain fire in the belly of his big canoe and make it snort with toil?  Then
might he not also possess some great mysterious medicine?
</p><p>Sometimes thus ran the thoughts of Wazhinga Saba, and his heart
became glad with the gladness of a young revenge.  He had at last formed
a great plan.
</p><p>One evening during the time when the squaws pull the weeds in the
gardens (May), runners, sent to watch the river from the bluffs, came
puffing into the tepee of Wazhinga Saba.  "Monda Tonga!  (big canoe)
Wahgah!  Wahgah!" they cried, motioning excitedly toward the river.  At
that moment the long sonorous howl of a steamboat's whistle came from
the south and echoed in the bluffs.  The Chief leaped to his feet, his face
glowing with a great joy.
</p><p>"Go!  Bring the Wahgah to Wazhinga Saba!" he cried, and the
runners bounded out of the tepee and disappeared in the direction of the
river.  An hour later a half dozen white men led by the runners and
followed by a curious mob of Omahas, approached the tepee of the Great
Chief.  The rabble, however, satisfied its curiosity at a respectful distance
from the "talking sticks" which the traders carried.
</p><p>With much ceremony Wazhinga Saba received his white brothers,
and dispersed the crowd with a motion of his arm.  The traders, through
their interpreter, at once set about displaying a stock of gaudy trifles, but
Wazhinga Saba would have none of them.  He forthwith explained his
peculiar needs.
</p><p>"He wants some kind of strong medicine," said the interpreter to the
traders.
</p><p>"Tell him about whiskey," they said.
</p><p>The interpreter talked with the Chief in the Omaha tongue.
</p><p>"He wants to know what it can do," said the interpreter laughing.
</p><p>"Make much crazy," volunteered the traders, executing an
extravagant pantomime of drunkenness: "So!"
</p><p>Wazhinga Saba's face beamed as he watched the white man's insane
evolutions.  Perhaps he was mentally putting Tawagaha in the same
ridiculous position.  Yes! that was the medicine he wanted!
</p><p>The interpreter explained, with much recourse to hyperbole, the
great value of the medicine in question, and the Chief answered by
showing the big stack of bison hides which he would give for ever so
little.  When a rich child wants anything a trade is easy; and when the
traders withdrew from the Chief's tepee, Wazhinga Saba sat gloating over
a jug of "medicine."
</p><p>The next morning the St. Ange, well-stocked with buffalo hides,
took the current, whistling like a live thing glad of a full stomach, and the
Omahas took up their usual routine of life.
One morning a runner left the
<pb n="58"/>
<figure rend="block"><figDesc>Illustration with caption: "He muttered a
curse upon his smiling enemy and died." [omitted]</figDesc></figure>
<pb n="59"/>
tepee
of Wazhinga Saba and took his way to Tawagaha's village.  He entered
the tepee of the self-constituted chief and spoke kind things into his ear
for Wazhinga Saba.  It was represented with many honeyed words that
the Big Chief's heart ached with his past unkindness to Tawagaha, with
whom he wished to talk and feast that the past might be as a dead thing.
</p><p>Tawagaha, having the tender heart which goes with generosity, at
once arose and followed the runner to the tepee of Wazhinga Saba, where
many other sweet words met his ear.
</p><p>They feasted and smoked the peace pipe, and Tawagaha forgot.  At
last Wazhinga Saba produced an earthen bowl containing a copper-colored liquid.
</p><p>"Wazhinga Saba has talked much with the good spirits," said the
Big Chief.  "Here is the water of kindness; drink and we shall be
friends."
</p><p>Tawagaha looked suspiciously at the mysterious water.
</p><p>"See!" said Wazhinga Saba, "it is colored with the color of the
evening after a day of winds.  Wazhinga Saba has been cruel like the
winds, and this is the evening of his hate.  Drink, and there shall be a big
sunrise of friendship!"
</p><p>Tawagaha raised the earthen bowl to his lips.
</p><p>"It is the gift of the good spirits," said the Big Chief, coaxingly.
</p><p>Tawagaha drank great draughts, and set the bowl down.
</p><p>"It bites!" he said.
</p><p>"Like hate!" said Wazhinga Saba.
</p><p>After a silence Tawagaha frowned.
</p><p>"It gnaws!" said he.
</p><p>"Like cruel words," said the Chief.
</p><p>Tawagaha sat for some time like one stunned.  Then he grasped his
head with both hands and leaped to his feet.
</p><p>"It tickles!" he shrieked, and leaped out of the tepee yelling and
beating his head with his fists.  He dashed through the village and the
people scattered before him.  Civilization had not yet given them a
broad understanding!
</p><p>Tawagaha shouted and laughed and shrieked.  He danced and
struck enormous blows at an imaginary enemy, and ran howling to his
village.  When he had disappeared, Wazhinga Saba came out of his
tepee and spoke grave words to his startled people.
</p><p>"Tawagaha's head is on fire," he said.  "Wakunda has punished him
for his deed against the great Wazhinga Saba!  Let none follow
Tawagaha!"
</p><p>The people trembled as they heard.  They shook their heads and
were glad that they had not followed the daring youth.  The same day a
crier went through the village of Tawagaha and repeated the words of the
Chief in a loud voice:
</p><p>"Come back to the village of Wazhinga Saba," he cried; "the Great
Chief loves his people and would protect them from evil spirits."
</p><p>A primitive Indian was always superstitious first and generous
afterward.  He would do more for the fear of a black spirit than for the
love of a leader.  So it happened that the people of the little village at
once moved to the larger village, again coming under the control of
Wazhinga Saba.
</p><p>Then spring came to the heart of the Chief, and he could smile
again.
</p><p>But Tawagaha, having fallen into a heavy slumber in his tepee,
awoke the next day and the fire was dead in his brain.  He arose and
walked about his village, but found it deserted.  He stopped and thought
deeply, as if trying to recollect a vague dream.  At last he remembered the
mysterious liquid.  Then all was clear to him.  He knew whither his
people had gone, and he walked toward the larger village with a heavy
heart.
<pb n="540"/>
</p><p>When he entered the village there was none to give him greeting.
His own people looked at him tremblingly, and fled from him.  He
wandered through the village, but everywhere it was the same.  It was
like a ghost roaming through a village of ghosts.  None spoke to him.
Everywhere the people shook their heads and shut themselves in their
tepees.  The very children hid at his coming and peered after him when
he had passed.
</p><p>Then Tawagaha gave a great cry of despair that was followed only
by the silence.  When the people ventured to come out of their tepees,
Tawagaha had disappeared.
</p><p>The summer came&mdash;a burning summer.  The prairie is a double
wonder.  It can blossom like an oasis and burn like a Sahara.  The breath
of the winds is its life or its death.  The Southwest strikes it barren.
</p><p>In the beginning of the month of the bellowing of the bulls (July),
the terrible wind awakened.  The prairie grew sallow as the skin of an
impoverished thing.  The corn in the gardens wilted.  The creeks were
anaemic veins creeping sluggishly into the river that dwindled to a creek.
The great smoky water was as a giant stricken with fever.  Its sandbars
were as the protrusions of mighty ribs.
</p><p>The people sent up a wail like the echo of the Southwest's moan.
And there was much crying after the rain, but no cloud reared it's white
head from under the dazzling horizon.
</p><p>Wazhinga Saba sang a thunder song, but the rain spirits were deaf.
The blue basins of the rain were dried up.
</p><p>But one evening as the people sat about their tepees talking about
the rains that did not come, the sound of a wild voice arose upon the dull
air.  The people sat charmed into breathlessness and listened.  They
recognized the mysterious syllables of the thunder song.  Who was the
singer?  Was it a spirit?
</p><p>In answer to the silent question the naked form of a man, emaciated
as with famine, walked with slow steps through the village.  His head
was thrown back and his lips were parted with ecstatic song.
</p><p>As the people looked upon the face of the singer they shuddered,
for it was the face of Tawagaha!  He passed on through the village
chanting the song that the thunder spirits love, and disappeared.
</p><p>That night it happened that the clouds gathered and thundered and
the rain came in torrents.  When the day dawned, the people's voices
gathered into a great cry:
</p><p>"It was Tawagaha!  He brought the rain!  Where is Tawagaha?"
The shout echoed in the steaming hills and the hills sent back an answer.
The answer was a man who walked with the swift step of happy feet
toward the village.
</p><p>Thus was Tawagaha re-instated in the people's favor.  And
Wazhinga Saba's hate grew like a wilted thing that has been watered with
the rains.
</p><p>The summer passed and the fall came, and with it came the trading
boat, St. Ange.  Again the traders were conducted to the lodge of the Big
Chief.  One of the white men, with a broad grin upon his face, asked
through the interpreter if the medicine of last spring had acted properly.
</p><p>"Ninga!  Peazha!" replied the Chief, shaking his head decidedly.
</p><p>"He says it was no good!" explained the interpreter.
</p><p>"Ask him what he wants now?" said one of the white men.
</p><p>The interpreter spoke briefly to the Chief, who began to explain
with much impersonation of description, contorting his face, writhing
with his body and at last falling in a tragic representation of death.
</p><p>"He wants something that will hurt much and kill," the interpreter
explained.
<pb n="541"/>
</p><p>"Strychnine!" suggested one of the traders.
</p><p>"Think we've got some on the boat," added another; and a man
was forthwith sent after the desired medicine.  He soon returned and
displayed a small phial containing a white granular substance.
</p><p>'This will kill," said the interpreter to the Chief.
</p><p>Wazhinga Saba became excited.  He offered a stack of buffalo
hides as high as his knees.  The traders shook their heads.  Then the chief
doubled the imaginary pile.  Still there was no trade.
</p><p>"What will it do?  Show me," said the Chief to the interpreter.  A
dog had followed one of the white men and now it ran about expressing
good humor with its sinuous tail.  A piece of meat was procured from
the Chief and a small particle of strychnine placed upon it.  This
was fed to the dog, who ate it greedily.  Suddenly its eyes became
glazed; it fell howling to the ground, writhed, and died!
</p><p>The Chief's eyes blazed.  He pointed to the peak of the tepee and
swung his arm about him, thus saying that he would fill his tepee with
buffalo hides in exchange for the medicine.
</p><p>The trade was made, and when the hides had been collected from
among the people of the village, the white men withdrew groaning
beneath their spoils.
</p><p>Forthwith the wily Wazhinga Saba set his brain in motion; it had
become a diabolical machine propelled by hate.  He knew that Tawagaha
would refuse to feast with him again; so he decided to feast with
Tawagaha.  He waited four days (for four is a magic number) and upon
the fourth evening he went, humbly dressed, to the tepee of his rival.  He
entered and fell upon his face before the youth, groaning as with great
mental anguish.
</p><p>The heart of Tawagaha, like all great hearts, was pitiful.  He raised
the Chief and told him to speak his grief.
</p><p>"The days of Wazhinga Saba have been many," began the Chief,
sniveling with a burlesque grief, "many and cruel.  Now his head is white
and his strength passes.  Does the young man feel no pity for the old.  We
have been enemies, but Wazhinga Saba has become as a snake without
fangs; pity him, and you shall be his chief!"
</p><p>Tawagaha heard and was deceived.
</p><p>"Tawagaha pities," said he; "let us smoke the peace pipe and eat
together that we may be friends."
</p><p>The two smoked.  Then Tawagaha's squaw placed an iron kettle,
bought from the white men, over a fire, and boiled a great piece of
buffalo meat.
</p><p>When the meat was cooked, Wazhinga Saba arose and bowing
over the kettle, dropped something into it.  "The blessing of an old man
is good," he said.
</p><p>Tawagaha opened the feast, bulging his cheeks with a liberal bite.
The old man watched.
</p><p>Suddenly the face of the young man grew livid.  He shrieked and
fell to the floor, writhing and groaning in terrible agony.  His strong
limbs contracted; his muscles stood out in knots; his veins swelled blue.
Then with a last great effort he muttered a curse upon his smiling enemy,
and died.
</p><p>Wazhinga Saba heard the curse and his triumph brought him terror.
He fled to his tepee and shut himself up for many days.
</p><p>There was much wonder among the people, and when the boldest
ventured to question the old chief concerning the death of Tawagaha he
could only groan.
</p><p>Some years after Wazhinga Saba fell ill with the small-pox, and
believing it to be the curse of Tawagaha, he died in terror.

</p><p>I have stood upon a high hill of
<pb n="62"/>
the present Omaha
Reservation.  It is known as the Blackbird Hill for there the terrible chief
was buried, sitting upon his horse with all his arms about him, that he
might see the Big Knives (white men) come up the river in their fire-breathing canoes, as he said.
</p><p>As I stood there I felt both admiration and pity.  But when I asked
an old Omaha about the dread chief, he scowled and would not answer.
The memory of wrongs lives long and dies slowly.</p>


</div1>
</body>
</text>
</TEI.2>

