<?xml version="1.0"?>

<?dlps id="NeiSmil"?>
<?dlps page-images="none" figure-images="no"?>
<?dlps transcription="other"?>

<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/tei-p4/tei2.dtd" [
<!ENTITY % POSTKB "INCLUDE">
<!ENTITY % TEI.extensions.ent SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.ent">
<!ENTITY % TEI.extensions.dtd SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.dtd">
<!ENTITY % ISOnum SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/charent/iso-num.ent"> %ISOnum;

]>
<TEI.2 id="NeiSmil">
<teiHeader type="migrated" creator="Etext">
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title type="main">The Smile of God</title>
<title type="sort">smile of god</title>
<author>Neihardt, John G.</author>
<respStmt>
<resp>Creation of machine-readable version:</resp>
<name>Judy Boss</name>
<resp>Conversion to TEI.2-conformant markup:</resp>
<name>University of Virginia Library Electronic Text Center.</name>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt>
<extent>ca. <num type="kilobytes">17</num> kilobytes</extent>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>University of Virginia Library</publisher>
<pubPlace>Charlottesville, Virginia</pubPlace>
<idno type="ETC">NeiSmil</idno>
<date value="1996">1996</date>
<availability status="public">
<p n="copyright">Copyright &copy; 1996 by the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia</p>
<p n="access">Publicly accessible</p>
</availability>
<idno type="uva-pid">uva-lib:476251</idno>
</publicationStmt>
<seriesStmt>
<title>University of Virginia Library, Text collection</title>
<idno type="uva-set">UVA-LIB-Text</idno>
</seriesStmt>
<notesStmt>
<note>
<p>p. 544 changed "by John G. Neihardt" to "by J.G. Neihardt" P.544, line 1, changed "father Eastward" to "farther Eastward" p. 545, line 4 changed "huddered" to "shuddered" p. 545, line 9 changed "dream;" to "dream:" ,</p>
</note>
</notesStmt>
<sourceDesc>
<biblFull>
<titleStmt>
<title type="main">The Smile of God</title>
<title level="j">Overland Monthly, n.s. 38 January 1902</title>
<title type="sort">smile of god</title>
<author>John G. Neihardt</author>
</titleStmt>
<editionStmt>
<p>1st edition</p>
</editionStmt>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>California Publishing Co.</publisher>
<pubPlace>San Francisco</pubPlace>
<date value="1902-01">January, 1902</date>
</publicationStmt>
<notesStmt>
<note>
<p>January 1902 n.s. 38 pp. 544-547</p>
</note>
</notesStmt>
</biblFull>
</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc>
<encodingDesc>
<projectDesc>
<p>Prepared for the University of Virginia Library Electronic TextCenter.</p>
</projectDesc>
<editorialDecl>
<p>All quotation marks retained as data.</p>
<p>Keywords in the header are a local Electronic Text Center scheme to aid in establishing analytical groupings.</p>
</editorialDecl>
<refsDecl>
<p>ID elements are given for each page element and are composed of the text'sunique cryptogram and the given page number, as in AusEmma1 for page one of Jane Austen's Emma.</p>
</refsDecl>
</encodingDesc>
<profileDesc>
<creation>
<date value="1902-01">January, 1902</date>
</creation>
<langUsage>
<language id="eng" usage="main">English</language>
</langUsage>
<textClass>
<keywords>
<term>fiction; prose</term>
<term>Native American</term>
</keywords>
</textClass>
</profileDesc>
<revisionDesc>
<change>
<date value="1996-09">September 1996</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>corrector</resp>
<name>Tom Lukas</name>
</respStmt>
<item>SGML TEI-2 markup.</item>
</change>
<change>
<date value="2005-07">July 2005</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>Corrector</resp>
<name>John Ivor Carlson</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Converted to XML and/or checked tags.</item>
</change>
<change>
<date value="2007-09">September 2007</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>Migration</resp>
<name>Ethan Gruber, University of Virginia Library</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Converted XML markup from TEI Lite to uva-dl-tei (TEI P4 with local customizations).</item>
</change>
<change>
<date value="2008-01">January 2008</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>Migration</resp>
<name>Greg Murray, University of Virginia Library</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Programmatically updated TEI header markup (but not header content) for minimal compliance with current QA requirements.</item>
</change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>
<text id="d1">
<body id="d2">
<div1 type="story" id="d3"><pb n="544"/>
<head>The Smile of God<lb/>
An Omaha Indian Story<lb/>
 by J. G. Neihardt</head>

     <p>THE Omahas were hunting bison.  The young moon was thin and bent
like a bow by the arm of a strong man when they had left their
village in the valley of Neshuga (Smoky Water, the Missouri).
Night after night it had grown above their cheerless tepees, ever
farther Eastward, until now it came forth no more, but lingered
in its black lodge like a brave who has walked far, and keeps his
tepee because the way was hard and long.

</p><p>

 All through the time of the growing and dying moon, the
Omahas had sought for the bison.  Upon a hundred hills they had
halted to gaze beneath the arched hand into the lonely valleys,
from whence came no sound of lowing cows nor roaring bulls.  Like
the voice of famine through the lonesome air came the caw-caw of
the crow.  Like heaps of bleaching skeletons the far off sage
brush whitened.

</p><p>This evening as the women busied themselves with the
building of the tepees, there was no crooning on their lips.  The
valley, in which they were pitching their camp, was still but for
the clattering of the poles as they were placed in their conical
positions, or the flap of the blankets that were being bound
about the poles for a covering.  At dreary intervals a grazing
pony would toss its weary head and neigh nervously as if
wondering at the stillness of its masters.

</p><p>The silent squaws gathered armfuls of scrub oak and plum twigs
and lit fires that lapped the blackening air with hungry tongues
and sent their voices roaring up the hills, to be answered by
their echoes, that came back faintly like the lowing of a phantom
herd.

</p><p>The old men and the braves sat about the fires, and no word
was on their tongues.  From lip to lip the fragrant pipe passed,
yet even its softening influence could not move to speech the
lips it kissed.  Each face, upon which the firelight fell, was
hideous with the gauntness of hunger.

</p><p>One by one the runners, sent out in search of the herds,
came into camp.  With a slow, swinging trot these great lean men
approached, as the gaunt wolf approaches his lair in the cold
light of the morning after a lonesome night when no prey has been
abroad.  Sullen and silent they took their places in the cheerless
circle about the fires.  There was no need for words from them.
Their expectant companions looked into their stolid faces and
read the tale of despair so readily from the drawn skin and
sunken eyes, that they groaned!  That was the only sound to
betray the suffering of these stoical wolf-men.

</p><p>The glow of the West fell into the grayness of ashes, as a
camp fire falls when all the women sleep.  Then the dark came
over the eastern hills.  Far into the night the braves sat about
the fires, speechless.  As they listened, they could hear the
hungry children whining in their sleep.  Once a squaw, suddenly
awakening from her dreaming slumber near the <pb n="545"/>
fires, leaped to her feet and cried, "Ta, ta!"  ("Bison,
bison!")  The hoarse cry beat against the black hills and came
back like a mockery.  The men gazed into each other's faces and
grinned with twitching lips.

</p><p>Again the lonesome air slumbered, save for a weird,
monotonous song that arose from the tepee of the big medicine
man, Ashunhunga.  He was calling to Wakunda (God).  The song
droned itself into silence like the song of a locust when the
evening is quiet.

</p><p>After some time a sound of wailing came from the mysterious
tepee; and as the men turned their faces to the place, they
beheld the half-naked form of the medicine man passing like a
spectre amid the glow of the fires!  The dry skin clung to his
ribs and sinews.  His head was thrown back and the fires lit his
face.  Through his parted lips the white teeth shone.  Out of the
hollows of his eyes a wild light glared.  The dream was upon
him!  With bony hands clinched he beat his naked breast and cried:

</p><p>"Wa-hoo-ha-a!  Wa-hoo-ha-a!  The curse of Wakunda is upon
us!  The black spirits of the dead are about us!  For lo!
Ashunhunga has had a dream.  A black spirit came to him and its
were lightning and its voice was thunder as it said: 'Why do you
shelter him whom Wakunda hates?' Wa-hoo-ha-a!  Wa-hoo-ha-a!"

</p><p>Blood fell from the mysterious man's hands where the nails
clenched convulsively, and his arms and breast were smeared with
blood!  The listeners shuddered as the wild voice began anew.

</p><p>"Ashunhunga will talk to the black spirit.  He will learn
whom Wakunda hates.  Him shall we cast from us; then Wakunda will
smile and the valleys shall be thunderous with herds!"

</p><p>Beating his breast and gesticulating wildly with his long
bony arms, the old man passed back amid the tepees with wailing.
Those who sat about the fires were frozen by the wild words into
bronze statues of Fear!  Scarcely was a breath drawn.  Not a
muscle moved.  The black spirits of the dead were about them!  Not
a hand was raised to replenish the fires with fagots; the flames
sank and the embers sent a dull blue light upon the circle of
haggard faces.

</p><p>As Ashunhunga passed on toward his tepee he suddenly stumbled over a
shivering form, huddled closely into the shadow.  Quickly regaining his feet, he
saw that upon which he had stumbled.  It was a dwarfed, ill-shapen human body,
with short, crooked legs and long emaciated arms with grinning joints.  The form
raised itself upon his hands and knees, and looked upon the medicine man with
an idiotic leer upon its face.  It was Shanugahi Nettle, the cripple.
With a cry as of a squaw who sees a black spirit in her
sleep, Ashunhunga rushed into his tepee.  His mystical songs
wailed over the camp for a while; then ceased.  Ashunhunga,
overcome by his fanatical emotions, had fallen into a swoon.

</p><p>And he had a dream:
He was alone upon the prairie and hunger was pinching his entrails.  Then
there came a bison bull toward him, roaring through the silence!
He raised his bow and with sure aim sent an arrow singing into
the heart of the beast.  Then the air grew black save for a blue
light as of dying fires.  The bison began to change form!  Its
hind legs grew short and crooked; its front legs became long and
lean and sinewy like the arms of a starving man.  Its body
dwindled, dwindled, and it was human!  Its head became
indistinct, and wavered as with a haze.  Then it grew up boldly
in the ghastly light, and the face was the face of Shanugahi with
the idiot leer!

</p><p>The vision whirled giddily and sank into the dizzy
darkness.  With a cry as of one who is stabbed in his sleep,
Ashunhunga sprang from his blankets and rushed out of the tepee!

</p><p>Those who sat about the smouldering fires, startled from their dumb terror
by the cry, raised their faces and gazed upon that of the medicine man as he
passed.  They did not speak, but the question in their eyes was: "Who?"
"It is Shanugahi!" said Ashunhunga, in an aweing whisper.
"It is Shanugahi whom Wakunda hates; he has brought
<pb n="546"/>
the curse upon us!"
</p>

<p> ******* </p>


<p>The ill-shapen bronze mass of flesh
which was Shanugahi lay curled up in heavy slumber in the shadow
of a tepee.  Suddenly its sleep was broken by a heavy hand
reaching out of the darkness.  Shanugahi shook himself like a dog
roused from sleep, raised his head and gazed about.  He saw the
faces of a number of braves indistinct in the dim glow of the
fires.  Near by a pony, with a thong in its mouth, stood ready
for a rider.  A strange voice close to him whispered hoarsely:

</p><p>"Fly!  Fly!  The black spirits of the dead are about you!  The curse of
Wakunda is upon you.  Fly!"

</p><p>Shanugahi stared quickly about him, then turned his meaningless eyes
upon his tribesmen and leered.
Strong arms seized him and placed him astride the waiting
pony.  The thong was put in his hands.  Some one lashed the pony
across the haunches and it plunged down the valley into the
darkness!

</p><p>When the dazed rider had gone some distance, the meaning of
the whispered words came upon him.  Cold sweat sprang out on his
limbs.  He glanced behind him, and the night was swarming with
demons!  His shriek cut the stillness like a knife of ice!  He
grasped the mane of the pony with a convulsive clasp.  He dashed
his heels into the flanks of the terrorized brute.  The lone
gulches thundered with the beat of hoofs!  Bushes flew past, and
each was a pursuing black spirit!  Shanugahi clung closely to the
pony's back, hiding his face in its mane; clasping its neck with
all the strength of madness; pressing its ribs with his legs
until the straining animal groaned with pain and fright.  Clumps
of sage brush flew past dizzily, and each was a heap of whitened
bones.

</p><p>It was like falling in a nightmare through an unfathomed, immeasurable
black pit, save for the scamper of the coyote, as it sought the gulches whining, or
the tumbling flight of the owl or bat, fleeing upon wings that whirred in the
stillness!

</p><p>The pace of the pony became slower and slower.  Its breath
came in short, rasping gasps.  Then with a last effort of its
terrified limbs, it took the long incline of a hill, and upon the
bare summit tumbled to its knees.  Shanugahi rolled off its back,
and horse and rider, worn out with fright and fatigue, swooned
into heavy slumber.

</p><p>When Shanugahi awoke, the pale light that foregoes the
coming sun, lay upon the shivering hills.  He looked about him
and saw a circle of gray wolves staring at him with eyes like
moons dawn-stricken.  He felt about him for a weapon but found
only his stone pipe and pouch of red willow bark.  He filled his
pipe and lit it with a spark struck from the flint that strewed
the summit.  Then the sun peeped above the far sky line, and,
with its horizontal rays, touched the hills with glory.  Its
light warmed the frozen nerves of Shanugahi.  He puffed gray
rings of smoke into the air.  Then taking his pipe from his
mouth, he reared his hideous body into the glow of morning, and
with a long, bony arm, raised his smoking pipe to the smiling sun
in silent invocation.

</p><p>For some time motionless he stood, like a being of the black
depths praying for the mercy of the shining heights!  Then he
uttered two words:

</p><p>"Wakunda!  Ta!"  The staring wolves, moved by the hoarse,
	  wild voices, raised their noses
to the heavens with a howl, and slunk away into the ravines.


</p><p>The sun rose higher, and Shanugahi breathed into his veins
the laughing gold of the morning.  With all the simplicity of his
nature he forgot the terror of the night.  It was to him as some
vague and transient dream, dreamed many summers past.  Yet the
one fixed idea of finding the bison swayed his whole thought.

</p><p>His hunger had reached that stage in which it acts as a
heavy draught of some subtle intoxicant.  The stupor of days past
had been changed into a joyous and almost hopeful delirium; and
as he looked upon the sun, to him it was the smile of Wakunda.
Now he would find the bison.  He found the pony grazing nearby,
and leaping upon its back he <pb n="547"/>  urged its
stiffened limbs into a jog, and took the lonesome stretch of
prairie with songs upon his lips.

</p><p>All day the pony jogged across the prairie at an easy pace toward the
west.  At that time of the evening when the coolness comes with
the dew and the bugs awake with hummings among the grasses,
Shanugahi caught a roaring sound as of some sullen storm that
thunders beneath the horizon.  He checked his pony, and placing
his hands to his ears, listened intently.  He knew the sound.
Dismounting, he crawled to the top of a hill and looked into a
broad valley.  As far as he could see, straining his eyes, the
valley was black with bison!  For a moment he stood as in a
spell.  Then a great joy lashed his blood into a frenzy.  He
rushed to his pony, and, mounting, turned its head to the east.

</p><p>The night came down, and still Shanugahi held his pony to a
run.  His brain whirled giddily.  Now he had found the bison; his
people would not starve.  He sang and shouted and laughed until
his voice broke into a cackle.  The delirium of the rider was
caught by the pony.  With all the wiry might of long generations
of prairie herds, it sent the thundering hills and valleys under
its flying feet.
</p>

<p> ******* </p>



<p>At that time of the morning when the East grows pale and
slumber is the deepest, the famished tribe, having moved a weary
day's journey westward, was sleeping heavily.  Suddenly a hoarse
shout shattered their dreams and made the hills clamorous with
echoes!  The whole camp leaped from its blankets and stared with
blinking eyes in the direction of the shout.  There upon the brow
of the hill that overlooked the camp, stood a horse and rider,
set in bold relief against the pale sky of the morning!  With a
long bony arm the rider pointed to the westward, and again he
cried in a weak, broken voice:

</p><p>"Ta!  Ta!"

</p><p>Then horse and rider collapsed like the figures of a dream
that wavers with the morning!  A number of braves, running up the
hill, found the bodies of the pony and Shanugahi.  Upon the lips
of the dead rider lingered a calm smile of contentment.

</p><p>"It is the smile of Wakunda!" said one old man in awe.
"Wakunda smiles!" shouted the braves.
The whole camp caught up the cry:
"Bison!  Bison!  Wakunda smiles!  Wakunda smiles!"
And before the sun rose they were moving westward on the trail of
Shanugahi.
</p>


<p>* * * * * * * </p>


<p> Two nights afterward there was joy
in the camp of the Omahas.  Having found the long-sought herd,
they had feasted heavily, and now they slept as the wolf sleeps
when the prey has been plenteous.

</p><p>Beside a fire two old men were still awake, and as they
smoked, they talked of Shanugahi.  He had found the herd.
Wakunda had smiled upon him.  Yet Shanugahi was only a cripple!

</p><p>"Ugh!" they both grunted after a thoughtful silence, shaking
their heads in wonderment at so incomprehensible a thing.  Then,
wrapping themselves in their blankets, they slept.</p>


</div1>
</body>
</text>
</TEI.2>

