<?xml version="1.0"?>

<?dlps id="NorComi"?>
<?dlps page-images="none" figure-images="no"?>
<?dlps transcription="other"?>

<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/tei-p4/tei2.dtd" [
<!ENTITY % POSTKB "INCLUDE">
<!ENTITY % TEI.extensions.ent SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.ent">
<!ENTITY % TEI.extensions.dtd SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.dtd">
<!ENTITY % ISOnum SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/charent/iso-num.ent"> %ISOnum;
<!ENTITY % ISOpub SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/charent/iso-pub.ent"> %ISOpub;
]>

<TEI.2 id="NorComi">
<teiHeader type="migrated" creator="Etext">
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title type="main">Comida: An Experience in Famine.</title>
<title type="sort">comida an experience in famine</title>
<author>Norris, Frank</author>
<respStmt>
<resp>Creation of machine-readable version:</resp>
<name>Judy Boss</name>
<resp>Conversion to TEI.2-conformant markup:</resp>
<name>University of Virginia Library Electronic Text Center</name>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt>
<extent>ca. <num type="kilobytes">25</num> kilobytes</extent>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>University of Virginia Library</publisher>
<pubPlace>Charlottesville, Virginia</pubPlace>
<idno type="ETC">NorComi</idno>
<date value="1995">1995</date>
<availability status="public">
<p n="copyright">Copyright &copy; 1995 by the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia</p>
<p n="access">Publicly accessible</p>
</availability>
<idno type="uva-pid">uva-lib:476256</idno>
</publicationStmt>
<seriesStmt>
<title>University of Virginia Library, Text collection</title>
<idno type="uva-set">UVA-LIB-Text</idno>
</seriesStmt>
<sourceDesc>
<biblFull>
<titleStmt>
<title type="main">Comida: An Experience in Famine.</title>
<title type="sort">comida an experience in famine</title>
<author>Frank Norris</author>
</titleStmt>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>
<hi rend="italic">Atlantic Monthly</hi> no. 83</publisher>
<pubPlace>Boston, Mass.</pubPlace>
<date value="1899">1899</date>
</publicationStmt>
</biblFull>
</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc>
<encodingDesc>
<projectDesc>
<p>Prepared for the University of Virginia Library Electronic Text Center</p>
</projectDesc>
<editorialDecl>
<p>All quotation marks retained as data</p>
<p>All unambiguous end-of-line hyphens have been removed, and the
trailing part of a word has been joined to the preceding line.</p>
<p id="ETC">Keywords in the header are a local Electronic Text Center scheme
to aid in establishing analytical groupings</p>
</editorialDecl>
<refsDecl>
<p>ID elements are given for each page element and are composed of the text's
unique cryptogram and the given page number, as in AusEmma1 for page one of
Jane Austen's Emma.</p>
</refsDecl>
</encodingDesc>
<profileDesc>
<creation>
<date value="1899">1899</date>
</creation>
<langUsage>
<language id="eng" usage="main">English</language>
</langUsage>
<textClass>
<keywords>
<term>non-fiction; prose</term>
</keywords>
</textClass>
</profileDesc>
<revisionDesc>
<change>
<date value="1995-08">August 1995</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>corrector</resp>
<name>Jamie L Spriggs, Electronic Text Center, University of Virginia</name>
<name>Deirdre A Johnson, Electronic Text Center, University of Virginia</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Added header, Tagged with TEI.2-compatible SGML, Parsed against "teilite" dtd</item>
</change>
<change>
<date value="2005-07">July 2005</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>Corrector</resp>
<name>John Ivor Carlson</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Converted to XML and/or checked tags.</item>
</change>
<change>
<date value="2007-09">September 2007</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>Migration</resp>
<name>Ethan Gruber, University of Virginia Library</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Converted XML markup from TEI Lite to uva-dl-tei (TEI P4 with local customizations).</item>
</change>
<change>
<date value="2008-01">January 2008</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>Migration</resp>
<name>Greg Murray, University of Virginia Library</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Programmatically updated TEI header markup (but not header content) for minimal compliance with current QA requirements.</item>
</change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text id="d1">
<body id="d2">

<div1 type="essay" id="d3"><pb n="343"/>
<head>COMIDA: AN EXPERIENCE IN FAMINE.</head>

<p>BY grace of our guide, our phrase book, and our Salva-Webster
Dictionary, we managed to pick up a good deal of Spanish during the
Santiago campaign, but the one word our guide did not tell us, the
one expression we did not look up in the Diccionario, was the very
one we understood most quickly: its meaning was apparent the
instant we heard it uttered.  We shall never forget <hi rend="italic">comida</hi> and
all that it stands for.</p>
<p>It means "food;" not breakfast, dinner, or supper, not food in
dishes and served by a waiter in the hotel, not a polite knife-and-fork affair in any sense of the word.  Comida is downright
nourishment, sordid, vulgar nutriment, of the kind that fills empty
stomachs after a three days' abstinence,&mdash;the kind that we ladled
out of camp kettles to six thousand starving refugee children at
Caney during the second day's truce.  This is comida.  But to get
the full effect of the word you must separate it into syllables,
pronouncing the <hi rend="italic">i</hi> like double <hi rend="italic">e</hi>, and drawing it out into a
pitiful, quavering whine.  Better still, you must hear the word
cried from six thousand shriveled mouths, with appropriate gestures
in the direction of the lips and the pit of the stomach.</p>
<p>"Co-mee-dah!  Co-<hi rend="italic"> mee-e</hi>-dah!"</p>
<p>We rode into Caney late in the afternoon, at about what ought
to have been supper time.  For forty-eight hours the refugees from
Santiago had been coming in.  The civil governor of the city had
told the non-combatants that they would not be out of Santiago more
than twenty-four hours, and had forbidden them the use of any
vehicles; what they carried they must carry on their backs.</p>
<p>At the end of the first day the refugees had eaten such little
food as they took with them on their exodus.  The better class had
missed three consecutive meals, some of the poorer had not eaten in
two days, and for a week previous they had all been slowly starving
in the beleaguered city.</p>
<p>The town of Caney is built around the plaza; a grove of trees
runs down the middle of this plaza; the church, used as a barracks
on the day of the battle, is at one end, the public buildings are
at the other.  When we rode into this square, we found it a
veritable bedlam.  American and European crowds are brown.  A cuban
crowd is white, and looks larger for that reason.  Thousands upon
thousands of men in white linen suits, women in white skirts, and
children in white loin-cloths&mdash;when they wore any clothes at all&mdash;
came and went, up and down, back and forth, in and out, weaving a
maze, a bewildering, shifting web, where warp and woof alike were
white.  Each figure seemed to have a particular definite
destination, quite distinct from his neighbor's,&mdash;a destination
which it was imperative he should reach at once; and for that
reason, he, or more often she, squirmed and pushed and writhed
through the press, using elbow and shoulder with all the strength
of the emaciated body.  But others there were who sat in rows,
double and triple rows, on the edge of the square, prone and inert
amidst the white bundles of their household effects, exhausted,
listless, stunned and stupefied by the terrific clamor.</p>
<p>For, from all these struggling, boiling thousands, from all
this seething mass of white, from the strained and shrunken throats
of all these starvelings, one word&mdash;a cry, a monotonous deafening
plaint&mdash;rose into the air, knocking at one's ears, assaulting one's
attention, persistent, raucous, a piercing wail: "Comida!  Comida!"</p>
<p>In our haversacks we had hard-bread, <pb n="344"/>  bacon, and a
handful of ground coffee,&mdash;our rations for two days.  I reached for
the hard-bread and drew it out.  In an instant my horse was
literally lifted from his feet, and hands, hands, hands,
outstretched, lean, white, black, and brown, small and large, a
thicket growth of hands grew instantly from the crowd.  I gave till
my sack was empty, a hardbread for each hand,&mdash;now to a white hand
and now to a black, so as to keep from repeating as far as
possible.  The bacon and coffee went even more quickly, and were
eaten as they were, raw and uncooked.  But it was only baiting the
crowd; what were two days' rations!</p>
<p>"Comida!  Comida!"</p>
<p>We pushed our horses across the plaza to the church.  The red
cross had just been established on a terrace adjoining.  A negro
trooper was on guard, and inside the wall, on the terrace itself,
kettles were being set out and bags of corn meal opened.  Here,
alone, with no one to help him but a couple of utterly inefficient
Cubans, we met with an old friend, Dr. Bangs, of the hospital ship
State of Texas.</p>
<p>Let us pause to make a note of Dr. Bangs, for he was at last
the right man in the right place.  He was a stout man, with a very
red face and a voice like the exhaust of a locomotive.  He wore an
absurd pith helmet battered out of all shape, and his beard was a
fortnight old.  But there was the right stuff in Dr. Bangs.  Early
and late, hot or cold, rain or shine, the doctor toiled and toiled
and toiled; feeding the thousands, building fires, sending this man
for wood and that man for water, perspiring, gesticulating,
bellowing, but in the end "getting the thing into shape," directing
and dividing the stream of supplies till the last refugee was fed.
But that was not until afterward.  It was a two days' labor, and on
that particular evening everybody was still hungry,&mdash;hungry to
starvation point.</p>
<p>At once he impressed us&mdash;willing enough we were&mdash;into the
service.  "Now, fellows," he shouted,&mdash;he always shouted, did the
doctor,&mdash;"we want to get at the children first!  Tell 'em to send
up the children first!"  With a crowd's instinct, a hungry crowd's
instinct, for food, the refugees had divined that the terrace by
the church was to be the distributing point.  We went back to the
edge of the terrace, and with the full strength of our lungs
shouted for the space of five minutes (after consulting our phrase
book): "Ninos primero!  Ninos primero!"  "Comida!" shouted the
crowd in answer.  "Comida!  Comida!" deaf to everything but the
clamor of empty stomachs.  But somehow at last they understood;
somehow at last wood was found, three huge fires were built, and
camp kettles (borrowed from Mr. Ramsden, the British consul) filled
with corn-meal mush set a-cooking.  It was six o'clock when we
began.  The terrace was just high enough to shut out the view of
the plaza, but at every fresh suggestion that the distribution was
to begin, a waving forest of hands topped the terrace wall, and the
lamentable wail broke out afresh, "Comida!  Comida!"</p>
<p>By seven o'clock this cry changed in volume.  It was no longer
deep-toned; it began to be shrill and piping, and there were no
more hands above the terrace wall.  We did not like to look over
the wall; it was not a pleasant sight, and our appearance only
awakened false hopes, but we knew that the children were
assembling.  "Tell 'em," roared the doctor, wiping the sweat from
his forehead with the back of the hand that held the ladle, "tell
'em it's 'most done,&mdash;tell 'em pretty soon now."</p>
<p>I went to the edge of the terrace, and leaned over.  It was
yet light enough to see, to see about three thousand children, half
of them naked, the other half ragged beyond words.  What a mass!
Close to the gate the jam was terrific; they were packed as sand is
packed, so that they moved, not as individuals, but <pb n="345"/>  as
groups and masses, swaying forward and back, and from side to side,
without knowing why.  I could see but a pavement of faces, crushed
together cheek to cheek, upturned, pinched and agonized, shrill-voiced with the little rat that nipped and gnawed at their poor
starved stomachs.  Further on, where the press was not so great,
the children reached toward me empty cans, pots, pails, tin cups,
vessels of all sizes and descriptions, and they put their hands
(not their fingers) to their mouths with always the same cry of
unutterable distress, "Comida!  Comida!"</p>
<p>"Poco tiempo!" I called to them.  "Poquito tiempo!"  And at
last they understood, and were quiet for nearly a minute.  When I
went back the doctor took me aside.</p>
<p>"Now," he shouted, "there's something I want you to look after
personally.  There's an old woman"&mdash;he pointed her out, sitting in
a pathetic round heap on the chapel steps&mdash;"who hasn't had anything
to eat in three days.  When we're ready to distribute, I want you
to see to it yourself that she gets something.  Understand?  She's
been waiting her two hours."</p>
<p>I told him that I understood, and we went back to work.  Ten
minutes later the corn meal was ready.  One of us was to stand at
each of the kettles with a tin army cup in hand.  The children were
to be let in in groups of twenty; and of these twenty, five at a
time were to come up to the kettles to have us ladle out the meal
into their tin pails or cups, or whatever they should bring.</p>
<p>"Now do you catch on to that?" roared the doctor.</p>
<p>"Perfectly.  Are we all ready?"</p>
<p>"Yes."</p>
<p>"Where's the old woman?"</p>
<p>She had gone.  Tired out with waiting, she had quietly gone
away.  For nearly three hours she had sat patiently on the chapel
steps, waiting, waiting, confused, dazed, and misconstruing the
broken Spanish that was spoken to her.  Then at last, at the end of
hope, she had gone away.  I could see her plainly in the
imagination, can see her now, her back bent, weak, worn out, going
away meekly almost at the very moment that the food was being
brought to her.  I had that old woman on my conscience for a long
time.</p>
<p>The doctor went to the gate and let in twenty children.  But
twenty more instantly crowded in, then thirty, then fifty, a
hundred, two hundred, five hundred, a thousand.  The whole rout of
starving little wretches invaded the terrace, took it by assault,
and huddled in one corner, dazzled by the light of the fires,
bewildered, a little frightened, but insistent still, goaded on by
their hunger, and muttering under their breath, "Comida!  Comida!"</p>
<p>Well, we had to drive them back into their corner,&mdash;drive them
back brutally and by main strength.  But even as I pushed and
thrust, a little hand&mdash;ever so little a hand&mdash;took hold of my
wrist.  It was that of a tiny girl, almost too weak to stand, but
she held a pitiful empty sardine can toward me, and whispered
confidentially, with a great attempt at cheerfulness, "Comida, eh?
Comida por me?" and put her hand, not to her lips, but to her
stomach.  We came to know this gesture afterward.  So long as they
pointed to their mouths we could allow the applicants to wait their
turn, but when they pointed to their stomachs we knew that we must
be quick and that it was almost time for the restoratives.</p>
<p>We began the distribution.  We drew a line in the dust in
front of the crowd, and announced that any who crossed that line
should have no comida: that kept them in hand fairly well.  They
came up in groups of five, and we gave to each three quarters of a
cupful of corn-meal porridge, and caused each one to pass out
through the door of the chapel so soon as his or her measure was
full.  They were docile enough then, and watched us <pb n="346"/>  gravely
and quietly as we filled their cups.  None of them, so far as I
could see, ate any of their corn meal upon the spot.</p>
<p>The worst of it was that the meal gave out before all were
fed, and we had to tell some twenty of them that there was "no mas
esta noche" (no more tonight), and they were to come back "manana
a ocho hora."  I do not like to think of this part of the business.
To have been so hungry, to have waited so long, to have come so
near and seen so many others fed, and then&mdash;  No, one had better
pass this over,&mdash;this and the old woman.</p>
<p>The last child had gone supperless to such bed as he could
find, and we were thinking of our own beds, when a girl of perhaps
sixteen presented herself.  "No more," we told her,&mdash;"no mas
comida; come back manana."  But it was not comida that this one
wanted.</p>
<p>"Enfermo," she answered.  I wish you could have heard the
pitiful quaver of the voice.  "Enfermo,"&mdash;a little, a very little
more, and it would have been a sob.  She was very frail and a nice-looking girl, taking her altogether; sick and absolutely alone
amongst all those thousands.  "Enfermo," she said again, looking
fixedly at the embers of the expiring fires.  We had her taken over
to Mr. Ramsden's house, with a note giving directions as to what
should be done for her.  Poor, frail, weak-voiced creature!  We
never saw her again.</p>
<p>Making our own camp that night was no trivial affair.  We had
had no supper, but we were far too tired to think of cooking one.
The horses had been picketed behind the church, but for their
better security we broke in the doors at the rear and led them
through the chapel and out upon the terrace.  We off-saddled in the
chapel itself, and, I am rather ashamed to add, used the communion
rail as a saddle rack.  But there was little of the sacerdotal left
to the chapel at that time.  It was extremely and intensely
profaned, was that chapel, loopholed for Mausers, with Mauser
ammunition pouches and bayonet scabbards, cartridges and empty
Spanish haversacks, strewing the floor and littering the altar
itself.  Three huge, half-empty boxes of clothing from Waltham,
Massachusetts, stood about, and there were some Red Cross flour,
sugar, and meal sacks.  While we were off-saddling, my horse&mdash;a
broncho pony from Southern California&mdash;elected to become frightened
at the torn altar cloth that trailed and flapped in the draught
between two loopholes, and for a moment had the whole place by the
ears.  And all this while, over the altar, Mary the mother of God,
in the flaring light of the commissary candles, looked down upon us
and the disordered chapel as calmly as ever she had looked upon the
kneeling peasants in the light of burning tapers.  It was a
strange, incongruous scene,&mdash;the shattered chapel, the bayonet
scabbards, the Mauser cartridges clinking underfoot, the prim stiff
calicoes and ginghams from Waltham, and the cow-puncher's pony
shying from an altar cloth woven by fingers that were dust two
hundred years ago.</p>
<p>We were tired enough, Heaven knows, and keyed up to the
highest tension, so that one of the incidents that closed that
eventful day affected us more deeply and keenly than otherwise it
might have done.  We were all standing by the fire just before
turning in, listening to the starving thousands settling themselves
to sleep close at hand, when the doctor suddenly exclaimed, in that
thunderous trumpet voice of his, "Well, fellows, here's something
I do every night that you can't do at all!" and with the words he
took out his left eye and polished it on a leg of his trousers.  I
was faint in an instant, the thing was so unexpected, so positively
ghastly.  Not even the sight of the division hospital, a week
before, had so upset me.</p>
<p>When we woke in the morning,&mdash;<pb n="347"/> very early,&mdash;we found
that we ourselves had been sleeping under strange conditions.  The
main body of the church had been used as a hospital.  An amputated
arm had been buried in the dirt of the terrace close to where we
had spread our blankets,&mdash;half buried, as we were able to judge in
the morning.  This grisly relic had flanked us on one side all
night, two yellow-fever cases occupied another side, a thousand
starving refugees were on the third, while the desecrated chapel
with all its incongruities confronted us upon the fourth.  But this
was not all.  For fear of the rain we had roofed ourselves in with
boards that we had found lying in and about the chapel.  In the
light of the morning we saw that one of these was the signboard of
the church, but also that it was coated thick with a glaze of dull
red.</p>
<p>"Comida!  Comida!"</p>
<p>Even army bacon, coffee, and hardbread lose their flavor when
this cry comes between you and your tin mess kit.  We were not long
at breakfast, and by the time I had come back from watering the
horses the doctor had the kettles going.  We promptly ran short of
wood, and announced over the parapet of the terrace that all those
who should bring us wood for the fires should be fed first.  To
those who offered themselves for this service we gave tickets, made
by breaking pasteboard ammunition boxes into squares, and writing
thereon the name of Dr. Bangs.  For two hours the crowd around the
terrace grew, and grew, and grew, until I veritably believe half of
Santiago was there, stretching toward us innumerable empty pots,
pans, and tin pails, and with thousands of voices wailing, "Comida!
Comida!"</p>
<p>We let the starvelings into the inclosure of the parapet when
the corn meal was ready, and ladled to them by the hour, as we had
done to the children the night before.  The children who had missed
their food in the evening came back now and received double
rations; but they fought on the steps of the terrace,&mdash;men, women,
and children,&mdash;and gashed one another with the sharp edges of their
tins, as they struggled for first place in a way that was sickening
to see.</p>
<p>Yet in spite of these things it was not always easy to believe
that <hi rend="italic">all</hi> of these people were in actual need of food,&mdash;as they
indubitably were.  You almost perforce associate starvation with
rags.  It is difficult to imagine a well-dressed person as hungry;
you cannot but believe that clean linen and smart gowns cover well-fed bodies.  Or even though you know hunger to exist in such a
case, you can scarcely bring yourself to take it seriously.  You
refuse to consider it as anything more terrible than an exaggerated
appetite.</p>
<p>There were plenty of such cases at Caney on that day.  We met
with one of them, and made a mistake which we shall always
remember.  We had been down in the plaza and around the outskirts
of the crowd, taking pictures and snapshots, and were working our
way slowly back to the steps of the terrace, when we came upon two
very pretty and very neatly dressed girls of perhaps eighteen and
nineteen.</p>
<p>"Comida?" they asked, both in a breath.</p>
<p>We told them that we would ourselves get them comida, and at
once; they should not wait for the regular distribution.  Ah, that
was kind, they answered, and they thanked us very prettily.  With
that the idea of corn-meal porridge vanished entirely from our
thick, stupid Anglo-Saxon minds, and we fell a-talking to them.
Both would have passed for pretty girls anywhere, and one of them
carried a pink silk parasol.  Of course we were idiots, but it is
hard to reconcile a pink silk parasol with famine; and though we
knew that they were hungry, we forgot, and passed it over as the
hunger of a girl at an evening dance,&mdash;forgot,
<pb n="348"/>
I say, and
went on talking to them in our halting, broken-backed Spanish,
until one of them gave a little tremulous gasp and broke into
tears.  We remembered quickly enough then, and it was with the
feeling of assassins that we hurried them off through the crowd and
around to the back door of the church.  We had both of us "got a
girl something to eat" before, at teas and functions at home, when
we had fought our way through the press, but this was a strange
variation on the old theme.  Now the stuffed olives and lettuce
sandwiches were corn meal porridge and commissary canned beans, and
the girls had not eaten in two and a half days.</p>
<p>We stayed at Caney nearly all the next day, helping the
doctor, who but for us was entirely alone.  As for the relief
committees composed of Cubans, the less said of them the better.
They were supposed to cooperate with the doctor, and might have
been of immense service during those terrible three days of famine.
They were there, these committees, for we saw them as they came to
offer congratulations and to be presented.  But beyond this their
activity did not go.  They did absolutely nothing,&mdash;lit never a
fire, gathered never a stick of wood, drew never a quart of water.</p>
<p>"I don't want your congratulations!" the harassed, overworked
doctor bellowed.  "I don't want your presentations!
I want <hi rend="italic">wood</hi>, I want <hi rend="italic">water</hi>, and oh,
I want those fifty cases of <hi rend="italic">condensed milk!"</hi></p>
<p>The loss of this condensed milk was a grievance which the
doctor could not forget.  To the Cubans had been intrusted the duty
of transporting fifty cases from Siboney to Caney.  The milk never
arrived, and I know of one little baby who died in its mother's
arms for lack of it.  How many more died, unknown and unnoted?
Twenty? a dozen? six?  Hard to say.  That one, at least, was not
saved is laid to the account of that Cuban relief committee.</p>
<p>Food and workers were alike insufficient to meet the demands
of thirty thousand starving people on those first two days.  We
stayed and worked as long as we could, and a little after noon we
rode away in a drenching rain.  But for nearly half a mile down the
road, as our steaming horses toiled through mud, fetlock-deep, the
vague murmur of the crowd in the plaza came back to us, prolonged,
lamentable, pitiful beyond expression,&mdash;the cry of people dying for
lack of food.</p>
<p>Comida!  Comida!</p>
                                  <signed><hi rend="italic"> Frank Norris.</hi></signed>

</div1>
</body>
</text>
</TEI.2>
