<?xml version="1.0"?>

<?dlps id="NorShip"?>
<?dlps page-images="none" figure-images="no"?>
<?dlps transcription="other"?>

<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/tei-p4/tei2.dtd" [
<!ENTITY % POSTKB "INCLUDE">
<!ENTITY % TEI.extensions.ent SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.ent">
<!ENTITY % TEI.extensions.dtd SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.dtd">
<!ENTITY % ISOnum SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/charent/iso-num.ent"> %ISOnum;
<!ENTITY % ISOpub SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/charent/iso-pub.ent"> %ISOpub;

]>
<TEI.2 id="NorShip">
<teiHeader type="migrated" creator="Etext">
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title type="main">The Ship That Saw a Ghost</title>
<title type="sort">ship that saw a ghost</title>
<author>Norris, Frank</author>
<respStmt>
<resp>Creation of machine-readable version:</resp>
<name>Judy Boss</name>
<resp>Creation of digital images:</resp>
<name/>
<resp>Conversion to TEI.2-conformant markup:</resp>
<name>University of Virginia Library Electronic Text Center.</name>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt>
<extent>ca. <num type="kilobytes">36</num> kilobytes</extent>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>University of Virginia Library</publisher>
<pubPlace>Charlottesville, Virginia</pubPlace>
<idno type="ETC">NorShip</idno>
<date value="1996">1996</date>
<availability status="public">
<p n="copyright">Copyright &copy; 1996 by the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia</p>
<p n="access">Publicly accessible</p>
</availability>
<idno type="uva-pid">uva-lib:476258</idno>
</publicationStmt>
<seriesStmt>
<title>University of Virginia Library, Text collection</title>
<idno type="uva-set">UVA-LIB-Text</idno>
</seriesStmt>
<notesStmt>
<note>
<p>Judy Boss made the following editorial changes to the print version: page 490, paragraph 4, line 3, "Strakher" to "Strokher"; page 492, paragraph 1, line 10, "father" to "farther"; page 492, paragraph 2, line 2, "neigbor's" to "neighbor's"; page 495, paragraph 12, line 3, "house" to "house."; page 498, paragraph 2, line 8, "docilly" to "docilely"; page 498, paragraph 2, line 10, "stubornly" to "stubbornly".</p>
</note>
</notesStmt>
<sourceDesc>
<biblFull>
<titleStmt>
<title type="main">The Ship That Saw a Ghost</title>
<title level="j">Overland Monthly</title>
<title type="sort">ship that saw a ghost</title>
<author>Frank Norris</author>
</titleStmt>
<editionStmt>
<p>1st Edition</p>
</editionStmt>
<extent>pp. 489-499</extent>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>F. Marriott</publisher>
<pubPlace>San Francisco</pubPlace>
<date value="1902-12">December 1902</date>
<idno type="callNo">Print copy consulted: UVa Library Call Number: Micfilm S-147</idno>
</publicationStmt>
</biblFull>
</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc>
<encodingDesc>
<projectDesc>
<p>Prepared for the University of Virginia Library Electronic Text Center.</p>
</projectDesc>
<editorialDecl>
<p>All quotation marks retained as data.</p>
<p>All unambiguous end-of-line hyphens have been removed, and the trailing part of a word has been joined to the preceding line.</p>
<p>The images exist as archived TIFF images, one or more JPEG versions for general use, and thumbnail GIFs.</p>
<p>Keywords in the header are a local Electronic Text Center scheme to aid in establishing analytical groupings.</p>
</editorialDecl>
</encodingDesc>
<profileDesc>
<creation>
<date value="1902-12">December 1902</date>
</creation>
<langUsage>
<language id="eng" usage="main">English</language>
</langUsage>
<textClass>
<keywords>
<term>fiction; prose</term>
</keywords>
</textClass>
</profileDesc>
<revisionDesc>
<change>
<date value="1996-11">November 1996</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>corrector</resp>
<name>Craig Simmons; Electronic Text Center at The University of Virginia</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Added TEI header and tags</item>
</change>
<change>
<date value="2005-07">July 2005</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>Corrector</resp>
<name>John Ivor Carlson</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Converted to XML and/or checked tags.</item>
</change>
<change>
<date value="2007-09">September 2007</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>Migration</resp>
<name>Ethan Gruber, University of Virginia Library</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Converted XML markup from TEI Lite to uva-dl-tei (TEI P4 with local customizations).</item>
</change>
<change>
<date value="2008-01">January 2008</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>Migration</resp>
<name>Greg Murray, University of Virginia Library</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Programmatically updated TEI header markup (but not header content) for minimal compliance with current QA requirements.</item>
</change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text id="d1">
<body id="d2">


<div1 type="story" id="d3"><pb n="489"/>
<head><hi rend="italic">The Ship That Saw a Ghost</hi>
<lb/><lb/><hi rend="italic">BY FRANK NORRIS</hi> <ref target="n1">[1]</ref>
<lb/><lb/>Copyrighted, 1902.
</head>

<p>
VERY much of this story must remain untold, for the reason that if
it were definitely known what business I had aboard the tramp
steam-freighter Glarus, three hundred miles off the South American
coast on a certain summer's day some few years ago, I would very
likely be obliged to answer a great many personal and direct
questions put by fussy and impertinent experts in maritime law&mdash;who are
paid to be inquisitive.  Also, I would get "Ally Bazan,"
Strokher and Hardenberg into trouble.

</p><p>Suppose, on that certain summer's day, you had asked of
Lloyd's agency where the Glarus was, and what was her destination
and cargo.  You would have been told that she was twenty days out
from Callao, bound north to San Francisco in ballast; that she had
been spoken by the bark Medea and the steamer Benevento; that she
was reported to have blown out a cylinder head, but being
manageable, was proceeding on her way under sail.

</p><p>That is what Lloyd's would have answered.

</p><p>If you know something of the ways of ships and what is
expected of them, you will understand that the Glarus to be some
half a dozen hundred miles south of where Lloyd's would have her,
and to be still going south, under full steam, was a scandal that
would have made her brothers and sisters ostracize her finally and
forever.

</p><p>And that is curious, too.  Humans may indulge in vagaries
innumerable, and may go far afield in the way of lying; but a ship
may not so much as quibble without suspicion.  The least lapse of
"regularity," the least difficulty in squaring performance with
intuition, and behold

<pb n="490"/>
she is on the black list and her captain, owners, officers, agents
and consignors, and even supercargoes are asked to explain.

</p><p>And the Glarus was already on the blacklist.  From the
beginning her stars had been malign.  As the Breda, she had first
lost her reputation, seduced into a filibustering escapade down the
South American coasts, where in the end a plain-clothes United
States detective&mdash;that is to say a revenue cutter&mdash;arrested her off
Buenos Ayres and brought her home, a prodigal daughter,
besmirched and disgraced.

</p><p>After that she was in some dreadful black-birding business in a
far quarter of the South Pacific; and after that&mdash;her name changed
finally to the Glarus&mdash;poached seals for a syndicate of Dutchmen
who lived in Tacoma, and who afterwards built a club house out of
what she earned.

</p><p>And after that we got her.

</p><p>We got her, I say, through Ryder's South Pacific Exploitation
Company.  The "President" had picked out a lovely, lively little deal
for Hardenberg, Strokher and Ally Bazan (the three Black Crows),
which he swore would make them "independent rich" the rest of
their respective lives.  It is a promising deal (B. 300 it is on Ryder's
map), and if you want to know more about it you may write to ask
Ryder what B. 300 is.  If he chooses to tell you that is his affair.

</p><p>For B. 300&mdash;let us confess it&mdash;is, as Hardenberg puts it, as
crooked as a dog's hind leg.  It is as risky as barratry.  If you pull it
off you may&mdash;after paying Ryder his share&mdash;divide sixty-five, or
possibly sixty-seven, thousand dollars betwixt you and your
associates.  If you fail, and you are perilously like to fail, you will
be sure to have a man or two of your companions shot, maybe
yourself obliged to pistol certain people, and in the end fetch up at
Tahiti, prisoner in a French patrol boat.

</p><p>Observe that B. 300 is spoken of as still open.  It is so, for the
reason that the Three Black Crows did not pull it off.  It still stands
marked up in red ink on the map that hangs over Ryder's desk in the
San Francisco office; and anyone can have a chance at it who will
meet Cyrus Ryder's terms.  Only he can't get the Glarus for the
attempt.

</p><p>For the trip to the island after B. 300 was the last occasion on
which the Glarus

<pb n="491"/> will smell blue water or taste the trades.
She will never clear again.  She is lumber.

</p><p>And yet the Glarus on this very blessed day of 1902 is riding
to her buoys off Sausalito in San Francisco bay, complete in every
detail (bar a broken propeller shaft), not a rope missing, not a screw
loose, not a plank started&mdash;a perfectly equipped steam-freighter.

</p><p>But you may go along the Front in San Francisco from
Fisherman's Wharf to the China steamships' docks and shake your
dollars under the seamen's noses, and if you so much as whisper
Glarus they will edge suddenly off and look at you with scared
suspicion, and then, as like as not, walk away without another word.
No pilot will take the Glarus out; no captain will navigate her; no
stoker will feed her fires; no sailor will walk her decks.  The Glarus
is suspect.  She has seen a ghost.

</p><p>* * * * * * *

</p><p>It happened on our voyage to the Island after this same B. 300.
We had stood well off from shore for day after day, and Hardenberg
had shaped our course so far from the track of navigation that since
the Benevento had hulled down and vanished over the horizon, no
stitch of canvas nor smudge of smoke had we seen.  We had passed
the Equator long since, and would fetch a long circuit to the
southard, and bear up against the Island by a circuitous route.  This
to avoid being spoken.  It was tremendously essential that the
Glarus should not be spoken.  I suppose, no doubt, that it was the
knowledge of our isolation that impressed me with the dreadful
remoteness of our position.  Certainly the sea in itself looks no
different at a thousand than at a hundred miles from shore.  But as
day after day I came out on deck, at noon, after ascertaining our
position on the chart (a mere pin point in a reach of empty paper),
the sight of the ocean weighed down upon me with an infinitely
great awesomeness&mdash;and I was no new hand to the high seas even
then.

</p><p>But at such times the Glarus seemed to me to be threading a
loneliness beyond all words and beyond all conception desolate.
Even in more populous waters, when no sail notches the line of the
horizon, the propinquity of one's kind is nevertheless a thing
understood, and to an unappreciated degree, comforting.  Here,
however, I knew we were out, far out in the desert.  Never a keel for
years upon years before us had parted these waters, never a sail had
bellied to these winds.  Perfunctorily, day in and day out we turned
our eyes through long habit towards the horizon.  But we knew,
before the look, that the searching would be bootless.  Forever and
forever, under the pitiless sun and cold blue sky stretched the indigo
of the ocean floor.  The ether between the planets can be no less
empty, no less void.  I never, till that moment, could have so much
as conceived the imagination of such loneliness, such utter stagnant
abomination of desolation.  In an open boat, bereft of comrades, I
should have gone mad in thirty minutes.

</p><p>I remember to have approximated the impression of such
empty immensity only once before, in my younger days, when I lay
on my back on a treeless, bushless mountain side, and stared up into
the sky for the better part of an hour.  You probably know the trick.
If you do not, you must understand that if you look up at the blue
long enough, steadily enough, the flatness of the thing begins little
by little to expand, to give here and there; and the eye travels on and
on and up and up, till at length (well for you that it lasts but the
fraction of a second), you all at once see space.  You generally stop
there and cry out, and&mdash;your hands over your eyes&mdash;are only too glad
to grovel close to the good old solid earth again.  Just as I, so often
on short voyage, was glad to wrench my eyes away from that horrid
vacancy, to fasten them upon our sailless masts and stack, or to lay
my grip upon the sooty smudged taffrail of the only thing that stood
between me and the Outer Dark.

</p><p>For we had come at last to that region of the Great Seas, where
no ship goes, the silent sea of Coleridge and the Ancient One, the
unplumbed, untracked, uncharted

<pb n="492"/> Dreadfulness, primordial, hushed, and
we were as much alone as a grain of star
dust whirling in the empty space beyond Uranus and the ken of the
greater telescopes.

</p><p>So the Glarus plodded and churned her way onward.  Every
day and all day the same pale blue sky and unwinking sun bent over
that moving speck.  Every day and all day the same black-blue
water-world, untouched by any known wind, smooth as a slab of
syenite, colorful as an opal, stretched out and around and beyond
and before and behind us, forever, illimitable, empty.  Every day the
smoke of our fires veiled the streaked whiteness of our wake.  Every
day Hardenberg (our skipper) at noon pricked a pin-hole in the chart
that hung in the wheel house, and that showed we were so much
farther into the wilderness.  Every day the world of men, of
civilization, of newspapers, policemen, and street railways, receded,
and we steamed on alone, lost and forgotten in that silent sea.

</p><p>"Jolly lot o' room to turn raound in," observed Ally Bazan, the
colonial, "withaout steppin' on y'r neighbor's toes."

</p><p>"We're clean, clean out o' the track of navigation," Hardenberg
told him.  "An' a blessed good thing for us, too.  Nobody ever comes
down into these waters.  Ye couldn't pick no course here.
Everything leads to nowhere."

</p><p>"Might as well be in a bally balloon," said Strokher.

</p><p>I shall not tell of the nature of the venture on which the Glarus
was bound, further than to say it was not legitimate.  It had to do
with an ill thing done over two centuries ago.  There was money in
the venture, but it was to be gained by a violation of metes and
bounds which are better left intact.

</p><p>The island toward which we were heading is associated in the
minds of men with a Horror.  A Ship had called there once, two
hundred years in advance of the Glarus&mdash;a ship not much unlike the
crank high-prowed caravel of Hudson, and her company had landed,
and having accomplished the evil they had set out to do, made shift
to sail away.  And then, just after the palms of the island had sunk
from sight below the water's edge, the unspeakable had happened.
The Death that was not Death had arisen from out the sea and stood
before the Ship; and over it and the blight of the thing lay along the
decks like mould, and the ship sweated in the terror of that which is
yet without a name.  Twenty men died in the first week, all but six
in the second.  These six, with the shadow of insanity upon them,
made out to launch a boat, returned to the island and died there,
after leaving a record of what had happened.

</p><p>The six left the ship exactly as she was, sails all set, lanterns
all lit, left her in the shadow of the Death that was not Death.  The
wind made at the time, they said, and as they bent to their bars, she
sailed after them, for all the world like a thing refusing to abandon
them or be herself abandoned, till the wind died down.  Then they
left her behind, and she stood there, becalmed, and watched them
go.  She was never heard of again.

</p><p>Or was she&mdash;well, that's as may be.

</p><p>But the main point of the whole affair to my notion, has
always been this.  The ship was the last friend of those six poor
wretches who made back for the island with their poor chests of
plunder.  She was their guardian, as it were, would have defended
and befriended them to the last; and also we, the Three Black Crows
and myself, had no right under heaven, nor before the law of men,
to come prying and peeping into this business&mdash;into this affair of the
dead and buried past.  There was sacrilege in it.  We were no better
than body snatchers.

</p><p>* * * * * *

</p><p>When I heard the others complaining of the loneliness of our
surroundings, I said nothing at first.  I was no sailor man and I was
on board only by tolerance.  But I looked again at the maddening
sameness of the horizon&mdash;the same vacant, void horizon that we had
seen now for sixteen days on end, and felt in my wits and in my
nerves that same formless rebellion and protest such as comes when
the same note is reiterated

<pb n="493"/>
over and over again.

</p><p>It may seem a little thing that the mere fact of meeting with no
other ship should have ground down the edge of the spirit.  But let
the incredulous&mdash;bound upon such a hazard as ours&mdash;sail straight into
nothingness for sixteen days on end, seeing nothing but the sun,
hearing nothing but the thresh of his own screw, and then put the
question.

</p><p>And yet, of all things, we desired no company.  Stealth was
our one great aim.  But I think there were moments&mdash;toward the last
&mdash;when the Three Crows would have welcomed even a cruiser.

</p><p>Besides, there was more cause for depression, after all, than
mere isolation.

</p><p>On the seventh day, Hardenberg and I were forward by the cat-head adjusting
the grain with some half-formed intent of spearing
the porpoises that of late had begun to appear under our bows, and
Hardenberg had been computing the number of days we were yet to
run.

</p><p>"We are some five hundred odd miles off that island by now,"
he said, "and she's doing her thirteen knots
handsome.  All's well so far&mdash;but do you know, I'd just as soon raise
that point o' land as soon as convenient."

</p><p>"How so?" said I, bending on the line.  "Expect some
weather?"

</p><p>"Mr. Dixon," said he, giving me a curious glance, "the sea is a
queer proposition, put it any ways.  I've been a sea-farin' man since I
was as big as a minute, and I know the sea, and what's more, the
Feel o' the Sea.  Now, look out yonder.  Nothin', hey?  Nothin' but
the same ol' skyline we've watched all the way out.  The glass is as
steady as a steeple, and this ol' hooker, I reckon, is as sound as the
day she went off the ways.  But just the same, if I were to home
now, a-foolin' about Gloucester way in my little dough-dish&mdash;d'ye
know what?  I'd put into port.  I sure would.  Because why?
Because I got the Feel o' the Sea, Mr. Dixon.  I got the Feel o' the
Sea."

</p><p>I had heard old skippers say something of this before, and I
cited to Hardenberg the experience of a skipper captain I

<pb n="494"/>
once knew who had turned turtle in a calm sea off Trincomalee.  I
asked what this Feel of the Sea was warning him against just now
(for on the high sea any premonition is a premonition of evil, not of
good.)  But he was not explicit.

</p><p>"I don't know," he answered moodily, and as if in great
perplexity, coiling the rope as he spoke.  "I don't know.  There's
some blame thing or other close to us, I'll bet a hat.  I don't know the
name of it, Mr. Dixon, and I don't know the game of it, but there's a
big Bird in the air, just out of sight som-eres, and," he suddenly
exclaimed, smacking his knee and leaning forward, "I&mdash;don't&mdash;like&mdash;it&mdash;one&mdash;dam'&mdash;bit."

</p><p>The same thing came up in our talk in the cabin that night,
after the dinner was taken off, and we settled down to tobacco.
Only, at this time, Hardenberg was on duty on the bridge.  It was
Ally Bazan who spoke instead.

</p><p>"Seems to me," he hazarded, "as haow they's somethin' or
other a-goin' to bump up, pretty blyme soon.  I shouldn't be
surprized, naow, y'know, if we piled her up on some bally uncharted
reef along o' to-night and went strite daown afore we'd had a
bloomin' charnce to s'y 'So long, gen'lemen all.'"

</p><p>He laughed as he spoke, but when, just at that moment, a pan
clattered in the galley, he jumped suddenly with an oath, and looked
hard about the cabin.

</p><p>Then Strokher confessed to a sense of distress also.  He'd been
having it since day before yesterday, it seemed.

</p><p>"And I put it to you the glass is lovely," he said, "so it's no
blow.  I guess," he continued, "we're all a bit seedy and ship sore."

</p><p>And whether or not this talk worked upon my own nerves, or
whether in very truth the Feel of the Sea had found me also, I do not
know; but I do know that after dinner that night, just before going to
bed, a queer sense of apprehension came upon me, and that when I
had come to my stateroom, after my turn upon deck, I became
furiously angry with nobody in particular, because I could not at
once find the matches.  But here was a difference.  The other men
had been merely vaguely uncomfortable.

</p><p>I could put a name to my uneasiness.  I felt that we were being
watched.

</p><p>* * * * * * *

</p><p>It was a strange ship's company we made after that.  I speak
only of the Crows and myself.  We carried a scant crew of stokers,
and there was also a chief engineer.  But we saw so little of him that
he did not count.  The Crows and I gloomed on the quarter-deck
from dawn to dark, silent, irritable, working upon each other's
nerves till the creak of a block would make a man jump like cold
steel laid to his flesh.  We quarreled over absolute nothings,
glowered at each other for half a word, and each one of us, at
different times, was at some pains to declare that never in the course
of his career had he been associated with such a disagreeable trio of
brutes.  Yet we were always together, and sought each other's
company with painful insistence.

</p><p>Only once were we all agreed, and that was when the cook, a
Chinaman, spoiled a certain batch of biscuits.  Unanimously we fell
foul of the creature with so much vociferation as fish wives till he
fled the cabin in actual fear of mishandling, leaving us suddenly
seized with noisy hilarity&mdash;for the first time in a week.  Hardenberg
proposed a round of drinks from our single remaining case of beer.
We stood up and formed an Elk's chain and then drained our glasses
to each other's health with profound seriousness.

</p><p>That same evening, I remember, we all sat on the quarter-deck
till late and&mdash;oddly enough&mdash;related each one his life's history up to
date; and then went down to the cabin for a game of euchre before
turning in.

</p><p>We had left Strokher on the bridge&mdash;it was his watch&mdash;and had
forgotten all about him in the interest of the game, when&mdash;I suppose
it was about one in the morning&mdash;I heard him whistle long and shrill.
I laid down my cards and said:

</p><p>"Hark!"

</p><p>In the silence that followed we heard at first only the muffled
lope of our engines, the cadenced snorting of the exhaust, and the
ticking of Hardenberg's

<pb n="495"/> big watch in his waistcoat that he
had hung by the arm hole to the back of his chair.  Then from the
bridge, above our deck, prolonged, intoned&mdash;a wailing cry in the
night&mdash;came Strokher's voice: "Sail oh-h-h."

</p><p>And the cards fell from our hands, and, like men turned to
stone, we sat looking at each other across the soiled red cloth for
what seemed an immeasurably long minute.

</p><p>Then stumbling and swearing, in a hysteria of hurry, we gained
the deck.

</p><p>There was a moon, very low and reddish, but no wind.  The
sea beyond the taffrail was as smooth as lava, and so still that the
swells from the cutwater of the Glarus did not break as they rolled
away from the bows.

</p><p>I remember that I stood staring and blinking at the empty
ocean&mdash;where the moonlight lay like a painted stripe reaching to the
horizon&mdash;stupid and frowning, till Hardenberg, who had gone on
ahead, cried:

</p><p>"Not here&mdash;on the bridge!"

</p><p>We joined Strokher, and as I came up the others were asking:

</p><p>"Where?  Where?"

</p><p>And there, before he had pointed, I saw&mdash;we all of us saw&mdash;.
And I heard Hardenberg's teeth come together like a spring trap,
while Ally Bazan ducked as though to a blow, muttering:

</p><p>"Gord'a mercy, what nyme do ye put to a ship like that?"

</p><p>And after that no one spoke for a long minute, and we stood
there, moveless black shadows, huddled together for the sake of the
blessed elbow touch that means so incalculably much, looking off
over our port quarter.

</p><p>For the ship that we saw there&mdash;oh, she was not a half mile
distant&mdash;was unlike any ship known to present day construction.

</p><p>She was short, and high-pooped, and her stern, which was
turned a little towards us, we could see, was set with curious
windows, not unlike a house.  And on either side of this stern were
two great iron cressets such as once were used to burn signal fires
in.  She had three masts with mighty yards swung 'thwart ship, but
bare of all sails save a few rotting streamers.  Here and there about
her a tangled mass of rigging drooped and sagged.

</p><p>And there she lay, in the red eye of the setting moon, in that
solitary ocean, shadowy, antique, forlorn, a thing the most
abandoned, the most sinister I ever remember to have seen.

</p><p>Then Strokher began to explain volubly and with many
repetitions.

</p><p>"A derelict, of course.  I was asleep; yes I was asleep.  Gross
neglect of duty.  I say I was asleep&mdash;on watch.  And we worked up
to her.  When I woke, why&mdash;you see, when I woke, there she was,"
he gave a weak little laugh, "and&mdash;and now, why, there she is, you
see.  I turned around and saw her sudden like&mdash;when I woke up, that
is."

</p><p>He laughed again, and as he laughed, the engines far below our
feet gave a sudden hiccough.  Something crashed and struck the
ship's sides till we lurched as we stood.  There was a shriek of
steam, a shout&mdash;and then silence.

</p><p>The noise of the machinery ceased; the Glarus slid through the
still water, moving only by her own decreasing momentum.

</p><p>Hardenberg sang, "Stand by!" and called down the tube to the
engine room.

</p><p>"What's up?"

</p><p>I was standing close enough to him to hear the answer in a
small faint voice:

</p><p>"Shaft gone, sir."

</p><p>"Broke?"

</p><p>"Yes, sir."

</p><p>Hardenberg faced about.

</p><p>"Come below.  We must talk."  I do not think any of us cast a
glance at the Other Ship again.  Certainly I kept my eyes away from
her.  But as we started down the companionway, I laid my hand on
Strokher's shoulder.  The rest were ahead.  I looked him straight
between the eyes as I asked:

</p><p>"Were you asleep?  Is that why you saw her so suddenly?"

</p><p>It is now five years since I asked the question.  I am still
waiting for Strokher's answer.

</p><p>Well, our shaft was broken.  That was flat.  We went down
into the engine room and saw the jagged fracture that

<pb n="496"/> was
the symbol of our broken hopes.  And in the course of the next five
minutes' conversation with the chief, we found that, as we had not
provided against such a contingency, there was to be no mending of
it.  We said nothing about the mishap coinciding with the
appearance of the Other Ship.  But I know we did not consider the
break with any degree of surprise after a few moments.

</p><p>We came up from the engine room and sat down to the cabin
table.

</p><p>"Now what?" said Hardenberg, by way of beginning.

</p><p>Nobody answered at first.

</p><p>It was by now three in the morning.  I recall it all perfectly.
The ports opposite where I sat were open and I could see.  The
moon was all but full set.  The dawn was coming up with a copper
murkiness over the edge of the world.  All the stars were yet out.
The sea, for all the red moon and copper dawn, was gray, and there,
less than half a mile away, still lay our consort.  I could see her
through the portholes with each slow careening of the Glarus.

</p><p>"I vote for the island," cried Ally Bazan, "shaft or no shaft.
We rigs a bit o' syle, y'know&mdash;" and thereat the discussion began.

</p><p>For upwards of two hours it raged, with loud words and shaken
forefingers, and great noisy bangings of the table, and how it would
have ended I do not know, but at last&mdash;it was then maybe five in the
morning&mdash;the lookout passed word down to the cabin:

</p><p>"Will you come on deck, gentlemen?"  It was the mate who
spoke, and the man was shaken&mdash;I could see that&mdash;to the very vitals
of him.  We started and stared at one another, and I watched little
Ally Bazan go slowly white to the lips.  And even then no word of
the Ship, except as it might be this from Hardenberg:

</p><p>"What is it?  Good God Almighty, I'm no coward, but this
thing is getting one too many for me."

</p><p>Then without further speech he went on deck.

</p><p>The air was cool.  The sun was not yet up.  It was that strange,
queer mid-period between dark and dawn, when the night is over
and the day not yet come, just the gray that is neither light nor dark,
the dim dead blink as of the refracted light from extinct worlds.

</p><p>We stood at the rail.  We did not speak, we stood watching.  It
was so still that the drip of steam from some loosened pipe far
below was plainly audible, and it sounded in that lifeless, silent
grayness, like&mdash;God knows what&mdash;a death tick.

</p><p>"You see," said the mate, speaking just above a whisper,
"there's no mistake about it.  She is moving&mdash;this way."

</p><p>"Oh, a current, of course," Strokher tried to say cheerfully,
"sets her toward us."

</p><p>Would the morning never come?

</p><p>Ally Bazan&mdash;his parents were Catholic&mdash;began to mutter to
himself.

</p><p>Then Hardenberg spoke aloud.

</p><p>"I particularly don't want&mdash;that&mdash;out&mdash;there&mdash;to cross our bows.
I don't want it to come to that.  We must get some sails on her."

</p><p>"And I put it to you as man to man," said Strokher, "where
might be your wind."

</p><p>He was right.  The Glarus floated in absolute calm.  On all that
slab of ocean nothing moved but the Dead Ship.

</p><p>She came on slowly; her bows, the high clumsy bows pointed
toward us, the water turning from her forefoot.  She came on; she
was near at hand.  We saw her plainly&mdash;saw the rotted planks, the
crumbling rigging, the rust corroded metal work, the broken rail, the
gaping deck, and I could imagine that the clean water broke away
from her sides in refluent wavelets as though in recoil from a thing
unclean.  She made no sound.  No single thing stirred aboard the
hulk of her&mdash;but she moved.

</p><p>We were helpless.  The Glarus could stir no boat in any
direction; we were chained to the spot.  Nobody had thought to put
out our lights, and they still burned on through the dawn, strangely
out of place in their red and green garishness, like masquers
surprised by daylight.

</p><p>And in the silence of that empty ocean, in that queer half light
between dawn

<pb n="497"/> and day, at six o'clock,
silent as the settling of the dead to the bottomless bottom of the
ocean, gray as fog, lonely, blind, soulless, voiceless, the Dead Ship
crossed our bows.

</p><p>I do not know how long after this the Ship disappeared, or
what was the time of day when we at last pulled ourselves together.
But we came to some sort of decision at last.  This was to go on&mdash;under sail.
We were too close to the Island now to turn back for&mdash;for a broken shaft.

</p><p>The afternoon was spent fitting on the sails to her, and when
after nightfall the wind at length came up fresh and favorable, I
believe we all felt heartened and a deal more hardy&mdash;until the last
canvass went aloft, and Hardenberg took the wheel.

</p><p>We had drifted a good deal since the morning, and the bows of
the Glarus were pointed homeward, but as soon as the breeze blew
strong enough to get steerage way, Hardenberg put the wheel over,
and as the booms swung across the deck headed for the island again.

</p><p>We had not gone on this course half an hour&mdash;no, not twenty
minutes&mdash;before the wind shifted a whole quarter of the compass
and took the Glarus square in the teeth, so that there was nothing for
it but to tack.  And then the strangest thing befell.

</p><p>I will make allowance for the fact that there was no center
board nor keel to speak of to the Glarus.  I will admit that the sails
upon a nine hundred ton freighter are not calculated to speed her,
nor steady her.  I will even admit

<pb n="498"/> the possibility of a
current that set from the island toward us.  All this may be true, yet
the Glarus should have advanced.  We should have made a wake.

</p><p>And instead of this,
our stolid, steady, trusty old boat was&mdash;what shall I say?

</p><p>I will say that no man may thoroughly understand a ship&mdash;after
all.  I will say that new ships are cranky and unsteady, that old and
seasoned ships have their little crotchets, their little fussinesses that
their skippers must learn and humor if they are to get anything out
of them, that even the best ships may sulk at times, shirk their work,
grow unstable, perverse, and refuse to answer helm and handling.
And I will say that some ships that for years have sailed blue water
as soberly and as docilely as a street-car horse has plodded the
treadmill of the 'tween-tracks, have been known to balk, as
stubbornly and as conclusively as any old Bay Billy that ever wore a
bell.  I know this has happened, because I have seen it.  I saw, for
instance, the Glarus do it.

</p><p>Quite literally and truly we could do nothing with her.  We
will say, if you like, that that great jar and wrench when the shaft
gave way shook her and crippled her.  It is true, however, that
whatever the cause may have been, we could not force her toward
the island.  Of course, we all said "Current;" but why didn't the log-line trail?

</p><p>For three days and three nights we tried it.  And the Glarus
heaved and plunged and shook herself just as you have seen a horse
plunge and rear when his rider tries to force him at the steam roller.

</p><p>I tell you I could feel the fabric of her tremble and shudder
from bow to stern post, as though she were in a storm; I tell you she
fell off from the wind, and broad-on drifted back from her course
till the sensation of her shrinking was as plain as her own staring
lights and a thing pitiful to see.

</p><p>We rowelled her and we crowded sail upon her, and we coaxed
and bullied and humored her, till the Three Crows, their fortune
only a plain sail two days ahead, raved and swore like insensate
brutes, or shall we say like mahouts, trying to drive their stricken
elephant upon the tiger&mdash;and all to no purpose.  "Damn the damned
current and the damned luck and the damned shaft and all,"
Hardenberg would exclaim, as from the wheel he would watch the
Glarus falling off.  "Go on, you old hooker&mdash;you tub of junk!  My
God, you'd think she was scared!"

</p><p>Perhaps the Glarus was scared, perhaps not; that point is
debatable.  But it was beyond doubt or debate that Hardenberg was
scared.

</p><p>A ship that will not obey is only one degree less terrible than a
mutinous crew.  And we were in a fair way to have both.  The
stokers whom we had impressed into duty as A. B.'s, were of course
superstitious.  They had seen&mdash;what we had seen; and they knew
how the Glarus was acting and it was only a question of time before
they got out of hand.

</p><p>That was the end.  We held a final conference in the cabin and
decided that there was no help for it&mdash;we must turn back.

</p><p>And back we accordingly turned, and at once the wind
followed us, and the "current" helped us, and the water churned
under the forefoot of the Glarus, and the wake whitened under her
stern, and the log line ran out from the rail and strained back as the
ship worked homeward.

</p><p>We had never a mishap from the time we finally swung her
about; and, considering the circumstances, the voyage back to San
Francisco was propitious.

</p><p>But an incident happened just after we had started back.  We
were perhaps some five miles on the homeward track.  It was early
evening and Strokher had the watch.  At about seven o'clock he
called me up on the bridge.

</p><p>"See her?" he said.

</p><p>And there, far behind us, in the shadow of the twilight, loomed
the Other Ship again, desolate, lonely beyond words.  We were
leaving her rapidly astern.  Strokher and I stood looking at her till
she dwindled to a dot.  Then Strokher said:

</p><p>"She's on post again."

</p><p>And when months afterward we limped into the Golden Gate
and cast anchor off the "Front," our crew went ashore as soon as
discharged, and in half a dozen

<pb n="499"/>  hours the legend was in
every sailors' boarding house and in every seaman's dive, from
Barbary Coast to Black Tom's.

</p><p>It is still there, and that is why no pilot will take the Glarus
out, no captain will navigate her, no stoker feed her fires, no sailor
walk her decks.  The Glarus is suspect.  She will never smell blue
water again, nor taste the trades.  She has seen a Ghost.
</p>

<note id="n1"><seg type="note-symbol">[1]</seg> <p>Frank Norris died in San Francisco, October 25, 1902.</p></note>
</div1>
</body>
</text>
</TEI.2>



