<?xml version="1.0"?>

<?dlps id="NurExam"?>
<?dlps page-images="none" figure-images="no"?>
<?dlps transcription="other"?>

<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/tei-p4/tei2.dtd" [
<!ENTITY % POSTKB "INCLUDE">
<!ENTITY % TEI.extensions.ent SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.ent">
<!ENTITY % TEI.extensions.dtd SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.dtd">
<!ENTITY % ISOpub SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/charent/iso-pub.ent"> %ISOpub;

]>
<TEI.2 id="NurExam">
<teiHeader type="migrated" creator="Etext">
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title type="main">Rebecca Nurse Collection:
Examination of Rebecca Nurse</title>
<title type="sort">rebecca nurse collection examination of rebecca nurse</title>
<author>Nurse, Rebecca</author>
<respStmt>
<resp>Creation of machine-readable version:</resp>
<name>Carolyn Fay, Electronic Text Center</name>
<resp>Creation of digital images:</resp>
<name/>
<resp>Conversion to TEI.2-conformant markup:</resp>
<name>University of Virginia Library Electronic Text Center.</name>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt>
<extent>ca. <num type="kilobytes">11</num> kilobytes</extent>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>University of Virginia Library</publisher>
<pubPlace>Charlottesville, Virginia</pubPlace>
<idno type="ETC">NurExam</idno>
<date value="1998">1998</date>
<availability status="public">
<p n="copyright">Copyright &#xa9; 1998 by the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia</p>
<p n="access">Publicly accessible</p>
</availability>
<idno type="uva-pid">uva-lib:476598</idno>
</publicationStmt>
<seriesStmt>
<title>University of Virginia Library, Text collection</title>
<idno type="uva-set">UVA-LIB-Text</idno>
</seriesStmt>
<notesStmt>
<note>
<p>This document is part of a collection of documents pertaining to the Rebecca Nurse witchcraft trial of 1692 in Salem Village, Massachusetts, collected and edited by Richard B. Trask in "The Devil hath been raised." This electronic collection is a pilot project that is part of a larger digital enterprise which will collect together all of the documents pertaining to the Salem witchcraft trials. This enterprise is a project undertaken by the Electronic Text Center. Benjamin C. Ray, professor of Religious Studies, is the project supervisor.</p>
</note>
</notesStmt>
<sourceDesc>
<biblFull>
<titleStmt>
<title type="main">Rebecca Nurse Collection:
Examination of Rebecca Nurse</title>
<title level="m">"The Devil hath been raised:" A Documentary History of the Salem Village Witchcraft Outbreak of March 1692</title>
<title type="sort">rebecca nurse collection examination of rebecca nurse</title>
<author>Rebecca Nurse</author>
<respStmt>
<resp>Editor</resp>
<name>Richard B. Trask</name>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt>
<editionStmt>
<p>Revised Edition</p>
</editionStmt>
<extent>p. 55</extent>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>Yeoman Press</publisher>
<pubPlace>Danvers, Mass.</pubPlace>
<date value="1997">1997</date>
<idno type="callNo">Print copy consulted: personal copy</idno>
</publicationStmt>
</biblFull>
</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc>
<encodingDesc>
<projectDesc>
<p>Prepared for the University of Virginia Library Electronic Text Center.</p>
</projectDesc>
<editorialDecl>
<p>The images exist as archived TIFF images, one or more JPEG versions for general use, and thumbnail GIFs.</p>
<p>Some keywords in the header are a local Electronic Text Center scheme to aid in establishing analytical groupings.</p>
</editorialDecl>
</encodingDesc>
<profileDesc>
<creation>
<date value="1692-03-24">1692-03-24</date>
</creation>
<langUsage>
<language id="eng" usage="main">English</language>
</langUsage>
<textClass>
<keywords>
<term>nonfiction</term>
<term>prose</term>
<term>feminine</term>
</keywords>
</textClass>
</profileDesc>
<revisionDesc>
<change>
<date value="1998-07">July 1998</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>corrector</resp>
<name>Carolyn Fay, Electronic Text Center</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Added TEI header and tags.</item>
</change>
<change>
<date value="2005-07">July 2005</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>Corrector</resp>
<name>John Ivor Carlson</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Converted to XML and/or checked tags.</item>
</change>
<change>
<date value="2007-09">September 2007</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>Migration</resp>
<name>Ethan Gruber, University of Virginia Library</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Converted XML markup from TEI Lite to uva-dl-tei (TEI P4 with local customizations).</item>
</change>
<change>
<date value="2008-01">January 2008</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>Migration</resp>
<name>Greg Murray, University of Virginia Library</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Programmatically updated TEI header markup (but not header content) for minimal compliance with current QA requirements.</item>
</change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>
<text id="d1">
<body id="d2">
<div1 type="statement" n="1692-03-24" id="d3">
<head>
<hi rend="bold">Examination of Rebecca Nurse</hi><lb/>
The examination of Rebekah Nurse at Salem Village<lb/>
24.Mar.<hi rend="underline">1691/2</hi>
</head>

<p> Harthorn. What do you say (speaking to one afflicted) have you seen
this Woman hurt you?<lb/>

Yes, she beat me this morning<lb/>

Abigial. Have you been hurt by this Woman? Yes<lb/>

Ann Putman in a grievous fit cryed out that she hurt her. Goody Nurse,
here are two An: Putman the child &amp; Abigail Williams complains of your
hurting them What do you say to it<lb/>



N. I can say before my Eternal father I am innocent, &amp; God will clear my
innocency<lb/>

Here is never a one in the Assembly but desires it, but ifyou be guilty
Pray God discover you.<lb/>

Then Hen: Kenny rose up to speak Goodm: Kenny what do you say<lb/>

Then he entered his complaint &amp; farther said that since this Nurse came
into the house he was seizd twise with an amazd condition<lb/>

Here are not only these but, here is ye wife of Mr. Tho. Putman who
accuseth you by credible information &amp; that both of tempting her to
iniquity, &amp; of greatly hurting her.<lb/>

N. I am innocent &amp; dear &amp; have not been able to get out of doors these
8. or 9. dayes.<lb/>

Mr. Putman: give in what you have to say<lb/>

Then Mr. Edward Putman gave in his relate Is this true Goody Nurse<lb/>

I never afflicted no child never in my life You see these accuse you, is
it true<lb/>

No.<lb/>
Are you an innocent person relating to this Witchcraft.<lb/>

Here Tho: Putmans wife cryed out, Did you not bring the Black man with
you, did you not bid me tempt God &amp; dyeHow oft have you eat and drunk yr
own damaon<lb/>

What do you say to them<lb/>

Oh Lord help me, &amp; spread out her hands, &amp; the afflicted were greviously
vexed<lb/>

</p><p>

Do you not see what a solemn condition these are in? when your hands are
loose the persons are afflicted.  Then Mary Walcot (who often heretofore
said she had seen her, but never could say or did say that she either
bit or pincht her, or hurt her) &amp; also Eliz: Hubbard under the like
circumstances both openly accused her of hurting them.
</p><p>

Here are these 2 grown persons now accuse you, wt say you? Do not you
see these afflicted persons, &amp; hear them accuse you.<lb/>

The Lord knows I have not hurt them: I am an innocent person<lb/>

It is very awfull to all to see these agonies &amp; you an old Professor
thus charged with contracting with the Devil by the effects of it &amp;
yet to see you stand with dry eyes when there are so many whet -<lb/>

You do not know my heart
You would do well if you are guilty to confess &amp; give Glory to God<lb/>
I am as clear as the child unborn<lb/>

What uncertainty there may be in apparitions I know not, yet this with
me strikes hard upon you that you are at this very present charged with
familiar spirits-this is your bodily person they speak to: they say now
they see these familiar spirits com to your bodily person, now what do
you say to that<lb/>

I have none Sir:<lb/>

If you have confess &amp; give glory to God I pray God clear you if you
be innocent, &amp; if you are guilty discover you And therefore give me an
upright answer: have you any familiarity with these spirits?<lb/>

No, I have none but with God alone.<lb/>

How came you sick for there is an odd discourse of that in the mouths of
many-<lb/>

I am sick at my stumach-<lb/>
Have you no wounds<lb/>
I have none but old age<lb/>

You do know whither you are guilty, &amp; have familiarity with the
Devil, &amp; now when you are here present to see such a thing as these
testify a black man whispering in your ear, &amp; birds about you what
do you say to it<lb/>


It is all false I am clear<lb/>

Possibly you may apprehend you are no witch, but have you not been led
aside by temptations that way<lb/>

I have not<lb/>

What a sad thing it is that a church member here &amp; now an other of
Salem, should be thus accused and charged Mrs Pope fell into a grevious
fit, &amp; cryed out a sad thing sure enough-And then many more fell into
lamentable fits.  Tell us have not you had visible appearances more than
what is common in nature?<lb/>

I have none nor never had in my life<lb/>


Do you think these suffer voluntary or involuntary<lb/>
I cannot tell<lb/>
That is strange every one can judge<lb/>
I must be silent<lb/>

They accuse you of hurting them, &amp; if you think it is not
unwillingly but by designe, you must look upon them as murderers<lb/>

I cannot tell what to think of it<lb/>

Afterwards when this was som. what insisted on she said I do not think
so: she did not understand aright what was said Well then give an answer
now, do you think these suffer against their wills or not<lb/>

I do not think these suffer against their wills<lb/>
Why did you never visit these afflicted persons<lb/>
Because I was afraid I should have fits too<lb/>

Upon the motion of her body fitts followed upon the complainants
abundantly &amp; very frequently<lb/>

Is it not an unaccountable case that when #[they] you are examined these
persons are afflicted?<lb/>

I have got no body to look to but God<lb/>

Again upon stirring her hands the afflicted persons were seized with
violent fits of torture<lb/>

Do you believe these afflicted persons are bewitcht<lb/>
 I do think they are<lb/>

When this Witchcraft came upon the stage there was no suspicion of
Tituba (Mr. Parris's Indian woman) she profest much love to that child
Betty Parris but it was her apparition did the mischief, &amp; why
should not you also be guilty, for your apparition doth hurt also.<lb/>

Would you have me bely my self-<lb/>
she held her Neck on one side, &amp; accordingly so were the
afflicted taken<lb/>

Then Authority requiring it Sam: Parris read what he had in
characters taken from Mr. Tho: Putmans wife in her fitts<lb/>

What do you think of this<lb/>
I cannot help it, the Devil may appear in my shape.<lb/>

</p><p>

This a true account of the sume of her examination but by reason of geat noyses by the afflicted &amp; many speakers, many things are pretermitted
</p><p>
Memorandum

</p><p>

Nurse held her neck on one sid &amp; Eliz: Hubbard (one of the sufferers)
had her neck set in that posture whereupon another Patient Abigail
Williams cryed out set up Goody Nurses head the maid's neck will be
broke &amp; when some set up Nurses head Aaron Wey observed that Betty
Hubbards was immediately righted.

</p><p>

Salem Village March 24.th 1691/2

The Revert Mr Samuell Parris being desired to take in wrighting ye
Examination of Rebekah Nurse hath Returned itt as aforesaid

</p><p>


Upon heareing the aforesd and seeing what wee then did see together with
ye Charges of the persons then present&mdash;wee Committed Rebekah Nurse ye
wife of frans Nurce of Salem Village unto theire Majests Goale in Salem
as p a Mittimus then given out, in order to farther Examination

</p><p>

*John Hathome<lb/>
	Assists<lb/>
*Jonathan. Corwin
</p>
</div1>
</body>
</text>
</TEI.2>

