<?xml version="1.0"?>

<?dlps id="NurPort"?>
<?dlps page-images="none" figure-images="no"?>
<?dlps transcription="other"?>

<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/tei-p4/tei2.dtd" [
<!ENTITY % POSTKB "INCLUDE">
<!ENTITY % TEI.extensions.ent SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.ent">
<!ENTITY % TEI.extensions.dtd SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.dtd">

]>
<TEI.2 id="NurPort">
<teiHeader type="migrated" creator="Etext">
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title type="main">Rebecca Nurse Collection:
Israel Forter, Elizabeth Porter, Daniel Andrew &amp; Peter Cloyce For Rebecca Nurse</title>
<title type="sort">rebecca nurse collection israel forter, elizabeth porter daniel andrew &amp; peter cloyce for rebecca nurse</title>
<author>Nurse, Rebecca</author>
<respStmt>
<resp>Creation of machine-readable version:</resp>
<name>Carolyn Fay, Electronic Text Center</name>
<resp>Creation of digital images:</resp>
<name/>
<resp>Conversion to TEI.2-conformant markup:</resp>
<name>University of Virginia Library Electronic Text Center.</name>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt>
<extent>ca. <num type="kilobytes">7</num> kilobytes</extent>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>University of Virginia Library</publisher>
<pubPlace>Charlottesville, Virginia</pubPlace>
	<idno type="ETC">NurPort</idno>
<date value="1998">1998</date>
<availability status="public">
<p n="copyright">Copyright &#xa9; 1998 by the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia</p>
<p n="access">Publicly accessible</p>
</availability>
<idno type="uva-pid">uva-lib:476604</idno>
</publicationStmt>
<seriesStmt>
<title>University of Virginia Library, Text collection</title>
<idno type="uva-set">UVA-LIB-Text</idno>
</seriesStmt>
<notesStmt>
<note>
<p>This document is part of a collection of documents pertaining to the Rebecca Nurse witchcraft trial of 1692 in Salem Village, Massachusetts, collected and edited by Richard B. Trask in "The Devil hath been raised." This electronic collection is a pilot project that is part of a larger digital enterprise which will collect together all of the documents pertaining to the Salem witchcraft trials. This enterprise is a project undertaken by the Electronic Text Center. Benjamin C. Ray, professor of Religious Studies, is the project supervisor.</p>
</note>
</notesStmt>
<sourceDesc>
<biblFull>
<titleStmt>
<title type="main">Rebecca Nurse Collection:
Israel Forter, Elizabeth Porter, Daniel Andrew &amp; Peter Cloyce For Rebecca Nurse</title>
<title level="m">"The Devil hath been raised:" A Documentary History of the Salem Village Witchcraft Outbreak of March 1692</title>
<title type="sort">rebecca nurse collection israel forter, elizabeth porter daniel andrew &amp; peter cloyce for rebecca nurse</title>
<author>Rebecca Nurse</author>
<respStmt>
<resp>Editor</resp>
<name>Richard B. Trask</name>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt>
<editionStmt>
<p>Revised Edition</p>
</editionStmt>
<extent>p. 48</extent>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>Yeoman Press</publisher>
<pubPlace>Danvers, Mass.</pubPlace>
<date value="1997">1997</date>
<idno type="callNo">Print copy consulted: personal copy</idno>
</publicationStmt>
</biblFull>
</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc>
<encodingDesc>
<projectDesc>
<p>Prepared for the University of Virginia Library Electronic Text Center.</p>
</projectDesc>
<editorialDecl>
<p>The images exist as archived TIFF images, one or more JPEG versions for general use, and thumbnail GIFs.</p>
<p>Some keywords in the header are a local Electronic Text Center scheme to aid in establishing analytical groupings.</p>
</editorialDecl>
</encodingDesc>
<profileDesc>
<creation>
<date value="1692-03-21">1692-03-21</date>;
<date value="1692-03-22">1692-03-22</date>;
<date value="1692-03-23">1692-03-23</date>
</creation>
<langUsage>
<language id="eng" usage="main">English</language>
</langUsage>
<textClass>
<keywords>
<term>fiction</term>
<term>prose</term>
<term>feminine</term>
</keywords>
</textClass>
</profileDesc>
<revisionDesc>
<change>
<date value="1998-07">July 1998</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>corrector</resp>
<name>Carolyn Fay, Electronic Text Center</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Added TEI header and tags.</item>
</change>
<change>
<date value="2005-07">July 2005</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>Corrector</resp>
<name>John Ivor Carlson</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Converted to XML and/or checked tags.</item>
</change>
<change>
<date value="2007-09">September 2007</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>Migration</resp>
<name>Ethan Gruber, University of Virginia Library</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Converted XML markup from TEI Lite to uva-dl-tei (TEI P4 with local customizations).</item>
</change>
<change>
<date value="2008-01">January 2008</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>Migration</resp>
<name>Greg Murray, University of Virginia Library</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Programmatically updated TEI header markup (but not header content) for minimal compliance with current QA requirements.</item>
</change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>
<text id="d1">
<body id="d2">
<div1 type="statement" id="d3">
<head>
<hi rend="bold">Israel Forter, Elizabeth Porter, Daniel Andrew &amp; Peter Cloyce<lb/>
For Rebecca Nurse</hi>
</head>
<p>


<hi rend="italic">This undated statement concerns a visit made to the Francis and
Rebecca Nurse home sometime prior to March 23. The four visitors
included Rebecca's sister Sarah's husband Peter Cloyce, as well as three
prominent village inhabitants. They wanted to warn Rebecca that her name
was being mentioned by some of the afflicted persons. Her reaction, and
sincerity were poignant.</hi>

</p><p>

We whos nams Are under writen being desiered to goe to goodman nurs his
hous to speeke with his wife and tell her that several of the Aflicted
persons mentioned her: and Acordingly we went and we found her in A weak
and Lowe condition in body as shee told us and had been sicke allmost A
weak and we asked how it was otherwis with her and shee said shee blest
god for it shee had more of his presents in this sickens then sometime
shee have had but not soe much as shee desiered: but shee would with the
Apostle pres forward to the mark: and many other places of scriptur to
the Like purpos:  and then of her owne Acord shee begane to speek of the
Affliction that was Amongst them and in perticuler of Mr Parris his
family and howe shee was greved for them though shee had not been to see
them: by Reason of fits that shee formerly use to have for people said
it was Awfull to:behold: but shee pittied them with: all her harte: and
went to god for them: but shee said shee heard that there was persons
spoke of that wear as Innocent as shee was shee belived and After much
to this purpos: we told her we heard that shee was spoken of allsoe:
well she said if it be soe ye will of the Lord be done: she sate still
Awhille being as it wear Amazed: and then shee said well as to this
thing I am as Innocent as the child unborne but seurly shee said what
sine hath god found out in me unrepented of that he should Lay such an
Affliction upon me In my old Age: and Acording to our best observation
we could not decern that shee knewe what we came for before we tould her

</p><p>
Israel porter<lb/>
Elizabeth porter
</p><p>

To the substance of what is Above we if caled there too: are Ready to
testifie on:oath<lb/>

Daniell Andrew<lb/>
Peter Cloys
</p><p>

<hi rend="italic">(Peabody Essex, Museum, Salem, Mass., Salem Witchcraft Papers, # 16)</hi>
</p>

</div1>
</body>
</text>
</TEI.2>

