<?xml version="1.0"?>

<?dlps id="OskCaus"?>
<?dlps page-images="none" figure-images="no"?>
<?dlps transcription="other"?>

<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/tei-p4/tei2.dtd" [
<!ENTITY % POSTKB "INCLUDE">
<!ENTITY % TEI.extensions.ent SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.ent">
<!ENTITY % TEI.extensions.dtd SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.dtd">
<!ENTITY % ISOnum SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/charent/iso-num.ent"> %ISOnum;
<!ENTITY % ISOpub SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/charent/iso-pub.ent"> %ISOpub;

]>


<TEI.2 id="OskCaus">
<teiHeader type="migrated" creator="Etext">
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title type="main">"Remaining Causes of Indian Discontent"</title>
<title type="sort">remaining causes of indian discontent</title>
<author>Oskison, John M.</author>
<respStmt>
<resp>Creation of machine-readable version:</resp>
<name>Judy Boss</name>
<resp>Conversion to TEI.2-conformant markup:</resp>
<name>University of Virginia Library Electronic Text Center</name>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt>
<extent>ca. <num type="kilobytes">23</num> kilobytes</extent>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>University of Virginia Library</publisher>
<pubPlace>Charlottesville, Virginia</pubPlace>
<idno type="ETC">OskCaus</idno>
<date value="1995">1995</date>
<availability status="public">
<p n="copyright">Copyright &copy; 1995 by the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia</p>
<p n="access">Publicly accessible</p>
</availability>
<idno type="uva-pid">uva-lib:476266</idno>
</publicationStmt>
<seriesStmt>
<title>University of Virginia Library, Text collection</title>
<idno type="uva-set">UVA-LIB-Text</idno>
</seriesStmt>
<sourceDesc>
<biblFull>
<titleStmt>
<title type="main">"Remaining Causes of Indian Discontent"</title>
<title>North American Review 184</title>
<title type="sort">remaining causes of indian discontent</title>
<author>John M. Oskison</author>
</titleStmt>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>Franklin Square</publisher>
<pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
<date value="1907-03-01">March 1, 1907</date>
</publicationStmt>
<notesStmt>
<note>
<p>This article first appeared in <hi rend="italic">North American
Review</hi> 184, pages 486-493.</p>
</note>
</notesStmt>
</biblFull>
</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc>
<encodingDesc>
<projectDesc>
<p>Prepared for the University of Virginia Library Electronic Text Center</p>
</projectDesc>
<editorialDecl>
<p>All quotation marks retained as data</p>
<p>All unambiguous end-of-line hyphens have been removed, and the
trailing part of a word has been joined to the preceding line.</p>
<p>The images exist as archived TIFF images, one or more JPEG versions
for general use, and thumbnail GIFs.</p>
<p id="ETC">Keywords in the header are a local Electronic Text Center scheme
to aid in establishing analytical groupings</p>
</editorialDecl>
<refsDecl>
<p>ID elements are given for each page element and are composed of the text's
unique cryptogram and the given page number, as in AusEmma1 for page one of
Jane Austen's Emma.</p>
</refsDecl>
</encodingDesc>
<profileDesc>
<creation>
<date value="1907-03-01">March 1, 1907</date>
</creation>
<langUsage>
<language id="eng" usage="main">English</language>
</langUsage>
<textClass>
<keywords>
<term>non-fiction; prose</term>
<term>Native American</term>
</keywords>
</textClass>
</profileDesc>
<revisionDesc>
<change>
<date value="1994-12-13">December 13, 1994</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>corrector</resp>
<name>Jennifer Hanna</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Added TEI-compatible header and tags.</item>
</change>
<change>
<date value="2005-07">July 2005</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>Corrector</resp>
<name>John Ivor Carlson</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Converted to XML and/or checked tags.</item>
</change>
<change>
<date value="2007-09">September 2007</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>Migration</resp>
<name>Ethan Gruber, University of Virginia Library</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Converted XML markup from TEI Lite to uva-dl-tei (TEI P4 with local customizations).</item>
</change>
<change>
<date value="2008-01">January 2008</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>Migration</resp>
<name>Greg Murray, University of Virginia Library</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Programmatically updated TEI header markup (but not header content) for minimal compliance with current QA requirements.</item>
</change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text id="d1">
<body id="d2">

<div1 type="article" id="d3"><pb n="486"/>
<head>REMAINING CAUSES OF INDIAN DISCONTENT.<lb/>
<lb/>
BY JOHN M. OSKISON.</head>


<p>WHEN the White River Utes left their reservation in Utah
recently in angry protest against the Government's allotment of
their land, they attracted attention to a vanishing type of
discontented Indian.
</p><p>Only one big distinctively Indian problem&mdash;the distribution of
Indian Trust and Treaty Funds&mdash;remains to be settled by Congress.
Others, such as irrigation for arid and semi-arid lands occupied by
the tribes, the menace of tuberculosis, the supplying of good day-schools, the blight of the liquor traffic, and the over-reaching
arm of the speculator in oil, mineral and grazing lands, are in
some measure the problems of all the West.  Continued urging by the
Indian Office and the friends of Indian progress is resulting in a
merger of the tribesman with his white neighbors and a sinking of
the reservation problem in the community problem.  Nine out of ten
"reservation" Indians are self-supporting.  Five of these nine are
working in competition with white laborers, mechanics, farmers and
stock-raisers of the West.  The other four are doing work, more or
less well, provided by the Government in place of pauperizing
rations.  Except for the children in Government schools, and the
old, sick and infirm, few Indians now live on the direct bounty of
Congress.
</p><p>The Indian as a landholder is familiar, but as a capitalist he
is not so well known.  Yet there is in the United States Treasury
to the credit of some 53,000 Indians of sixty tribes more than
$35,000,000.  Nearly all of this is in the form of Trust Funds,
held, in varying amounts, for these tribes, only the interest being
paid from year to year.  The money has come from the sale of land
from time to time. <pb n="487"/>
</p><p>When the land allotment law was passed, in 1887, it was
bitterly opposed by the tribes.  Later, it became a popular measure
with the progressive Indians who were ambitious to distinguish
themselves as individuals.  This ambitious Indian wants the Trust
Funds segregated so that they may be paid, in proportionate share,
to every individual who is qualified to use his share.  Next to the
Dawes allotment law of 1887, this legislation will do most to break
up the old communal life that has been nursed by the Government's
reservation policy.  Holding vast areas of land "in common," with
no opportunity to secure private ownership, made the Indians feel
as if they were heirs to an estate in chancery.  There was no
incentive to develop a community-holding; reservations were leased
to cattlemen and farmers who had no interest in their ultimate
improvement.  Upon the allotment of tribal lands, this prop is
knocked from under the Indian: the problem of getting a living
becomes a personal problem.
</p><p>That other prop, the tribal fund, should be removed.  To
illustrate: So long as a member of the Osage tribe knows that he is
one of 2,000 heirs to a fund of $8,360,000, and that his
proportionate share of interest at five per cent. on this tribal
fund will be paid to him regularly, he feels no spur to become a
producing member of his community.  If it were permitted, however,
to set aside Frank Corndropper's share of the $8,360,000 and pay it
over when he could convince the Government that he is qualified to
use it, Frank Corndropper would bestir himself.  His example would
be followed by Fred Labadie, and by Black Eagle, and by others,
until every separate account between the United States Treasury and
the Osage Indians would be closed out.  Until that is done, no
Osage can be made to realize that he is a competitor of the white
man in any vital sense.
</p><p>Legislation designed to segregate Indian funds has been urged
upon Congress for years.  At Washington, however, the fear of
opening a way for exploiters of the Indians has blocked this needed
measure.  The conscience of their guardian is as tender towards
these wards now as it once was lethargic.  Last year Representative
Lacey of the House Committee on Indian Affairs introduced a bill
into Congress authorizing the President in his discretion to allot
tribal funds and open separate accounts with individuals.  The bill
was amended in the Senate to allow the President to designate
individuals of a tribe who had shown <pb n="488"/>  the capacity to use
money wisely, as allottees of tribal funds.  But this would leave
a common fund to be divided later, and would not meet the views of
the Indians' well-wishers.  Unsatisfactory as the amended bill was,
however, the Indian Office urged it as a first step.  But the
measure failed of enactment.
</p><p>Certain "Treaty" funds, derived usually from "agreements to be
good," the income from which is available, but the principal of
which has never been appropriated by Congress, should also be
capitalized and segregated.  Periodical payments of interest on
these funds, usually in trifling sums, serve to remind the Indian
that he is still a dependent.  For example, the Oneidas of
Wisconsin, more than two thousand in number, are entitled to the
annual payment of $1,000.  The majority of them are farmers.  They
live well, in neat houses, and their children are at school.  In no
way do they require the material help of the Government.  Yet once
a year the whole tribe is called away from home to draw forty-eight
cents apiece!
</p><p>Whether the yearly dole be forty-eight cents, interest on a
Treaty Fund, or $350, earned by the large Osage Trust Fund, the
objection to it holds.  The Commissioner of Indian Affairs has
clearly indicated that as long as tribal funds remain undivided
"the Government has no way of setting free and closing the door
behind any Indian who is able fully to care for his own."  That the
way back to idleness and dependence should be left open is a
legitimate cause for complaint among the modern Indians.
</p><p>Of the fifty-one and a half millions of acres of land occupied
by the "reservation" Indians, nearly thirty-two millions lie within
the States and Territories of Arizona, New Mexico, California,
Nevada, Utah, Oregon, Idaho, Wyoming and Montana.  Ten and a half
millions more are included in the Dakotas.  In all these eleven
States and Territories irrigation is a vital subject, and in most
it is counted upon to make whatever future lies before them.
Nearly seventeen millions of acres of Arizona's huge area are owned
by Indians; not one acre in a thousand is arable without water.
The same is true of the million seven hundred thousand acres of
Indian land in New Mexico.  Most of the seven and a half millions
of acres held by the Montana tribes will not be productive without
irrigation.  Idaho's nine hundred and fifty thousand acres, and
Wyoming's million seven hundred and fifty thousand acres of tribal
holdings are mainly arid <pb n="489"/>  and semi-arid.  The ten millions
of acres in the Dakotas include great tracts of drought-smitten
land.  How vital, therefore, to the modern, progressive Indian a
vigorous irrigation policy is can be understood from these figures.
</p><p>The white man with whom the Indian must expect to compete in
the West is having his irrigation needs attended to by the
Government; the Reclamation Service is working at top speed,
hampered only by the difficulty of getting workmen, and its plans
are enlarging marvellously.  But the Reclamation Service has
nothing to do with putting water on Indian lands except in a half-dozen instances where a part of a reservation happens to fall
within a big project.  To the Indian Office is left the task of
making arid Indian lands productive, and the Indian Office is
severely handicapped for the task.  Until two years ago only Indian
funds could be used to construct irrigation works; last year and
the year before Congress appropriated $185,000 "for construction of
ditches and reservoirs, purchase and use of irrigation tools and
appliances, and purchase of water rights on reservations."  The sum
is a paltry one.  It will be needed to outfit surveyors and to
"begin to get ready to dig."
</p><p>Thus far the Government's work in supplying water to the
reservations has been of a haphazard character.  It has been
undertaken, not primarily to make the cactus desert and the
sagebrush plain blossom, but to provide work for able-bodied
Indians in lieu of rations.  Whole systems built under this policy
have been swept away by floods.  In the cases of the Mission
Indians of California and the Pimas of Arizona, the Indian Office
has not been able even to protect the tribesmen in their use of
water that had been theirs for years.  White settlers above the
reservations calmly appropriated the flow that had made the Mission
Indians and the Pimas prosperous and self-supporting, and the
Indian Office saw these people beggared.  With the best intentions
in the world, the Indian Office can make only the weakest showing
with its own Reclamation Service.  In the last report of the
Commissioner of Indian Affairs, eleven separate projects for
putting water on reservations are described; in but a single
instance was it possible to record more than the merest beginning.
</p><p>Seven years ago the agent for the Pine Ridge Sioux in South
Dakota reported that the annual average death-rate on the
reservation was fifty-two per thousand.  Last year, Dr. J. R.
Walker, <pb n="490"/>  one of the two agency physicians, reported that
this rate had been reduced to thirty-two per thousand.  The
difference represents a saving due to Dr. Walker's long campaign
against ignorance of sanitary laws.  So successful has this
campaign been that last year the Indians themselves collected all
but a small fraction of the money needed to publish in their native
Dakotah language a pamphlet describing a clean, well-regulated
home, and instructing home-builders in drainage and ventilation.
</p><p>The change from tepee to cabin has cost scores of lives, and
is likely to cost thousands more.  The old Indian camp was
frequently changed; the wind blowing through the tents counteracted
the effects of lax sanitation.  When the cabin was built and the
permanent home on the allotment established, the Indian did not
realize the necessity for changing his habits of life.  Filthy,
overcrowded, overhot shanties breed tuberculosis.  Ignorance of
"civilized" clothes, leading to the wearing of thick garments in
summer and thin garments in winter as often as the other way about,
makes pneumonia a serious menace.  Ignorance of the meaning of
quarantine leads to epidemics that carry off a much larger
percentage of victims than among the whites.
</p><p>It has been impossible for the government's physicians to
teach the newly-housed Indian how to live.  Their time is fully
occupied with the urgent cases.  On the Pine Ridge reservation, for
example, which is approximately the size of Connecticut, there are
two doctors to look after the health of 7,000 Sioux.  Neither of
these has been supplied with surgical instruments; indeed, surgery,
so far as the Bureau of Indian affairs is concerned, might never
have been practised.  Still, the modern Indian does not complain
that doctors are scarce, for in all of the thinly settled West the
doctor is a rare visitor.  His just cause for discontent is that he
has been urged to build a house and wear "store clothes" without
being told how to live under a roof and save woollen underclothes
for cold weather.  Agents, agency physicians, school
superintendents and field matrons continue to send in alarming
reports, showing the spread of the "white plague" among the tribes.
They emphasize the importance of a campaign of instruction, and
they point out the immediate need of a sanitarium and school in the
Southwest where all consumptive Indians, adults and children, may
be sent.
</p><p>It is important, if the "white man's West" and the Indian's
<pb n="491"/>  West are to merge, that the children of Indian
parents shall
be educated, wherever possible, in the same schools with white boys
and girls.  A few of the progressive men in the tribes realize
this, though the average Indian does not.  From reports made to the
Bureau at Washington it is found that about 450 public schools are
either on reservations or near enough to permit Indian children to
attend.  In case a public school takes a reservation pupil, the
Government agrees to pay to the county authorities the
proportionate cost of its teaching.  Last year, however, only
ninety-four contracts of this kind were made&mdash;ninety-four Indian
children enrolled in the common public schools out of a total, in
Government, mission and non-reservation contract schools, of
29,500.  To the Indian's own indifference this small showing is
mainly due, but there exists in the West, besides, a strong
prejudice against seating an Indian child beside a white child.
</p><p>The Westerner's aversion to the reservation pupil is
unfortunate.  It discourages the newer type of Indian, for no one
sees clearer than he the need for beginning the process of merger
at the earliest possible moment.  He has accepted in good faith the
doctrine that his tribal life must be changed, that he must become
in every sense a competitor of the white man.  The logical result
of such a recognition of superior wisdom would be to secure that
wisdom, along with the white man, at a common source.  In theory,
the public-school authorities of the West agree; in many cases
Indian children are included in the State scholastic census, and
funds are apportioned as though the doors of the schools were not
shut to the little shy people.  A small cloud now, this prejudice
will assume a very real importance as the tribesmen come to closer
grips with their white neighbors.
</p><p>In the bill of complaint filed against their white neighbors
and the Government by the modern "reservation" Indians, the usurer
and the trickster, familiar pests in the white man's West, are
cited as defendants.  These have succeeded the conscienceless old
traders.  Their methods are different, but their aim is the same&mdash;
to strip the ignorant Indian of everything that can be obtained.
In his report to the Indian Office in 1905, Colonel Randlett, one
of the best Indian agents in the service, in charge of the Kiowa
agency in Oklahoma, cites an interesting case.  An Oklahoma bank
official was arrested for trespassing on the reservation.  His
business there, he explained, was to collect interest on loans
<pb n="492"/>  made to Indians.  On inquiry, it was found that these loans
bore interest at any rate between 150 and 3,360 per cent.
</p><p>The case was not an isolated one, wrote Colonel Randlett.
"This practice of extorting usurious rates of interest (from the
Indians) is not confined to the despised professional gamblers, but
is generally found to be a habit of senior officials of National as
well as State banks."  Wherever periodical payments are made to
tribes, or where personal property can be secured as pledges, loan
sharks thrive, and it is not an unreasonable demand the Indians
make who want to be protected from them.
</p><p>Trickery of another kind is reported by the agent in charge of
the Shawnee, Pottawottomi and Kickapoo reservation in Oklahoma.  In
an Act of Congress approved March 3, 1905, restrictions were
removed from the allotments of seven Kickapoo Indians.  Six of
these lay adjacent to the growing town of Shawnee, and are of
exceptional value as town-site additions.  The agent declares that
"unless some legal steps are taken to prevent the passing of title
from the Indians interested, they will soon have lost property
worth no less than $100,000.  This matter certainly represents a
gigantic fraudulent scheme."  It is accepted by the intelligent
Indians as well as their well-wishers among the whites that the
only way to teach the tribesman the value of land and money is to
let him use it.  But this does not mean connivance with sharpers.
It does not mean, as in the case of the Colville Indians in
Washington, allowing white men to go upon a reservation and
"locate" a farm under pretence of working the claim as a placer
mine.  Captain Webster, in charge of the Colville agency, hints
that "here is a fine field for an expert to trap a conscienceless
lot of individuals and corporations who regard Government holdings
as legitimate prey."
</p><p>Between the liquor-seller and the Government the old quarrel
over the right of an Indian to buy whiskey has reached a
threatening stage.  The Supreme Court held, in a recent decision,
that it is not against the law to sell liquor to an Indian who has
taken his allotment, and, by that act, become a citizen of the
United States.  An Act of Congress, long relied upon by the Indian
Office to keep the Indian and whiskey apart, was by this decision
declared unconstitutional.  It was declared to be an infringement
upon the rights of citizens.  In spite of the decision, the Indian
Office has declared that an allotted Indian must go out-<pb n="493"/> side
the reservation, or off his allotment, to buy liquor.  It is
anticipated that the whiskey-sellers will keep up the fight and
attempt to secure the removal of the remaining restrictions.  No
one is more interested than the modern Indian in the efforts of the
Indian Office to put off the time for letting the tribesman have
free access to the saloons until he has become a competing factor
in the life of his community.  No one is more concerned over the
victories of the liquor-sellers.  Whiskey flows toward all
frontiers, and is one of the "civilizing influences" that is
resisted by white men as vigorously as by the shrewd Indian who
wishes to preserve his race as industrial competitors.
</p><p>When the trust periods begin to expire on allotments already
taken by the Indians, as they will in five years, there will be
confusion.  Questions of heirship that should have been settled
long ago will involve Indians in costly litigation.  A majority
perhaps of the allottees will have died in the trust periods.  Who
is to inherit?  Registers of marriages and records of family
relationships are wofully incomplete, and there looms ahead endless
costly suits among claimants, with only the lawyers to profit
thereby.  Left to themselves, the Indians had no incentive to
record their family histories.  It is a necessity imposed upon them
by the adoption of our laws, and it is a just cause for complaint
that the making of these records has been neglected.
</p><p>The bill of complaint contains many minor counts, such as the
new greed of the monopolists who are allowed to trade with the
Indians, the costly restrictions on the sale of inherited Indian
lands, and the demoralizing "work system."  Certain of these counts
are directed against a Government that is striving with honesty and
vigor to satisfy its wards, and some against the white civilization
that surrounds the Indian.  In its body, the bill is in striking
contrast to those so often drawn in the last half-century.  To an
extraordinary degree, it embodies the complaints heard by the alert
traveller in any part of the sparsely settled West, whether Indian
reservation or white settlement.  It is significant as indicating
the practical disappearance of the old "Indian question," and more
significant as a sign that the tribesman is becoming a factor in
his community.
</p>
<p>JOHN M. OSKISON.</p>


</div1>
</body>
</text>
</TEI.2>
