<?xml version="1.0"?>

<?dlps id="OskDive"?>
<?dlps page-images="none" figure-images="no"?>
<?dlps transcription="other"?>

<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/tei-p4/tei2.dtd" [
<!ENTITY % POSTKB "INCLUDE">
<!ENTITY % TEI.extensions.ent SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.ent">
<!ENTITY % TEI.extensions.dtd SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.dtd">
<!ENTITY % ISOnum SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/charent/iso-num.ent"> %ISOnum;
<!ENTITY % ISOpub SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/charent/iso-pub.ent"> %ISOpub;

]>

<TEI.2 id="OskDive">
<teiHeader type="migrated" creator="Etext">
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title type="main">Diverse Tongues: A Sketch</title>
<title type="sort">diverse tongues a sketch</title>
<author>Oskison, John M.</author>
<respStmt>
<resp>Creation of machine-readable version</resp>
<name>Judy Boss, University of Omaha</name>
</respStmt>
<respStmt>
<resp>Conversion to TEI-conformant markup</resp>
<name>University of Virginia Library Electronic Text Center</name>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt>
<extent>ca. <num type="kilobytes">10</num> kilobytes</extent>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>University of Virginia Library</publisher>
<pubPlace>Charlottesville, Virginia</pubPlace>
<idno type="ETC">OskDive</idno>
<date value="1995">1995</date>
<availability status="public">
<p n="copyright">Copyright &copy; 1995 by the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia</p>
<p n="access">Publicly accessible</p>
</availability>
<idno type="uva-pid">uva-lib:476267</idno>
</publicationStmt>
<seriesStmt>
<title>University of Virginia Library, Text collection</title>
<idno type="uva-set">UVA-LIB-Text</idno>
</seriesStmt>
<sourceDesc>
<biblFull>
<titleStmt>
<title type="main">Diverse Tongues: A Sketch</title>
<title type="sort">diverse tongues a sketch</title>
<author>Oskison, John</author>
</titleStmt>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>Current Literature</publisher>
<date value="1910-09">September 1910</date>
</publicationStmt>
<seriesStmt>
<p>Vol. 49</p>
</seriesStmt>
</biblFull>
</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc>
<encodingDesc>
<projectDesc>
<p>Prepared for the University of Virginia Library Electronic Text Center</p>
</projectDesc>
<editorialDecl>
<p>All quotation marks retained as data</p>
<p>Verification made against printed text</p>
<p>All unambiguous end-of-line hyphens have been removed, and the
trailing part of a word has been joined to the preceding line.</p>
<p id="ETC">Keywords in the header are a local Electronic Text Center scheme
to aid in establishing analytical groupings</p>
</editorialDecl>
<refsDecl>
<p>ID elements are given for each page element and are composed of the text's
unique cryptogram and the given page number, as in SpeFQue1 for page one of
Spenser's Faerie Queene.</p>
</refsDecl>
</encodingDesc>
<profileDesc>
<creation>
<date value="1910">1910</date>
</creation>
<langUsage>
<language id="eng" usage="main">English</language>
</langUsage>
<textClass>
<keywords>
<term>fiction; prose</term>
</keywords>
</textClass>
</profileDesc>
<revisionDesc>
<change>
<date value="1995-02">February 1995</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>corrector</resp>
<name>Kelly Tetterton</name>
</respStmt>
<item>updated header and tags</item>
</change>
<change>
<date value="1995-01">January 1995</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>corrector</resp>
<name>David Seaman</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Header and basic TEI SGML encoding added</item>
</change>
<change>
<date value="2005-07">July 2005</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>Corrector</resp>
<name>John Ivor Carlson</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Converted to XML and/or checked tags.</item>
</change>
<change>
<date value="2007-09">September 2007</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>Migration</resp>
<name>Ethan Gruber, University of Virginia Library</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Converted XML markup from TEI Lite to uva-dl-tei (TEI P4 with local customizations).</item>
</change>
<change>
<date value="2008-01">January 2008</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>Migration</resp>
<name>Greg Murray, University of Virginia Library</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Programmatically updated TEI header markup (but not header content) for minimal compliance with current QA requirements.</item>
</change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>
<text id="d1">

<body id="d2">
<div1 type="story" id="d3">
<head>
Oskison, John.  "Diverse Tongues: A Sketch."  <lb/>
<hi rend="italic"> Current Literature</hi> 49 (Sept. 1910): 343-344.
</head>
<pb n="343"/>

<p>Several months ago a new magazine made its appearance in New
York.  Its title is "1910."  Next year its title will be "1911."
It is a labor of love, being conducted by a little group of writers
and artists who contribute to its columns whatsoever each one is
pleased to contribute.  So far the result has been good for the
readers as well as the contributors.  The following sketch is taken
from its columns.  It is written by John Oskison and it leaves one
a little teary around the eye-lashes.

</p><p>"YES, at twelve o'clock to-night."
</p><p>"What's that, Bess?  What's going to happen at twelve
o'clock?"
</p><p>At the Chief Engineer's table sat a young woman of eighteen;
on one side sat her brother, a boy of fifteen, and opposite to her
sat a youth of twenty, the light of her eyes.  It was the brother's
shrill, impulsive, impatient question that had disturbed the table.
</p><p>"Why don't you listen, 'Greedy'?"  The last word was
whispered, and as she spoke the girl's eyes were half turned to her
mother, sitting beyond the boy.
</p><p>"Oh, Bess, tell me what's going to happen at twelve o'clock."
The boy had ignored the taunt.
</p><p>"Well, if you must know, little 'Pop Eyes' (again she lowered
her voice), they're going to bury a little boy in the sea&mdash;a little
boy about your size."  The girl's tone was supremely irritating;
her brother shrilled: "Oh, Bess, you....!"  But he got no farther.
The mother, a powerful, blonde woman of forty, turned, and,
wheeling the boy's chair, commanded, "Leave the table at once,
Wendel!"  When he had gone she turned to her daughter: "Were you
teasing Wendel, Bess?"
</p><p>"No, Mama.  I was telling Bruce what the third officer told
Grace Clarkson and me to-day.  A little child died in the steerage
yesterday, and it is to be buried at sea to-night at twelve
o'clock.  Then Wendel wanted to hear, and I told him he should have
listened."
</p><p>"Wendel is very quick tempered."  The mother resumed her
dinner placidly.
</p><p>The third officer had spread his news well.  After dinner, in
the smoke room, it caused a little pause in the animated
conversation of the groups into which it fell; on deck, one couple
of promenaders met another, the four talked eagerly together for a
moment and went on a little less boisterously; over their coffee in
the social hall, the older women discussed the possibility of
anyone, young or old, ill or well, surviving a voyage in the
steerage.  Parties were formed and pledged one another to sit up to
"see it."
</p><p>The concert in the saloon was a good one that evening.  A
driving, mid-summer rain had sent all of the promenaders inside.
Looking around at the crowded tables, the round-faced cornettist,
leader of the orchestra, plunged into the opening spasm of a
popular march.  A rag-time piece followed, then the "Turkish
Patrol" was conducted to its post, the relief followed, and the
weary soldiers were marched away to barracks.  At ten o'clock the
"Poet and Peasant" had been played; and half an hour later, with
the final blast of "Silverheels," the leader packed his cornet
away, music racks collapsed at a touch, and the deafening hum of
two hundred persons talking rose to the decorated ceiling.
</p><p>Outside, the wind was still blowing fiercely, tho the rain had
ceased.  From the great yellow stacks of the steamer, banners of
black streamed across the stars.  The soft throb of the engines
could be heard only when one walked past the open ventilators on
the leeward side.  The boat deck was deserted save for a young
couple who <pb n="344"/>  had not forgotten their resolution, made during
the concert, to come up and "wait for the funeral."  Until half-past eleven occasional heads were thrust above the companionways
and withdrawn at the first blast of wind that sucked down from
above.
</p><p>Except for the light beside the log at the very stern and two
luminous windows in the little steerage deck cabin, the ship seemed
as lifeless as a derelict, and as dark.  The stern light shone
clear on the outcurving arm of a life-boat davit; one watching it
for five minutes might see the white davit turn into the long neck
of a peering, grinning monster, looking overside at the seething
froth behind the screws to find there, if he might, some joke
worthy of his mirth.  Pinned to the railing twenty feet forward of
the log-light and flapping wildly in the wind, was a row of baby-napkins, placed there to dry before sunset and forgotten.
</p><p>Eight bells had struck and the faint sound of hammering that
had been heard at intervals in the last half-hour continued.  For
some reason there was a delay.
</p><p>At the quarter-hour past midnight, the door of the small
steerage cabin was opened; the light from within shone faintly on
the drying deck.  Then the light was obscured; steps sounded,
shuffling and muffled, and two sailors, bareheaded, appeared, with
the little box carried between them.  Behind came the captain,
stepping briskly.  The doctor was there&mdash;as he came out of the door
he flung a cigaret overboard.  The third officer closed the door
after him, and for a moment the procession was lost to sight.  It
reappeared in the glow of the log-light.  Halting abruptly, the
sailors balanced the box on the rail.  One end of it was obviously
heavier than the other.  Someone at dinner had remarked: "They put
coal in to weight it, but it never goes to the bottom&mdash;the water's
too dense."
</p><p>The captain stepped up beside the railing, took off his cap
and placed his hand on the balancing box.  He was slightly bald and
quite gray.  In the feeble light his real face showed pale,
ascetic, and the gold braiding of his uniform could not be seen.
Shadows made him priestlike.  The doctor's cap came off, the third
officer uncovered, there was a moment of stillness, the captain
muttered: "One, two, three, in God's name," nodded, and the two
sailors slipped the box quietly off the rail.

                      *  *  *  *  *<lb/>

</p><p>"Ye Gods, it's dark up here, Bess."
</p><p>"Yes; mother would have a fit if she knew we'd been here for
an hour&mdash;Cut it out, Bruce; no, I won't kiss you!&mdash;Say!  Listen to
that."  Up from the steerage deck rose a sane sentence of grief:
</p><p><hi rend="italic"> "He was my little-a baby; now he is in the great sea; God
help-a me."</hi>
</p>

</div1>
</body>
</text></TEI.2>
