<?xml version="1.0"?>

<?dlps id="OskFrie"?>
<?dlps page-images="none" figure-images="no"?>
<?dlps transcription="other"?>

<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/tei-p4/tei2.dtd" [
<!ENTITY % POSTKB "INCLUDE">
<!ENTITY % TEI.extensions.ent SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.ent">
<!ENTITY % TEI.extensions.dtd SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.dtd">
<!ENTITY % ISOnum SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/charent/iso-num.ent"> %ISOnum;
<!ENTITY % ISOpub SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/charent/iso-pub.ent"> %ISOpub;
]>

<TEI.2 id="OskFrie">
<teiHeader type="migrated" creator="Etext">
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title type="main">"Friends of the Indian."</title>
<title type="sort">friends of the indian</title>
<author>Oskison, John M.</author>
<respStmt>
<resp>Creation of machine-readable version:</resp>
<name>Judy Boss</name>
<resp>Conversion to TEI.2-conformant markup:</resp>
<name>University of Virginia Library Electronic Text Center</name>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt>
<extent>ca. <num type="kilobytes">10</num> kilobytes</extent>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>University of Virginia Library</publisher>
<pubPlace>Charlottesville, Virginia</pubPlace>
<idno type="ETC">OskFrie</idno>
<date value="1995">1995</date>
<availability status="public">
<p n="copyright">Copyright &copy; 1995 by the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia</p>
<p n="access">Publicly accessible</p>
</availability>
<idno type="uva-pid">uva-lib:476268</idno>
</publicationStmt>
<seriesStmt>
<title>University of Virginia Library, Text collection</title>
<idno type="uva-set">UVA-LIB-Text</idno>
</seriesStmt>
<sourceDesc>
<biblFull>
<titleStmt>
<title type="main">"Friends of the Indian"</title>
<title type="sort">friends of the indian</title>
<author>John Okison</author>
</titleStmt>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>New York Evening Post Company</publisher>
<pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
<date value="1905">1905</date>
</publicationStmt>
<seriesStmt>
<p>The Nation; A Weekly Journal
81, 26  Oct. 1905: 332-333.</p>
</seriesStmt>
<notesStmt>
<note>
<p>Journal is devoted to politics, literature,
science &amp; art</p>
</note>
</notesStmt>
</biblFull>
</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc>
<encodingDesc>
<projectDesc>
<p>Prepared for the University of Virginia Library Electronic Text Center</p>
</projectDesc>
<editorialDecl>
<p>All quotation marks retained as data</p>
<p>Spell-check and verification made
against printed text using WordPerfect spell checker</p>
<p>All unambiguous end-of-line hyphens have been removed, and the
trailing part of a word has been joined to the preceding line.</p>
<p id="ETC">Keywords in the header are a local Electronic Text Center scheme
to aid in establishing analytical groupings</p>
</editorialDecl>
<refsDecl>
<p>ID elements are given for each page element and are composed of the text's
unique cryptogram and the given page number, as in AusEmma1 for page one of
Jane Austen's Emma.</p>
</refsDecl>
</encodingDesc>
<profileDesc>
<creation>
<date value="1905">1905</date>
</creation>
<langUsage>
<language id="eng" usage="main">English</language>
</langUsage>
<textClass>
<keywords>
<term>non-fiction; prose</term>
<term>Native American</term>
</keywords>
</textClass>
</profileDesc>
<revisionDesc>
<change>
<date value="1995-08">August 1995</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>corrector</resp>
<name>Lorrie S. Chisholm, Electronic Text Center, University of
Virginia Library System.</name>
</respStmt>
<item>General TEI tagging, removed unambiguous line-end hyphenation
and ran electronic spellcheck using wp5.</item>
</change>
<change>
<date value="2005-07">July 2005</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>Corrector</resp>
<name>John Ivor Carlson</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Converted to XML and/or checked tags.</item>
</change>
<change>
<date value="2007-09">September 2007</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>Migration</resp>
<name>Ethan Gruber, University of Virginia Library</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Converted XML markup from TEI Lite to uva-dl-tei (TEI P4 with local customizations).</item>
</change>
<change>
<date value="2008-01">January 2008</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>Migration</resp>
<name>Greg Murray, University of Virginia Library</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Programmatically updated TEI header markup (but not header content) for minimal compliance with current QA requirements.</item>
</change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text id="d1">
<body id="d2">




<div1 type="article" id="d3"><pb n="332"/>
<head><hi rend="italic">"FRIENDS OF THE INDIAN."</hi></head>

<p>At last year's "Lake Mohonk Conference of Friends of the
Indian and Other Dependent Peoples," Mr. Bonaparte quoted a naval
officer as once declaring that "the service would never be worth a
&mdash; until all the well-meaning people in it had been hanged."  He
hinted that something of the same tenor might have been said with
equal justice of the activity of champions of the Indian who are
merely well-meaning.  Knowledge and discretion in those who have
undertaken unofficially to influence the conduct of Indian affairs
would have tempered their zeal usefully in the years when service
was most needed; and, though little fault can now be found with the
methods and personnel of the Indian Rights Association and similar
bodies, there is still a too noticeable tendency to let good
intentions evaporate in earnest, purposeless talk.  That "court of
final appeal, public opinion," has been appealed to so often that
the last advocate must needs be silver-tongued indeed to rouse more
than a momentary interest.  The Indian service, bad as it has been
at times, has accomplished more for the disappearing natives than
it has been credited with in the popular mind.  It would have done
still more if its critics had been inspired by accurate information
and good judgment.
</p><p>Suppose some well-informed, persistent friend of the Pimas in
Arizona had taken up the matter of white encroachment on the
tribe's water rights along the Gila River eighteen years ago.  Is
it conceivable that he would have advised the poor Indians to take
the matter to the Department of Justice?  If he had done that, he
would have gone contrary to the teachings of history.  He might
have foreseen exactly what happened last year when the


<pb n="333"/>

district attorney in charge of the case recommended that the suit
begun in 1886 be dropped on the ground of the excessive costs of
pushing it to a favorable conclusion, and the impossibility of
enforcing a decree "because of the varied interests involved."  The
moral of Indian litigation against the invading settler could have
been read as plainly in 1886 as in 1876 or in 1905: The Indian,
"not taxed, not voting," has no real standing in the courts
organized by and for the American people.  The "varied interests
involved" was a phrase in common use long ago to explain away
apparent miscarriages of justice.  Those 960 white settlers using
the water from the Gila River which for generations had irrigated
the Pimas' wheat fields, were as confident of holding their ditches
when they built them as it is in human experience to be.  Why,
then, did the Indians go to court and patiently watch their fields
revert to desert land while the proceedings dragged along for half
a generation?  Simply because some well-meaning, unhanged friends
advised them that they had a good case.
</p><p>It is not the despairing cynic who advises the Indian, "For
God's sake, get the ballot in your hands as soon as possible."
Thirty years ago, a Commissioner of Indian Affairs, commenting on
the twenty-five years' struggle of the California Mission Indians
to preserve themselves, said: "This class of Indians seems forcibly
to illustrate the truth that no man has a place or a fair chance to
exist under the Government of the United States who has no part in
it."  It is such elementary considerations as this that have been
overlooked by the friends of the Indian.  In Congress, the final
court where the cause of a dependent people is decided, the white
invader has representation, and the Indian has none.  Bishop
Whipple, in 1863, said: "I submit to every man the question whether
the time has not come for a nation to hear the cry of wrong, if not
for the sake of the heathen [Indian], for the sake of the memory of
our friends whose bones are bleaching on our prairies."  In 1877,
the white settlers of the Northwest prevailed upon their
representatives in Congress to remove the small Ponca tribe of
Indians from their old home in southeastern Dakota, where they had
built comfortable houses and opened farms, to the Indian Territory,
where in a year a third of their number died.  The Ponca
reservation was wanted for those troublesome Sioux who were keeping
the gold-hunters out of the Black Hills.  The nation "heard" the
cry of wrong, as uttered by Bishop Whipple; but Congress drove the
Poncas from the Niobrara in obedience to the demands of a handful
of constituents in Iowa, Minnesota, and Nebraska.
</p><p>On the whole, the Audubon movement has succeeded better than
that to protect the Indians.  Bishop Whipple and those who meet
annually at Lake Mohonk have insisted, and do insist, that the
Government deal with the Indians as with human beings whose rights
are co-extensive with those of the whites.  Theoretically, their
attitude is correct.  Public opinion has approved them and
applauded their sentiments.  Practically, they have plodded along
without accomplishing as much as could an obscure Western member of
the House of Representatives with a vote on a harbor-improvement
bill to trade for a vote to dam Salt River and irrigate Grass
Valley.  The Indian, until he is absorbed and enfranchised, is not
a "person."  That was settled in California in the course of the
degradation of the Mission tribes.  Treaties and agreements with
Indians may be abrogated at the pleasure of Congress.  That was
finally and formally decided by the Supreme Court in the Lone Wolf
case, two years ago.  The attitude of the settler, at whose request
every Indian removal has been made and every tribal reservation
extinguished, has been plain and consistent from the beginning.  It
has been equally plain that the settler, with a sympathetic and
industrious representative in Congress, would decide the attitude
of the Indian Department.
</p><p>The need for friends with discretion and detailed knowledge of
the economic and political history of the tribes is, of course,
obvious at this day.  It should be just as obvious in the case of
the other "dependent peoples" whose welfare under the guidance of
our Government is becoming more and more the subject of friendly
discussion at Lake Mohonk.  The promoter of an inter-island
steamship line for the Philippines has his champion in Congress,
while Secretary Taft has no vote to trade, and can only offer a
trip to Manila for a vote to reduce the duties on imports from the
islands.
</p>

</div1>
</body>
</text>
</TEI.2>
