<?xml version="1.0"?>

<?dlps id="OyeLast"?>
<?dlps page-images="none" figure-images="no"?>
<?dlps transcription="other"?>

<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/tei-p4/tei2.dtd" [
<!ENTITY % POSTKB "INCLUDE">
<!ENTITY % TEI.extensions.ent SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.ent">
<!ENTITY % TEI.extensions.dtd SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.dtd">
<!ENTITY % ISOnum SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/charent/iso-num.ent"> %ISOnum;
<!ENTITY % ISOpub SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/charent/iso-pub.ent"> %ISOpub;
]>

<TEI.2 id="OyeLast">
<teiHeader type="migrated" creator="Etext">
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title type="main">"The Last Protest: A Story of Montana."</title>
<title type="sort">the last protest a story of montana</title>
<author>Oyen, Henry</author>
<respStmt>
<resp>Creation of machine-readable version:</resp>
<name>Judy Boss</name>
<resp>Conversion to TEI.2-conformant markup:</resp>
<name>University of Virginia Library Electronic Text Center</name>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt>
<extent>ca. <num type="kilobytes">25</num> kilobytes</extent>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>University of Virginia Library</publisher>
<pubPlace>Charlottesville, Virginia</pubPlace>
<idno type="ETC">OyeLast</idno>
<date value="1995">1995</date>
<availability status="public">
<p n="copyright">Copyright &copy; 1995 by the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia</p>
<p n="access">Publicly accessible</p>
</availability>
<idno type="uva-pid">uva-lib:476275</idno>
</publicationStmt>
<seriesStmt>
<title>University of Virginia Library, Text collection</title>
<idno type="uva-set">UVA-LIB-Text</idno>
</seriesStmt>
<sourceDesc>
<biblFull>
<titleStmt>
<title type="main">"The Last Protest: A Story of Montana"</title>
<title type="sort">the last protest a story of montana</title>
<author>Henry Oyen</author>
</titleStmt>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>The Century Co.</publisher>
<pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
<date value="1904">1904</date>
</publicationStmt>
<seriesStmt>
<p>
<hi rend="italic">Century Magazine</hi> 68 (1904): Pages 319-324.</p>
</seriesStmt>
</biblFull>
</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc>
<encodingDesc>
<projectDesc>
<p>Prepared for the University of Virginia Library Electronic Text Center</p>
</projectDesc>
<editorialDecl>
<p>All quotation marks retained as data</p>
<p>Spell-check and verification made
against printed text using WordPerfect spell checker</p>
<p>All unambiguous end-of-line hyphens have been removed, and the
trailing part of a word has been joined to the preceding line.</p>
<p id="ETC">Keywords in the header are a local Electronic Text Center scheme
to aid in establishing analytical groupings</p>
</editorialDecl>
<refsDecl>
<p>ID elements are given for each page element and are composed of the text's
unique cryptogram and the given page number, as in AusEmma1 for page one of
Jane Austen's Emma.</p>
</refsDecl>
</encodingDesc>
<profileDesc>
<creation>
<date value="1904">1904</date>
</creation>
<langUsage>
<language id="eng" usage="main">English</language>
</langUsage>
<textClass>
<keywords>
<term>fiction, prose</term>
<term>Native American</term>
</keywords>
</textClass>
</profileDesc>
<revisionDesc>
<change>
<date value="1995-08-03">August 3, 1995</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>corrector</resp>
<name>Lorrie S. Chisholm, Electronic Text Center, University of
Virginia Library System.</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Minimal TEI tagging, removed unambiguous line-end hyphenation
and ran electronic spell-check using wp51.</item>
</change>
<change>
<date value="2005-07">July 2005</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>Corrector</resp>
<name>John Ivor Carlson</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Converted to XML and/or checked tags.</item>
</change>
<change>
<date value="2007-09">September 2007</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>Migration</resp>
<name>Ethan Gruber, University of Virginia Library</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Converted XML markup from TEI Lite to uva-dl-tei (TEI P4 with local customizations).</item>
</change>
<change>
<date value="2008-01">January 2008</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>Migration</resp>
<name>Greg Murray, University of Virginia Library</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Programmatically updated TEI header markup (but not header content) for minimal compliance with current QA requirements.</item>
</change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text id="d1">
<body id="d2">
<div1 type="part" n="1" id="d3">
<pb n="319"/>
<p>WHEN the teachers at the government school had instructed Young
Moon thoroughly in the various branches of knowledge prescribed in
the course, they presented him with an engrossed diploma setting
forth his qualifications as a scholar, and told him that the great
wide world was before him&mdash;his to conquer or serve as he saw fit.
</p><p>The teachers were very well satisfied with Young Moon.  They
had seen him come to the school from the tepees up in the valley
with the dark, unreasoning savagery of the ages in his heart.  They
had taken him just as he came to them, and had wrought with him;
and now when he departed there was enlightenment where there had
been darkness, and civilization where the savage had held sway.  So
the teachers were vain of him,&mdash;for was he not all their
handiwork?&mdash;and had visions of him performing miracles in the work
of elevating his own people.  Which was all very pleasant and
satisfying.
</p><p>Young Moon took the diploma and went back to the tepees by the
river.  The great outside world which the teachers pictured so
alluringly held no charms for him.  He had been to the school of
the white man, and he had seen, and he knew that the ways of the
white brother were positively not as his ways.  The fact was
ridiculously evident to Young Moon.  What possible good could there
be in a community where one must of a necessity eat at regular
intervals and wash himself with alarming frequency, where the
beauties of a mysterious thing called duty were continually dinned
into one's ears, and where the people lived, moved, and had their
being under the rule of an insignificant whirring clock?  What
sense could there be in abiding in the tepees of a dubious thrall
of work?  Why live, if one must make of himself a slave?  No, no;
Young Moon's philosophy of life ran far from such lines.
</p><p>So when the teachers at the school were through with him, he
was very well satisfied to return to the loose, duty-free ways of
his fathers, where soap and tooth-brushes were not, and where life
was not a constant, strained pursuit of "golden moments."
</p><p>It was good to be back in the tepees by the river.  This was
the place to live; it was life to feel the sense of full freedom of
the wide, free prairie, to see the Big Hills beckoning familiarly
from the blue, hazy distance, and to hear the river, which, with
its double rows of green cottonwoods, always sang down the valley.
Verily this was the place for an Indian; here was his home, here
his abiding-place on earth.  Here, all undisturbed by any false
notions of work and duty, the old life moved along in the old, old
way.  Each day was sufficient unto itself, and the days came in
never-failing supply, and there was peace and quiet.
</p><p>But there was not the peace of his fathers for Young Moon.  He
had learned too much.  He had imbibed the wisdom of the white man
to a disturbing degree, and he had become possessed of ideas.  This
was bad, inasmuch as they were ideas scarcely compatible with the
precepts of the teachers.
</p><p>The white man was master in a land where he should scarcely be
tolerated.  It was this idea that disturbed Young Moon's

<pb n="320"/>
peace of mind.  The white man was master.  All over, everywhere, in
the valley, were the signs of his superiority in numbers and power.
His houses lay scattered over the face of the land, his irrigation
ditches scarred the earth for miles and miles, and his fences were
binding the valley and the foot-hills in a bond of hostile barb-wire.
In a few years there would be only white men in the valley.
</p><p>Of course this idea was old and foolish.  The old men laughed
at Young Moon in the council-tepee.
</p><p>"Yoh, yoh," they said; "what the young man says is true&mdash;very
true.  But others have said the same many times before him."  And
they lighted their pipes indifferently.
</p><p>Young Moon came away from the old men with a hard, dry lump in
his throat.  The humbled acquiescence of his people to the order of
things that were had angered him.  These things were all wrong, and
the old men knew it.  Yet they sat and smoked in indolent, dog-like
content.  The old men were surely squaws.
</p><p>Young Moon lighted a thin, flat cigarette and gazed out over
the valley.  He was not in a frame of mind conducive to sweet,
conventional thoughts.  He had gone to the council-tepee with his
mind full of great ideas for the peaceful reform of conditions, and
the old men had laughed at him.  They had laughed and scoffed; they
had scoffed at him, Young Moon, who had been to the school and
knew, and all high motives and peaceful inclinations had fled from
him.
</p><p>It was July&mdash;hot, sultry July.  The Crows came out of their
tepees to sit cross-legged in the sun, gazing blankly out at the
dancing heat-haze and experiencing the many weird emotions that
come to the child of the tepees with the bright sun.  The women of
the tribe were methodically performing the duties of the household,
but the men had forgotten that such things existed.  An old man
grumblingly ordered a boy to go to work in the corn, and the boy,
sitting with wide-open eyes staring out into space, laughed without
moving.
</p><p>The sun is bad for young bucks; it is the sun that brings back
the old, half-forgotten desire for the war-path.  Young Moon, as he
sat gazing down the valley, began to feel and see as he had never
done before.  There was a red, misty haze over all the landscape.
In it moved men and animals and things; but they were not of the
time of Young Moon, at least the Young Moon whom the teachers had
known.
</p><p>Young Moon dreamed, and there came into the mist of red a
vision of the one-time glory of his people.  But he knew that this
was the past&mdash;dead and gone.  He dreamed again, and saw a picture
of glorious, bloody strife.  Things were clearer in the mist now,
and Young Moon saw the visions change, and in the place of the one
of strife was one of the glorious future: the Indian come into his
own again, and the country once more free&mdash;his alone.
</p><p>The sun grew red before Young Moon's eyes.  The river running
down the valley turned to a thread of blood.  He rose slowly and
went inside his tepee.  All day he sat there, gazing blankly at the
skin sides, but seeing far beyond.  Gradually his sight grew
stronger.  He saw a streak of flaming red which ran from the door
of his tepee far away toward the east, and which obliterated all
evidence of civilization in the valley.  Thus did the Great Spirit
evidence itself to Young Moon.  The Young Moon of the government
school, diploma, and civilization had died, and in his place was
the Young Moon of the tepees and primitive, savage instincts.
</p><p>Outside in the sun the other young bucks of the tribe sat and
awaited only a leader to turn them into heartless, ravaging
warriors.
</p><p>When the night came, an old squaw sat in the edge of gloom and
firelight and crooned softly an old war-song.  This was bad; not
for years had this song been sung in the tepees.  The old men
cursed the squaw fervidly and bade her be silent.
</p><p>"No, no!" growled the young men angrily, "she shall sing."
</p><p>The old squaw sang again, now an old song of prophecy and
golden promise.  A great medicine-man, impervious to death, was to
come and lead his people to the retaking of their own.  The time
was now ripe for his advent.  It was the old, old undying cry for
the Messiah, and as the old squaw ceased there was deep silence
around the fire.  A child coughed feebly as the smoke veered into
its face.  Somewhere in the dark a tepee flap flew back, and in an
instant the old men were on their feet, with angry imprecations on
their lips; for Young Moon, arrayed in the full glory of a chief on
the war-path, was standing by the fire.  The

<pb n="321"/>
old squaw ran
to him.  With both hands upon his shoulders, she gazed searchingly
into his eyes.  Then, raising a skinny claw into the air, she
shrieked loudly and called him the great one, the invulnerable, of
whom she had prophesied.  There would be much fighting and blood,
and freedom, now, she cried.  The days of sickening calm were over.
The old men sat and smoked, as impassive as graven images; but the
young braves slid noiselessly away in the dark, and returned
wearing the black feathers and buckskin apron of the Crow dancers.
An old chief by the fire deliberately took the pipe from his mouth.
"Young Moon looks well in the feathers&mdash;almost as well as a cow in
harness," he said pleasantly.
</p><p>"And Little Wolf is also a great man," retorted Young Moon,
hotly.  "He works well in the field, almost as well as the women."
</p><p>Little Wolf emitted a puff of smoke from between set teeth for
answer.
</p><p>"Why does not the great chief answer?" queried Young Moon,
sneeringly.  "A great man&mdash;a man who sells as much hay as does
Little Wolf&mdash;should talk much when the talk is to him."
</p><p>Still, Little Wolf gazed stolidly over the fire, apparently
mute and deaf.
</p><p>"Come, Little Wolf, you do not answer," continued Young Moon,
sweetly.  "Have the fences of the white man run across our great
chief's mouth that he is dead of tongue as well as of heart?"
</p><p>Little Wolf took the pipe from his mouth and arose.
</p><p>"Listen, boy," said he, solemnly, "to one who saw your father
die ere you could speak.  Your talk is the talk that all the bucks
utter when their years are of a certain number.  So have I heard
many talk; but all who have done as they talked are dead now.
Listen to my speech, Young Moon, and the rest of you, for I know of
what I speak.  I, too, was once of the age when the thirst for the
white man's scalp was strong.  But the white man still has his
scalp, and I&mdash;I am thankful to raise corn on the land he leaves to
me."
</p><p>The young men, as they looked, saw only a senile old man
gabbling aimlessly, while in Young Moon was their ideal of youthful
strength and leadership.
</p><p>Then Young Moon threw off all caution.  He was wild now&mdash;wild
with the old red desire for strife and bloody violence which had
become almost atrophied in him&mdash;and he would make the other young
men wild also.  He threw back his head and gave vent to a cry such
as had never in his day echoed through the tepees of the peaceful
Crows.  With shaking, twisting body he began to lope slowly toward
Little Wolf.  With a shout he swung out into a semi-circle, and
passing before the old men, returned to his starting-point.
</p><p>"Young Moon!  Young Moon!  What is it you do?" cried Little
Wolf, in alarm.  "It is not the moon of the dance; it is not the
time for the feathers.  The white man is not a child for boys to
make war upon.  'T is better to stay in the camp, where the food
and the women are plenty."
</p><p>Young Moon was looping toward him again.
</p><p>"For you is the tepee made to stay in, Little Wolf," he
shouted derisively.  "Go there, stay there with the women.  You are
old; that is your place now."
</p><p>He loped back in a slightly more pronounced curve.  "You are
old, Little Wolf," he called again.  "Your time has passed.  The
old, withered stalk must move to one side when the strong young
shoot comes forth."
</p><p>Another brave sprang suddenly into his wake.  The old squaw
squatted herself suddenly and began the ugly, monotonous "Ay-yah,
a-anah, ah-ya" of the dance-chant.  Young Moon sprang forward as if
spurred by some unseen power.  His course now became a circle
around the fire&mdash;a magic path on the ground for others to follow.
One by one the bucks fell in behind.  The young women came and
chanted; the dance was on.
</p><p>The old men deliberately placed their belongings and women in
wagons and moved away to a new camp, leaving the old one in
possession of the young men and their women.
</p><p>Far into the night the fires of the camp showed the weird,
dancing figures of Young Moon and his followers.  Also, Young Moon,
by reason of the knowledge of certain strange things acquired at
the school, performed many wonderful miracles, and the young men
also hailed him as the great medicine-man, and acknowledged him
their leader.
</p><p>Early on the morning of the next day they rode to the camp of
their elders.  Before

<pb n="322"/>
their tepees they sat mounted, and
mocked the old men, voicing their praises of the wonderful medicine
of Young Moon.
</p><p>"So may it be," muttered one old man.  "Good may his medicine
be; but bad&mdash;bad for crazy young colts&mdash;will they find the medicine
of the white man."
</p><p>The young men laughingly turned and rode down the valley
toward the Creek of the Rotten Grass, following which they would
quickly find the white man&mdash;and strife.  The young women, roughly
discarded, marched shamefacedly to the new camp; but some who had
remained with the bucks, although their husbands were not yet
chosen, were driven in disgrace from the tepees they sought to
enter.
</p>
</div1>

<div1 type="part" n="2" id="d4">
<head>II</head>

<p>"TEDDY" COLLINS, who rode range for the "2 O &amp; E" Ranch, had come
north toward the head-waters of the Creek of the Rotten Grass to
head off a bunch of strays that had persisted in running off the
range and was wandering far north toward the reservation.  Collins
had the herd headed southward again, and was driving it with
language that was picturesque and vigorous down the river-trail,
when Young Moon came with a gallop and a whoop over the ridge.
</p><p>Collins was greatly surprised and very little pleased.
Threescore fat steers bearing the 2 O &amp; E brand were directly in
the path of the redskins, and in the traditions of the range it is
told that this is not good for steers.  The tough little cow-pony
came around on his hind legs to face the Indians.
</p><p>One man sat quietly in the middle of the trail with his right
hand raised and empty, but the score that came over the ridge
swerved to one side and stopped before they came to the one.
Collins wondered curiously where the Indians had procured the
whisky, for to him it was very evident that they were happily
drunk.  Young Moon he recognized easily; he had won a lame pony
from him at the big poker game after the round-up last fall.  But
at the poker game Young Moon was attired in a cheap black suit of
store clothes instead of a bonnet of feathers and a gaudy apron.
</p><p>Young Moon rode up to within easy-speaking distance and
dismounted.  Collins gathered himself up firmly in the saddle.
</p><p>"How," greeted the Indian.
</p><p>"How," returned the cow-boy.
</p><p>"You better go 'way," said Young Moon, with a decisive sweep
of the arm.
</p><p>"Go 'way h&mdash;," replied Collins, laconically.  "What yuh
driving at, anyhow?"
</p><p>"We going down the creek," said Young Moon.  "You and your
people go away&mdash;back to where you come from."
</p><p>"Oh, so that's the game, eh?" said Collins, cheerily.  "Well,
yuh'd better not do anything rough, ol' pigeon-toe, or they'll have
a slue of those stiff-necks from Fort Custer down here an' shoot
yuh good an' plenty."
</p><p>Young Moon laughed.  The poor mortal "stiff-necks" attempting
to contend with the Great Spirit&mdash;truly it was amusing.  Eloquently
and with many gestures he hastened to inform Collins that before
long the Indian would pitch his tepee on the parade-ground at the
fort.  The regime of the white man was at an end in the land; Young
Moon, he whom the spirits had rendered invulnerable, said it.
</p><p>Collins would have laughed gleefully if Young Moon attired in
the ordinary raiment of civilization had given utterance to such
fanciful language.  But here was Young Moon, more than half naked,
entirely sober, and with a score of bucks at his back, calmly
saying that the white man was to be driven out of the valley.  It
was evident that Young Moon and his bucks were not on a drunk, but
on the war-path.  This sort of thing, Collins felt, was distinctly
out of place now.  Such things had passed into the school-history
stage.
</p><p>"Old man, lemme tell yuh something," he said confidingly,
leaning over the saddle pommel.  "Yuh're trying to run your bluff
away too late.  Don't yuh go for to buck the brass-buttons now;
they're too strong for yuh.  Yuh jest mosey 'long back to yer
reserve an' act decent.  Sabe?  I'm only a-telling yuh for yer own
good."
</p><p>Again Young Moon laughed scornfully.
</p><p>"We go down there.  Sabe?" he said positively, pointing down
the trail behind Collins.  Then the flash of savage rage, the wild,
blinding desire to slay, came to him, and he whipped the well-worn
short-barreled Winchester from beneath his blanket and fired from
the hip point-blank into the herd.  Collins's six-shooter came out
and up with a jerk.  He was no longer the suave diplomat and
benevolent Indian adviser;

<pb n="323"/>
this Indian was killing the cattle under his charge.
</p><p>"Hol' on there, yuh &mdash; &mdash; low-lived &mdash;, yuh!" he
called fiercely.  "Don't yuh try any more o' that funny work, or
I'll let &mdash; into yuh so quick yuh'll never know what hit yuh.
Yuh can go to Fort Custer, or yuh can go to &mdash;, if yuh want to;
but I tell yuh right here, if yuh ever get past here, it'll be
after yuh an' me an' a whole lot of yer friends have cashed in.
Sabe?"
</p><p>Young Moon understood fully.  The cow-puncher was mad.  Mad
cow-punchers with big blue six-shooters in their hands are not
objects to fuss lightly with.  Young Moon hesitated.
</p><p>For a moment the two faced each other silently, the Indian and
the cow-puncher, the gaudy, picturesque savage and the commonplace
utilitarian, the old and the new.  Both had much to think of in
that moment.  Young Moon tried hard to conceive some manner in
which he could get a good shot at Collins without danger to
himself.
</p><p>Collins was thinking of the property under his charge, the
herd running wildly back and forth in the trail below, and the new
home of Peterson the "newcomer," which lay farther down the valley,
the first of the houses in the path of Young Moon and his
followers.  Collins suddenly remembered that there was a young wife
in the home of the newcomer; also a little red-cheeked, yellow-haired baby, who had played in the dooryard when he passed there in
the morning on his search for the strays.
</p><p>"I suppose these rowdies 'u'd scare &mdash; out o' that little
woman if they ever get that far," he thought.  "They might even&mdash;
No; they'll never get a chance for that; I'm here to see they don't
get&mdash;"
</p><p>"Here, yuh!"  It was Collins who cried out.  Young Moon was
deliberately throwing the empty shell out of his rifle.  "Hol' on
the&mdash;"
</p><p>The words were cut short in Collins's mouth.  Action, swift,
sure, terrible, had taken their place.  Young Moon was down on his
face in the bunch-grass, and dust and a tiny thread of blue smoke
wreathed upward from Collins's pistol.  A dozen shoulders hunched
into shooting position and a dozen black rifle-barrels focused on
Collins.  But Young Moon began to rise to his feet slowly,
hesitatingly, as a drunken man rises.  His bonnet was off, the
feathers were awry, the hot, stale dust was thick upon a face gray
with terror, and a look of awful, unutterable surprise was in his
small black eyes.  He stretched his arms outward&mdash;the gesture of a
chief commanding quiet, peace.
</p><p>"You see now that I am the Great Spirit," he said boastfully.
"The white man's bullet slays the flesh, but the spirit still
lives."  He stood up straight and virile in the sunlight and
shouted, "I cannot die!"
</p><p>Deliberately he turned to take aim at Collins.
</p><p>No quick snap-shot this time.  Young Moon fell prone on his
face, his limbs out-stretched in the rigidity which tells
unquestionably of death, sudden and violent.
</p><p>His followers waited silently and expectantly for him to rise,
and Collins deliberately turned his back on the band and rode down
the trail.
</p><p>"Oh, Young Moon!  Arise, arise, Young Moon!" called the bucks.
</p><p>The wind that waved the prairie-grass stirred slightly some of
the war-feathers; otherwise there was no motion.
</p><p>"Speak!  Oh, speak, Great Spirit!" they cried as they rode up
to him.  But the spirit failed to respond.
</p><p>"So, so he is dead," said one who dismounted and turned him on
his back.
</p><p>The band glanced as one man down the valley, where Collins was
driving the herd before him at a gallop.  It seemed an easy matter
to overtake him, but&mdash;Young Moon, their wonderful medicine-man, the
invulnerable, was dead.
</p><p>His brother, with the aid of another, silently placed the body
securely on a pony, and the band silently followed as the pony
turned his nose north toward the reservation.
</p><p>"Uh, so only Young Moon is dead?" queried the old men
sneeringly when they saw the laden pony.
</p><p>The young men said naught, but with hanging heads accepted the
sneers due them as stoically as the old men had received the taunts
of a few nights ago.  The old squaw had the body brought to her
tepee, for his kin would not own him, and a breed-dog sat outside
and howled long and loud in the night.  Otherwise the camp would
have slept quite peacefully.

<pb n="324"/>
</p><p>Collins, as he rode past Peterson's with the herd, saw the
woman holding the yellow-haired baby by the hands, while the little
one, gurgling with laughter, tottered around in a somewhat
uncertain circle.
</p><p>"Hallo, Meester Cohlenss!" called the woman, cheerily.  "Ai
see you got t'ose cows oll right."
</p><p>"Oh, yes," said Collins; "yes, I got the cows all right."
</p>

</div1>
</body>
</text>
</TEI.2>
