<?xml version="1.0"?>

<?dlps id="OyeManw"?>
<?dlps page-images="none" figure-images="no"?>
<?dlps transcription="other"?>

<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/tei-p4/tei2.dtd" [
<!ENTITY % POSTKB "INCLUDE">
<!ENTITY % TEI.extensions.ent SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.ent">
<!ENTITY % TEI.extensions.dtd SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.dtd">
<!ENTITY % ISOnum SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/charent/iso-num.ent"> %ISOnum;
<!ENTITY % ISOpub SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/charent/iso-pub.ent"> %ISOpub;

]>

<TEI.2 id="OyeManw">
<teiHeader type="migrated" creator="Etext">
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title type="main">The Man Who Would Not Be Saved</title>
<title type="sort">man who would not be saved</title>
<author>Oyen, Henry</author>
<respStmt>
<resp>Creation of machine-readable version:</resp>
<name>Judy Boss</name>
<resp>Conversion to TEI.2-conformant markup:</resp>
<name>University of Virginia Library Electronic Text Center.</name>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt>
<extent>ca. <num type="kilobytes">15</num> kilobytes</extent>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>University of Virginia Library</publisher>
<pubPlace>Charlottesville, Virginia</pubPlace>
<idno type="ETC">OyeManw</idno>
<date value="1996">1996</date>
<availability status="public">
<p n="copyright">Copyright &copy; 1996 by the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia</p>
<p n="access">Publicly accessible</p>
</availability>
<idno type="uva-pid">uva-lib:476276</idno>
</publicationStmt>
<seriesStmt>
<title>University of Virginia Library, Text collection</title>
<idno type="uva-set">UVA-LIB-Text</idno>
</seriesStmt>
<sourceDesc>
<biblFull>
<titleStmt>
<title type="main">The Man Who Would Not Be Saved</title>
<title level="j">Overland Monthly</title>
<title type="sort">man who would not be saved</title>
<author>Henry Oyen</author>
</titleStmt>
<editionStmt>
<p>Volume 40</p>
</editionStmt>
<extent>24-26.</extent>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>California Pub. Co.</publisher>
<pubPlace>San Francisco</pubPlace>
<date value="1902-07">July 1902</date>
</publicationStmt>
</biblFull>
</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc>
<encodingDesc>
<projectDesc>
<p>Prepared for the University of Virginia Library Electronic Text
Center.</p>
</projectDesc>
<editorialDecl>
<p>All quotation marks retained as data.</p>
<p>Spell-check and verification made
against printed text using WordPerfect spell checker.</p>
<p>All unambiguous end-of-line hyphens have been removed, and the
trailing part of a word has been joined to the preceding line.</p>
<p>The images exist as archived TIFF images, one or more JPEG versions
for general use, and thumbnail GIFs.</p>
<p id="ETC">Keywords in the header are a local Electronic Text Center scheme
to aid in establishing analytical groupings.</p>
</editorialDecl>
<refsDecl>
<p>ID elements are given for each page element and are composed of the text's
unique cryptogram and the given page number, as in AusEmma1 for page one of
Jane Austen's Emma.</p>
</refsDecl>
</encodingDesc>
<profileDesc>
<creation>
<date value="1902">1902</date>
</creation>
<langUsage>
<language id="eng" usage="main">English</language>
</langUsage>
<textClass>
<keywords>
<term>fiction; prose</term>
<term>Native American</term>
</keywords>
</textClass>
</profileDesc>
<revisionDesc>
<change>
<date value="1996-05">May 1996</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>corrector</resp>
<name>Judy Boss</name>
</respStmt>
<item>I have made the following changes to the text:
page 24 para. 16 line 3  markmanship] marksmanship;
page 26 para.  8 line 3  mascaleros.] Mescaleros.</item>
</change>
<change>
<date value="1996-05">May 1996</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>corrector</resp>
<name>Catherine Tousignant</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Added TEI header and tags</item>
</change>
<change>
<date value="2005-07">July 2005</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>Corrector</resp>
<name>John Ivor Carlson</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Converted to XML and/or checked tags.</item>
</change>
<change>
<date value="2007-09">September 2007</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>Migration</resp>
<name>Ethan Gruber, University of Virginia Library</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Converted XML markup from TEI Lite to uva-dl-tei (TEI P4 with local customizations).</item>
</change>
<change>
<date value="2008-01">January 2008</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>Migration</resp>
<name>Greg Murray, University of Virginia Library</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Programmatically updated TEI header markup (but not header content) for minimal compliance with current QA requirements.</item>
</change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text id="d1">

<body id="d2">
<div1 type="story" id="d3"> <pb n="24"/>
<head>The Man Who Would Not Be Saved<lb/>
BY HENRY OYEN</head>

<p>AN almost dismantled, forsaken, adobe house stood alone near the
edge of the sand-plain in the midst of a world of sand, sun and
mountains.

</p><p>To the east a range of squalid black rocks rose into a
precipitous mountain range, striving with their dark and foreboding
presence to subdue the exuberant gladness of the brilliant sunshine.
To the west the monotonous yellow level stretched out like a tawny
carpet, to where a slight rise in the land caused it to meet the sky
as sharp and distinct as a placid lake meets the sandy beach.

</p><p>On the side of the shack nearest to the mountain side stood a
new freshly-painted army ambulance; a note of modernity interluded in a
world-old symphony of sand, rocks, and atmosphere.

</p><p>Crosswise on the tongue of the vehicle, limp as a half-filled
grain bag, lay the form of a man clad in the stripeless trousers of a
private soldier, and near him, in a tangle of gear and harness, lay a
pair of the mule team that he had but recently driven.

</p><p>At first glance it was easily discernible that man and mules
were but recently dead from gunshot wounds, and here and there a bullet
had torn its way through the sides of the ambulance, ripping off
splinters and exposing the white wood beneath the dark paint.  On
every hand were unmistakable signs of strife.

</p><p>Within the adobe house Second Lieutenant Horton, recently Cadet
Horton of West Point, now stationed at Fort Pratt, was hurriedly making
preparations to resist the band of Apaches who swarmed amongst the
black rocks and took occasional pot shots at the house, until the
officers at Fort Pratt would become alarmed at the non-appearance of
the ambulance, and send a force over the trail and rescue him and the
girl who was with him.

</p><p>The devoted Mescaleros who squatted behind the rocks were in no
haste to rush in and finish the game which they had so securely
trapped.

</p><p>They had two mute witnesses up there among the rocks, two who
were just as dead as the private who lay across the ambulance tongue,
to testify to the marksmanship of the man in the house, and the rest
were in no frame of mind to risk their lives by exposing themselves to
his fire.  There was much time.  There was but one man in the
house&mdash;and a woman.  Long before the troop had arrived from Fort Pratt
they could have easily disposed of the man, looted the ambulance, and
scattered out over their almost untraceable trails among the
mountains.  And the woman?  Well, Suilateau, their chief, would
probably accept her as his share of the loot and add her to his
already generous list of wives.

</p><p>So they crouched closely down behind their shelters, and
leisurely satisfied their instincts for long-range shooting.

</p><p>Horton, quite well aware that the trait of
self-preservation&mdash;the terrible dislike to be the "first through the
breach"&mdash;was exceptionally well-developed in the race to which those
among the rocks belonged, hoping that by giving them an exhibition of
his shooting he might cause them to delay their attack at close
quarters until the dark afforded them a cloak, and by that time&mdash;well,
if the men from Fort Pratt had not put in appearance before then,
there would be a vacancy in the line of Second Lieutenants.

   <pb n="25"/>

</p><p>So Horton carefully directed the girl to a corner where the
walls appeared strongest and hastily began to cut loopholes, and
organized himself into a garrison of one to fight a score.

</p><p>The bright sunlight which caused every speck on the mountain
side to stand out wonderfully vivid, materially aided him, and after he
had found the correct range he managed by carefully shooting at every
exposed redskin to force a very wholesome fear into the soul of the
enemy.

</p><p>The girl, entirely inefficient to render any aid, sat silently
watching with a wonderful kind of interest the boy who was doing all
that man could do to save his life and her own.  Occasionally a bullet
bored through the mud walls and sent the dry mud flying in their faces,
but the range was great and the walls stopped the majority of the
bullets.

</p><p>The hours seemed to come and go, to them; a dozen times Horton
had momentarily ceased his fire to listen for the welcome thud of
hoofs, and as often was disappointed.  It was in reality but an hour
before he suddenly discovered that his supply of rifle ammunition had
been expended, and that the six charges in his pistol were his only
remaining articles of defense.  The girl saw this as he discarded the
rifle and drew the pistol, and felt her heart sink as she realized the
situation.  She saw him as he gazed searchingly out over the plain in
an effort to discern a bit of friendly blue, and saw the despair which
no man can hope to conceal, come into his face and snuff out the bit
of hope and dignity brought there by the joy of well fought combat.

</p><p>Horton carefully examined each precious charge in the pistol,
striving to force himself to think calmly; and all the time an unknown
voice repeatedly asserted that further resistance was entirely
useless.  Still, possessed by that wonderful Anglo-Saxon courage which
grows more and more rebelliously firm as the fight goes more and more
to the enemy, he quietly informed the girl that he had only begun to
fight, and by his demeanor attempted to live the lie.

</p><p>Instinct, however, told the girl that his cheerfulness was
entirely assumed, but by neither word nor look did she betray this
knowledge.

</p><p>Silent, not voicing vain regrets, nor weak vindictives, they
stood, living for the moments that reeled off with fearful regularity,
each fraught with the question of life or death.  Occasionally Horton,
from force of habit, glanced at his timepiece, and each time he
slightly shook his head.

</p><p>The wary Apaches, noting that the white man's terrible rifle was
stilled, had stolen down to the last fringe of rocks that offered them
protection, and were making visible preparations for a rush.  Still,
they knew that the blue-shirted cavalryman had an uncomfortable habit
of shooting terribly fast and accurate at short range, with the
pistol, and so they still hesitated.

</p><p>Horton closely watching their every move and carefully weighing
every circumstance, reluctantly decided that the time had come to make
the girl aware of the hopelessness of their situation.

</p><p>"It's all up with us now, I'm afraid, Miss Jordan," he said
quietly.  "They're getting ready for a rush out there, I see, and when
they try that, I'm afraid I won't be able to hold them off.  I'll only
have time to fire probably a couple of shots, then they'll&mdash;"

</p><p>"I know," she said quickly, as if the privilege of speech was a
relief after the long pulseless wait.  "We'll be killed.  Well, you'll
find that I'm not afraid to die."

</p><p>The boy became visibly embarrassed.

</p><p>"'Tisn't that," he said, drooping his eyes to the floor.  "They
won't kill you, you know, Miss Jordan; 'tisn't their style with white
women.  They'll&mdash;they'll let you live; you understand, don't you, Miss
Jordan?"

</p><p>For a moment she did not comprehend, then when the revelation
dawned upon her all her composure and self-possession gave way.

</p><p>"My God, they don't really do that, do they?" she cried.

</p><p>The boy nodded.

</p><p>"Oh, it can't be," she said, clasping her hands as the
fearfulness of the boy's disclosures grew upon her.  "I'd sooner

   <pb n="26"/>

die a hundred times."  She stopped suddenly, for her eyes, roaming
furtively, had fallen upon the pistol in the boy's hand, the only
lethal weapon remaining to them.  Her gaze rose steadily to his frank
eyes, and for a moment they gazed at each other, each fully cognizant
of the other's thoughts.  The boy grew sick at heart, for there was a
world of pleading in the girl's eyes.

</p><p>"You will, won't you?" she said abruptly.  "You'll surely spare
me the fate of falling into their hands alive."  It was a weak little
plea, a plea which told of all hope for life departed, and only a wish
remaining for decent death.

</p><p>Horton walked to a loop-hole and scanned the plain in an effort
to find one clue upon which to hang a single thread of hope.  But
nothing new appeared to disturb the never-ending monotony of the
landscape.  Then the hope died in his breast.

</p><p>"It shall be as you wish, Miss Jordan," he said simply.

</p><p>"Thank you," she said.

</p><p>He stooped and reverently placed her hand to his lips.  He would
have also spoken, for they had come to be very close to each other in
this short moment of awful trial, but an unknown odor of sanctity held
him in reserve.  He held her hand for a moment, then dropped it and
turned to the door.

</p><p>It was a pathetically heroic tableau they presented as they
stood there, subdued by the calmness of despair, awaiting the end.

</p><p>The afternoon sun came slantingly in through the rude windows
and cast strange, golden lights and dark shadows upon them.

</p><p>Outside the sun shone on the yellow sand and the black rocks as
it had shone from the beginning, and a breath of sun laden breeze
coming into the room mocked them with the song that the world was still
good to live in.

</p><p>The girl stood with clasped hands, gazing straight towards from
where the fatal bullet would come, perfectly resigned and fearless to
meet her God; the boy with bowed head, subdued by the duty imposed
upon him, stood facing the door, idly rolling the cylinder of the
revolver between his thumb and finger, waiting, waiting.

</p><p>When the first naked braves bounded up to the door with rifles
held at ready, he fired twice, quickly, at the foremost, then as more
came forward to take the fallen's places, he turned and skillfully shot
her through the heart.  When he turned to meet his fate Horton feared
for a moment that his senses had left him.

</p><p>The foremost Apache fell a wriggling heap in the doorway as if
struck down by a swift and powerful hand, and almost simultaneously
one more fell likewise.

</p><p>It was some seconds afterwards that the rifle reports coming up
from the mountain pass where Lieutenant Thompson and his troop&mdash;
traveling towards Fort Pratt&mdash;were firing, dismounted, told Horton
that he was saved.

</p><p>For a moment the new lease on life fairly exhilarated him.
Then his eyes fell upon the form of the girl, as she, a white, still
heap upon the mud floor, lay beside him.

</p><p>After all, Thompson and his men were too late.  He was not to be
saved.  The girl was dead, and he had no right&mdash;

</p><p>The first trooper to enter was a lightly-mounted private, and he
found them lying almost side by side.

</p><p>Lieutenant Thompson, when he saw them, remarked that there
would be two more scores for Horton's company to even up when it came
their day to reckon face to face with Suilateau's Mescaleros.
</p>
</div1>

</body>
</text>
</TEI.2>

