<?xml version="1.0"?>

<?dlps id="ParNew"?>
<?dlps page-images="none" figure-images="no"?>
<?dlps transcription="other"?>

<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/tei-p4/tei2.dtd" [
<!ENTITY % POSTKB "INCLUDE">
<!ENTITY % TEI.extensions.ent SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.ent">
<!ENTITY % TEI.extensions.dtd SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.dtd">
<!ENTITY % ISOlat1 SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/charent/iso-lat1.ent"> %ISOlat1;
<!ENTITY % ISOnum SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/charent/iso-num.ent"> %ISOnum;
 
]> 
<TEI.2 id="ParNew"> 
<teiHeader type="migrated" creator="Etext">
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title type="main">The New Theories of Economics</title>
<title type="sort">new theories of economics</title>
<author>Pareto, Vilfredo, 1848-1923</author>
<respStmt> 
<resp>Creation of machine-readable version:</resp> 
<name>McMaster University Archive for the History of Economic Thought</name> 
<resp>Conversion to TEI.2-conformant markup:</resp> 
<name>University of Virginia Library Electronic Text Center.</name>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt> 
<extent>ca. <num type="kilobytes">44</num> kilobytes</extent> 
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>University of Virginia Library</publisher>
<pubPlace>Charlottesville, Virginia</pubPlace> 
<idno type="ETC">ParNew</idno> 
<date value="2001">2001</date>
<availability status="public">
<p n="copyright">Copyright &copy; 2001 by the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia</p>
<p n="access">Publicly accessible</p>
</availability>
<idno type="uva-pid">uva-lib:476278</idno>
</publicationStmt>
<seriesStmt>
<title>University of Virginia Library, Text collection</title>
<idno type="uva-set">UVA-LIB-Text</idno>
</seriesStmt> 
<sourceDesc>
<biblFull>
<titleStmt>
<title type="main">The New Theories of Economics</title>
<title level="m">The Journal of Political Economy, Volume 5, Issue 4 (Sep,. 1897), 485-502.</title>
<title type="sort">new theories of economics</title>
<author>Vilfredo Pareto</author>
</titleStmt> 
<extent>Internet Resource</extent> 
<publicationStmt> 
<idno type="callNo">Source copy consulted: JSTOR through UVA library: http://links.jstor.org/sici?sici=0022- 
3808%28189709%295%3A4%3C485%3ATNTOE%3E2.0.CO%3B2-R</idno>
</publicationStmt> 
</biblFull>
</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc> 
<encodingDesc>
<projectDesc>
<p>Prepared for the University of Virginia Library Electronic Text Center.</p>
</projectDesc> 
<editorialDecl>
<p>All unambiguous end-of-line hyphens have been removed, and the  trailing part of a word has been joined to the preceding line.</p> 
<p id="ETC">Some keywords in the header are a local Electronic Text Center scheme  to aid in establishing analytical groupings.</p>
</editorialDecl> 
</encodingDesc> 
<profileDesc>
<creation>
<date value="1897">1897</date>
</creation> 
<langUsage>
<language id="eng" usage="main">English</language>
</langUsage> 
<textClass>
<keywords>
<term>nonfiction</term> 
<term>prose</term> 
<term>masculine</term> 
</keywords> 
</textClass>
</profileDesc> 
<revisionDesc>
<change>
<date value="2002-07">July, 2002</date> 
<respStmt>
<resp>corrector</resp> 
<name>Wilson Brissett, Electronic Text Center</name>
</respStmt> 
<item>Added TEI header and tags.</item>
</change> 
<change>
<date value="2005-07">July 2005</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>Corrector</resp>
<name>John Ivor Carlson</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Converted SGML to XML and/or corrected tagging.</item>
</change>
<change>
<date value="2007-09">September 2007</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>Migration</resp>
<name>Ethan Gruber, University of Virginia Library</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Converted XML markup from TEI Lite to uva-dl-tei (TEI P4 with local customizations).</item>
</change>
<change>
<date value="2008-01">January 2008</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>Migration</resp>
<name>Greg Murray, University of Virginia Library</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Programmatically updated TEI header markup (but not header content) for minimal compliance with current QA requirements.</item>
</change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader> 
<text id="d1"> 
<body id="d2"> 
<div1 type="essay" id="d3"> 
<div2 type="text" id="d4"> 
   <p>Several criticisms of a work<ref target="n1">1</ref> that I have recently 
published have shown me that certain points of view from which 
the new economic theories can be considered have not been 
thoroughly understood. In this paper I propose to give a brief 
expose of these theories. 
</p><p>The present study is purely objective. It is not my intention 
to point out the part played by the various economists in the 
formulation of the new theories, nor have I attempted to separate 
the large amount of work done by my predecessors from my own 
modest contribution. If I sometimes speak in my own name, I do so 
merely to avoid placing the responsibility on other writers for 
errors I may have introduced into their theories. 
</p><p>As a matter of fact, art has always preceded science. When in 
the course of the evolution of human knowledge art and science 
have drifted apart, critics have never been wanting who were 
ready to assert that science was productive of no useful results. 
Criticisms of this kind are largely founded on the fact that a 
science has not nearly so immediate a utility as the cognate art. 
It is also to be said that art cannot confine itself to its 
teaching function; it must also demonstrate its persuasive power. 
Consequently art is obliged to make use of certain rhetorical 
devices with which science has nothing to do. As the most 
persuasive reasoning is not always the soundest, it happens that 
economic science often differs from economic art in the means of 
expression employed. Science considers means of expression solely 
from the point of view of their power to disclose the truth, 
whereas art must primarily consider their efficiency as means of 
persuasion. From this it follows that economic science will not 
hesitate to use mathematics, philology, physiology, etc.; whereas 
art can draw upon these sciences to but a very limited extent for 
fear of not being understood by the majority of those it 
undertakes to persuade. 
</p><p>It is not my intention at this point to consider the general 
question of the utility of the pure sciences. In passing it may 
be said by way of illustration that any person who believes in 
the uselessness of the science of astronomy will act prudently in 
not reading a book the title of which shows that it treats of 
this subject. On the other hand, if he enjoys reading works on 
this science it would be foolish for him to stop at every page to 
express the wish that the author had written a more valuable 
work, e. g., a trade almanac. It is also to be thoroughly 
understood that a question may legitimately be entirely ignored 
or wholly put aside, but if it is considered at all it must be 
treated as fully as the resources of the science at the time 
permit. 
</p><p>There can be no doubt that the exact and real sense of the 
famous phrase of Tacitus: <hi rend="italic">Agri pro numero cultorum ab universis 
in vices occupantur, quos mox inter se secundum dignationem 
partiuntur</hi>.... has nothing to do with the present welfare of 
humanity. A statesman having in hand the passage of a law 
affecting the landed property of his country might therefore be 
justly condemned were he to waste his time in trying to find out 
the meaning of this phrase. Any person who might have the time 
and curiosity to know exactly what had been the system of 
property among the Germans must needs read the principal authors 
who have studied this famous phrase of Tacitus. After having once 
taken up the task it would, however, be very annoying to be 
interrupted in one's study by the remark of an intruder to this 
effect: "You are wasting your time. You use too much Latin; you 
make a mistake in quoting Greek so often, for many cannot read 
that language. The ancient Germans and their land system are not 
in my line." To the last remark I can only reply that if you are 
not interested in a certain line of work you would do better not 
to interfere but let those proceed without interruption who are 
interested in the particular subject and who will take the pains 
to investigate it in every way calculated to lead them to the 
truth. 
</p><p>To acquire wealth may be pleasanter than only to know the 
manner in which it is distributed. For my part, were I of the 
opinion that a certain book would contribute more than any other 
to establish free trade in the world at large I would not 
hesitate an instant to give myself up heart and soul to the study 
of this particular work, putting aside for the time all study of 
pure science. The man in whose power it might be to find out the 
means of alleviating the sufferings of the poor would have done a 
far greater deed than the one who contents himself solely with 
knowing the exact numbers of poor and wealthy people in society. 
However, if anyone wished to pursue such a line of study, he 
should be left at liberty to use such means as may enable him to 
discover the law according to which incomes vary. 
</p><p>In speaking of a mathematical formula that gives an 
approximate expression of this law, Professor Charles Gide says 
that "the latter is endowed with no power, either of intimidating 
or discouraging any one of those who aspire to a greater equality 
of social conditions;" which is equivalent to saying that 
astronomical studies will not have the power "of intimidating or 
discouraging" lovers in the choice of a star of their own. The 
investigator who is in search of the law of the distribution of 
wealth does not aim to encourage or dissuade anyone; he is simply 
intent on discovering the truth. This does not imply that some 
questions are not of greater importance from a strictly 
scientific view than others. Thus mechanics affords us the means 
of studying the movements of celestial bodies which attract each 
other according to a given law, but it is obvious that in this 
study special attention will center on the movements which take 
place in so far as bodies are subject to attraction under this 
law and that no time will be wasted in exhaustive study of other 
laws that have nothing to do with the matter in hand. 
</p><p>Let us therefore put aside, once for all, discussions 
regarding the greater or less utility of science or its power of 
persuading anyone to choose for himself between alternatives, and 
let us direct our attention solely to the laws governing certain 
phenomena. A reader who may have no interest in following a 
discussion on this line may as well discontinue his reading. 
Voltaire tells how Micromegas descended to earth and observed 
mankind. Micromegas, before he could fully comprehend human 
actions, would have to perceive that a large class of activities 
aims at providing what is useful or pleasant, that another class 
of actions depends on the sentiment arising from the mutual 
attraction between the sexes, and that there is a third class 
which does not aim directly at the enjoyments of sense. This 
third class of actions proceeds on certain sentiments called 
moral, religious, patriotic, etc. Micromegas, if he is to make 
progress in the study of this great number of actions going on 
before him, must soon see the necessity of classifying the 
activities and examining each class separately. This ordering of 
things is needful in every line of study. It would not do to 
blend the study of anatomy with that of chemistry. This does not 
in the least imply that the anatomist underrates chemistry, or 
<hi rend="italic">vice versa</hi>; it only says that but one subject can be 
advantageously investigated at a time. 
</p><p>Economic questions up to this time have too often been 
construed to coincide with questions of law. The time has now 
come to separate the two, just as in its time a separation was 
made between chemistry and physics. What are the economic results 
of strikes? This is a question distinct from the other question 
as to whether laborers have or have not the right to organize 
strikes. Nothing is gained, from a scientific point of view, in 
not separating these two very different questions. It must also 
be well understood that in dealing with a practical case both 
questions must be solved. Science proceeds by analysis, whereas 
synthesis is required where practice is concerned. 
</p><p>Propositions that are exclusively scientific are of two 
kinds: (1) descriptive propositions, describing what has taken 
place so monetary systems are described with reference to time 
and place; (2) hypothetical propositions, which search into what 
would have happened under given specific conditions - so, for 
instance, what would happen if paper money were issued in a 
country accustomed to a circulation of gold. 
</p><p>These two kinds of propositions fairly correspond to those 
which are in mechanics included under the two heads of actual and 
virtual movements. Given a system of material points, the problem 
is to find the actual movements of these points. This is a 
question following under the first head. Of the second kind would 
be the question as to what movements these points would describe 
on the basis of the relations actually existing between them. 
These latter movements, not realized in fact, but which might 
have taken place without violating the conditions assumed, are 
what are called virtual movements. 
</p><p>In my opinion both political economy and social science have 
in view the study of two analogous kinds of movements. The first 
kind constitutes the doctrine of evolution; it is the class of 
movements to which social science has given the greater 
attention. This class of movements is characteristic of the 
studies which bear the name "historical" in political economy. 
The second class of movements or questions is of interest as 
bearing on the problem what relation given specific facts bear to 
the welfare of humanity; in other words, what are the potential 
movements conducive to the maximum welfare of humanity? In what 
relation do they stand to actual movements? These problems can be 
solved, if at all, through analysis and abstraction. That is to 
say, an endeavor is to be made to isolate and study the principal 
phenomenon. Those who censure political economy for pursuing this 
method seem to be unaware of the fact that all sciences, without 
exception, must follow this method. Certain critics cry out 
apodictically against the new theories as being absurd because 
they attempt to state economic phenomena "in mathematical 
formula." But no such pretentious attempt has been made. To try 
to state economic phenomena in the shape of mathematical formula 
would be very much like the physicist trying to apply without 
modification his mathematical formula for the descent of falling 
bodies in a vacuum to the movement of a feather floating on the 
wind. These critics may therefore be told that, far from aiming 
to express complex phenomena in a simple formula, economists 
broadly avow that they do not know and will never know the theory 
of any concrete phenomena in all its details. They are solely 
acquainted with ideal phenomena which make a continually closer 
approximation to the concrete cases. Let us take a very simple 
example - the fall of a heavy body. The complete theory of its 
movement is unknown. Who, then, can give us the theory of the 
movement of a falling feather? If we simplify our problem by 
supposing a heavy body to be falling in a vacuum and attracted by 
the earth alone, we may infer the well-known theory of falling 
bodies. We thereupon complicate the problem by introducing the 
fact of the air's resistance, and in this way arrive at theories 
approaching more and more closely to reality. 
</p><p>Such are the considerations which lead to the method of 
successive approximations in political economy. In my <hi rend="italic">Cours</hi> I 
have developed this theory more fully, and therefore shall only 
indicate its nature here. 
</p><p>Rational mechanics gives us a first approximation to the 
theory of the equilibrium and of the movements of bodies. In the 
same way the theories of Jevons, Walras, Marshall, Irving Fisher, 
and others present us with a first approximation to the full 
theory of economic phenomena. It must be clearly understood that 
it is only an approximation; it is similar to that just made in 
the case of the heavy body supposed to fall in a vacuum. Pure 
economics has no better way of expressing the concrete economic 
phenomenon than rational mechanics has for representing the 
concrete mechanical one. It is at this point that there is a 
place for mathematics. The problem of pure economics bears a 
striking likeness to that of rational mechanics. Now, in point of 
empirical fact, men have as yet not succeeded in treating the 
latter problem without the aid of mathematics. It therefore 
appears quite legitimate to appeal also to mathematics for 
assistance in the solution of the economic problem. 
</p><p>Many people think that the advantage arising from the use of 
mathematics consists in making demonstration more rigorous. This 
is an error. A demonstration well constructed by the method of 
ordinary logic is just as rigorous as one made by the application 
of that other kind of logic which bears the name of mathematics. 
The advantage of mathematics lies chiefly in this, that it 
permits us to treat problems far more complicated than those 
generally solved by ordinary logic. Most economists insist upon 
the mutual dependence of different economic phenomena. But a 
purely verbal recognition of this fact is not all that can be 
done or all that is required. What we want is to determine, at 
least approximately, the relations existing between the economic 
phenomena under discussion and so obtain a clear conception of 
their interdependence. A system of equations similar to the one 
used in mechanics to represent the equilibrium and the movement 
of bodies is afforded by this method of approximation. This 
representation is, no doubt, in this way approached in a rough 
way at best, and yet the approximation serves better than 
nothing. It is better to know that the earth is nearly round than 
to imagine that it is a flat surface. 
</p><p>Professor Walras' great contribution to economic discussion 
was his discovery of a general system of equations to express the 
economic equilibrium. I cannot, for my part, sufficiently admire 
this portion of his work, but I must add that I entirely disagree 
with him on what he has to say in his work entitled <hi rend="italic">&Eacute;tudes 
d'&eacute;conomie sociale</hi>. Professor Walras thinks it possible to draw 
certain economic deductions from metaphysical principles of 
jurisprudence. This opinion is worthy of respect, but I am unable 
to accept it. I am a believer in the efficiency of experimental 
methods to the exclusion of all others. For me there exist no 
valuable demonstrations except those that are based on facts. 
Foremost among the general problems to be solved by mathematics 
is the question of the determination or indetermination of 
economic problems. It is well known that wherever the number of 
conditions (equations) is equal to the number of unknown 
quantities, a problem is easily solved. This simple consideration 
helps us instantly to understand why the so-called "laws of 
maximum prices" contain a logical and formal impossibility. 
</p><p>I have endeavored to extend to dynamic questions the use of 
the equations given for the static equilibrium. The most accurate 
description possible of the economic phenomenon is to be reached 
in this way. Is it not a most remarkable fact that a system of 
equations should thus be able to express not only the general 
character of economic phenomena, but every single detail as far 
as we may have any knowledge of them. The entire body of economic 
theory is henceforth bound together in this way and knitted into 
an integral whole. If our equations are constructed each for a 
homogeneous group, and several of these groups are considered, we 
get the theory of non-competing groups of Cairns and an 
effectively complete theory of international trade, together with 
an adequate scientific interpretation of the theory of 
comparative cost. By the use of these general formulas we find 
the coefficients of production. A consideration of their 
variability leads us up to a recognition of the function of the 
entrepreneurs and to the theory of different systems of 
production according as we postulate either free competition or 
monopoly or a socialistic r&eacute;gime. It is to be borne in mind that 
consumers are reckoning in terms of marginal utility or 
"ophelimity," while the entrepreneur is counting in terms of 
money. Some of the criticisms that I have seen might have been 
unnecessary if account had been taken of this distinction. A 
consideration of the size of industrial enterprises leads us to 
recognize that there exists in general a definite <hi rend="italic">maximum</hi> at 
which the expansion of enterprises stops under a r&eacute;gime of free 
competition, there being no advantage in increasing them beyond 
or leaving them short of what corresponds to this magnitude. Our 
general formula also directs our attention to the distribution of 
savings among the different uses to which they can be put. From a 
study of the degree of facility <ref target="n2">2</ref> with which savings can be 
turned into different species of capital a rigorous theory of 
rent can be deduced. The general equations show us, besides, how 
the economic aggregate is thrown into vibration under the action 
of forces which stimulate it. The study of these vibrations leads 
to a theory of crises. When once the economic aggregate has in 
this way been already apprehended it is easy to understand that 
the divisions into which we break up the aggregate in studying 
separately exchange, production, and capitalization are quite 
arbitrary, although they may be useful helps in study. In reality 
these three operations are simultaneous. If this be so it becomes 
absolutely necessary to consider them again as a whole after 
having examined them in isolation -- to make a synthesis after 
having analyzed the phenomena. This general conception of 
economic aggregate finds an analogy in the conception which an 
astronomer has of the solar system when he has apprehended the 
general equations of mechanics. 
</p><p>It is to be borne in mind that, since any economic phenomenon 
requires time for its completion, the amount of goods under 
consideration in any given case is the quantity which is produced 
and consumed in a given period of time. Besides this the use of 
capital could not be conceived apart from the time relation. 
Professor Irving Fisher has developed these considerations with 
much ability. 
</p><p>The general equations of the economic equilibrium are 
obtained on the hypothesis of a decreasing marginal utility, and 
it therefore becomes necessary to ask whether these equations 
yield results which are borne out by experience. This, indeed, is 
the only adequate demonstration of the propositions that 
political economy claims as its own and makes the subject of its 
discussion. The first part of the argument is of use only as 
drawing the conclusions from certain hypotheses, and says nothing 
as to their validity as statements of concrete facts. To test 
their validity in this respect deductions must be compared with 
experience; (1) because this affords the definitive proof of the 
hypotheses already made, which until this test be made remain 
probable only--<hi rend="italic">a priori</hi>; and (2) because it affords a means of 
testing whether this means of presenting economic phenomena 
really exhibits the substantial bearing of the phenomena in 
question. 
</p><p>So, for instance, experience teaches us in a general way that 
the quantity of goods demanded by consumers decreases with an 
increase in their price. Do or do not the general equations of 
the economic equilibrium lead us to this conclusion on 
theoretical grounds? If the question is answered in the 
affirmative the ground for accepting the general equations is 
strengthened, whilst if it is answered in the negative the 
general equations in question must be rejected. Many of the 
critics who have commented upon my <hi rend="italic">Cours</hi> have not understood this 
to be the case; they very erroneously imagined that when thus 
comparing my deductions with facts I intended thereby to prove 
the latter. But a fact cannot be demonstrated - it must be 
observed; it can then be used to test the validity of a 
deduction. Even the simplest and most elementary facts are to be 
made use of in making these verifications. From a failure to 
appreciate this rule of procedure critics have been led to make 
such reflections on my work as the following. 
</p><p>"After a long deduction from a formula he states that the 
truthfulness of that which is deduced can be seen at once from 
simpler considerations. Such overfondness for mathematical 
machinery strengthens the impression that exists among many that 
this machinery is capable only of grinding out truisms." Remarks 
of exactly similar tenor might be made upon the discussion of 
light-interference on the basis of the well-known equations of 
light-vibrations. But the theory of undulations does not and 
cannot demonstrate the phenomena of interference; on the contrary 
it is on the ground of these phenomena that the theory is 
accepted. The general equations of the economic equilibrium are 
not of avail for demonstrating the law of supply and demand; on 
the contrary, the equations which represent the chief phenomena 
of supply and demand are proven by experience. There is no truism 
in all this. The accuracy and therefore the value of a 
calculating machine might well be tested by an actual operation, 
e. g., multiplying 15 by 12 and comparing the product with the 
result obtained by the usual method. But this verification must 
not be considered a demonstration, and it must not be said that 
an expensive and complicated machine has been constructed for the 
sole purpose of multiplying 15 by 12. Another writer, Mr H.L. 
Moore, repeats the foregoing objection <ref target="n3">3</ref> in nearly the same 
words. He says: "After making the complex development, he points 
out that substantially the same results might be obtained without 
the use of differential calculus. Professor Pareto cannot expect 
to reconcile his non-mathematical reader with this method of 
confusing him by telling him (&sect; 56) that if he does not 
understand the mathematical explanations he will have all the 
advantage in learning the language in which they are given!" Mr 
Moore would convey the impression to his readers that the 
observation he quotes concerns this truism; but this is not the 
case. My observation concern <hi rend="italic">those results</hi> that cannot be reached 
<hi rend="italic">otherwise</hi>, while the inference which can be made "<hi rend="italic">without the use 
of differential calculus</hi>" is a simple verification. Similar 
verifications are to be found in any treatise upon mechanics; but 
that such may be the case Mr Moore does not seem to realize. If 
the rebuke administered by this acute critic is merited in the 
case just cited, it is also merited in numerous other cases which 
seem to have escaped him, for the instances of such resort to 
verification in my <hi rend="italic"><hi rend="italic">Cours</hi></hi> are numerous. Now it is precisely 
because the general formula of economic equilibrium cover a large 
number of economic questions which can be demonstrated in other 
ways, often very simple, that we take these formula to represent 
this whole range of the economic phenomena.<ref target="n4">4</ref> 
</p><p>For a like reason I have used every occasion to verify my 
theoretical deductions by statistics and history on this subject; 
J.S. Mill's work on logic contains several pages which it might 
be worth the while for some of our critics to reread. 
</p><p>In the early stages of every science there is apt to be a 
good deal of reasoning about terms rather than about the things 
themselves. This method of procedure, however, is not entirely 
erroneous. Words are often the depositories of the experience of 
men, and so long as a new-born science has not succeeded in 
accumulating for itself a sufficient aggregate of direct 
experience it may find it advantageous to have recourse to the 
common fund of experience more or less vaguely represented by 
words. There comes a time, however, in the development of science 
at which the fund formed by direct experience becomes sufficient 
and at which the disadvantages attached to the vagueness of 
experience, such as is given us by everyday words, outweighs the 
advantages to be derived from them. This is precisely the state 
of affairs in political economy. I believe this science would 
gain a great advantage by developing a terminology of its own, 
just as chemistry, physics, and anatomy have done. But in this 
transition period many persons judge of works which are written 
according to the new methods as if they had been written 
according to the principles which have prevailed in the past. As 
a consequence, criticisms which I consider of absolutely no value 
have been made upon the terminology which I have chosen to employ 
in my <hi rend="italic">Cours</hi>. For instance, it has seemed to me to be convenient 
to adopt Professor Walras' definition of capital; I have not, 
however, deduced any conclusions from it. If anyone should prefer 
a different definition, there would be no objection to his using 
it, and he would obtain the same results as I have if he reasoned 
exclusively about things and not about words alone. I should even 
venture so far as to say that I could rewrite the whole of my 
<hi rend="italic">Cours</hi>, and obtain the same results, without even mentioning the 
term "capital," if it were worth the while to attempt the feat. 
In fact, the base of calculations as regards production is the 
budget of the producer. Here is a person who owned a ship which 
cost him &pound;2000 on the first of January 1895; its value decreased 
to &pound;1800 by the first of January 1896. During the year 1895 the 
person in question expended &pound;1000 and received for the hire of 
his vessel &pound;4100. These facts must be gathered from his budget, 
whatever be the form in which it appears. The equations of 
production in reality only formulate facts of a similar 
character. But among the various forms which a balance sheet can 
assume, there is one which is particularly suitable for use in 
certain theoretical deductions. Let us suppose that we are 
putting down the figures of our balance sheet and that we put the 
vessel down for &pound;2000, the value it had on the first of January 
1895. As the ship is now worth only &pound;1800 we are obliged to 
charge the sum of &pound;200 to expenses so as not to violate the form 
of the budget. Now, since we know that the vessel has the same 
value on the first of January 1895 as on the first of January of 
the following year, we may just as well eliminate it altogether 
from the balance. The vessel figures in our business only because 
it has rendered us a certain amount of "services" during the year 
1895. 
</p><p>The method of bookkeeping we used for the vessel may be used 
in the case of many other things. As it is convenient to 
designate these things by a name, let us call them "capitals." 
And let us refrain from thinking that in giving them a name we 
change their nature, and let us at all events not waste our time 
in discussing the name to be given them. If anyone prefers a 
different name from the one we have selected, he is free to adopt 
it. If it should be found convenient to state the budget in some 
other form than that adopted, we need not hesitate to do so, as 
the results will doubtless be the same. The very same thing can 
be considered as capital or not as capital, according to our way 
of looking at it when we draw up the balance sheet of production. 
To be capital is not to possess an objective quality analogous to 
specific weight, chemical constitution, etc.; it is a 
characteristic which depends upon the way we use a thing in the 
process of production. 
</p><p>Another perfectly valueless discussion is the one on the 
question as to whether it is preferable to use the term "factors 
of production" or the term "coefficients of industry." Let us 
suppose that four hectares are needed to produce eighty 
hectolitres of corn. These four hectares are called "factors of 
production" of <hi rend="italic">the</hi> corn. Professor Walras takes as a premise in 
his discussion the quantity of ground needed to give a unit of 
produce. In the case assumed four-eightieths or one-twentieth of 
a hectare is required to raise one hectolitre of corn. Professor 
Walras gives to this one-twentieth of a hectare the name 
"coefficient of industry." Now, does it not amount to the same 
thing to say that four hectares of ground yield eighty 
hectolitres of corn, or that the one-twentieth part of a hectare 
yields one hectolitre of corn? One must be overfond of disputing 
about words, to let oneself drift into endless discussions as to 
the best term for presenting any given fact. We might mention a 
great many other discussions of the same character - all 
similarly wanting in simple common sense. But I prefer to drop 
this subject and to pass on to the consideration of more serious 
questions. 
</p><p>The presentation of the economic phenomenon in its entirety 
affords a clear comprehension of the effects of all conceivable 
economic organizations concerned; but it must be borne in mind 
that this knowledge will always remain approximate only. Science 
does not attempt to establish any particular method of economic 
organization, and it is not the business of science to do so. 
Science does, however, attempt to solve problems of the following 
kind: (1) What are the effects of a r&eacute;gime of free competition? 
(2) What are those of a r&eacute;gime of monopoly? (3) Those of a 
collectivist r&eacute;gime? All these questions must, of course, be 
treated, not from a polemical point of view, but solely for the 
purpose of ascertaining what results would follow upon their 
installation. It is especially necessary for us to discover what 
relation these results bear to the aggregate well being of 
humanity; and to do this not only a first approximation, but a 
second and a third, and perhaps even more, must be made, because 
the later approximations take account of secondary facts which 
are easily neglected in the earlier ones. The r&eacute;gimes compared 
may appear to yield identical results if only a first 
approximation be undertaken, and may differ materially in their 
results when reconsidered for the purpose of a second 
approximation. 
</p><p>By following this line we have been able vigorously to prove 
that the coefficients of production are determined by the 
entrepreneurs in a r&eacute;gime of free competition precisely in the 
same way as a socialist government would have to fix them if it 
wanted to realize a maximum of ophelimity for its subjects. This 
proposition is one of the main points of the so-called classical 
political economy; but it was necessary to give this proposition 
precision, in order to see clearly the limits within which it 
holds true and what conditions it assumes as given. This was also 
necessary in order to obtain a general proposition showing that 
every indirect transfer of wealth from one individual to another 
is accompanied by a loss of wealth. As a result of this it 
appears that if a socialist government is to obtain a maximum of 
well being for its subjects it must modify the distribution of 
wealth only in a direct way - say by taxing some people for the 
benefit of others, or by some similar means. A second 
approximation will take account of the expense of putting the 
mechanism of free competition into full play, and will compare 
this expense with that necessary for establishing some other new 
mechanism which society may wish to test. This is the way in 
which an engineer would first compare two systems of machinery 
from a theoretic point of view, keeping to the principles of 
thermodynamics for steam engines; then he would make tests of 
friction, loss of steam power, etc., in each system. 
</p><p>This method of approaching the subject differs substantially 
from that adopted by a large class of economists, who, after 
giving in their adhesion to a system, put forth all their power 
in showing its advantages and in defending it against all attacks 
to which it may be exposed. I once more repeat that I am far from 
condemning such economists, for I regard their work as one of 
great utility. This being the situation, I have no desire to 
offer a substitute for their work, but simply to add to it a 
purely scientific study. All the conclusions to which deductive 
studies founded on the general equations of the economic 
equilibrium can lead us must finally be verified by a careful 
scrutiny of facts, both present and past - that is to say, by 
statistics, by close observation, and by the evidence of history. 
This is the method of all the material sciences. Deductive 
studies in political economy must not be opposed to the 
inductive; these two lines of work should, on the contrary, 
supplement each other, and neither should be neglected. 
</p><p>The incidence of duties is a special case of such alterations 
as the economic equilibrium undergoes when certain of its 
conditions are modified. The new theories give us an exact idea 
of the nature of the incidence of duties. In order to ascertain 
this with exactness we must have at hand the numerical data 
bearing on this incidence; but statistics have not as yet 
supplied them. This delays the practical application. A great 
advance toward the solution of the problem has been made, 
however, when the method has been found by which the problem is 
to be solved. So, for instance, if we wish to know the area of a 
rectangle two things are required - (1) the knowledge that the 
area is to be obtained by multiplying the width by the length and 
(2) the exact measurements of the width and the length. Geometry 
gives us only the former item. 
</p><p>The laws of the distribution of wealth evidently depend on 
the nature of man and on the economic organization of society. We 
might derive these laws by deductive reasoning, taking as a 
starting point the data of the nature of man and of the economic 
organization of society. Will this work sometime be completed? I 
cannot say; but at present it is certain that we lack sufficient 
data for undertaking it. At present the phenomena must be 
considered synthetically, and every endeavor must be made to 
discover if the distribution of wealth presents any uniformity at 
all. Fortunately the figures representing the distribution of 
wealth group themselves according to a very simple law, which I 
have been enabled to deduce from unquestioned statistical 
data.<ref target="n5">5</ref> This law being empirical, it may not always remain 
true, especially not for all mankind. At present, however, the 
statistics which we have present no exceptions to the law; it may 
therefore provisionally be accepted as universal. But exceptions 
may be found, and I should not be greatly surprised if some day a 
well-authenticated exception were discovered. 
</p><p>Meanwhile, this law as it stands has most important 
theoretical results, and these resulting formula may be employed 
without limitations of time and place, provided the law be 
verified by statistics. 
</p><p>Mathematics is employed in connection with this law, but in a 
totally different way from that in which has been utilized in the 
analytical studies considered at the outset. In those studies the 
complexity of the phenomena compelled us to make use of 
mathematics; in the case we have just been considering they 
present us under the forms of a simple curve the entire sum of 
results supplied by statistics. But in the one case, as in the 
other, those who are not well at home in the use of mathematics 
can nevertheless master the results gained through their use. In 
my <hi rend="italic">Cours</hi> it has been possible to throw the mathematical parts 
into footnotes, and the text can thus be read without hindrance 
by persons who have no knowledge of mathematics. 
</p><p>This law of the distribution of wealth, which has so lately 
been discovered, may some day be of use in the study of the 
different races of men in this respect.<ref target="n6">6</ref> The application of 
the law is certainly conditioned by the heterogeneity of the 
population. It does not in any way prejudice other theories of 
the distribution of wealth, for the law is merely the synthesis 
of numberless statistical facts. It can be compared in some 
respects to Kepler's law in astronomy; we still lack a theory 
that may make this law of distribution rational in the way in 
which the theory of universal gravitation has made Kepler's law 
rational.</p> 
 
<p>VILFREDO PARETO.<lb/> 
UNIVERSITY OF LAUSANNE.</p> 
</div2> 
 
<div2 type="notes" id="d5"><head>NOTES</head> 
 
<note id="n1"><seg type="note-symbol">1.</seg> <p><hi rend="italic">Cours d'&eacute;conomie politique;</hi> Lusanne, F. Rouge, 1896, 2 
vols.</p></note> 
 
<note id="n2"><seg type="note-symbol">2.</seg> <p>I am not at all satisfied with this way of presenting my idea; 
but to give it more precision, without entering into a lengthy 
explanation, would be quite impossible without making use of 
mathematical symbols. The desire to keep mathematical symbols out 
of the text explains why in my <hi rend="italic">Cours</hi> the theory of rent appears 
to the notes. It was impossible to give it the desired 
rigorousness and precisements without the employment of 
mathematical symbols.</p></note> 
 
<note id="n3"><seg type="note-symbol">3.</seg> <p><hi rend="italic">Annuals of the American Academy</hi>, May 1897.</p></note> 
 
<note id="n4"><seg type="note-symbol">4.</seg> <p>The same critic says: "<hi rend="italic">A curious slip for a mathematical 
economist is made in the discussion of population</hi>, a slip that 
parallels the error of Malthus." To substantiate this he isolates 
a phrase which he finds in the text -- where there are no 
mathematics -- and gives it to the reader under the impression 
that to prove that the progress of wealth in England has not 
followed the law laid down by Malthus I furnish but this single 
ground of inference, viz., that between two given epochs the 
growth of wealth has been more rapid than that of population. He 
then argues at length to show that one can always make out an 
arithmetical progression in such form that its terms, within 
given limits, will be greater than those of a given geometrical 
progression. Without giving in detail "the complex development" 
of my critic's argument, it may be characterized as equivalent to 
the proposition that it is always possible to show that within 
given limits the ordinates of a straight line will be larger than 
those of a given curve. The reader who may not be satisfied with 
Mr Moore's assertion on this point, and who may be willing to 
take the trouble to verify the case by reference to my <hi rend="italic">Cours</hi>, 
will find (Vol. I, page 341) the following expression for the 
gross income in England:</p> 
 
<p rend="center"> <hi rend="italic">R</hi> = 346.30 X l0<hi 
rend="super">0.01104t</hi></p> 
 
<p>The following words, which explain the phrase isolated by Mr 
Moore, should also be read: "On voit que la raison de la 
progression est beaucoup plus rapide que celle qui a &eacute;t&eacute; 
trouv&eacute;e 
(211<hi rend="super">1</hi>) pour l'augmentation de la population. C'est ce qui explique 
comment la richesse par t&ecirc;te d'habitant a augment&eacute; 
considerablement." Accordingly, in the text I have observed that 
in England wealth has grown more rapidly than population, and in 
the notes I have furnished the precise expression for the 
<hi rend="italic">geometrical progression</hi> which has been followed by the growth of 
wealth. Is it not "a curious slip" for a critic not to have seen 
this? The reason why the explanation has to be sought for in the 
notes is simply this,--it could not be given without the use of 
mathematics and I desired to keep mathematics out of the text. In 
conclusion it may be said that it should not be deemed 
unnecessary to read the book one attempts to criticise.</p></note> 
 
<note id="n5"><seg type="note-symbol">5.</seg> <p>This law is as follows: N = A/(<hi rend="italic">x</hi>+<hi rend="italic">b</hi>)a. 
In which <hi rend="italic">N</hi> represents 
the number of individuals having an income greater than <hi rend="italic">x</hi> or 
<hi rend="italic">A</hi>; <hi rend="italic">b</hi> 
is a constant which For aggregate incomes is in general zero, or 
very near it; <hi rend="italic">a</hi> is another constant whose value lies between 1 
and 2. The law applies only to incomes a little above the 
minimum. The form of the curve in the immediate neighborhood of 
this minimum income is still undetermined, for statistics do not 
furnish us sufficient information for its determination. Since 
the publication of my <hi rend="italic">Cours</hi> I have examined many new statistical 
data, and they all verify the law which I had there formulated. 
The results of my later investigations have been published in the 
<hi rend="italic">Giornale degli Economisti</hi> (Rome).</p></note> 
 
<note id="n6"><seg type="note-symbol">6.</seg> <p>Mr. Carlos C. Closson has made an important 
contribution to this line of study in this JOURNAL for Septmeber 1896.</p></note> 
 
</div2> 
</div1> 
</body> 
</text> 
</TEI.2> 
