<?xml version="1.0"?>

<?dlps id="PeaArti"?>
<?dlps page-images="none" figure-images="no"?>
<?dlps transcription="other"?>

<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/tei-p4/tei2.dtd" [
<!ENTITY % POSTKB "INCLUDE">
<!ENTITY % TEI.extensions.ent SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.ent">
<!ENTITY % TEI.extensions.dtd SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.dtd">
<!ENTITY % ISOnum SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/charent/iso-num.ent"> %ISOnum;
<!ENTITY % ISOlat1 SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/charent/iso-lat1.ent"> %ISOlat1;
<!ENTITY % ISOpub SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/charent/iso-pub.ent"> %ISOpub;
 
]> 
<TEI.2 id="PeaArti"> 
<teiHeader type="migrated" creator="Etext">
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title type="main">The Artistic Side of Chicago</title>
<title type="sort">artistic side of chicago</title>
<author>Peattie, Elia Wilkinson, 1862-1935</author>
<respStmt> 
<resp>Creation of machine-readable version:</resp> 
<name/> 
<resp>Conversion to TEI.2-conformant markup:</resp> 
<name>Text prepared by the 1998-99 Kathryn and W. Harry Schwarzschild Graduate Fellow Elizabeth Styron for the University of Virginia Electronic Text Center..</name>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt> 
<extent>ca. <num type="kilobytes">30</num> kilobytes</extent> 
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>University of Virginia Library</publisher>
<pubPlace>Charlottesville, Virginia</pubPlace> 
<idno type="ETC">PeaArti</idno> 
<date value="1999">1999</date>
<availability status="public">
<p n="copyright">Copyright &copy; 1999 by the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia</p>
<p n="access">Publicly accessible</p>
</availability>
<idno type="uva-pid">uva-lib:476280</idno>
</publicationStmt>
<seriesStmt>
<title>University of Virginia Library, Text collection</title>
<idno type="uva-set">UVA-LIB-Text</idno>
</seriesStmt> 
<sourceDesc>
<biblFull>
<titleStmt>
<title type="main">The Artistic Side of Chicago</title>
<title level="m">Atlantic Monthly</title>
<title type="sort">artistic side of chicago</title>
<author>Peattie, Elia Wilkinson 1862-1935</author>
</titleStmt> 
<editionStmt>
<p>This article is excerpted from Volume 84 (Dec. 1899)</p>
</editionStmt> 
<extent>pp. 828-834</extent> 
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>Houghton, Mifflin and Company</publisher> 
<pubPlace>Boston</pubPlace> 
<date value="1899">1899</date> 
<idno type="callNo">Source copy consulted: UVa Library, AP 2 .A8</idno>
</publicationStmt> 
</biblFull>
</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc> 
<encodingDesc>
<projectDesc>
<p>Prepared for the University of Virginia Library Electronic Text Center.</p>
</projectDesc> 
<editorialDecl>
<p>All unambiguous end-of-line hyphens have been removed, and the  trailing part of a word has been joined to the preceding line.</p> 
<p id="ETC">Some keywords in the header are a local Electronic Text Center scheme  to aid in establishing analytical groupings.</p>
</editorialDecl> 
</encodingDesc> 
<profileDesc>
<creation>
<date value="1899">1899</date>
</creation> 
<langUsage>
<language id="eng" usage="main">English</language>
</langUsage> 
<textClass>
<keywords>
<term>nonfiction</term> 
<term>prose</term> 
<term>feminine</term> 
<term>Women Writers</term>
</keywords> 
</textClass>
</profileDesc> 
<revisionDesc>
<change>
<date value="1999-01">January 1999</date> 
<respStmt>
<resp>corrector</resp> 
<name>Elizabeth Styron, Electronic Text Center</name>
</respStmt> 
<item>Added TEI header and tags</item>
</change> 
<change>
<date value="2005-07">July 2005</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>Corrector</resp>
<name>John Ivor Carlson</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Converted SGML to XML and/or corrected tagging.</item>
</change>
<change>
<date value="2007-09">September 2007</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>Migration</resp>
<name>Ethan Gruber, University of Virginia Library</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Converted XML markup from TEI Lite to uva-dl-tei (TEI P4 with local customizations).</item>
</change>
<change>
<date value="2008-01">January 2008</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>Migration</resp>
<name>Greg Murray, University of Virginia Library</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Programmatically updated TEI header markup (but not header content) for minimal compliance with current QA requirements.</item>
</change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader> 
 
 
 
<text id="d1"> 
 
 
 
 
 
<body id="d2"> 
 
 
 

 
<div1 type="article" id="d3"> <pb n="828"/>
 <head>THE ARTISTIC SIDE OF CHICAGO.</head> 
     <p>O<hi rend="small-caps">NE</hi> who enters Chicago unacquainted with it, having no open 
sesame to its hospitable doors, knowing the city only by its streets, 
its hotels, and its theatres, is disturbed by an unpleasant emotion.  If 
he comes from some well-regulated, cultivated, and placid town of 
the eastern part of this country, or from England or Germany, he 
feels shaken out of poise and peace by a tremendous discord.  He 
sees a city ankle-deep in dirt, swathed in smoke, wild with noise, 
and frantic with the stress of life.  He sees confusion rampant, and 
the fret and fume of the town rise and brood above it like hideous 
Afrits. 
</p><p>But as time goes on   &mdash;   and even supposing the man continues 
to remain a stranger among the two millions of his fellow men who 
make up the city   &mdash;   he experiences a change of sentiment.  He 
ceases to be shocked, and becomes interested.  It occurs to him that 
if commerce is ever epic, it is so here.  He feels the beat of the city 
like the vibration of mighty drums, and the thing he thought a 
discord he discovers to be the rhythm of great movements.  The 
drab sky, the dirty streets, the dusky air, the dark-clothed figures of 
the people, are all in harmony, and it seems dramatically fitting that 
a city in the throes of its toil should wear its working clothes.  It is 
grimy with its labor, and breathless and noisy forging its Balmung 
with mighty shouts. 
</p><p>He who comes to Chicago to seek his fortune, possessing 
delicate traditions, having been brought up among persons of 
similar traditions, is confused and angered by the treatment he 
receives.  He discovers that he must be successful if he would be 
noticed; that he must be in need if he would be helped.  But if he 
makes his way in law-abiding, frugal, and lonely fashion, he will 
attract no attention.  And first and last, in poverty and in riches, in 
sickness and in health, the town will roar at him; if he is afraid, it 
will roar twice as loud as it did before.  Its furnaces and forges, its 
cable systems and syndicates, its slaughterhouses and wheatpits, its 
railroads and elevators, its greedy breadwinners and greedy 
millionaires, and the boats upon its filthy river will all roar.  So, 
inevitably, at last, in a puny way, he will roar back.  He will say 
Chicago has no peace, no leisure, no aspirations save those of a 
materialistic sort, no religion, no refinement.  Sometimes, even after 
he has found he is mistaken in saying these things, he will go on 
saying them, because he cannot forgive Chicago for enticing him, 
with her commercial allurements, away from the home of his youth 
and the things to which he was born.  He lays to her account all the 
pangs of homesickness which he suffers, and he misrepresents her, 
as it is the fate of new cities to be misrepresented. 
</p><p>There are thousands of well-born and well-trained men in 
Chicago, who, coming here from other places and leaving that 
which was most dear to them behind, have traveled from their 
offices to their homes and back again, dull as cow-herds that slouch 
along a worn path from barn to field.  They know nothing of the city 
that may not be seen beside their daily paths or experienced in the 
routine of business.  These men complain that Chicago means 
nothing to them but the dollar; and in their egotism they forget that 
they mean nothing more to Chicago.  In fact, the artistic sense has 
always existed among us surreptitiously.  For thirty years and more 
those who have been conscious of the inner spirit of the city have 
recognized an avid desire for intellectual and &aelig;sthetic 
pleasures, in the indulgence of which 
 
<pb n="829"/> 
 
the fierce labor and competition of the town might be forgotten.  It 
was about thirty years ago that Chicago had her first distinguished 
painter; about that time a famous sculptor set up his work-shop 
here, and a number of young men met to read Dante in his native 
tongue; then came the Browning class, the first to be organized in 
America; and then was organized a woman's club, the first of many, 
but remaining to this day one of the most aspiring of its kind. 
</p><p>These were the first visible signs of the desire for beauty and 
for mental recreation among the men and women of Chicago, &mdash; 
men and women engaged in the most amazing performance in the 
way of rapid city-building which the history of the world has ever 
known.  It was inevitable that such a city should be essentially, even 
violently democratic, and that in the pursuit of beauty, as in all 
other things, equal opportunities should be offered to all.  When 
parks were put in the plan of the city, they were put in for the poor 
people; when libraries were made, they were made free, and in at 
least one of these generous collections were provided books 
designed especially for workers in all manner of mechanism and 
handcraft.  Of large libraries there are three.  The public library has 
sub-stations in the suburbs and in remote parts of the city, that the 
expense of time and travel may be saved; for the city is of great 
extent.  The other two libraries are the result of private munificence.  
Their almost inexhaustible resources are free as air, and every 
workman may avail himself of their privileges.  The three libraries 
have wisely bought their books with reference one to the others, that 
the greatest variety of books possible might be obtained, and the 
convenience of students of all sorts thus be met. 
</p><p>The democratic idea held in art as in other matters, and when, 
through the unselfish exertion of a number of very busy men and 
women, the Art Institute came into existence, it was made as nearly 
free as possible.  There are over a thousand pupils in attendance 
now, some of whom are children of representative families, and 
some the Arabs of the street.  There is a permanent exhibit of very 
good worth within the walls, and exhibits drawn from the cities of 
the Old World as well as the New are frequent.  The instructors and 
lecturers are men and women of many schools.  Some are 
conservative, with Old World traditions; some are newspaper artists, 
who work "for the God of Things as They Are;" some are former 
students of the Institute; others are foreigners, who lament the 
"atmosphere" of older cities.  It is very pleasant to know that a 
number of these instructors have identified themselves for years 
past with movements intended to acquaint the towns lying beyond 
Chicago with pictures and artists. 
</p><p>The completion of the handsome Fine Arts Building has given 
those engaged in artistic pursuits a feeling of stability, and has led to 
increased sociability.  There are painters and sculptors to be found 
on some floors; on other floors are musicians, teachers of dramatic 
art, collectors of gems and antique curios.  Then there are clubs of 
one sort and another.  The Chicago Woman's Club, which offers 
prizes to artists, looks after women in police stations, argues 
publicly with politicians from the mayor down, writes papers, and 
entertains royally on occasion.  Also there is the Fortnightly, a 
woman's club, with a history and a rigidly limited membership.  
Near at hand the Caxton Club has its exquisite suite of rooms, in 
which it holds exhibitions of fine bindings, book plates, antique 
books, and illuminations.  Here, too, is the Hundred and One Club, 
to which newspaper folk and other writers belong; and a very well-known club of rich young women, who for ten years have 
befriended the girls in the factories in ways both practical and 
sentimental, to the cementing of friendship between the fortunate 
and 
 
<pb n="830"/> 
 
the unfortunate.  Also there is the Little Room, which meets once a 
week, at the hour when it grows too dark to paint, at the studio of 
Mr. Ralph Clarkson, and finds comfort in a samovar and sociability.  
To be entitled to membership, one must have created something in 
the world of art.  Writers, painters, sculptors, architects, and 
musicians belong, and even a reviewer or two who are said to have 
created a prejudice.  But while achievement is the passport to the 
doors of the Little Room, once within all evidences of toil and 
talent must be hidden: the clay is covered, the easel draped, the desk 
closed, the piano locked; and hospitality rules. 
</p><p>The Arts and Crafts Society alone refuses to meet at this 
rendezvous, but for a time clanged its anvils and lit its braziers in 
the attic of the Woman's Temple, far above nervous neighbors.  
Now it meets at Hull House.  This society is composed of men and 
women who turn the rooms under their mansard roofs into smithies, 
set up kilns in their furnace rooms, and fashion their own furniture.  
They aim to do original work or none at all, and their shaping and 
carving, their burning and beating of woods and metals, result in 
many articles which are beautiful and some which are unique.  In 
addition to the work in silver and gold and bronze and wood, some 
hand-weaving has been done; for the members are lavish of 
experiments, of which, if the successes bring but little glory, the 
failures bring abundant merriment, and, fortunately, no one takes 
the pretty achievements too seriously. 
</p><p>Bookmaking in all its aspects has called out some pleasing 
endeavors.  On its mechanical side it has been entered into with 
enthusiasm.  Private printing has been undertaken with keen 
interest, and at several private presses reproductions of old books 
and delicate editions of new ones have been made by amateurs.  A 
few ladies have essayed the designing and binding of books: a 
representative of Hull House has recently returned from the Dove 
Bindery at London, after perfecting herself in this art, with the 
intention of making binding one of the industries of the manual 
workers at Hull House.  Some attractive illumination in books has 
been shown in public lately, the work of a Chicago woman who has 
numerous disciples, and another woman has made the painting of 
stereopticon slides a fine art.  One young man is winning approval 
as the illustrator of ecclesiastical books; two brothers, very young 
men, have brought a luxuriant fancy and a rare sense of color to use 
in the making of book covers, and another young man has gained 
for himself a national reputation in work along the same lines. 
</p><p>As for the writers, there is among them at least one cunning 
master of style; there is another who faithfully depicts the lift of the 
city; and there are a number who interpret the life of the further 
West,   &mdash;   the West of "the open and the sky."  It must be admitted 
that this concentration upon the West is a token of provincialism, &mdash; 
a provincialism different in its quality, however, from that which is 
noticeable among those who live in New York.  At the metropolis, 
where artists and writers live in an atmosphere of appreciation, and 
feel that they are the children of her greatness, no burden of duty 
and no pressure of circumstance, save that of a personal nature, is 
laid upon them.  But in Chicago one who writes feels impelled to 
explain the impulsive, terrible, exhaustless city to the world, and to 
account for it by calling attention to the forces which lie back of it.  
Hurrying with the never ebbing crowd along her streets, living the 
eager life with the others, amazed daily at the momentum of the 
place, seeing there is scarcely any people of the globe for which the 
town is not an asylum, one feels it a duty, almost a command, to put 
the thing down in words, and give the world an idea of the city's 
energy and achievement.  It is this which has given some of the best 
known 
 
<pb n="831"/> 
 
writers of the West the "sacramental view of literature," as one of 
them ironically expressed it.  For Chicago has a passionate zest for 
life; it is arrogant, swaggering, half drunken with pride, puffed up at 
its benevolence, its large-mindedness, and its ingenuity; and it 
conceals, as a blustering young man will conceal a virtue or a 
tenderness, the nostalgia for beauty which yearns in its heart.  True, 
it expressed it quite frankly once, in the World's Fair, but, as if 
ashamed of this confidence, it tore the buildings from their 
foundations, or gave to the flames, the winds, and the junk shop the 
manifestations of this "one hour of madness and of joy."  When the 
betraying beauty was destroyed, and the people had got back to their 
toil and their common-placeness, they once more looked the world 
in the face like honest men. 
</p><p>We are all quite free to admit that the large and comprehensive 
novel of Chicago has not yet been written, and it may be that it is an 
impossibility, like the great American novel.  Chicago is too diverse 
for any book to represent more than one phase of its life.  Henry 
Fuller, Will Payne, and George Ade have already faithfully 
reproduced certain phases; and John McCutcheon, the newspaper 
artist, has been as true to facts with his pencil as they have been 
with their pens.  Many have made Chicago the scene of their books, 
but they have not written subjectively, nor with a full understanding 
of the whims, the purposes, and the aspirations of the place; 
consequently, their novels, however readable, cannot be accepted 
by the city as being genuine biography.  Some of these books, most 
to be commended for literary value and for general interest, reveal 
an almost puerile misunderstanding of Chicago, and must be 
accounted failures when looked upon as local histories.  It may be 
the widespread conviction that the conditions of the West are 
peculiar, and the sturdy provincialism which goes with it, that is 
responsible for the good-fellowship among the art workers of 
Chicago.  The jealousies which so frequently exist among groups of 
that sort have never lifted their evil heads here.  Those who know 
the inner life of other and older towns say that nowhere else among 
art workers is there as much sociability and good feeling as in 
Chicago.  The informal evenings, with their free bonhomie, their 
music, reading, and talk, reconcile many a stranger within the gates 
to his exile from home, and bind the colony more closely together. 
</p><p>But if Western artists and writers have a moral responsibility 
in regard to their section, what shall be said of the architects, of 
whom the city has an aspiring and picturesque company?  That, in 
spite of the ugliness of Chicago, which is an admitted fact, they 
have one honest achievement to their credit.  They have almost 
created that important form of construction, commercial 
architecture.  The "sky scraper" of steel, glass, and terra cotta   &mdash;   a 
daring contrivance, and well suited to the place and its needs   &mdash;   has 
appeared here in its perfection.  Perhaps the ideal office building of 
the country is the Marquette building, which is not merely adapted 
to all the demands of such a structure, but, furthermore, is 
ornamented consistently.  The exploits of the distinguished Jesuit 
whose name the building bears are represented in mosaics and 
mural decorations about the rotunda; the wild animals of the 
territory which the traveler and priest explored are reproduced in the 
bold work of Kemeys, the animal sculptor, and the Indians among 
whom Marquette dwelt live again in O'Neill's famous medallions.  
As perfect in its way is the wholesale house of Marshall Field.  
There are in the country few buildings of solid masonry more 
substantial, convenient, and effective than the Auditorium, with its 
hotel and vast audience chamber; and few edifices with a 
fa&ccedil;ade so calm and noble as that presented by the First 
Church of Christ, on Drexel Boulevard. 
 
<pb n="832"/> 
 
</p><p>The homes of Chicago, to be sure, can-not be said to have any 
typical or general style, unless it be the hideous fashion which puts 
up a front of stone twenty-five feet wide, and confesses to the fraud 
with two hundred feet of common brick wall on the other three 
sides, broken with fire escapes and rear porches.  Were the city 
more closely built, these crimes against sincerity might be partly 
concealed; but there is still space,   &mdash;   space which, like the marshes 
of Glynn, is all revealing.  Even the lavish homes on the boulevards, 
luxurious as they are, are lacking in harmonious effect.  Money has 
been almost recklessly spent upon them, and there they stand in 
bewildering diversity, imitating all manner of things, from 
Florentine palaces to castellated feudal strongholds, and reaching 
for miles along the drives of the three divisions of the city and far 
out into the country.  A horse would be wearied to travel from the 
old Cyrus McCormick mansion to the end of the Lake Shore 
residences, as they reach beyond Lincoln Park and follow the 
Sheridan Road through an unbroken line of smart suburbs.  There 
are, besides, miles upon miles, compact and commonplace, of the 
homes of workingmen, and it is in these grim and unlovely stretches 
that the architecture of the city takes on its most offensive aspect.  
To the children of these localities who can know little or nothing of 
beauty, to the women who work there and seldom go far from their 
own neighborhood, the city, it seems, must become monstrous. 
</p><p>It is to such people, whose toil and intelligence have made 
Chicago what it is, that those who have a message of beauty hold 
the heaviest responsibility.  And there are many who have not been 
oblivious of this fact.  In the midst of the crowded communities of 
toilers there are eleven or twelve settlements where the higher 
studies, the languages, the arts, and the crafts are taught to a greater 
or less extent.  Many are denominational, one is Jewish, some are 
non-sectarian, and the most influential, Hull House, is without 
religious prejudice or limitation.  For it is like charity, that beareth 
all things, believeth all things, hopeth all things, endureth all things.  
The wisdom and patience of Jane Addams guide its work, but it 
takes the co&ouml;peration of many to bring about the results 
which are now discernible.  Year by year, many of the most 
cultivated young men and women in the city add their energy to this 
stream of light and beauty, so that it may truthfully be said that no 
child need hunger for knowledge, no one with a desire for art in any 
direction need let his talent die for want of opportunity to develop 
it. 
</p><p>It is often said that Chicago is a cruel city.  If it is so, it is 
obviously without intention.  The clangor and bluster incidental to 
its toil are enough to affright the stoutest heart, if there be no money 
in the purse and no home at the end of the journey.  But it is a 
tender-hearted city, after all; and when it has beaten the life out of 
man or woman with its million iron hoofs, it is very sorry, and 
weeps from its innumerable eyes, and tries passionately to make up 
for it in deeds of benevolence.  This may not seem, on the face of it, 
to have anything to do with a sense of beauty, but it has.  The noisy 
and swaggering town has a heart that yearns for beauty, and that 
desires the comfort of all men.  This is a part of her youth, of her 
democracy and her honesty.  There are some hard task-masters 
within her limits, as there must indubitably be in a town where 
syndicates abound and corporations have their way; but public 
sentiment still holds up an ideal, and if by chance the wheels of 
greed and selfishness bespatter it, it is gilded anew, and once more 
lifted up that the people may see it. 
</p><p>The building of Chicago has been a much more difficult thing 
than those who traverse its streets to-day can appreciate; for it rests  
on a sandy slough, where the 
 
<pb n="833"/> 
 
lake once rocked; its buildings are erected on piles, its streets have 
been elevated, and miles upon miles of its substructure are 
composed of practically solid masonry.  Hundreds of acres have 
been filched from the lake, which, jealous of the theft, batters at the 
sea wall and undermines the esplanades.  But in spite of all this, 
boulevards skirt the lake, intersect the city, and pass about it in a 
vernal belt from park to park.  There are certainly six of the greater 
parks, yearly increasing in beauty as trees and shrubbery grow, and 
many smaller breathing places.  The city council has recently 
authorized the purchase of playgrounds for the children.  These 
places of peace and arboreal beauty offer pleasant paths to the 
hurried and worried folk of the town, and for a time, at least, give a 
sense of leisure and freedom from care.  Here, in summer time, 
there are open-air concerts, some of them paid for by the park 
commissioners, and some by private citizens.  A few citizens make 
up the annual deficit attending the season of the Chicago orchestra, 
of which Theodore Thomas is the leader; at these concerts the most 
impecunious music lover may listen to the best music in the world 
interpreted by a gifted leader and an enthusiastic orchestra. 
</p><p>But these indications of a growing devotion to that which 
warms the heart with beauty and with joy are not the measurement 
of aspiration.  They do not tell of that eager interest in art among the 
youth of the city, which a few years ago, if it existed at all, did not 
find expression.  Nor do they reveal the intense earnestness of 
artists and writers in this part of the world,   &mdash;   artists and writers 
whose earnestness may defeat itself, but who surely blaze the path 
for others who shall do better than they.  Nor can they reveal the 
mood of society, which, though it is not artistic, is inclined to look 
generously upon art, and humorously at itself. 
</p><p>"We have made our money in pigs," once said a young 
gentleman who was then president of the Art Institute, "but is that 
any reason why we should not spend it in pictures?" 
</p><p>The artistic sense of Chicago partakes of the spirit of the town, in 
that it persists in spite of all contumely.  It is the fashion to 
depreciate it, to laugh at all pretensions to achievement on any save 
commercial lines, and to berate the city generally whenever it is 
mentioned.  To all this Chicago turns a broad, good-humored smile, 
and tramps on through her mud, indifferent and besmeared.  She has 
no time to pause; she is too busy and absorbed even to clean her 
streets; that which would be a disgrace to another city is only an 
incident with her.  She is so confident of her destiny that she takes 
no note of mistakes, is not irritated at her failures nor depressed at 
her shortcomings.  On the contrary, she is amused at herself,   &mdash;   at 
her exaggerations, her absurdities.  But she knows, after all, that she 
is not understood.  She knows that deep in her heart is an ideal, and 
it is the knowledge of this ideal which is responsible for the 
excessive civic pride noticeable in those who live within her limits.  
It is the belief in this ideal which inspires confidence in her ultimate 
artistic expression. 
</p><p>To an artist, one of the charms of the West is that it has been 
only partly exploited.  Yet when Kipling remarked in Captains 
Courageous, that the story of the New West was yet to be written, it 
was peculiarly irritating, especially to those of us who believed that 
at least one man knew the West, and had told the tale of it in simple 
stories which stuck to the imagination and the memory like burs.  
But whether or not Kipling's observation be true of the wider West, 
it is certainly true of Chicago.  The city awaits her artistic creator.  
She may think she exists in literature; but if she does, it is only in a 
form at once evanescent and tentative.  No one has yet risen to 
rescue her from oblivion 
 
<pb n="834"/> 
 
and give her immortality through art.  Therefore, the most 
encouraging thing about the newly developed &aelig;stheticism of 
Chicago is the opportunity for virile and original work which lies at 
hand.  The city seems to cry out to the workers with the pencil and 
the pen: "See what stories I offer you, what contrasts, what 
tragedies!  See the mingling of strange peoples, the mob of wild 
faces from less fortunate lands, the old stories that are written on 
these faces, and the new stories on the faces of those born with old 
ideas to new conditions!  Here is material for painter and poet, 
philosopher and novelist!"  In one neighborhood the people read 
Yiddish, have a system of commerce all their own and a Sinaitic 
law.  You may see the old men sitting at noonday, silent, for 
worship, in a bare room above a fruit store.  They do not hear the 
roar of the city, for they are absorbed in thought, though tumult and 
squalor are all about them.  In another part of town there is a 
neighborhood composed almost exclusively of Poles, and you may 
catch a glimpse of a little bride, all in white, tripping down the 
murky street, with the wedding party capering at her heels.  If you 
turn into the district by the rolling mills, gigantic men will reply to 
your questions in English which is yet not English, giving you big 
mouthfuls of dialect.  And here in a little neighborhood apart are 
Icelanders,   &mdash;   Icelanders who have not forgotten the sagas, and who, 
when they are homesick, summon up visions of fishermen's huts on 
wild fire-fashioned rock.  Of Swedes, too, there is a mighty number, 
and of the Germans more than all.  But the story of the American is 
greatest, for it is his land and his day, and he is drunk with his own 
achievements.  He plays at the game of commerce, and is satisfied; 
for losing or winning does not so much matter to him as that he 
have the chance of the game. 
</p><p>These are among the aspects of Chicago which wait to be set 
down.  They are understood by the people who meet and laugh 
together in hours after work, but whether they will be reproduced or 
not is left on the knees of the gods. 
</p><p>There seems to be no reason, however, the opportunity for 
training being free, the material for work being at hand, and the 
talent for work being manifest, why brave things in artistic 
achievement should not be done in Chicago within the next few 
years. 
</p><p>It is true, there are those who think that art, like the cyclone, 
has its paths, and that Chicago is far removed from the worn 
thoroughfare which the Muses tread; they expect us to be content 
with ugliness and non-expression, and to treat any creative ideas 
that come to us as the pretty princes in the Tower were treated.  But 
this would be too callous by far; it would be too cynical; nay, it 
would be too humble.  It is our fortune not to be callous, or cynical, 
or humble.  The dreams and effervescence of youth are still ours.  
We still hope to embody these visions and excitations in palpable 
beauty.  It does not even matter to us if the rest of the world is 
amused at our declaration of principles, our confession of artistic 
faith; for we are elate with the reckless confidence of those who 
have not yet had a chance to fail.</p> 
      <signed><hi rend="italic">Elia W. Peattie.</hi></signed> 
 
</div1> 
</body> 
</text> 
</TEI.2>
