<?xml version="1.0"?>

<?dlps id="PeaDoor"?>
<?dlps page-images="none" figure-images="no"?>
<?dlps transcription="other"?>

<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/tei-p4/tei2.dtd" [
<!ENTITY % POSTKB "INCLUDE">
<!ENTITY % TEI.extensions.ent SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.ent">
<!ENTITY % TEI.extensions.dtd SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.dtd">
<!ENTITY % ISOpub SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/charent/iso-pub.ent"> %ISOpub;
]> 
<TEI.2 id="PeaDoor"> 
<teiHeader type="migrated" creator="Etext">
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title type="main">The Door</title>
<title type="sort">door</title>
<author>Peattie, Elia Wilkinson, 1862-1935</author>
<respStmt> 
<resp>Creation of machine-readable version:</resp> 
<name>Judy Boss</name> 
<resp>Conversion to TEI.2-conformant markup:</resp> 
<name>University of Virginia Library Electronic Text Center.</name>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt> 
<extent>ca. <num type="kilobytes">33</num> kilobytes</extent> 
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>University of Virginia Library</publisher>
<pubPlace>Charlottesville, Virginia</pubPlace> 
<idno type="ETC">PeaDoor</idno> 
<date value="1999">1999</date>
<availability status="public">
<p n="copyright">Copyright &#xa9; 1999 by the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia</p>
<p n="access">Publicly accessible</p>
</availability>
<idno type="uva-pid">uva-lib:477245</idno>
</publicationStmt>
<seriesStmt>
<title>University of Virginia Library, Text collection</title>
<idno type="uva-set">UVA-LIB-Text</idno>
</seriesStmt> 
<sourceDesc>
<biblFull>
<titleStmt>
<title type="main">The Door</title>
<title level="j">Reader</title>
<title type="sort">door</title>
<author>Peattie, Elia Wilkinson, 1862-1935</author>
</titleStmt> 
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>Bobbs-Merrill Company</publisher> 
<pubPlace>Indianapolis</pubPlace> 
<date value="1906">1905-1908</date> 
<idno type="callNo">Source copy consulted: UVa Library, S-687</idno>
</publicationStmt> 
<notesStmt>
<note>
<p>This story appeared in v. 7 (Jan 1906), p. 168-176.</p>
</note>
</notesStmt>
</biblFull>
</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc> 
<encodingDesc>
<projectDesc>
<p>Prepared for the University of Virginia Library Electronic Text Center.</p>
</projectDesc> 
<editorialDecl>
<p>All unambiguous end-of-line hyphens have been removed, and the  trailing part of a word has been joined to the preceding line.</p> 
<p id="ETC">Some keywords in the header are a local Electronic Text Center scheme  to aid in establishing analytical groupings.</p>
</editorialDecl> 
</encodingDesc> 
<profileDesc>
<creation>
<date value="1906">1906</date>
</creation> 
<langUsage>
<language id="eng" usage="main">English</language>
</langUsage> 
<textClass>
<keywords>
<term>fiction</term> 
<term>prose</term> 
<term>feminine</term> 
<term>Women Writers</term>
</keywords> 
</textClass>
</profileDesc> 
<revisionDesc>
<change>
<date value="1999-04">April 1999</date> 
<respStmt>
<resp>corrector</resp> 
<name>June Griffin, Electronic Text Center</name>
</respStmt> 
<item>Added TEI header and tags</item>
</change> 
<change>
<date value="2005-07">July 2005</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>Corrector</resp>
<name>John Ivor Carlson</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Converted SGML to XML and/or corrected tagging.</item>
</change>
<change>
<date value="2007-09">September 2007</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>Migration</resp>
<name>Ethan Gruber, University of Virginia Library</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Converted XML markup from TEI Lite to uva-dl-tei (TEI P4 with local customizations).</item>
</change>
<change>
<date value="2008-01">January 2008</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>Migration</resp>
<name>Greg Murray, University of Virginia Library</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Programmatically updated TEI header markup (but not header content) for minimal compliance with current QA requirements.</item>
</change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader> 
<text id="d1">  
<body id="d2"> 
<div1 type="story" id="d3"> 
<head> 
The Door<lb/> 
 
<hi rend="italic">By Elia W. Peattie</hi><lb/> 
 
AUTHOR OF "THE SHAPE OF FEAR," ETC.</head> 
 
<div2 type="chapter" n="1" id="d4">
<p>"HE'S asleep, isn't he?" asks the man. 
</p><p>"I can't be sure.  I never <hi rend="italic">could</hi> be sure!  With his eyes 
always closed as they are, and with that odd habit he has of lying so 
still, I can't make out half the time whether he's sleeping or waking." 
</p><p>"You haven't told him anything yet, I suppose?" 
</p><p>"Told him?  No.  Oh, no, I haven't told him!" 
</p><p>The woman shivers perceptibly, and draws closer to the 
leaping fire on the hearth. 
</p><p>"Of course," continues the man, speaking cautiously still, "you 
may as well explain the situation to him.  He's too young to take it 
to heart, and I know you agree with me that it's going to be the best 
thing for him in the end.  Those childless people, shut in as they are, 
will be perfectly devoted to the child.  His misfortune is going to be 
a direct appeal to their sympathies.  He'll be the great factor of their 
lives    &mdash;    you know that, Madeline?  While in our lives he would be 
but an incident, and a disturbing one at that.  It isn't that I dislike the 
little fellow.  He couldn't help being born, and he couldn't help 
being blind.  He couldn't help having Alexander Cameron for his 
father.  But I can help having him in my home, Madeline, to remind 
me of things I want to forget.  You understand, don't you?  I'm a 
jealous man.  I was made that way.  I'd give ten years of my life to 
have had you fresh from your mother's arms    &mdash;    to make you see me 
and no one else; to live in your heart and in your mind alone.  The 
sight of the boy 
 
<pb n="169"/> 
 
would be a perpetual irritation.  I couldn't endure it, Madeline.  It 
would make a sort of monster out of me!" 
</p><p>He leans forward to draw her into his arms, but she evades him 
and steals to the door of an inner room. 
</p><p>"Donald!  Donald!" she calls softly. 
</p><p>There is no movement in the little bed by the wall.  A child's 
slight form is visible there, well-covered with its blue quilt.  The 
light catches his reddish-gold curls and displays a portion of a 
delicate profile. 
</p><p>The woman comes back to the fire. 
</p><p>"It's wonderful," she says moodily, "how like and unlike his 
father he is!" 
</p><p>The man's large jowl gives a grotesque movement as if his 
teeth ground hard upon each other. 
</p><p>"But how am I to help all that?" cries the woman, spreading 
out her hands.  "There's no use, Henry, in denying my past!  We 
can't have things as we want them in this world.  We have to take 
them as we find them.  That's the sensible way!" 
</p><p>The man comes close to her. 
</p><p>"But I tell you," he cries, "that I am going to make you forget 
it!  The thought of you fills my heart, and I mean to make you forget 
everything except the present.  And that's to be made up of love!  
Can't you feel as I do, Madeline, that there's nothing else in the 
world but that?  Why, it's the beginning and end of my days.  The 
thought wakes up with me, walks with me, breathes with me, sleeps 
with me!" 
</p><p>The face of the woman flushes deeply.  She leans forward till 
the laces droop from her white throat, on which the man fixes his 
eyes greedily. 
</p><p>"Well," she whispers, "I think I ought to be forgiven if I go 
looking for happiness for a while!  If people knew the whole truth, 
they'd forgive me, Henry, wouldn't they?" 
</p><p>"People do as they please, Madeline!  They take joy when they 
can get it.  Do you suppose any other man would have waited as I 
have; you've been free four years.  I've known for one year, and I've 
loved you from the moment my eyes fell on you.  It never occurred 
to me then that you were anything but a girl!  I tell you, Madeline, 
I'll never forget the torture of that discovery    &mdash;    the discovery that 
you were a widow and that Donald    &mdash;   " 
</p><p>"Oh, Donald!"  There is poignancy in the cry.  "If it were not 
for Donald    &mdash;   " 
</p><p>"Now that's foolish, Madeline!  Consider a moment.  The boy 
is a tyrant in his way    &mdash;   " 
</p><p>"He's so helpless!  That's why, Henry    &mdash;    so helpless." 
</p><p>"Well, he's been encouraged to be helpless.  And he's a 
petulant, ungrateful little fellow.  In the life we will probably lead it 
would be out of the question for you to give him personal care.  
He'd have to be turned over to servants; and it's a thousand times 
better for him, as you can see, to go to the Brandenbergs out there at 
the farm.  But, to be perfectly frank, whether it's better for him or 
not, it's got to be, Madeline.  If the boy's with you he'll be first    &mdash;    
sooner or later he'll be first.  And then I'll hate him." 
</p><p>"It comes to this," says the woman, "that I choose between 
you?" 
</p><p>The man shows no capitulation.  His eyes are glowing, his lips 
parted, and the strong pulse shows in his throat. 
</p><p>"Precisely," he nods. 
</p><p>"Oh!" breathes the woman staring at him. 
</p><p>"Well," he expostulates.  "Be reasonable, Madeline!  Haven't I 
seen you look at the boy with positive aversion?  More than once, in 
my presence, you've drawn away from him involuntarily when he 
came putting his arms about your neck." 
</p><p>"It was in your presence!" she murmurs with a subtle 
insinuation.  But he does not observe that, and urges his point. 
</p><p>"He's the picture of his father!  That's the core of the matter.  
You shrank from 
 
<pb n="170"/> 
 
the father, and you shrink from the son.  The chances are, as he 
grows older, the resemblance will become more marked and your 
repugnance will increase.  Nervous, irritable, with a sort of disease 
of pride    &mdash;    don't you recognize the traits you have told me of in your 
   &mdash;    in your husband?" 
</p><p>The woman twists her fingers in and out.  There is a silence, 
and the two have the effect of combating each other with their 
thoughts.  There is at once a repulsion and an attraction between 
them, and when by chance their eyes meet, they hold each other 
with a look at once ecstatic and apprehensive. 
</p><p>At last the silence is broken.  It is the woman who speaks. 
</p><p>"I began wrong!" she cries.  "I began wrong!  Maybe I'm 
destined to go wrong to the end!" 
</p><p>"You are right for me," Stonehurst interrupts.  "You are perfect 
for me." 
</p><p>But Madeline does not heed him. 
</p><p>"My childhood was pitiable," she says, as much to herself as to 
her companion.  "It was worse    &mdash;    it was grotesque.  I had 
extravagant dreams, and I was surrounded with the ugliest realities.  
There was the boarding-house that poor mother kept, and where she 
worked like a slave.  The kitchen was dark and had a moldy smell, 
and there were rats in the pantries.  She had brother John and Aunt 
Ann and me, all to feed and clothe.  She thought for us all, and hung 
over that old burned-out range, with the cross-bars sagging in the 
middle.  Her face got as hard as granite, and her eyes    &mdash;    lovely eyes  
   &mdash;    got dim.  I was full of fine dreams, and always trying to pretend 
that things were beautiful and that we were happy.  I had a great 
deal of belief in myself.  I was always going to do something 
wonderful.  But after all, I couldn't get ahead of the mere work of 
the house, and my dreams boiled in me!  Nothing could have been 
more ridiculous than I was    &mdash;    a great gangling girl all choked up 
with grief and pride and revolt and passion and love and pity and 
hate!" 
</p><p>"Poor child!" murmurs Stonehurst. 
</p><p>"I am trying to excuse myself to you," she explains, drawing 
nearer.  "Donald's sleeping now.  Can't you hear his breathing?  We 
needn't be so cautious in what we are saying.  Oh, that's one of the 
things that has always annoyed me so in him    &mdash;    his habit of 
listening!  I suppose that, as he couldn't use his eyes, all the 
inquisitiveness of childhood has gone into his ears."  She sits staring 
at the fire for a moment or two while the man looks at her. 
</p><p>"You never have told me," he says under his breath, "how it 
came about that you married Alexander Cameron." 
</p><p>The woman clings to him with her look, her face scarlet with a 
curious shame. 
</p><p>"But I feel," she cries, "as if it were a dream!  When you are 
here with me it seems as if I must sweep the facts away and cry out 
'But I never belonged to any one but you    &mdash;    but you, Henry!'  Why, 
it's as if I had always held a vision of you in my heart and as if you 
had come now to fulfil it in the flesh!" 
</p><p>The man slips from his chair upon his knees and presses her 
hands to his lips.  They are silent for a time, and only his deep 
breathing is audible.  Then he arises. 
</p><p>"After all," he says with a smile which strangely illuminates 
his somber face.  "Facts are of little consequence compared with our 
inner knowledge.  Tell me    &mdash;    I must know some time    &mdash;    tell me 
about Cameron." 
</p><p>Suddenly she laughs, and there is a witchery in her glance. 
</p><p>"Silence is a little glass ball!" she cries.  "There is nothing 
durable about it.  Sooner or later it has to be broken."  She makes as 
though she ground something between her glowing palms.  "See, I 
shatter it now!  Stir the fire, Henry.  Thank you.  Well    &mdash;    well    &mdash;    he 
boarded with my mother, don't you see, whenever he stopped in the 
village on his way to town to sell his fruit or stock or wheat.  He    &mdash;    
he saw me.  I always waited on the table.  He    &mdash;    brought me presents 
from the farm, and 
</p> 
 
<pb n="171"/> 
<p> 
took me riding now and then.  I thought he was kind, and I was glad 
he did not talk.  I liked my own thoughts better than anything he 
could say.  One day he drove mother and me out to his farm    &mdash;    
Cameron Meadows, it is called.  We went in May when everything 
was in blossom.  I felt like singing or shouting, and I couldn't see 
how he and mother could speak so low.  We saw his woods and 
orchards, his pasture lands and hay fields, his wheat lands and his 
garden places.  He showed us his sheep, his cattle, his horses, his 
very hogs and chickens.  There were order and plenty everywhere.  
And in the midst of a hundred beeches stood the old house.  His 
grandfather built it, you know.  It is a beautiful house, Henry    &mdash;    
seven windows in the upper part, looking from the trees with a wise 
expression; and below, flanked with windows to the left and right, 
the great door." 
</p><p>She pauses for a moment and lifts her hand with a curious 
gesture. 
</p><p>"I shall never forget what an impression that door made on me 
when I looked at it first!" 
</p><p>"And why, Madeline?" 
</p><p>"Oh, it was such a benignant door!  You may laugh, but 
actually, if it had not been for the door, I believe I should never 
have consented to be mistress of Cameron Meadows at all!  It was a 
single door, but wide, with good brass hinges and cross bands and 
locks.  Above it was a fan light, with delicate yellowing old lace 
plaited in it.  It was as we were about to enter the door that Mr. 
Cameron said to me: 'I want you to cross this threshold as my 
promised wife.'  At first I was astonished    &mdash;    and afraid.  I hardly had 
been thinking of him at all.  I had been wishing I had a companion 
that beautiful day while mother and Mr. Cameron talked together.  I 
stood for a moment saying nothing, and thoughts went racing 
through my head as memories do through the brain of a drowning 
man.  And then I happened to look up at the door    &mdash;    everything 
swimming before me    &mdash;    and a curious idea came to me.  The old 
door looked so rich in experience, and seemed so fitted to watch the 
generations of men and women come and go that I fell into step, so 
to speak.  I thought of the brides that had crossed that threshold, and 
something irresistible compelled me to make myself one of them.  
And I said 'yes.'  At least, they say I said yes.  I know Mr. Cameron 
drew me into the house looking more pleased than I had supposed 
he knew how to look; but I could hardly see him for a strange vision 
that I had of the people who had finished with their lives and been 
carried out of that door!  Actually I seemed to see a procession there 
with the long black box-like thing with its fringed pall!  But I was 
not afraid.  It was majestic    &mdash;    the vision    &mdash;    I fancied how I would be 
carried out of there, too, and I liked even that thought.  I liked 
anything that was not poverty-stricken and semi-vagrant and mean!  
Mother was there all the time smiling at me in that curious patient 
way of hers.  I had never before noticed how terribly thin she 
looked.  Perhaps it was partly her trailing black dress, or the little 
bonnet on her white hair    &mdash;    but anyway, she seemed to be appealing 
to me to save her from drudgery in her pathetic old age.  I put out 
my hands to her, and it was she    &mdash;    not Mr. Cameron    &mdash;    into whose 
arms I fell.  And I wept there a long, long time." 
</p><p>Stonehurst gnaws his lip and says nothing. 
</p><p>"We were married in a month.  I took mother home with me, 
and Aunt Ann was boarded at a farmer's near by and brother John 
sent away to school.  Mr. Cameron did everything as he had agreed.  
And then mother    &mdash;    mother died.  She was tired out, and when she 
felt we no longer needed her, she gave up the will to live.  And the 
old door had seen a new processional and another recessional, as I 
had seen in my vision that first day.  Then I settled down to my life.  
There were the 
 
<pb n="172"/> 
 
workpeople to see to; and there were Mr. Cameron's friends to 
entertain; and there were church duties and visits to make.  
Everything was laid out for me.  Every day was filled up with things 
I ought to do.  I was so busy that even my dreams were crowded 
out." 
</p><p>"No, no!  Your dreams are the most substantial part of you, 
Madeline.  That's what is so marvelous about you.  There they are 
always, so familiar and immemorial!  You say they are your 
dreams, but I believe they are mine!  Or they are everybody's!  You 
got them out of the heart of the ages, or you stole them from poets!  
You can't say things as others do.  There is something so moving in 
your voice!  I've always felt you to be a mystery!  That's why I 
adore you so!  I wonder if you know how everything you say moves 
me?" 
</p><p>"I'm a mystery, maybe, because I have never found myself.  I 
live in a hermit land, and there is only me to wander about in it." 
</p><p>"Have I not entered it, Madeline, Madeline?" 
</p><p>The woman laughs sadly. 
</p><p>"Have you?  Sometimes I think you have, and other times I think 
I have only found your footprints on the sand and that I am 
searching for you!  But then real things have always seemed like 
shadows and shadows like realities to me.  There at Cameron 
Meadows, the work, the house, the people, were like moving 
shapes.  The summer passed and a white winter came.  I had hoped 
we might go to the city for a while, but Mr. Cameron thought I 
ought to be very quiet then.  No one visited us except the farm 
neighbors.  Mr. Cameron bought my books for me    &mdash;    they were his 
choice.  It used to get dark at four o'clock, and there were 
interminable twilights, with the clock ticking on the stairs.  After 
that came the almost silent dinners and then the long evenings with 
Mr. Cameron at his accounts.  Sometimes I laughed out loud and 
made Mr. Cameron wonder if I were mad.  I used to go out and rush 
through the woods.  I used to beat the tree trunks with my bare fists.  
At last I grew torpid.  I was surprised when the Sundays came 
around.  And then    &mdash;    then Donald came.  That was a fearful 
experience, but I wouldn't have missed it.  I was interested at last    &mdash;    
it was suffering with some significance to it.  I remember three 
horrible days passed and I was sunk in strange visions.  I must have 
suffered physically almost to the limit of endurance.  But it isn't that 
I remember    &mdash;    it is the visions.  They were of battlefields and the 
dying; I heard the cries of the thirsting and wounded, and the sobs 
of men who were homesick.  I was on the sea tossing in the storm 
with men who were not afraid to die.  I went to the guillotine 
through streets of people who hated me, and I wept with pity for 
them.  Then, when it was all over, something had happened to 
Donald    &mdash;    some paralysis.  He was blind!" 
</p><p>The man gives an inarticulate exclamation, at once pitying and 
repugnant. 
</p><p>"We were dismayed, his father and I."  Stonehurst flinches 
from the intimacy of the reference.  "We sent to surgeons far and 
wide.  We carried the child here and there.  We did everything but 
let him be tortured.  We stood guard against that.  But in the end 
nothing was done.  We had to give up hope." 
</p><p>The woman's tone deepens and the recital gathers in passion. 
</p><p>"So life grew more and more hateful, you understand.  The 
child was peevish, and for two years I didn't know what it was to 
have a night's rest.  Mr. Cameron slept in a distant part of the house 
that he might not hear the baby cry.  He couldn't endure that.  'Can't 
you stop that crying?' he would say to me.  'Can't you find out what 
is the matter with that child?'  He would walk the floor and wring 
his hands or plunge out of doors." 
</p><p>She drags her fingers down her cheeks, leaving marks upon the 
flesh, which make her seem almost gaunt. 
</p><p>"Between the child that could not see 
 
<pb n="173"/> 
 
and that cried day and night, and the man in a frenzy or irritability, I 
grew to hate life!  It was like being on the rack.  I used, often and 
often, to wish that we were all dead." 
</p><p>Stonehurst starts to speak, but she interrupts him. 
</p> 

<p>"Then Mr. Cameron died.  I think he was 
broken-hearted about Donald.  And after that I spent three years 
doing my duty.  Three interminable years I lived in solitude, looking 
after the dairy and the farm, and nursing Donald.  And all the time I 
was struggling to get hold of an idea about the rights of an 
individual to select and take for himself.  So one day it came to me 
that the old door stood open    &mdash;    the door of the house that had 
welcomed me, that had imprisoned me and that was going to 
liberate me.  It had seen my poor child groping through it on his 
hands and knees, then stumbling through in his first steps, and 
falling    &mdash;    falling so often!  It had seen the master carried forth.  And 
I meant that it should see me go out in search of my life.  My life 
was there outside, somewhere, awaiting me.  The door stood wide    &mdash;    
it seemed to give me permission to go." 
</p><p>She turns to the man with one of her swift smiles. 
</p><p>"And so I found my life," she whispers and holds out her 
hands. 
</p><p>The room has in it for a time an enchanting silence.  The 
October wind stirs without in an air rich with perfumes of decay; 
the soft breathing of the child is faintly audible; and the coals fall 
now 
 
<pb n="174"/> 
 
and then in the glowing bed on the hearth.  Suddenly the child cries 
in his sleep, and Madeline starts to her feet guiltily.  She hastens to 
the bedroom, and Stonehurst hears her soothing her boy with 
inarticulate sounds and soft pattings.  When she comes back she 
stands by the fire, and Stonehurst, arising, looks across the hearth at 
her. 
</p><p>"He isn't so well these days," she says, using the pronoun as 
mothers will.  I've had such happiness in these rooms, but Donald 
has never found his way about and so he hasn't liked it.  He is shut 
up too much, and it's the most difficult thing imaginable to find a 
toy that will amuse him.  He enjoys himself best at the farm." 
</p><p>"That's the place for him," agrees Stonehurst.  "He'll have pets 
in plenty and the right sort of food and exercise.  These 
Brandenbergs, from what you tell me, will be devoted to him.  You 
said they were mother and son?  The son is a grown man, I 
suppose." 
</p><p>"Yes." 
</p><p>"He's looking after your interests for you, isn't he?" 
</p><p>"Carl Brandenberg?  Yes.  He understands the place perfectly." 
</p><p>"Well, don't place too much confidence in him.  Remember it's 
a large property you have." 
</p><p>"Carl Brandenberg cheats nobody    &mdash;    and <hi rend="italic">never me</hi>." 
</p><p>"No?  But why not you particularly?" 
</p><p>"His father before him managed for the Camerons.  He inherits 
loyalty." 
</p><p>"Do you wish me to inquire into the conditions of his adoption 
of Donald?  For he would wish to have the adoption according to 
law, I suppose." 
</p><p>"Need we think about that just yet?" 
</p><p>"Why, yes.  We are to be married next month    &mdash;    the twelfth    &mdash;   " 
</p><p>"The fifteenth, if you please." 
</p><p>"The fifteenth!  Aren't you moving the days along?  No?  Well, 
the fifteenth.  We shall start for France at once.  It is obvious that 
everything must be settled before we go.  These people will, I have 
no doubt, send you frequent communications about    &mdash;   " 
</p><p>"I don't want them!  I don't want them!  Understand that 
clearly, when Donald goes out of my life he goes out utterly." 
</p><p>The man sighs as if with relief. 
</p><p>"Well, that's sensible.  I like your resolution.  It's better for 
both of you to drop the relationship.  When is the boy to be taken 
out there?" 
</p><p>Madeline is regarding him as if she had never seen him before.  
Glancing at her, he draws back almost with apprehension.  Then a 
joyful flush suffuses her face and neck.  She gives a cry and leans 
toward him, soliciting him with the glory of her eyes, the 
lusciousness of her lips.  He can not profane the moment with 
words, but after a time she volunteers: 
</p><p>"To-morrow I shall take Donald to the farm.  The 
Brandenbergs are impatient for him.  There is a teacher they wish to 
engage for him who is awaiting my decision." 
</p><p>"You're not going to change your mind, Madeline?  I have a 
curious feeling about you.  You are so inexpressibly    &mdash;    illusive." 
</p><p>She does not heed what he is saying.  She seizes his arms in 
her grasp. 
</p><p>"I can't lose you," she cries.  "Having known you, love, I can't 
lose you!  Ah, I can't!  I can't!" 
</p><p>But presently she is impatient for his departure and interrupts 
his half-playful reassurances. 
</p><p>"You must go    &mdash;    you must go!  I am inflexible about the hour, 
you know!  And it has come.  How I admire my prudence!" 
</p><p>"But if you go to the country to-morrow, shall you be able to 
return?  Am I to spend the evening with you as usual?" 
</p><p>"How else?  Good night, good night." 
</p><p>"My love, your impetuosity is too much for me.  At least let 
me find my posses- 
<pb n="175"/> 
 
sions.  There    &mdash;    my hat    &mdash;    thank you.  Good night, Madeline.  Sleep 
very sweetly    &mdash;    and don't change that date again." 
</p><p>"I protest I never changed it." 
</p><p>"I say you must have done so.  Stick fast to your resolution 
about the boy.  It's best; believe me, it's best.  You'll rejoice a year 
from now    &mdash;    and so will he    &mdash;    that it was done.  Good night, my 
dear." 
</p><p>He is willing to go, but she is possessed with a sorrowful 
passion.  She holds him, appealing with her eyes for that 
intoxicating gaze of his.  Suddenly she pushes him from her, drives 
him with tempestuous laughter from the room, catches his fingers at 
the last and lifts them to her lips, then puts the door between them.  
He hears the bolt shoot, hears something sounding like a sob, pauses 
to rap softly, begging a second's more delirious pain of parting; is 
answered with silence, and, touching the bell, summons the 
drowsing elevator boy. 
</p> 
</div2> 
 
<div2 type="chapter" n="2" id="d5"><head>"CHAPTER II"</head> 
 
 
<p>A beech wood in October.  Beyond, down a sheer bluff, West 
Water, with the sun low.  In the midst of the wood an old house, and 
walking slowly toward it a woman leading a blind child by the 
hand.  The soft pelt of the gold-bright leaves makes only the faintest 
sound. 
</p><p>"Donald, the place looks as if it were enchanted!  It is gold 
everywhere    &mdash;    the beeches, the water, the very air, are gold.  Take 
off your hat, my son.  Mother wants to see your golden head fit into 
the picture." 
</p><p>"It's hard walking through these leaves, isn't it, mother?  
They're up to my knees." 
</p><p>"I never saw them lie so thick.  You're tired, no doubt.  Shall 
we sit down and rest?  Sink right down on the leaves    &mdash;    lie back in 
them.  Isn't that good?  It's a mile through the orchard and along the 
drive, and you've been up since early morning and not had half 
enough to eat!  We ran away home, didn't we?" 
</p><p>"Yes.  What a queer thing it was to do!  What made you do that, 
mother?" 
</p><p>"I was afraid of something." 
</p><p>"Were you?  If you had told me I'd have comforted you." 
</p><p>"You do comfort me    &mdash;    just as much as if I'd told you." 
</p><p>"Oh, do I?  May I put flowers in your lap?  There is a sweet 
smell to your dress    &mdash;    like flowers.  And I like you to pat my face 
like that.  Your hands aren't any larger than mine    &mdash;    not so large!" 
</p><p>"Isn't it still?  There's not a soul in the house!  You ought to 
see how peaceful it looks.  The windows are gold    &mdash;    those toward 
the northwest.  From where I sit, Donald, I can see the door!" 
</p><p>"Can you?  We'll unlock it in a minute, mother." 
</p><p>"It looks as kind as ever." 
</p><p>"What fun it will be to open it!" 
</p><p>"Yes.  And when it is opened this time, I swear it shall never 
be locked again.  Not while we live, Donald.  Some one shall be 
there to answer if any one knocks.  In your father's time, and your 
grand-father's, and your great-grandfather's, it was never locked 
against any one who came.  Great men and beggars came to it, and 
none of them was turned away." 
</p><p>"I never fall when I go in and out of that door.  It's the best old 
door in the world!" 
</p><p>"Yes, it is.  Do you know, I'm going to have teachers come to 
help you grow up a wise, good man." 
</p><p>"But then I'm blind.  I can't do the way other boys do." 
</p><p>"Perhaps you'll do better than others.  You will own miles of 
good land    &mdash;    meadows, pastures, wheatland, orchards, forests.  You 
will have cattle and sheep, horses and fowls.  It will take a good 
man and one who knows a great deal to look after these things.  I 
shall have you taught many things.  Besides, you shall have a great 
deal of pleasure.  I have been 
 
 
<pb n="176"/> 
 
 
thinking all day of ways in which you and I were to have pleasure 
together." 
</p><p>"Mother, I never knew you to be the way you are to-day!" 
</p><p>"Am I different?" 
</p><p>"Yes    &mdash;    oh, yes.  I love you, mother." 
</p><p>"Do you, Donald?  Do you, indeed?" 
</p><p>"If you were always like this, I'd never be cross the way I have 
been." 
</p><p>"I am going to be with you always like this, my son." 
</p><p>The gold grows delicate in the west.  The glimmerings of the 
sun path fade away.  The boy sleeps lightly for a few moments, 
while the woman fixes her eyes upon the door, which seems to 
invite her to enter.  She reaches out her arms as she might to her 
mother.  The tears fall on her cheeks.  She seems to make silent 
confession to the door.  Of all she thinks, but one sentence finds 
utterance: 
</p><p>"I have been bereft of almost everything, but now I have found 
that worth all I lost!"  The soft gloom grows.  The water becomes 
shadowy.  Mystery is abroad in the woods.  The woman rouses the 
boy with a kiss. 
</p><p>"It is growing dark," she says.  "We must go in." 
</p><p>The boy laughs.  He does not mind the darkness.  He makes his 
way up through the leaves to the steps, climbs them gaily and puts 
his hand on the knob. 
</p><p>"It is locked," says his mother, "and the leaves are thick all 
about the threshold."  The boy still laughs.  She gives him the key 
and he puts it in the great lock.  The wide door swings open with a 
friendly sound.  The boy makes his way swiftly through the rooms, 
touching everything with eager hands.  His laughter comes out 
softly, like spring water from the earth.  The woman gropes about in 
the gloom, searching for a light.  After a time a lamp is burning.  
Madeline throws open the windows to admit the mellow air.  The 
darkness has deepened and wraps the old house about like a cloak. 
</p><p>"How curious!" she cries.  "We have orchards and bees and 
cattle, and not a mouthful that we may eat or drink!" 
</p><p>But as she speaks there is a knocking at the door, then a hearty 
voice crying: 
</p><p>"Welcome!  Welcome!  What a surprise!" 
</p><p>Madeline stops in the middle of the floor and stares at the 
farmerlike, capable figure which confronts her.  Her face is flushed, 
her eyes shy like those of a child who has done wrong and is now 
determined to be good. 
</p><p>"It's Carl!" cries the boy.  "It's that Carl Brandenberg." 
</p><p>He gathers the blind boy in his arms and hugs him with rough 
tenderness.  He runs his hands through the boy's hair and pulls at his 
ears. 
</p><p>"Wasn't your home-coming very sudden?" he asks. 
</p><p>"Nothing could have been more sudden," says the woman, 
half-defensively.  "And we are alone    &mdash;    and we've no food." 
</p><p>The man mocks them: "The Camerons of Cameron Meadow 
starving!  The bins empty, the cupboards bare!" 
</p><p>He waves his hand and is gone. 
</p><p>"He will bring us our supper," says the boy, nodding his head 
sagely.  Madeline begins tidying the house.  She spreads the table 
and lays places for three. 
</p><p>"We must have fresh water," she declares, and runs into the 
darkness.  The boy throws himself in his chair by the window and 
rocks back and forth contentedly.  He can hear the lake muttering its 
ancient tale below the cliff; hear the fall of the leaves; hear the soft 
wild noises of birds.  Then, after a time, a mingling of voices in the 
darkness.  He knows that his mother and the farmer are bringing in 
the water cold from the well, the milk warm from the cow, the 
bread, the honey and the fruit.  A sweet home-consciousness steals 
over him, and a breeze, rich with odors of the wood and the night, 
reaches him from the open door. 
</p> 
</div2> 
</div1> 
</body> 
</text> 
</TEI.2> 
