<?xml version="1.0"?>

<?dlps id="PoeColl"?>
<?dlps page-images="none" figure-images="no"?>
<?dlps transcription="other"?>

<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/tei-p4/tei2.dtd" [
<!ENTITY % POSTKB "INCLUDE">
<!ENTITY % TEI.extensions.ent SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.ent">
<!ENTITY % TEI.extensions.dtd SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.dtd">
<!ENTITY % ISOnum SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/charent/iso-num.ent"> %ISOnum;
<!ENTITY % ISOgrk1 SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/charent/iso-grk1.ent"> %ISOgrk1;
<!ENTITY % ISOpub SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/charent/iso-pub.ent"> %ISOpub;

]>

<TEI.2 id="PoeColl"> 
<teiHeader type="migrated" creator="Etext">
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title type="main">The Colloquy of Monos and Una</title>
<title type="sort">colloquy of monos and una</title>
<author>Poe, Edgar Allan, 1809-1849</author>
<respStmt>
<resp>Creation of machine-readable version</resp>
<name>Judy Boss, University of Omaha</name>
</respStmt>
<respStmt>
<resp>Conversion to TEI-conformant markup</resp>
<name>University of Virginia Library Electronic Text Center</name>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt> 
<extent>ca. <num type="kilobytes">26</num> kilobytes</extent> 
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>University of Virginia Library</publisher>
<pubPlace>Charlottesville, Virginia</pubPlace> 
<idno type="ETC">PoeColl</idno> 
<date value="1994">1994</date>
<availability status="public">
<p n="copyright">Copyright &copy; 1994 by the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia</p>
<p n="access">Publicly accessible</p>
</availability>
<idno type="uva-pid">uva-lib:476305</idno>
</publicationStmt>
<seriesStmt>
<title>University of Virginia Library, Text collection</title>
<idno type="uva-set">UVA-LIB-Text</idno>
</seriesStmt> 
<notesStmt>
<note>
<p>First created by Judy Boss; the text then went to Tom Almy's 
Bitter Butter Better BBS, where he removed the pagination, and then to 
The Internet Wiretap.</p>
</note>
</notesStmt> 
<sourceDesc>
<biblFull>
<titleStmt>
<title type="main">Tales of Mystery and Imagination</title>
<title type="sort">tales of mystery and imagination</title>
<author>Edgar Allan Poe</author>
</titleStmt> 
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>J. M. Dent &amp; Sons</publisher> 
<pubPlace>London</pubPlace> 
<date value="1912">1912</date>
</publicationStmt> 
<notesStmt>
<note>
<p>Source copy consulted: Call no. PS 2612 A1 1912, Alderman Library, University of Virginia</p>
</note>
</notesStmt>
</biblFull>
</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc> 
<encodingDesc>
<projectDesc>
<p>Prepared for the University of Virginia Library Electronic Text Center</p>
</projectDesc> 
<editorialDecl>
<p>All unambiguous end-of-line hyphens have been removed, and the 
trailing part of a word has been joined to the preceding line.</p> 
<p id="ETC">Keywords in the header are a local Electronic Text Center scheme 
to aid in establishing analytical groupings</p>
</editorialDecl> 
<refsDecl>
<p>ID elements are given for each page element and are composed of the text's 
unique cryptogram and the given page number, as in SpeFQue1 for page one of 
Spenser's Faerie Queene.</p>
</refsDecl>
</encodingDesc> 
<profileDesc>
<creation>
<date value="1841">1841</date>
</creation> 
<langUsage>
<language id="eng" usage="main">English</language> 
<language id="grc">Greek</language>
</langUsage> 
<textClass>
<keywords>
<term>fiction; prose</term>
</keywords>
</textClass>
</profileDesc> 
<revisionDesc>
<change>
<date value="1994-11">November 1994</date> 
<respStmt>
<resp>corrector</resp>
<name>Kelly Tetterton</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Repaginated because Judy Boss identified the source of the text; 
updated tags and header; greek entity references added to pp. 115, 117, 
118</item>
</change> 
<change>
<date value="1993-07">July 1993</date> 
<respStmt>
<resp>corrector</resp>
<name>Kelly Tetterton</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Minimal TEI tagging; note that this text is from an unknown 
edition, so the text has been paginated to The Complete Works of Edgar 
Allan Poe, ed. by James A. Harrison, vol. 2, New York: Thomas Y. 
Crowell and Company, 1902; unambiguous line-end hyphenation has been 
removed by Internet Wiretap</item>
</change>
<change>
<date value="2007-09">September 2007</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>Migration</resp>
<name>Ethan Gruber, University of Virginia Library</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Converted XML markup from TEI Lite to uva-dl-tei (TEI P4 with local customizations).</item>
</change>
<change>
<date value="2008-01">January 2008</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>Migration</resp>
<name>Greg Murray, University of Virginia Library</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Programmatically updated TEI header markup (but not header content) for minimal compliance with current QA requirements.</item>
</change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader> 
<text id="d1">  
<body id="d2">
<div1 type="story" id="d3">
<head>The Colloquy of Monos and Una</head> 
<pb n="115"/>  

<epigraph>
<q> 
  &Mgr;&egr;&lgr;&lgr;&ogr;&ugr;&tgr;&agr; &tgr;&agr;&ugr;&tgr;&agr;. <lb/> 
                                   SOPHOCLES, <hi rend="italic">Antig.</hi><lb/> 
              'These things are in the near future.' <lb/> 
</q> 
</epigraph> 


<p>UNA.  'Born again?' 
</p><p>MONOS.  Yes, fairest and best beloved Una, 'born again'. 
These were the words upon whose mystical meaning I had so long 
pondered, rejecting the explanation of the priesthood, until 
Death himself resolved for me the secret. 
</p><p>UNA.  Death! 
</p><p>MONOS.  How strangely, sweet Una, you echo my words!  I 
observe, too, a vacillation in your step &mdash; a joyous inquietude in 
your eyes.  You are confused and oppressed by the majestic 
novelty of the Life Eternal.  Yes, it was of Death I spoke.  And 
here how singularly sounds that word which of old was wont to 
bring terror to all hearts &mdash; throwing a mildew upon all pleasures! 
</p><p>UNA.  Ah, Death, the spectre which sate at all feasts.  How 
often, Monos, did we lose ourselves in speculations upon its 
nature!  How mysteriously did it act as a check to human bliss &mdash; 
saying unto it 'thus far, and no farther!'  That earnest mutual 
love, my own Monos, which burned within our bosoms &mdash; how vainly 
did we flatter ourselves, feeling happy in its first upspringing, 
that our happiness would strengthen with its strength!  Alas! as 
it grew, so grew in our hearts the dread of that evil hour which 
was hurrying to separate us for ever!  Thus, in time, it became 
painful to love.  Hate would have been mercy then. 
</p><p>MONOS.  Speak not here of these griefs, dear Una &mdash; mine, mine 
for ever now! 
</p><p>UNA.  But the memory of past sorrow &mdash; is it not present joy? 
I have much to say yet of the things which have been.  Above all, 
I burn to know the incidents of your own passage through the dark 
Valley and Shadow. 
</p><p>MONOS.  And when did the radiant Una ask anything of her 
Monos in vain?  I will be minute in relating all &mdash; but at what 
point shall the weird narrative begin? 
</p><p>UNA.  At what point? 
<pb n="116"/>  
</p><p>MONOS.  You have said. 
</p><p>UNA.  Monos, I comprehend you.  In Death we have both 
learned the propensity of man to define the indefinable.  I will 
not say, then, commence with the moment of life's cessation &mdash; but 
commence with that sad, sad instant when, the fever having 
abandoned you, you sank into a breathless and motionless torpor, 
and I pressed down your pallid eyelids with the passionate 
fingers of love. 
</p><p>MONOS.  One word first, my Una, in regard to man's general 
condition at this epoch.  You will remember that one or two of 
the wise among our forefathers &mdash; wise in fact, although not in the 
world's esteem &mdash; had ventured to doubt the propriety of the term 
'improvement', as applied to the progress of our civilization. 
There were periods in each of the five or six centuries 
immediately preceding our dissolution, when arose some vigorous 
intellect, boldly contending for those principles whose truth 
appears now, to our disenfranchised reason, so utterly obvious &mdash; 
principles which should have taught our race to submit to the 
guidance of the natural laws, rather than attempt their control. 
At long intervals some master-minds appeared, looking upon each 
advance in practical science as a retrogradation in the true 
utility.  Occasionally the poetic intellect &mdash; that intellect which 
we now feel to have been the most exalted of all &mdash; since those 
truths to us were of the most enduring importance could only be 
reached by that <hi rend="italic">analogy</hi> which speaks in proof-tones to the 
imagination alone, and to the unaided reason bears no weight &mdash; 
occasionally did this poetic intellect proceed a step farther in 
the evolving of the vague idea of the philosophic, and find in 
the mystic parable that tells of the tree of knowledge, and of 
its forbidden fruit, death-producing, a distinct intimation that 
knowledge was not meet for man in the infant condition of his 
soul.  And these men, the poets, living and perishing amid the 
scorn of the 'utilitarians' &mdash; of rough pedants, who arrogated to 
themselves a title which could have been properly applied only to 
the scorned &mdash; these men, the poets, ponder piningly, yet not 
unwisely, upon the ancient days when our wants were not more 
simple than our enjoyments were keen &mdash; days when <hi rend="italic">mirth</hi> was a 
word unknown, so solemnly deep-toned was happiness &mdash; holy, august, 
and blissful days, when blue rivers ran undammed, between hills 
unhewn, into far forest solitudes, primeval, odorous, and 
unexplored. 
</p><p>Yet these noble exceptions from the general misrule 
served but to strengthen it by opposition.  Alas! we had fallen upon 
<pb n="117"/>  
the 
most evil of all our evil days.  The great 'movement' &mdash; that was 
the cant term &mdash; went on: a diseased commotion, moral and physical. 
Art &mdash; the Arts &mdash; arose supreme, and, once enthroned, cast chains 
upon the intellect which had elevated them to power.  Man, 
because he could not but acknowledge the majesty of Nature, fell 
into child-ish exultation at his acquired and still-increasing 
dominion over her elements.  Even while he stalked a God in his 
own fancy, an infantine imbecility came over him.  As might be 
supposed from the origin of his disorder, he grew infected with 
system, and with abstraction.  He enwrapped himself in 
generalities.  Among other odd ideas, that of universal equality 
gained ground; and in the face of analogy and of God &mdash; in despite 
of the loud warning voice of the laws of <hi rend="italic">gradation</hi> so visibly 
pervading all things in Earth and Heaven &mdash; wild attempts at an 
omni-prevalent Democracy were made.  Yet this evil sprang 
necessarily from the leading evil &mdash; Knowledge.  Man could not both 
know and succumb.  Meantime huge smoking cities arose, 
innumerable.  Green leaves shrank before the hot breath of 
furnaces.  The fair face of Nature was deformed as with the 
ravages of some loathsome disease.  And methinks, sweet Una, even 
our slumbering sense of the forced and of the far-fetched might 
have arrested us here.  But now it appears that we had worked out 
our own destruction in the perversion of our <hi rend="italic">taste</hi>, or rather 
in the blind neglect of its culture in the schools.  For, in 
truth, it was at this crisis that taste alone &mdash; that faculty 
which, holding a middle position between the pure intellect and 
the moral sense, could never safely have been disregarded &mdash; it was 
now that taste alone could have led us gently back to Beauty, to 
Nature, and to Life.  But alas for the pure contemplative spirit 
and majestic intuition of Plato!  Alas for the       which he 
justly regarded as an all sufficient education for the soul! 
Alas for him and for it! &mdash; since both were most desperately needed 
when both were most entirely forgotten or despised.</p> 
<note n="1" place="foot"><p> 
'It will be hard to discover a better [method of 
education] than that which the experience of so many ages has 
already discovered; and this may be summed up as consisting in 
gymnastics for the body, and <hi rend="italic">music</hi> for the soul.'  &mdash; 
<hi rend="italic">Repub</hi>. lib. 2.  'For this reason is a musical education most 
essential; since it causes Rhythm and Harmony to penetrate most 
intimately into the soul, taking the strongest hold upon it, 
filling it with <hi rend="italic">beauty</hi> and making the man <hi rend="italic">beautiful-minded</hi>. . . .  He will praise and admire <hi rend="italic">the beautiful</hi>: will 
receive it with joy into his soul, will feed upon it, and 
<hi rend="italic">assimilate his own condition with it</hi>'  &mdash; <hi rend="italic">Ibid</hi>. lib. 3.  Music &mgr;&ogr;&ugr;&sgr;&igr;&kgr;&eegr; 
had, however, among the Athenians, a far more comprehensive 
signification than with us.  It included not only the harmonies 
of time and of 
<pb n="118"/>  
tune, but the poetic diction, sentiment and 
creation each in its widest sense.  The study of <hi rend="italic">music</hi> was 
with them in fact, the general cultivation of the taste &mdash; of that 
which recognizes the beautiful &mdash; in contra-distinction from 
reason, which deals only with the true. 
</p></note> 
<p>Pascal, a philosopher whom we both love, has said, how 
truly! &mdash; <hi rend="italic">'que tout notre raisonnement se reduit a ceder au 
sentiment'</hi>; and it is not impossible that the sentiment of the 
natural, had time permitted it, would have regained its old 
ascendancy over the harsh mathematical reason of the schools. 
But this thing was not to be.  Prematurely induced by 
intemperance of knowledge, the old age of the world drew on. 
This the mass of mankind saw not, or, living lustily although 
unhappily, affected not to see.  But, for myself, the Earth's 
records had taught me to look for widest ruin as the price of 
highest civilization.  I had imbibed a prescience of our Fate 
from comparison of China the simple and enduring with Assyria the 
architect, with Egypt the astrologer, with Nubia, more crafty 
than either, the turbulent mother of all Arts.  In the history of 
these regions I met with a ray from the Future.  The individual 
artificialities of the three latter were local diseases of the 
Earth, and in their individual overthrows we had seen local 
remedies applied; but for the infected world at large I could 
anticipate no regeneration save in death.  That man, as a race, 
should not become extinct, I saw that he must be 'born again'. 
</p><p>And now it was, fairest and dearest, that we wrapped our 
spirits daily, in dreams.  Now it was that, in twilight, we 
discoursed of the days to come, when the Art-scarred surface of 
the Earth, having undergone that purification</p> 
<note n="1" place="foot"><p> 
The word '<hi rend="italic">purification</hi>' seems here to be used with 
reference to its root in the Greek  &pgr;&ugr;&rgr;, fire. 
</p></note> 
<p> 
which alone 
could efface its rectangular obscenities, should clothe itself 
anew in the verdure and the mountain-slopes and the smiling 
waters of Paradise, and be rendered at length a fit dwelling-place for man: &mdash; for man the Death-purged &mdash; for man to whose now 
exalted intellect there should be poison in knowledge no more &mdash; 
for the redeemed, regenerated, blissful, and now immortal, but 
still for the <hi rend="italic">material</hi>, man. 
</p><p>UNA.  Well do I remember these conversations, dear Monos; 
but the epoch of the fiery overthrow was not so near at hand as 
we believed, and as the corruption you indicate did surely 
warrant us in believing.  Men lived; and died individually.  You 
yourself sickened, and passed into the grave; and thither your constant 
Una speedily followed you.  And though the century which has 
since elapsed, and whose conclusion brings 
<pb n="119"/>  
us thus together once 
more, tortured our slumbering senses with no impatience of 
duration, yet, my Monos, it was a century still. 
</p><p>MONOS.  Say, rather, a point in the vague infinity. 
Unquestionably it was in the Earth's dotage that I died.  Wearied 
at heart with anxieties which had their origin in the general 
turmoil and decay, I succumbed to the fierce fever.  After some 
few days of pain, and many of dreamy delirium replete with 
ecstasy, the manifestations of which you mistook for pain, while 
I longed but was impotent to undeceive you &mdash; after some days there 
came upon me, as you have said, a breathless and motionless 
torpor, and this was termed <hi rend="italic">Death</hi>, by those who stood around 
me. 
</p><p>Words are vague things.  My condition did not deprive me of 
sentience.  It appeared to me not greatly dissimilar to the 
extreme quiescence of him, who, having slumbered long and 
profoundly, lying motionless and fully prostrate in a midsummer 
noon, begins to steal slowly back into consciousness, through the 
mere sufficiency of his sleep, and without being awakened by 
external disturbances. 
</p><p>I breathed no longer.  The pulses were still.  The heart had 
ceased to beat.  Volition had not departed, but was powerless. 
The senses were unusually active, although eccentrically so &mdash; 
assuming often each others' functions at random.  The taste and 
the smell were inextricably confounded, and became one sentiment, 
abnormal and intense.  The rose-water with which your tenderness 
had moistened my lips to the last, affected me with sweet fancies 
of flowers &mdash; fantastic flowers, far more lovely than any of the 
old Earth, but whose prototypes we have here blooming around us. 
The eyelids, transparent and bloodless, offered no complete 
impediment to vision.  As volition was in abeyance the balls 
could not roll in their sockets &mdash; but all objects within the range 
of the visual hemisphere were seen with more or less distinction; 
the rays which fell upon the external retina, or into the cornea 
of the eye, producing a more vivid effect than those which struck 
the front or anterior surface.  Yet, in the former instance, this 
effect was so far anomalous that I appreciated it only as 
<hi rend="italic">sound</hi> &mdash; sound sweet or discordant as the matters presenting 
themselves at my side were light or dark in shade &mdash; curved or 
angular in outline.  The hearing at the same time, although 
excited in degree, was not irregular in action &mdash; estimating real 
sounds with an extravagance of precision, not less than of 
sensibility.  Touch had undergone a 
<pb n="120"/>  
modification more peculiar. 
Its impressions were tardily received, but pertinaciously 
retained, and resulted always in the highest physical pleasure. 
Thus the pressure of your sweet fingers upon my eyelids, at first 
only recognized through vision, at length, long after their 
removal, filled my whole being with a sensual delight 
immeasurable.  I say with a sensual delight.  <hi rend="italic">All</hi> my 
perceptions were purely sensual.  The materials furnished the 
passive brain by the senses were not in the least degree wrought 
into shape by the deceased understanding.  Of pain there was some 
little; of pleasure there was much; but of moral pain or pleasure 
none at all.  Thus your wild sobs floated into my ear with all 
their mournful cadences, and were appreciated in their every 
variation of sad tone; but they were soft musical sounds and no 
more; they conveyed to the extinct reason no intimation of the 
sorrows which gave them birth; while the large and constant tears 
which fell upon my face, telling the bystanders of a heart which 
broke, thrilled every fibre of my frame with ecstasy alone.  And 
this was in truth the <hi rend="italic">Death</hi> of which these bystanders spoke 
reverently, in low whispers &mdash; you, sweet Una, gaspingly, with loud 
cries. 
</p><p>They attired me for the coffin &mdash; three or four dark figures 
which flitted busily to and fro.  As these crossed the direct 
line of my vision they affected me as <hi rend="italic">forms</hi>; but upon passing 
to my side their images impressed me with the idea of shrieks, 
groans, and other dismal expressions of terror, of horror, or of 
woe.  You alone, habited in a white robe, passed in all 
directions musically about me. 
</p><p>The day waned; and, as its light faded away, I became 
possessed by a vague uneasiness &mdash; an anxiety such as the sleeper 
feels when sad real sounds fall continuously within his ear &mdash; low 
distant bell tones, solemn, at long but equal intervals, and 
commingling with melancholy dreams.  Night arrived; and with its 
shadows a heavy discomfort.  It oppressed my limbs with the 
oppression of some dull weight, and was palpable.  There was also 
a moaning sound, not unlike the distant reverberation of surf, 
but more continuous, which, beginning with the first twilight, 
had grown in strength with the darkness.  Suddenly lights were 
brought into the room, and this reverberation became forthwith 
interrupted into frequent unequal bursts of the same sound, but 
less dreary and less distinct.  The ponderous oppression was in a 
great measure relieved; and, issuing from the flame of each lamp, 
(for there were many,) there flowed unbrokenly into my ears a 
strain of melodious monotone.  And 
<pb n="121"/>  
when now, dear Una, 
approaching the bed upon which I lay outstretched, you sat gently 
by my side, breathing odour from your sweet lips, and pressing 
them upon my brow, there arose tremulously within my bosom, and 
mingling with the merely physical sensations which circumstances 
had called forth, a something akin to sentiment itself &mdash; a feeling 
that, half appreciating, half responded to your earnest love and 
sorrow; but this feeling took no root in the pulseless heart, and 
seemed indeed rather a shadow than a reality, and faded quickly 
away, first into extreme quiescence, and then into a purely 
sensual pleasure as before. 
</p><p>And now, from the wreck and the chaos of the usual senses, 
there appeared to have arisen within me a sixth, all perfect.  In 
its exercise I found a wild delight &mdash; yet a delight still 
physical, inasmuch as the understanding in it had no part. 
Motion in the animal frame had fully ceased.  No muscle quivered; 
no nerve thrilled; no artery throbbed.  But there seemed to have 
sprung up in the brain, <hi rend="italic">that</hi> of which no words could convey 
to the merely human intelligence even an indistinct conception. 
Let me term it a mental pendulous pulsation.  It was the moral 
embodiment of man's abstract idea of <hi rend="italic">Time</hi>.  By the absolute 
equalization of this movement &mdash; or of such as this &mdash; had the cycles 
of the firmamental orbs themselves, been adjusted.  By its aid I 
measured the irregularities of the clock upon the mantel, and of 
the watches of the attendants.  Their tickings came sonorously to 
my ears.  The slightest deviation from the true proportion &mdash; and 
these deviations were omni-prevalent &mdash; affected me just as 
violations of abstract truth are wont, on earth, to affect the 
moral sense.  Although no two of the time-pieces in the chamber 
struck individual seconds accurately together, yet I had no 
difficulty in holding steadily in mind the tones, and the 
respective momentary errors of each.  And this &mdash; this keen, 
perfect, self-existing sentiment of <hi rend="italic">duration</hi> &mdash; this sentiment 
existing (as man could not possibly have conceived it to exist) 
independently of any succession of events &mdash; this idea &mdash; this sixth 
sense, upspringing from the ashes of the rest, was the first 
obvious and certain step of the intemporal soul upon the 
threshold of the temporal Eternity. 
</p><p>It was midnight; and you still sat by my side.  All others 
had departed from the chamber of Death.  They had deposited me in 
the coffin.  The lamps burned flickeringly; for this I knew by 
the tremulousness of the monotonous strains.  But, suddenly these 
strains diminished in distinctness and in volume.  Finally they 
ceased.  The perfume in my nostrils died away. 
<pb n="122"/>  
Forms affected my 
vision no longer.  The oppression of the Darkness uplifted itself 
from my bosom.  A dull shock like that of electricity pervaded my 
frame, and was followed by total loss of the idea of contact. 
All of what man has termed sense was merged in the sole 
consciousness of entity, and in the one abiding sentiment of 
duration.  The mortal body had been at length stricken with the 
hand of the deadly <hi rend="italic">Decay</hi>. 
</p><p>Yet had not all of sentience departed; for the consciousness 
and the sentiment remaining supplied some of its functions by a 
lethargic intuition.  I appreciated the direful change now in 
operation upon the flesh, and as the dreamer is sometimes aware 
of the bodily presence of one who leans over him, so, sweet Una, 
I still dully felt that you sat by my side.  So, too, when the 
noon of the second day came, I was not unconscious of those 
movements which displaced you from my side, which confined me 
within the coffin, which deposited me within the hearse, which 
bore me to the grave, which lowered me within it, which heaped 
heavily the mound upon me, and which thus left me, in blackness 
and corruption, to my sad and solemn slumbers with the worm. 
</p><p>And here, in the prison-house which has few secrets to 
disclose, there rolled away days and weeks and months; and the 
soul watched narrowly each second as it flew, and, without 
effort, took record of its flight &mdash; without effort and without 
object. 
</p><p>A year passed.  The consciousness of <hi rend="italic">being</hi> had grown 
hourly more indistinct, and that of mere <hi rend="italic">locality</hi> had, in 
great measure, usurped its position.  The idea of entity was 
becoming merged in that of <hi rend="italic">place</hi>.  The narrow space 
immediately surrounding what had been the body, was now going to 
be the body itself.  At length, as often happens to the sleepers 
(by sleep and its world alone is <hi rend="italic">Death</hi> imaged) &mdash; at length, as 
sometimes happened on Earth to the deep slumberer, when some 
flitting light half startled him into awaking, yet left him half 
enveloped in dreams &mdash; so to me, in the strict embrace of the 
<hi rend="italic">Shadow</hi> came <hi rend="italic">that</hi> light which alone might have had power to 
startle &mdash; the light of enduring <hi rend="italic">Love</hi>.  Men toiled at the grave 
in which I lay darkling.  They upthrew the damp earth.  Upon my 
mouldering bones there descended the coffin of Una. 
</p><p>And now again all was void.  That nebulous light had been 
extinguished.  That feeble thrill had vibrated itself into 
quiescence.  Many <hi rend="italic">lustra</hi> had supervened.  Dust had returned 
to dust.  The worm had food no more.  The sense of being had 
<pb n="123"/>  
at 
length utterly departed, and there reigned in its stead &mdash; instead 
of all things &mdash; dominant and perpetual &mdash; the autocrats <hi rend="italic">Place</hi> 
and <hi rend="italic">Time</hi>.  For <hi rend="italic">that</hi> which <hi rend="italic">was not</hi> &mdash; for that which 
had no form &mdash; for that which had no thought &mdash; for that which had no 
sentience &mdash; for that which was soulless, yet of which matter 
formed no portion &mdash; for all this nothingness, yet for all this 
immortality, the grave was still a home, and the corrosive hours, 
co-mates. 
</p> 
 
</div1> 
</body> 
</text> 
</TEI.2> 
