<?xml version="1.0"?>

<?dlps id="PoeMell"?>
<?dlps page-images="none" figure-images="no"?>
<?dlps transcription="other"?>

<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/tei-p4/tei2.dtd" [
<!ENTITY % POSTKB "INCLUDE">
<!ENTITY % TEI.extensions.ent SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.ent">
<!ENTITY % TEI.extensions.dtd SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.dtd">
<!ENTITY % ISOnum SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/charent/iso-num.ent"> %ISOnum;
<!ENTITY % ISOpub SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/charent/iso-pub.ent"> %ISOpub;

]>

<TEI.2 id="PoeMell"> 
<teiHeader type="migrated" creator="Etext">
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title type="main">Mellonta Tauta</title>
<title type="sort">mellonta tauta</title>
<author>Poe, Edgar Allan, 1809-1849</author>
<respStmt>
<resp>Creation of machine-readable version</resp>
<name>Judy Boss, University of Omaha</name>
</respStmt>
<respStmt>
<resp>Conversion to TEI-conformant markup</resp>
<name>University of Virginia Library Electronic Text Center</name>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt> 
<extent>ca. <num type="kilobytes">40</num> kilobytes</extent> 
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>University of Virginia Library</publisher>
<pubPlace>Charlottesville, Virginia</pubPlace> 
<idno type="ETC">PoeMell</idno> 
<date value="1994">1994</date>
<availability status="public">
<p n="copyright">Copyright &copy; 1994 by the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia</p>
<p n="access">Publicly accessible</p>
</availability>
<idno type="uva-pid">uva-lib:476315</idno>
</publicationStmt>
<seriesStmt>
<title>University of Virginia Library, Text collection</title>
<idno type="uva-set">UVA-LIB-Text</idno>
</seriesStmt> 
<notesStmt>
<note>
<p>First created by Judy Boss; the text then went to Tom Almy's 
Bitter Butter Better BBS, where he removed the pagination, and then to 
The Internet Wiretap.</p>
</note>
</notesStmt> 
<sourceDesc>
<biblFull>
<titleStmt>
<title type="main">Tales of Mystery and Imagination</title>
<title type="sort">tales of mystery and imagination</title>
<author>Edgar Allan Poe</author>
<respStmt>
<resp>edited by</resp>
<name/>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt> 
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>J. M. Dent &amp; Sons</publisher> 
<pubPlace>London</pubPlace> 
<date value="1912">1912</date>
</publicationStmt> 
<notesStmt>
<note>
<p>Source copy consulted: Call no. PS 2612 A1 1912, Alderman Library, University of Virginia</p>
</note>
</notesStmt>
</biblFull>
</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc> 
<encodingDesc>
<projectDesc>
<p>Prepared for the University of Virginia Library Electronic Text Center</p>
</projectDesc> 
<editorialDecl>
<p>All unambiguous end-of-line hyphens have been removed, and the 
trailing part of a word has been joined to the preceding line.</p> 
<p id="ETC">Keywords in the header are a local Electronic Text Center scheme 
to aid in establishing analytical groupings</p>
</editorialDecl> 
<refsDecl>
<p>ID elements are given for each page element and are composed of the text's 
unique cryptogram and the given page number, as in SpeFQue1 for page one of 
Spenser's Faerie Queene.</p>
</refsDecl>
</encodingDesc> 
<profileDesc>
<creation>
<date value="1849">1849</date>
</creation> 
<langUsage>
<language id="eng" usage="main">English</language>
</langUsage> 
<textClass>
<keywords>
<term>fiction; prose</term>
</keywords>
</textClass>
</profileDesc> 
<revisionDesc>
<change>
<date value="1994-12">December 1994</date> 
<respStmt>
<resp>corrector</resp>
<name>Kelly Tetterton</name>
</respStmt>
<item>repaginated because Judy Boss identified the source of the text; 
updated tags and header</item>
</change> 
<change>
<date value="1993-08">August 1993</date> 
<respStmt>
<resp>corrector</resp>
<name>Kelly Tetterton</name>
</respStmt>
<item>minimal TEI tagging; note that this text is from an unknown 
edition, so the text has been paginated to The Complete Works of Edgar 
Allan Poe, ed. by James A. Harrison, vol. 6, New York: Thomas Y. 
Crowell and Company, 1902; unambiguous line-end hyphenation has been 
removed by Internet Wiretap</item>
</change> 
<change>
<date value="2005-07">July 2005</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>Corrector</resp>
<name>John Ivor Carlson</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Converted SGML to XML and/or corrected tagging.</item>
</change>
<change>
<date value="2007-09">September 2007</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>Migration</resp>
<name>Ethan Gruber, University of Virginia Library</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Converted XML markup from TEI Lite to uva-dl-tei (TEI P4 with local customizations).</item>
</change>
<change>
<date value="2008-01">January 2008</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>Migration</resp>
<name>Greg Murray, University of Virginia Library</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Programmatically updated TEI header markup (but not header content) for minimal compliance with current QA requirements.</item>
</change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader> 
<text id="d1">  
<body id="d2">
<div1 type="story" id="d3"> 
<head>Mellonta Tauta</head> 
<pb n="294"/>  
<epigraph><p>To the Editor of the Lady's Book</p> 
<p>I have the honour of sending you, for your magazine, an article 
which I hope you will be able to comprehend rather more 
distinctly than I do myself.  It is a translation, by my friend 
Martin Van Buren Mavis (sometimes called the 'Poughkeepsie 
Seer'), of an odd-looking MS, which I found, about a year ago, 
tightly corked up in a jug floating in the <hi rend="italic">Mare Tenebrarum</hi> &mdash; a 
sea well described by the Nubian geographer, but seldom visited 
now-a-days, except by the transcendentalists and divers for 
crotchets. &mdash; <lb/>
Very truly,<lb/> 
EDGAR A. POE
</p>
<p>ON BOARD BALLOON 'SKYLARK'<lb/> 
<hi rend="italic">April</hi> 1, 2848<lb/> 
</p> </epigraph>


<p>Now, my dear friend &mdash; now, for your sins, you are to suffer the 
infliction of a long gossiping letter.  I tell you distinctly 
that I am going to punish you for all your impertinences by being 
as tedious, as discursive, as incoherent and as unsatisfactory as 
possible.  Besides, here I am, cooped up in a dirty balloon, with 
some one or two hundred of the <hi rend="italic">canaille</hi>, all bound on a 
<hi rend="italic">pleasure</hi> excursion (what a funny idea some people have of 
pleasure!), and I have no prospect of touching <hi rend="italic">terra firma</hi> 
for a month at least.  Nobody to talk to.  Nothing to do.  When 
one has nothing to do, then is the time to correspond with one's 
friends.  You perceive, then, why it is that I write you this 
letter &mdash; it is on account of my <hi rend="italic">ennui</hi> and your sins. 
</p><p>Get ready your spectacles and make up your mind to be 
annoyed.  I mean to write at you every day during this odious 
voyage. 
</p><p>Heigho! when will any <hi rend="italic">Invention</hi> visit the human 
pericranium?  Are we for ever to be doomed to the thousand 
inconveniences of the balloon?  Will <hi rend="italic">nobody</hi> contrive a more 
expeditious mode of progress?  This jog-trot movement, to my 
thinking, is little less than positive torture.  Upon my word we 
have not made more than a hundred miles the hour since leaving 
home!  The very birds beat us &mdash; at least some of them.  I assure 
you that I do not exaggerate at all.  Our motion, no doubt, seems 
slower than it actually is &mdash; this on account of our having no 
objects about us by which to estimate our velocity, and on 
account of our going <hi rend="italic">with</hi> the wind.  To be sure, whenever we 
meet a balloon we have a chance of perceiving our rate, and then, 
I admit, things do not appear so very bad.  Accustomed as I am to 
this mode of travelling, I cannot get over a kind of giddiness 
<pb n="295"/>  
whenever a balloon passes in a current directly overhead.  It 
always seems to me like an immense bird of prey about to pounce 
upon us and carry us off in its claws.  One went over us this 
morning about sunrise, and so nearly overhead that its drag-rope 
actually brushed the net-work suspending our car, and caused us 
very serious apprehension.  Our captain said that if the material 
of the bag had been the trumpery varnished 'silk' of five hundred 
or a thousand years ago, we should inevitably have been damaged. 
This silk, as he explained it to me, was a fabric composed of the 
entrails of a species of earthworm.  The worm was carefully fed 
on mulberries &mdash; a kind of fruit resembling a watermelon &mdash; and, when 
sufficiently fat, was crushed in a mill.  The paste thus arising 
was called <hi rend="italic">papyrus</hi> in its primary state, and went through a 
variety of processes until it finally became 'silk'.  Singular to 
relate, it was once much admired as an article of <hi rend="italic">female 
dress</hi>!  Balloons were also very generally constructed from it. 
A better kind of material, it appears, was subsequently found in 
the down surrounding the seed-vessels of a plant vulgarly called 
<hi rend="italic">euphorbium</hi>, and at that time botanically termed milkweed. 
This latter kind of silk was designated as silk-buckingham, on 
account of its superior durability, and was usually prepared for 
use by being varnished with a solution of gum caoutchouc &mdash; a 
substance which in some respects must have resembled the <hi rend="italic">gutta 
percha</hi> now in common use.  This caoutchouc was occasionally 
called India rubber or rubber of whist, and was no doubt one of 
the numerous <hi rend="italic">fungi</hi>.  Never tell me again that I am not at 
heart an antiquarian. 
</p><p>Talking of drag-ropes &mdash; our own, it seems, has this moment 
knocked a man overboard from one of the small magnetic propellers 
that swarm in ocean below us &mdash; a boat of about six thousand tons, 
and, from all accounts, shamefully crowded. These diminutive 
barques should be prohibited from carrying more than a definite 
number of passengers.  The man, of course, was not permitted to 
get on board again, and was soon out of sight, he and his life-preserver.  I rejoice, my dear friend, that we live in an age so 
enlightened that no such a thing as an individual is supposed to 
exist.  It is the mass for which the true Humanity cares.  By the 
way, talking of Humanity, do you know that our immortal Wiggins 
is not so original in his views of the Social Condition and so 
forth, as his contemporaries are inclined to suppose?  Pundit 
assures me that the same ideas were put, nearly in the same way, 
about a thousand years ago, by an Irish philosopher called 
Furrier, on account of his keeping a retail 
<pb n="296"/>  
shop for cat-peltries 
and other furs.  Pundit <hi rend="italic">knows</hi>, you know; there can be no 
mistake about it.  How very wonderfully do we see verified, every 
day, the profound observation of the Hindoo Aries Tottle (as 
quoted by Pundit) &mdash; 'Thus must we say that, not once or twice, or 
a few times, but with almost infinite repetitions, the same 
opinions come round in a circle among men.' 
</p><p><hi rend="italic">April</hi> 2. &mdash;   Spoke to-day the magnetic cutter in charge 
of the middle section of the floating telegraph wires.  I learn 
that when this species of telegraph was first put into operation 
by Horse, it was considered quite impossible to convey the wires 
over sea; but now we are at a loss to comprehend where the 
difficulty lay!  So wags the world.  <hi rend="italic">Tempora mutantur</hi> &mdash; excuse 
me for quoting the Etruscan.  What <hi rend="italic">would</hi> we do without the 
Atlantic telegraph?  (Pundit says Atlantic was the ancient 
adjective.)  We lay to a few minutes to ask the cutter some 
questions, and learned, among other glorious news, that civil war 
is raging in Africa, while the plague is doing its good work 
beautifully both in Yurope and Ayesher.  Is it not truly 
remarkable that, before the magnificent light shed upon 
philosophy by Humanity, the world was accustomed to regard War 
and Pestilence as calamities?  Do you know that prayers were 
actually offered up in the ancient temples to the end that these 
<hi rend="italic">evils</hi> (!) might not be visited upon mankind?  Is it not 
really difficult to comprehend upon what principle of interest 
our forefathers acted?  Were they so blind as not to perceive 
that the destruction of a myriad of individuals is only so much 
positive advantage to the mass! 
</p><p><hi rend="italic">April</hi> 3. &mdash;   It is really a very fine amusement to ascend 
the rope-ladder leading to the summit of the balloon-bag and 
thence survey the surrounding world.  From the car below, you 
know, the prospect is not so comprehensive &mdash; you can see little 
vertically.  But seated here (where I write this) in the 
luxuriously-cushioned open piazza of the summit, one can see 
everything that is going on in all directions.  Just now, there 
is quite a crowd of balloons in sight, and they present a very 
animated appearance, while the air is resonant with the hum of so 
many millions of human voices.  I have heard it asserted that 
when Yellow or (as Pundit <hi rend="italic">will</hi> have it) Violet, who is 
supposed to have been the first aeronaut, maintained the 
practicability of traversing the atmosphere in all directions, by 
merely ascending or descending until a favourable current was 
attained, he was scarcely hearkened to at all by his 
contemporaries, who looked upon him as merely an ingenious sort 
of madman, because 
<pb n="297"/>  
the philosophers(?) of the day declared the 
thing impossible.  Really now it does seem to me <hi rend="italic">quite</hi> 
unaccountable how anything so obviously feasible could have 
escaped the sagacity of the ancient <hi rend="italic">savans</hi>.  But in all ages 
the great obstacles to advancement in Art have been opposed by 
the so-called men of science.  To be sure, <hi rend="italic">our</hi> men of science 
are not quite so bigoted as those of old; &mdash; oh, I have something 
<hi rend="italic">so</hi> queer to tell you on this topic.  Do you know that it is 
not more than a thousand years ago since the metaphysicians 
consented to relieve the people of the singular fancy that there 
existed but <hi rend="italic">two possible roads for the attainment of Truth</hi>! 
Believe it if you can!  It appears that long, long ago, in the 
night of Time, there lived a Turkish philosopher (or Hindoo 
possibly) called Aries Tottle.  This person introduced, or at all 
events propagated, what was termed the deductive or <hi rend="italic">a priori</hi> 
mode of investigation.  He started with what he maintained to be 
<hi rend="italic">axioms</hi> or 'self-evident truths', and thence proceeded 
'logically' to results.  His greatest disciples were one Neuclid 
and one Cant.  Well, Aries Tottle flourished supreme until the advent 
of one Hog, surnamed the 'Ettrick Shepherd', who preached 
an entirely different system, which he called the <hi rend="italic">a 
posteriori</hi> or <hi rend="italic">in</hi>ductive.  His plan referred altogether to 
Sensation.  He proceeded by observing, analysing, and classifying 
facts &mdash; <hi rend="italic">instantiae naturae</hi>, as they were affectedly called &mdash; 
into general laws.  Aries Tottle's mode, in a word, was based on 
<hi rend="italic">noumena</hi>; Hog's on <hi rend="italic">phenomena</hi>.  Well, so great was the 
admiration excited by this latter system that, at its first 
introduction, Aries Tottle fell into disrepute; but finally he 
recovered ground, and was permitted to divide the realm of Truth 
with his more modern rival.  The <hi rend="italic">savans</hi> now maintained that 
the Aristotelian and <hi rend="italic">Baconian</hi> roads were the sole possible 
avenues to knowledge.  'Baconian', you must know, was an 
adjective invented as equivalent to Hog-ian and more euphonious 
and dignified. 
</p><p>Now, my dear friend, I do assure you, most positively, that 
I represent this matter fairly, on the soundest authority; and 
you can easily understand how a notion so absurd on its very face 
must have operated to retard the progress of all true knowledge &mdash; 
which makes its advances almost invariably by intuitive bounds. 
The ancient idea confined investigation to <hi rend="italic">crawling</hi>; and for 
hundreds of years so great was the infatuation about Hog 
especially, that a virtual end was put to all thinking properly 
so called.  No man dared utter a truth to which he felt himself 
indebted to his <hi rend="italic">Soul</hi> alone.  It mattered not whether 
<pb n="298"/>  
the 
truth was even <hi rend="italic">demonstrably</hi> a truth, for the bullet-headed 
<hi rend="italic">savans</hi> of the time regarded only <hi rend="italic">the road</hi> by which he had 
attained it.  They would not even <hi rend="italic">look</hi> at the end.  'Let us 
see the means,' they cried, 'the means!'  If, upon investigation 
of the means, it was found to come neither under the category 
Aries (that is to say Ram) nor under the category Hog, why then 
the <hi rend="italic">savans</hi> went no farther, but pronounced the 'theorist' a 
fool, and would have nothing to do with him or his truth. 
</p><p>Now, it cannot be maintained, even that by the crawling 
system the greatest amount of truth would be attained in any long 
series of ages, for the repression of <hi rend="italic">imagination</hi> was an evil 
not to be compensated for by any superior <hi rend="italic">certainty</hi> in the 
ancient modes of investigation.  The error of these Jurmains, 
these Vrinch, these Inglitch, and these Amriccans (the latter, by 
the way, were our own immediate progenitors), was an error quite 
analogous with that of the wiseacre who fancies that he must 
necessarily see an object the better the more closely he holds it 
to his eyes.  These people blinded themselves by details.  When 
they proceeded Hoggishly, their 'facts' were by no means always 
facts &mdash; a matter of little consequence had it not been for 
assuming that they <hi rend="italic">were</hi> facts and must be facts because they 
appeared to be such.  When they proceeded on the path of the Ram, 
their course was scarcely as straight as a ram's horn, for they 
<hi rend="italic">never had</hi> an axiom which was an axiom at all.  They must have 
been very blind not to see this, even in their own day; for even 
in their own day many of the long 'established' axioms had been 
rejected.  For example &mdash; '<hi rend="italic">Ex nihilo nihil fit</hi>'; 'a body cannot 
act where it is not'; 'there cannot exist antipodes'; 'darkness 
cannot come out of light' &mdash; all these, and a dozen other similar 
propositions, formerly admitted without hesitation as axioms, 
were, even at the period of which I speak, seen to be untenable. 
How absurd in these people, then, to persist in putting faith in 
'axioms' as immutable bases of Truth! But even out of the mouths 
of their soundest reasoners it is easy to demonstrate the 
futility, the impalpability of their axioms in general.  Who 
<hi rend="italic">was</hi> the soundest of their logicians?  Let me see!  I will go and 
ask Pundit and be back in a minute. . . .  Ah, here we have it! 
Here is a book written nearly a thousand years ago, and lately 
translated from the Inglitch &mdash; which, by the way, appears to have 
been the rudiment of the Amriccan.  Pundit says it is decidedly 
the cleverest ancient work on its topic, Logic.  The author (who 
was much thought of in his day) was one Miller, or Mill; and 
<pb n="299"/>  
we 
find it recorded of him, as a point of some importance, that he 
had a mill-horse called Bentham.  But let us glance at the 
treatise! 
</p><p>Ah! &mdash; 'Ability or inability to conceive,' said Mr Mill, very 
properly, 'is in no case to be received as a criterion of 
axiomatic truth.'  What <hi rend="italic">modern</hi> in his senses would ever think 
of disputing this truism?  The only wonder with us must be, how 
it happened that Mr Mill conceived it necessary even to hint at 
anything so obvious.  So far good &mdash; but let us turn over another 
page.  What have we here? &mdash; 'Contradictions cannot both be true &mdash; 
that is, cannot co-exist in nature.'  Here Mr Mill means, for 
example, that a tree must be either a tree or not a tree &mdash; that it 
cannot be at the same time a tree and not a tree.  Very well; but 
I ask him <hi rend="italic">why</hi>.  His reply is this &mdash; and never pretends to be 
anything else than this &mdash; 'Because it is impossible to conceive 
that contradictories can both be true.'  But this is no answer at 
all, by his own showing; for has he not just admitted as a truism 
that 'ability or inability to conceive is <hi rend="italic">in no case</hi> to be 
received as a criterion of axiomatic truth'? 
</p><p>Now I do not complain of these ancients so much because 
their logic is, by their own showing, utterly baseless, 
worthless, and fantastic altogether, as because of their pompous 
and imbecile proscription of all <hi rend="italic">other</hi> roads of Truth, of all 
<hi rend="italic">other</hi> means for its attainment than the two preposterous 
paths &mdash; the one of creeping and the one of crawling &mdash; to which they 
have dared to confine the Soul that loves nothing so well as to 
<hi rend="italic">soar</hi>. 
</p><p>By the by, my dear friend, do you not think it would have 
puzzled these ancient dogmaticians to have determined by 
<hi rend="italic">which</hi> of their two roads it was that the most important and most 
sublime of <hi rend="italic">all</hi> their truths was, in effect, attained?  I mean 
the truth of Gravitation.  Newton owed it to Kepler.  Kepler 
admitted that his three laws were <hi rend="italic">guessed at</hi> &mdash; these three 
laws of all laws which led the great Inglitch mathematician to 
his principle, the basis of all physical principle &mdash; to go behind 
which we must enter the Kingdom of Metaphysics.  Kepler guessed &mdash; 
that is to say, <hi rend="italic">imagined</hi>.  He was essentially a 'theorist' &mdash; 
that word now of so much sanctity, formerly an epithet of 
contempt.  Would it not have puzzled these old moles, too, to 
have explained by which of the two 'roads' a cryptographist 
unriddles a cryptograph of more than usual secrecy, or by which 
of the two roads Champollion directed mankind to those enduring 
and almost innumerable truths which resulted from his deciphering 
the Hieroglyphics? 
<pb n="300"/>  
</p><p>One word more on this topic and I will be done boring you. 
Is it not <hi rend="italic">passing</hi> strange that, with their eternal prating 
about <hi rend="italic">roads</hi> to Truth, these bigoted people missed what we now 
so clearly perceive to be the great highway &mdash; that of Consistency? 
Does it not seem singular how they should have failed to deduce 
from the works of God the vital fact that a perfect consistency 
<hi rend="italic">must be</hi> an absolute truth!  How plain has been our progress 
since the late announcement of this proposition!  Investigation 
has been taken out of the hands of the ground-moles and given, as 
a task, to the true and only true thinkers, the men of ardent 
imagination.  These latter <hi rend="italic">theorize</hi>.  Can you not fancy the 
shout of scorn with which my words would be received by our 
progenitors were it possible for them to be now looking over my 
shoulder?  These men, I say, <hi rend="italic">theorize</hi>; and their theories are 
simply corrected, reduced, systematized &mdash; cleared, little by 
little, of their dross of inconsistency &mdash; until, finally, a 
perfect consistency stands apparent which even the most stolid 
admit, because it <hi rend="italic">is</hi> a consistency, to be an absolute and an 
unquestionable <hi rend="italic">truth</hi>. 
</p><p><hi rend="italic">April</hi> 4. &mdash;  The new gas is doing wonders, in conjunction 
with the new improvement with gutta percha.  How very safe, 
commodious, manageable, and in every respect convenient are our 
modern balloons!  Here is an immense one approaching us at the 
rate of at least a hundred and fifty miles an hour.  It seems to 
be crowded with people &mdash; perhaps there are three or four hundred 
passengers &mdash; and yet it soars to an elevation of nearly a mile, 
looking down upon poor us with sovereign contempt.  Still a 
hundred or even two hundred miles an hour is slow travelling, 
after all.  <hi rend="italic">Do</hi> you remember our flight on the railroad across 
the Kanadaw continent? &mdash; fully three hundred miles the hour &mdash; 
<hi rend="italic">that</hi> was travelling.  Nothing to be seen though &mdash; nothing to be 
done but flirt, feast and dance in the magnificent saloons.  Do 
you remember what an odd sensation was experienced when, by 
chance, we caught a glimpse of external objects while the cars 
were in full flight?  Everything seemed unique &mdash; in one mass.  For 
my part, I cannot say but that I preferred the travelling by the 
slow train of a hundred miles the hour.  Here we were permitted 
to have glass windows &mdash; even to have them open &mdash; and something like 
a distinct view of the country was attainable. . . .  Pundit says 
that <hi rend="italic">the route</hi> for the great Kanadaw railroad must have been 
in some measure marked out about nine hundred years ago!  In 
fact, he goes so far as to assert that actual traces of a road 
are still discernible &mdash; traces referable to a period quite as 
remote as that mentioned.  The 
<pb n="301"/>  
track, it appears, was <hi rend="italic">double</hi> 
only; ours, you know, has twelve paths; and three or four new 
ones are in preparation.  The ancient rails were very slight, and 
placed so close together as to be, according to modern notions, 
quite frivolous, if not dangerous in the extreme.  The present 
width of track &mdash; fifty feet &mdash; is considered, indeed, scarcely 
secure enough.  For my part, I make no doubt that a track of some 
sort <hi rend="italic">must</hi> have existed in very remote times, as Pundit 
asserts; for nothing can be clearer, to my mind, than that, at 
some period &mdash; not less than seven centuries ago, certainly &mdash; the 
Northern and Southern Kanadaw continents were <hi rend="italic">united</hi>; the 
Kanawdians, then, would have been driven, by necessity, to a 
great railroad across the continent. 
</p><p><hi rend="italic">April</hi> 5. &mdash;   I am almost devoured by <hi rend="italic">ennui</hi>.  Pundit 
is the only conversible person on board; and he, poor soul! can 
speak of nothing but antiquities.  He has been occupied all the 
day in the attempt to convince me that the ancient Amriccans 
<hi rend="italic">governed themselves</hi>! &mdash; did ever anybody hear of such an 
absurdity? &mdash; that they existed in a sort of every-man-for-himself 
confederacy, after the fashion of the 'prairie dogs' that we read 
of in fable.  He says that they started with the queerest idea 
conceivable, viz.: that all men are born free and equal &mdash; this in 
the very teeth of the laws of <hi rend="italic">gradation</hi> so visibly impressed 
upon all things both in the moral and physical universe.  Every 
man 'voted', as they called it &mdash; that is to say, meddled with 
public affairs &mdash; until, at length, it was discovered that what is 
everybody's business is nobody's, and that the 'Republic' (so the 
absurd thing was called) was without a government at all.  It is 
related, however, that the first circumstance which disturbed, 
very particularly, the self-complacency of the philosophers who 
constructed this 'Republic', was the startling discovery that 
universal suffrage gave opportunity for fraudulent schemes, by 
means of which any desired number of votes might at any time be 
polled, without the possibility of prevention or even detection, 
by any party which should be merely villainous enough not to be 
ashamed of the fraud.  A little reflection upon this discovery 
sufficed to render evident the consequences, which were that 
rascality <hi rend="italic">must</hi> predominate &mdash; in a word, that a republican 
government <hi rend="italic">could</hi> never be anything but a rascally one.  While 
the philosophers, however, were busied in blushing at their 
stupidity in not having foreseen these inevitable evils, and 
intent upon the invention of new theories, the matter was put to 
an abrupt issue by a fellow of the name of <hi rend="italic">Mob</hi>, who took 
everything into his own hands and set up a despotism, in 
comparison with which 
<pb n="302"/>  
those of the fabulous Zeros and Hellofagabaluses 
were respectable and delectable.  This Mob (a 
foreigner, by the by) is said to have been the most odious of all 
men that ever encumbered the earth.  He was a giant in stature &mdash; 
insolent, rapacious, filthy; had the gall of a bullock with the 
heart of an hyena and the brains of a peacock.  He died, at 
length, by dint of his own energies, which exhausted him. 
Nevertheless, he had his uses, as everything has, however vile, 
and taught mankind a lesson which to this day it is in no danger 
of forgetting &mdash; never to run directly contrary to the natural 
analogies.  As for Republicanism, no analogy could be found for 
it upon the face of the earth &mdash; unless we except the case of the 
'prairie dogs', an exception which seems to demonstrate, if 
anything, that democracy is a very admirable form of government &mdash; 
for dogs. 
</p><p><hi rend="italic">April</hi> 6. &mdash;   Last night had a fine view of Alpha Lyrae, 
whose disk, through our captain's spy-glass, subtends an angle of 
half a degree, looking very much as our sun does to the naked eye 
on a misty day.  Alpha Lyrae, although so <hi rend="italic">very</hi> much larger 
than our sun, by the by, resembles him closely as regards its 
spots, its atmosphere, and in many other particulars.  It is only 
within the last century, Pundit tells me, that the binary 
relation existing between these two orbs began even to be 
suspected.  The evident motion of our system in the heavens was 
(strange to say!) referred to an orbit about a prodigious star in 
the centre of the galaxy.  About this star, or at all events in 
the centre of gravity common to all the globes of the Milky Way 
and supposed to be near Alcyone in the Pleiades, every one of 
these globes was declared to be revolving, our own performing the 
circuit in a period of 117,000,000 of years!  <hi rend="italic">We</hi>, with our 
present lights, our vast telescopic improvements, and so forth, 
of course find it difficult to comprehend <hi rend="italic">the ground</hi> of an 
idea such as this.  Its first propagator was one Mudler.  He was 
led, we must presume, to this wild hypothesis by mere analogy in 
the first instance; but, this being the case, he should have at 
least adhered to analogy in its development.  A great central orb 
<hi rend="italic">was</hi>, in fact, suggested: so far Mudler was consistent.  This 
central orb, however, dynamically, should have been greater than 
all its surrounding orbs taken together.  The question might then 
have been asked &mdash; 'Why do we not see it?' &mdash; <hi rend="italic">we</hi>, especially, who 
occupy the mid region of the cluster &mdash; the very locality <hi rend="italic">near</hi> 
which, at least, must be situated this inconceivable central sun. 
The astronomer, perhaps, at this point, took refuge in the 
suggestion of non-luminosity; and here analogy was 
<pb n="303"/>  
suddenly let 
fall.  But even admitting the central orb non-luminous, how did 
he manage to explain its failure to be rendered visible by the 
incalculable host of glorious suns glaring in all directions 
about it?  No doubt what he finally maintained was merely a 
centre of gravity common to all the revolving orbs &mdash; but here 
again analogy must have been let fall.  Our system revolves, it 
is true, about a common centre of gravity, but it does this in 
connection with and in consequence of a material sun whose mass 
more than counterbalances the rest of the system.  The 
mathematical circle is a curve composed of an infinity of 
straight lines; but this idea of the circle &mdash; this idea of it 
which, in regard to all earthly geometry, we consider as merely 
the mathematical, in contra-distinction from the practical, idea &mdash; 
is, in sober fact, the <hi rend="italic">practical</hi> conception which alone we 
have any right to entertain in respect of those Titanic circles 
with which we have to deal, at least in fancy, when we suppose 
our system, with its fellows, revolving about a point in the 
centre of the galaxy.  Let the most vigorous of human 
imaginations but attempt to take a single step towards the 
comprehension of a circuit so unutterable!  It would scarcely be 
paradoxical to say that a flash of lightning itself, travelling 
<hi rend="italic">for ever</hi> upon the circumference of this inconceivable circle, 
would still <hi rend="italic">for ever</hi> be travelling in a straight line.  That 
the path of our sun along such a circumference &mdash; that the 
direction of our system in such an orbit &mdash; would, to any human 
perception, deviate in the slightest degree from a straight line 
even in a million of years, is a proposition not to be 
entertained; and yet these ancient astronomers were absolutely 
cajoled, it appears, into believing that a decisive curvature had 
become apparent during the brief period of their astronomical 
history &mdash; during the mere point &mdash; during the utter nothingness of 
two or three thousand years!  How incomprehensible that 
considerations such as this did not at once indicate to them the 
true state of affairs &mdash; that of the binary revolution of our sun 
and Alpha Lyrae around a common centre of gravity! 
</p><p><hi rend="italic">April</hi> 7. &mdash;   Continued last night our astronomical 
amusements.  Had a fine view of the five Neptunian asteroids, and 
watched with much interest the putting up of a huge impost on a 
couple of lintels in the new temple at Daphnis in the moon.  It 
was amusing to think that creatures so diminutive as the 
lunarians, and bearing so little resemblance to humanity, yet 
evinced a mechanical ingenuity so much superior to our own.  One 
finds it difficult, too, to conceive the vast masses, which these 
people 
<pb n="304"/>  
handle so easily, to be as light as our reason tells us 
they actually are. 
</p><p><hi rend="italic">April</hi> 8. &mdash;   Eureka!  Pundit is in his glory.  A balloon 
from Kanadaw spoke us to-day and threw on board several late 
papers; they contain some exceedingly curious information 
relative to Kanawdian or rather to Amriccan antiquities.  You 
know, I presume, that labourers have for some months been 
employed in preparing the ground for a new fountain at Paradise, 
the emperor's principal pleasure garden.  Paradise, it appears, 
has been, <hi rend="italic">literally</hi> speaking, an island time out of mind &mdash; 
that is to say, its northern boundary was always (as far back as 
any records extend) a rivulet, or rather a very narrow arm of the 
sea.  This arm was gradually widened until it attained its 
present breadth &mdash; a mile.  The whole length of the island is nine 
miles; the breadth varies materially.  The entire area (so Pundit 
says) was, about eight hundred years ago, densely packed with 
houses, some of them twenty storeys high; land (for some most 
unaccountable reason) being considered as especially precious 
just in this vicinity.  The disastrous earthquake, however, of 
the year 2050, so totally uprooted and overwhelmed the town (for 
it was almost too large to be called a village) that the most 
indefatigable of our antiquarians have never yet been able to 
obtain from the site any sufficient date (in the shape of coins, 
medals, or inscriptions) wherewith to build up even the ghost of 
a theory concerning the manners, customs, etc. etc., of the 
aboriginal inhabitants.  Nearly all that we have hitherto known 
of them is, that they were a portion of the Knickerbocker tribe 
of savages infesting the continent at its first discovery by 
Recorder Riker, a knight of the Golden Fleece.  They were by no 
means uncivilized, however, but cultivated various arts and even 
sciences after a fashion of their own.  It is related of them 
that they were acute in many respects, but were oddly afflicted 
with a monomania for building what, in the ancient Amriccan, was 
denominated 'churches' &mdash; a kind of pagoda instituted for the 
worship of two idols that went by the names of Wealth and 
Fashion.  In the end, it is said, the island became, nine-tenths 
of it, church.  The women, too, it appears, were oddly deformed 
by a natural protuberance of the region just below the small of 
the back &mdash; although, most unaccountably, this deformity was looked 
upon altogether in the light of a beauty.  One or two pictures of 
these singular women have, in fact, been miraculously preserved. 
They look very odd, <hi rend="italic">very</hi> &mdash; like something between a turkey-cock and a dromedary. 
<pb n="305"/>  
</p><p>Well, these few details are nearly all that have descended 
to us respecting the ancient Knickerbockers.  It seems, however, 
that while digging in the centre of the emperor's garden (which, 
you know, covers the whole island), some of the workmen unearthed 
a cubical and evidently chiselled block of granite, weighing 
several hundred pounds.  It was in good preservation, having 
received, apparently, little injury from the convulsion which 
entombed it.  On one of its surfaces was a marble slab with (only 
think of it) <hi rend="italic">an inscription &mdash; a legible inscription</hi>.  Pundit 
is in ecstasies.  Upon detaching the slab, a cavity appeared, 
containing a leaden box filled with various coins, a long scroll 
of names, several documents which appear to resemble newspapers, 
with other matters of intense interest to the antiquarian!  There 
can be no doubt that all these are genuine Amriccan relics 
belonging to the tribe called Knickerbocker.  The papers thrown 
on board our balloon are filled with fac-similes of the coins, 
MSS, typography, etc. etc.  I copy for your amusement the 
Knickerbocker inscription on the marble slab: &mdash; 
 
<lb/>         THIS CORNER STONE OF A MONUMENT TO THE 
<lb/>                       MEMORY OF 
<lb/>                   GEORGE WASHINGTON 
<lb/>      WAS LAID WITH APPROPRIATE CEREMONIES ON THE 
<lb/>               19TH DAY OF OCTOBER, 1847, 
<lb/>          THE ANNIVERSARY OF THE SURRENDER OF 
<lb/>                    LORD CORNWALLIS 
<lb/>           TO GENERAL WASHINGTON AT YORKTOWN, 
<lb/>                       A.D. 1781, 
<lb/>               UNDER THE AUSPICES OF THE 
<lb/>         WASHINGTON MONUMENT ASSOCIATION OF THE 
<lb/>                   CITY OF NEW YORK. 
 
</p><p>This, as I give it, is a verbatim translation done by Pundit 
himself, so there <hi rend="italic">can</hi> be no mistake about it.  From the few 
words thus preserved, we glean several important items of 
knowledge, not the least interesting of which is the fact that a 
thousand years ago <hi rend="italic">actual</hi> monuments had fallen into disuse &mdash; 
as was 
<pb n="306"/>  
all very proper &mdash; the people contenting themselves, as we 
do now, with a mere indication of the design to erect a monument 
at some future time; a corner-stone being cautiously laid by 
itself 'solitary and alone' (excuse me for quoting the great 
Amriccan poet Benton!) as a guarantee of the magnanimous 
<hi rend="italic">intention</hi>.  We ascertain, too, very distinctly, from this 
admirable inscription, the how, as well as the where and the 
what, of the great surrender in question.  As to the <hi rend="italic">where</hi>, 
it was Yorktown (wherever that was), and as to the <hi rend="italic">what</hi>, it 
was General Cornwallis (no doubt some wealthy dealer in corn). 
<hi rend="italic">He</hi> was surrendered.  The inscription commemorates the 
surrender of &mdash; what? &mdash; why, 'of Lord Cornwallis'.  The only 
question is, what could the savages wish him surrendered for. 
But when we remember that these savages were undoubtedly 
cannibals, we are led to the conclusion that they intended him 
for sausage.  As to the <hi rend="italic">how</hi> of the surrender, no language 
could be more explicit.  Lord Cornwallis was surrendered (for 
sausage) 'under the auspices of the Washington Monument 
Association' &mdash; no doubt a charitable institution for the 
depositing of cornerstones. &mdash;   But, heaven bless me! what is the 
matter?  Ah! I see &mdash; the balloon has collapsed, and we shall have 
a tumble into the sea.  I have, therefore, only time enough to 
add that, from a hasty inspection of fac-similes of newspapers, 
etc., I find that <hi rend="italic">the</hi> great men in those days among the 
Amriccans were one John, a smith, and one Zacchary, a tailor. 
</p><p>Good-bye, until I see you again.  Whether you ever get this 
letter or not is a point of little importance, as I write 
altogether for my own amusement.  I shall cork the MS up in a 
bottle, however, and throw it into the sea. 
               Yours everlastingly,<lb/> 
                                             PUNDITA<lb/> 
</p> 
 
</div1> 
</body> 
</text> 
</TEI.2> 
