<?xml version="1.0"?>

<?dlps id="PokFutu"?>
<?dlps page-images="none" figure-images="no"?>
<?dlps transcription="other"?>

<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/tei-p4/tei2.dtd" [
<!ENTITY % POSTKB "INCLUDE">
<!ENTITY % TEI.extensions.ent SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.ent">
<!ENTITY % TEI.extensions.dtd SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.dtd">
<!ENTITY % ISOnum SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/charent/iso-num.ent"> %ISOnum;
<!ENTITY % ISOpub SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/charent/iso-pub.ent"> %ISOpub;

]>
 
<TEI.2 id="PokFutu"> 

<teiHeader type="migrated" creator="Etext">
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title type="main">The Future of the Red Man</title>
<title type="sort">future of the red man</title>
<author>Pokagon, Simon</author>
<respStmt>
<resp>Creation of machine-readable version:</resp> 
<name>Judy Boss</name> 
<resp>Conversion to TEI.2-conformant markup:</resp>  
<name>University of Virginia Library Electronic Text Center</name>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt> 
<extent>ca. <num type="kilobytes">34</num> kilobytes</extent> 
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>University of Virginia Library</publisher>
<pubPlace>Charlottesville, Virginia</pubPlace> 
<idno type="ETC">PokFutu</idno> 
<date value="1995">1995</date>
<availability status="public">
<p n="copyright">Copyright &copy; 1995 by the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia</p>
<p n="access">Publicly accessible</p>
</availability>
<idno type="uva-pid">uva-lib:476326</idno>
</publicationStmt>
<seriesStmt>
<title>University of Virginia Library, Text collection</title>
<idno type="uva-set">UVA-LIB-Text</idno>
</seriesStmt> 
<sourceDesc>
<biblFull>
<titleStmt>
<title type="main">The Future of the Red Man</title>
<title type="sort">future of the red man</title>
<author>Simon Pokagon</author>
</titleStmt> 
<publicationStmt> 
<date value="1897-08">August 1897</date>
</publicationStmt> 
<seriesStmt>
<p>23</p>
</seriesStmt> 
<notesStmt>
<note>
<p>Pokagon, Simon.  "The Future of the Red Man."  <hi rend="italic">Forum</hi>  
23 (Aug. 1897): 698-708.</p>
</note>
</notesStmt>
</biblFull>
</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc> 
<encodingDesc>
<projectDesc>
<p>Prepared for the University of Virginia Library Electronic Text Center</p>
</projectDesc> 
<editorialDecl>
<p>All quotation marks retained as data</p> 
<p>All unambiguous end-of-line hyphens have been removed, and the 
trailing part of a word has been joined to the preceding line.</p> 
<p id="ETC">Keywords in the header are a local Electronic Text Center scheme  
to aid in establishing analytical groupings</p>
</editorialDecl> 
<refsDecl>
<p>ID elements are given for each page element and are composed of the text's 
unique cryptogram and the given page number, as in AusEmma1 for page one of  
Jane Austen's Emma.</p>
</refsDecl>
</encodingDesc> 
<profileDesc>
<creation>
<date value="1897-08">August 1897</date>
</creation> 
<langUsage>
<language id="eng" usage="main">English</language>
</langUsage> 
<textClass>
<keywords>
<term>non-fiction; prose</term> 
<term>Native American</term>
</keywords>
</textClass>
</profileDesc> 
<revisionDesc>
<change>
<date value="1995-10">October 1995</date> 
<respStmt>
<resp>corrector</resp> 
<name>Jamie L Spriggs, Electronic Text Center, University of Virginia</name>
</respStmt> 
<item>Added header; Numbered footnotes and moved them to the end of the text; 
Tagged with TEI.2-compatible SGML; Parsed against "teilite" dtd.</item>
</change> 
<change>
<date value="2005-07">July 2005</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>Corrector</resp>
<name>John Ivor Carlson</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Converted SGML to XML and/or corrected tagging.</item>
</change>
<change>
<date value="2007-09">September 2007</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>Migration</resp>
<name>Ethan Gruber, University of Virginia Library</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Converted XML markup from TEI Lite to uva-dl-tei (TEI P4 with local customizations).</item>
</change>
<change>
<date value="2008-01">January 2008</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>Migration</resp>
<name>Greg Murray, University of Virginia Library</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Programmatically updated TEI header markup (but not header content) for minimal compliance with current QA requirements.</item>
</change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader> 
 
<text id="d1">
	<body id="d2">
<div1 type="essay" id="d3"> <pb n="698"/>  
<head>THE FUTURE OF THE RED MAN. </head>
 
<p>OFTEN in the stillness of the night, when all nature seems 
asleep about me, there comes a gentle rapping at the door of my 
heart.  I open it; and a voice inquires, "Pokagon, what of your 
people?  What will their future be?"  My answer is: "Mortal man has 
not the power to draw aside the veil of unborn time to tell the 
future of his race.  That gift belongs to the Divine alone.  But it 
is given to him to closely judge the future by the present and the 
past."  Hence, in order to approximate the future of our race, we 
must consider our natural capabilities and our environments, as 
connected with the dominant race which outnumbers us &mdash; three hundred 
to one &mdash; in this land of our fathers. 
</p><p> First, then, let us carefully consider if Mis-ko-au-ne-ne-og 
(the red man) possesses, or is devoid of, loyalty, sympathy, 
benevolence, and gratitude, &mdash; those heaven-born virtues requisite 
for Christian character and civilization.  But, in doing so, let us 
constantly bear in mind that the character of our people has always 
been published to the world by the dominant race, and that human 
nature is now the same as when Solomon declared that "He that is 
first in his own cause seemeth just; but his neighbor cometh and 
searcheth him."  In our case we have ever stood as dumb to the 
charges brought against us as did the Divine Master before His 
false accusers; hence all charges alleged against us in history 
should be cautiously considered, with Christian charity.  There 
have been, and still are, too many writers who, although they have 
never seen an Indian in their lives, have published tragical 
stories of their treachery and cruelty.  Mothers, for generations 
past, have frightened their children into obedience with that 
dreaded scarecrow, "Look out, or the Injuns will get you!"; 
creating in the infant mind a false prejudice against our race, 
which has given birth to that base slander, "There is no good Injun 
but a dead one."  It is therefore no wonder that we are hated by 
some worse than Satan hates the salvation of human souls. 
</p><p> Let us glance backward to the year 1492.  Columbus and his 
officers and crew are spending their first Christmas on the border-islands of the New World.  It is not a merry, but a sad, Christmas 
to them.  They <pb n="699"/>  stand crowded on the deck of the tiny ship 
"Nina."  Four weeks since, Pinson, with the "Pinta" and her crew, 
deserted the squadron; and last night the flagship, "Santa Maria," 
that had safely borne the Admiral across an unknown sea to a 
strange land, was driven before the gale and stranded near the 
shore of Hispaniola.  Deserted by her crew and left to the mercy of 
the breakers, she lies prostrate on the perilous sands, shivering 
and screaming in the wind like a wounded creature of life 
responsive to every wave that smites her. 
</p><p> It is early morning.  Columbus sends Diego de Arna and Pedro 
Guthene to the great Chief of the Island, telling him of their sad 
disaster, and requesting that he come and help to save their goods 
from being swept into the sea.  The Chief listens with all 
attention to the sad news; his heart is touched; he answers with 
his tears; and orders his people to go at once, with their canoes 
well manned, and help to save the stranger's goods.  He also sends 
one of his servants to the Admiral with a message of sincere 
regrets for his misfortunes, offering all the aid in his power.  
Columbus receives the servant on shipboard; and, while he listens 
with gratitude to the cheering message delivered in signs and 
broken words, he rejoices to see coming to his relief along the 
shore a hundred boats, manned by a thousand men, mostly naked, 
bearing down upon the wrecked "Santa Maria," and swarming about her 
like bees around their hive.  The goods disappear from the ship as 
by magic, are rowed ashore, and safely secured.  Not one native 
takes advantage of the disaster for his own profit.  Spanish 
history declares that in no part of the civilized world could 
Columbus have received warmer or more cordial hospitality. 
</p><p> Touched by such tender treatment, Columbus, writing to the 
King and Queen of Spain, pays this beautiful tribute to the native 
Carib race: &mdash;  
 
</p><p> "They are a loving, uncovetous people, so docile in all things 
that I swear to your Majesties there is not in all the world a 
better race, or more delightful country.  They love their neighbors 
as themselves; their talk is ever sweet and gentle, accompanied 
with smiles; and though they be naked, yet their manners are 
decorous and praiseworthy." 
 
Peter Martyr, a reliable historian, has left on record the 
following: &mdash;  
 
</p><p> "It is certain the land among these people is as common as sun 
and water, and that 'mine and thine,' the seed of all misery, have 
no place with them.  They are content with so little that in so 
large a country they have rather a superfluity than a scarceness, 
so that they seem to live in the golden world, without toil, living 
in open gardens not intrenched or defended with walls.  They 


<pb n="700"/>   

deal justly one with another without books, without laws, 
without judges.  They take him for an evil and mischievous man who 
taketh pleasure in doing hurt to another; and although they delight 
not in superfluities, yet they make provision for the increase of 
such roots whereof they make bread, content with such simple diet 
wherewith health is preserved and disease avoided." &mdash; (PETER MARTYR, 
Decade 1, Book 3.) 
 
Does not this quotation most emphatically show that the red men of 
the New World did originally possess every virtue necessary for 
Christian civilization and enlightenment? 
</p><p> The question is often asked, "What became of the numerous 
Caribs of those islands?  They seemed to have vanished like leaves 
in autumn; for within a few years we find them supplanted by 
foreign slaves.  The noble Bishop Las Casas tells us, in pity, 
"With mine own eyes, I saw kingdoms as full of people as hives are 
of bees; and now, where are they?"  Almost all, he says, have 
perished by the sword and under the lash of cruel Spanish 
taskmasters, in the greedy thirst for gold. 
</p><p> Certain it is that in those days, which tried the souls of the 
Carib race, some fled from the lust and lash of their oppressors by 
sea to the coast of Florida, and reported to the natives there that 
Wau-be-au-ne-ne-og (white men), who fought with Awsh-kon-tay Au-ne-me-kee (thunder and lightning), who were cruel, vindictive, and 
without love, except a thirsty greed for gold, had come from the 
other side of Kons-ke-tchi-saw-me (the ocean) and made slaves of 
Mis-ko-au-ne-ne-og (the red man) of the islands, which was reported 
from tribe to tribe across the continent. 
</p><p> Scarcely a quarter-century passes since the enslavement of the 
Carib race, and Ponce de Leon, a Spanish adventurer, is landing 
from his squadron a large number of persons to colonize the coast 
of Florida.  A few years previously, while in pursuit of the 
fountain of youth, he had been here for the first time, on the day 
of the "Feast of Flowers."  Then, he was kindly received and 
welcomed by the sons of the forest.  Now, as then, the air is 
perfumed with the odor of fruits and flowers; and all on shore 
appears pleasing and inviting.  The Spaniards land, and slowly 
climb the terrace that bounds the sea.  Here they pause, planting 
side by side the Spanish standard and the cross.  But hark!  War-whoops are heard close by.  And there they come, &mdash; long lines of 
savages from the surrounding woods, who, with slings and darts, 
with clubs and stones, fall upon the dreaded Spaniards.  The 
onslaught is terrible.  Many are killed; and Ponce de Leon is 
mortally wounded.  He now begins to realize that among the savage 
hosts are Caribs who have escaped from slavery and death.  He well 
knows the bitter story <pb n="701"/>  of their wrong, and that this bloody 
chastisement is but the returning boomerang of Spanish cruelty.  
They flee from the avengers of blood to the ships.  The report they 
give of the savage attack, on their return to Spain, is so terrible 
that years pass before another attempt is made to colonize the land 
of fruits and flowers. 
</p><p> I deem it unnecessary to explain why these peaceful natives so 
soon became so warlike and vindictive.  Suffice it to say: "Enslave 
a good man and, like the wasp which stings the hand that holds it 
fast, he will make use of all the means which nature has placed in 
his power to regain his liberty."  During the first century of 
American history, many adventurers from different European 
countries sailed along the eastern coast of North America, &mdash; all 
reporting the natives peaceable and kind when not misused. 
</p><p> There was a tradition among our fathers that, before the 
colonization of North America, an armed band of Wau-be-au-ne-ne-og 
(white men), gorgeously clad, came on the war-path from the East, 
reaching the Dakotas, which then extended south as far as the mouth 
of the Arkansas River; that they were vindictive and cruel, 
destroying the natives wherever they went with Awsh-kon-tay Au-ne-me-kee (thunder and lightning).  They were looking for gold, their 
Man-i-to (god), and, not finding him, went down Mi-che-se-pe (the 
great river) and were seen no more.  Those cruel adventurers, who 
came among us by sea and land, must have awakened hatred and 
revenge in the hearts of our fathers, which may have been 
transmitted to their children. 
</p><p> It should be borne in mind that several European Powers 
colonized this continent about the same period, among whom the 
English and French took the lead.  Settlements were mostly made 
along the Atlantic coast, which was then occupied by the Algonquin 
family,<ref target="n1">1</ref> to which my tribe &mdash; the Pottawattamies &mdash; belong: them seem 
to have had a common origin and common language.  For a time the 
two races lived in peace.  The French in Canada seemed naturally to 
assimilate with our people, many of whom received the Catholic 
faith.  In course of time there were many marriages between the two 
races; and we began to look upon the great King of France as our 
invincible sovereign: for we were taught that he was king of all 
kings except the King of Waukwing 
 
<pb n="702"/>  

(heaven).  Their priests were devoted to their work; visiting 
all the tribes of the south and west, followed by French traders, 
planting the cross, the lilies, and the shield side by side.  The 
tribes firmly believed that the land belonged to their great king 
who loved them and would, if necessary, fight their battles for 
them.  With the exception of William Penn,<ref target="n2">2</ref> who settled 
Pennsylvania, the English who colonized the United States did not 
seem to have the tact of the French in their dealings with us.  
They were less liberal with presents, and apparently less united in 
their religious belief.  They were not so successful as the French 
in obtaining native converts; although some good ministers, like 
Roger Williams, did much to unite the races in brotherhood, and 
thereby delayed the final struggle. 
</p><p> Inroads were being continually made into Taw-naw-ke-win (our 
native land); and in seeking new homes we found ourselves invading 
the hunting-grounds of other tribes.  The warlike Iroquois of New 
York would not even allow the eastern tribes to pass through their 
country, &mdash; as a result, our forefathers seemed compelled to make a 
stand against the advance of the incoming race.  In doing so, our 
villages were laid waste with fire, our people slaughtered and 
burned by white warriors who seemed without number for multitude.  
Our fathers finally gave up the contest.  Some, to avoid the 
Iroquois, went West through Canada.  Others went West through 
Pennsylvania, meeting in Indiana, Michigan, and Wisconsin, then 
known as Indian Territory, where we found French priests and 
traders, who gave us a hearty welcome, assuring us that we should 
remain safe with them.  In course of time the English, finding the 
French traders posted along the western frontier, gave them to 
understand that the land they occupied belonged to the English, as 
well as the right to buy fur from the natives.  Hence the so-called 
French and Indian War was inaugurated, in the course of which many 
outrages were committed on the frontiers, &mdash; <hi rend="italic">all of them being 
charged to the Indians</hi>.  During this war a manifold tin box of 
curious make was found in a large village called Wa-gaw-naw-kee-zee, which lay along Lake Michigan, between Little Traverse Bay and 
the Straits of Mackinaw.  The unsuspecting Indians opened it, and 
in the innermost box found a mouldy substance.  Soon after, the 
smallpox &mdash; a disease unknown to our fathers &mdash; broke out among them; 
and O-daw-yo-e-waw Da-dodse-ses (their medicine men) all 
 
<pb n="703"/>  
died.  In fact every one taking the disease died.  Lodge after 
lodge was filled with unburied dead.  The great village was 
entirely depopulated.  Our fathers thought the disease was sent 
among them by the English because the Indians had helped the French 
during that war.  I have passed over the ancient site of this 
village.  Its bounds are clearly marked by second-growth forests, 
which now cover it.  It is fifteen miles long and from one to two 
miles wide. 
</p><p> Almost on the heels of this war, after France had ceded her 
rights to the English, came the Revolutionary war.  Our people had 
just begun to learn that they owed allegiance to the British, who 
had conquered our invincible French King.  They had seen the 
Bourbon flag taken down from the western forts, and replaced by the 
red cross of St. George; and they were compelled to shout, "Long 
live the King, &mdash; King George who rules from the Arctic Ocean to the 
Gulf of Mexico." 
</p><p> We now began selling furs to our new masters; receiving in 
exchange dry-goods and Awsh-kon-tay Ne-besh (fire-water), when we 
were called upon again to take the war-path, to aid our new king in 
subduing his rebellious colonies.  We could not serve two masters 
at the same time; hence remained loyal to our new king, while the 
Iroquois of New York and Canada were divided.  And so it was that 
all the dirty, cruel work of war between the revolutionists and the 
mother country was laid at the door of our people, whose mouths 
were dumb to defend or justify themselves in respect of the 
outrages charged against them.  These outrages were generally 
planned, and frequently executed, by white men, as was, in after 
years, the Mountain Meadow Massacre, of Mormon notoriety, for which 
also we were persecuted and suffered untold disgrace. 
</p><p> I always think of my people in those days as the dog kept by 
the schoolmaster to be whipped whenever a child disobeyed.  During 
the war of 1812 we were again incited through English influence to 
take the war-path.  Proctor, the English general of the Northwest, 
said to our heroic Tecumseh, "Assemble all your warriors together, 
join forces with us, and we will drive the Americans beyond the 
Ohio River, and Michigan shall be yours forever."  Such a promise, 
from so high an authority, awakened all the native energies of our 
being to regain our liberty and homes, for which we had been 
contending against overpowering forces. 
</p><p> The Ottawas and Chippeways of the north, the Pottawattamies 
and Miamies of the south, and other tribes gathered themselves 
together to make the last desperate effort to regain the promised 
land.  In this war <pb n="704"/>  our cause was far more sacred to us than 
was the Americans' to them.  They had drawn the sword in defence of 
<hi rend="italic">one</hi> of their rights; we, for <hi rend="italic">all of ours;</hi>  for our 
very existence, for our native land, and for the graves of our 
fathers, most sacred to our race. 
</p><p> The last engagement in which the confederated Algonquin tribes 
fought the Americans was at the battle of the Thames in Canada, on 
October 5, 1813, where we and the English were defeated by General 
Harrison, and General Tecumseh,<ref target="n3">3</ref> our brave leader, was killed. 
</p><p> After this battle our fathers became fully convinced that the 
small remnant of their tribes must either accept extermination, or 
such terms as their enemy saw fit to give.  So they sued for peace; 
and the American warriors, uplifted by victory, and our Algonquin 
fathers, bowed down by defeat, stood around the grave of the 
hatchet &mdash; buried forever &mdash; and smoked the pipe of peace together. 
</p><p> At one time I felt that our race was doomed to extermination.  
There was an awful unrest among the western tribes who had been 
pushed by the cruel march of civilization into desert places, where 
subsistence was impossible.  Starvation drove many to steal cattle 
from adjacent ranches; and when some of our people were killed by 
the cowboys, their friends were determined to take the war-path.  
I never failed on such occasions to declare most emphatically, "You 
might as well march your warriors into the jaws of an active 
volcano, expecting to shut off its fire and smoke, as to attempt to 
beat back the westward trend of civilization.  You must teach your 
sons everywhere that the war-path will lead them but to the grave." 
 
<pb n="705"/>  
</p><p> Having briefly reviewed some of our past history, the fact 
must be admitted that, when the white men first visited our shores, 
we were kind and confiding; standing before them like a block of 
marble before the sculptor, ready to be shaped into noble manhood.  
Instead of this, we were oftener hacked to pieces and destroyed.  
We further find in our brief review that the contending Powers of 
the Old World, striving for the mastery in the New, took advantage 
of our trustful, confiding natures, placing savage weapons of 
warfare in our hands to aid us in butchering one another. 
</p><p> It is useless to deny the charge, that at times we have been 
goaded to vindictive and cruel acts.  Some of my own tribe, 
however, were soldiers in the Northern army during the civil war.  
Some of them were taken, and held prisoners in the rebel prisons, 
and the cruelty which, according to the tales they tell, was 
witnessed there was never outdone in border warfare with the 
scalping-knife and tomahawk.  And yet I believe that, had the 
Northern people been placed in the South under like circumstances, 
their prisoners of war would have been treated with similar 
cruelty.  It was the result of a <hi rend="italic">desperate</hi> effort to save an 
expiring cause.  I believe there is no reasonable person, well 
grounded in United States history, who will not admit that there 
were ten times as many who perished miserably in Southern prisons 
as have been killed by our people since the discovery of America.  
I recall these facts not to censure, but to show that <hi rend="italic">cruelty 
and revenge are the offspring of war, not of race</hi>, and that 
nature has placed no impassable gulf between us and civilization. 
</p><p> It is claimed that the United States have paid out five 
hundred million dollars in trying to subdue the red man by military 
force.  But now &mdash; thank Heaven! &mdash; through the influence of good men 
and women who have thrown the search-light of the golden rule into 
the great heart of the nation, her policy is changed.  Where 
hundreds of thousands of dollars were paid out annually to fight 
him, like sums are now being paid yearly to educate him in 
citizenship and self-support; that his children may not grow up a 
race of savages to be again fought and again cared for at the 
expense of the nation.  I rejoice in the policy now being pursued.  
If not perfect, it is certainly on the right trail to success. 
</p><p> While a guest at Chicago, during the World's Fair, I spent 
much time at the United States Indian School.  There I met many 
delegations from different governmental schools.  I was 
particularly interested in the delegation from Albuquerque, New 
Mexico, composed <pb n="706"/>  of Navajos, Pinas-Mojaves, Pueblos, and 
others.  With pride I examined the articles which they had made, 
their clean, well-kept writing-books, and listened to their sweet 
vocal and instrumental music.  I then and there said, in my heart: 
"Thanks to the Great Spirit, I do believe the remnant of our race 
will yet live and learn to compete with the dominant race; proving 
themselves worthy of the highest offices in the gift of a free 
people." 
</p><p> The Indian school at Carlisle, Pennsylvania, has done wonders 
in showing what can be effected for the education of our children.  
The test there made is a reliable one, inasmuch as that school is 
made up of pupils from more than sixty different tribes, from all 
parts of the United States.  I was highly gratified a few months 
ago to learn that the football team from that school was able to 
defeat the champion Wisconsin team at Chicago, receiving many 
compliments from the immense crowd for their tact and self-control 
as well as for their physical development, &mdash; showing conclusively 
that our race is not, as some claim, becoming enfeebled and running 
out. 
</p><p> While I most heartily indorse the present policy of the 
Government in dealing with our people, I must admit &mdash; to be true to 
my own convictions &mdash; that I am worried over the ration system, under 
which so many of our people are being fed on the reservations.  I 
greatly fear it may eventually vagabondize many of them beyond 
redemption.  It permits the gathering of lazy, immoral white men of 
the worst stamp, who spend their time in idleness and in corrupting 
Indian morality.  I do hope the Government will provide something 
for them to do for their own good, although it should pay her 
little or nothing.  Again: I fear for the outcome of the Indian 
nations.  Our people in their native state were not avaricious.  
They were on a common level; and, like the osprey that divides her 
last fish with her young, so they acted toward each other.  But I 
find, to my sorrow, that, when you associate them with squaw men, 
and place them in power, they develop the wolfish greed of 
civilization, disregarding the rights of their less fortunate 
brothers.  I must admit that it staggers my native brain to 
understand what reason, equity, or justice there is in allowing 
independent powers to exist within the bounds of this Republic.  If 
the "Monroe doctrine," which has been so much petted of late years, 
should be enforced anywhere, it would certainly be in the line of 
good statesmanship to carry it out, at least in principle, at home. 
</p><p> Lastly, Pokagon must admit that he feels very deeply the 
ravages made among his people by the "intoxicating cup."  Were it 
an open <pb n="707"/>  enemy outside our lines, we might meet it with 
success.  But alas! it is a traitor within our camp, cunning as Wa-goosh (the fox).  It embraces and kisses but to poison like the 
snake &mdash; without the warning rattle.  Before I associated with white 
men, I had supposed that they were not such slaves to that soulless 
tyrant as the red man.  But I have learned that the cruel curse 
enslaves alike the white man in his palace and the red man in his 
hut; alike the chieftain and the king; the savage and the sage.  I 
am indeed puzzled to understand how it is that the white race, 
whose works seem almost divine, should not be able to destroy this 
great devil-fish, which their own hands have fashioned and launched 
upon the sea of human life; whose tentacles reach out into the 
halls of legislature and courts of law, into colleges and 
churches, &mdash; doing everywhere its wicked work. 
</p><p> As to the future of our race, it seems to me almost certain 
that in time it will lose its identity by amalgamation with the 
dominant race.  No matter how distasteful it may seem to us, we are 
compelled to consider it as a probable result.  Sensitive white 
people can console themselves, however, with the fact, that there 
are to-day in the United States thousands of men and women of high 
social standing whose forefathers on one side were full-blooded so-called savages; and yet the society in which they move, and in many 
cases they themselves, are ignorant of the fact.  All white people 
are not ashamed of Indian blood; in fact, a few are proud of it. 
</p><p> At the World's Fair on Chicago Day, after ringing the new 
Liberty Bell, and speaking in behalf of my people, I presented 
Mayor Harrison, according to the programme of the day, with a 
duplicate of the treaty by which my father, a Pottawattamie chief, 
in 1833, conveyed Chicago &mdash; embracing the fair-grounds and 
surrounding country &mdash; to the United States for about three cents per 
acre.  In accepting the treaty, the venerable Mayor said: "grateful 
to the spirit of the past, I am happy to receive this gift from the 
hand of one who is able to bestow it.  Chicago is proving that it 
recognizes the benefits conferred through this treaty.  I receive 
this from an Indian all the more gratefully because in my own veins 
courses the blood of an Indian.  Before the days of Pokagon, I had 
my origin in the blood that ran through Pocahontas.  I stand to-day 
as a living witness that the Indian is worth something in this 
world."<ref target="n4">4</ref> 
 
<pb n="708"/>  
</p><p> I have made diligent inquiries of the headmen of different 
tribes as to what estimate they place on the half-breeds among 
them.  Their general reply has been, "They are certainly an 
improvement on the pale face, but not on the red man."  Which no 
doubt is the case; for it is a lamentable fact that criminals, 
outlaws, and vagabonds are generally the first who seek homes among 
us, bringing with them nearly all the vices and diseases, and but 
few of the virtues, of civilization.  Yet, notwithstanding such an 
unfortunate mixture, we find some grand characters who have been 
able to rise high above the sins of parentage.  I have further 
found, by close observation, that those tinctured with our blood 
are far less subject to nervous diseases; but whether at the 
expense of intellectual force or otherwise, I am not so certain.  
Be that as it may, we cannot safely ignore the fact, that it is the 
physical development of the people of a nation that gives it 
strength and stability; that physical decay brings loss of 
executive ability, and has proved the overthrow of ancient 
kingdoms.  I do not wish it to be understood that I advocate or 
desire the amalgamation of our people with the white race.  But I 
speak of it as an event that is almost certain; and we had much 
better rock with the boat that oars us on than fight against the 
inevitable.  I am frequently asked, "Pokagon, do you believe that 
the white man and the red man were originally of one blood?"  My 
reply has been: "I do not know.  But from the present outlook, they 
surely will be." 
</p><p> The index-finger of the past and present is pointing to the 
future, showing most conclusively that by the middle of the next 
century all Indian reservations and tribal relations will have 
passed away.  Then our people will begin to scatter; and the result 
will be a general mixing up of the races.  Through intermarriage 
the blood of our people, like the waters that flow into the great 
ocean, will be forever lost in the dominant race; and generations 
yet unborn will read in history of the red men of the forest, and 
inquire, "Where are they?"</p> 
<signed>                              SIMON POKAGON.</signed> 
</div1> 
</body>

<back id="d4"> 
<div1 type="notes" id="d5">
<note id="n1"><seg type="note-symbol">It</seg> <p>is estimated that at the beginning of the seventeenth 
century the Algonquins numbered at least 250,000.  Their survivors 
number probably not more than 30,000.  Originally they occupied 
nearly all that portion of Canada and the United States lying west 
of the Mississippi River.  They suffered more from advancing 
civilization than all the other tribes.</p></note> 
<note id="n2"><seg type="note-symbol">It</seg> <p>is said that the treaty made by William Penn with the 
Indians was the only treaty never sworn to and never broken, and 
that during seventy years not a war-whoop was sounded in 
Pennsylvania.</p></note> 
<note id="n3"><seg type="note-symbol">At</seg> <p>the time of this battle, Tecumseh was a brigadier-general in the English army, with Proctor.  I have seen in United 
States histories pictures of Tecumseh, tomahawk in hand about to 
strike a soldier named Johnson, who claimed that he shot the 
dreaded chief with his pistol.  But I have repeatedly heard old 
Indian warriors say: "After the British infantry gave way, they 
came to an open or clear spot in the woods, and here Tecumseh 
ordered his men to halt and fight the Americans once more.  Just 
then the open space was swept by American musketry; and Tecumseh 
fell, saying, 'Me-daw-yo-em o-kawd (My leg is shot off).  Hand me 
two loaded guns.  I will have the last shot.  Maw-tchawn'we-wib (Be 
quick and go).'  These were the last words of Tecumseh."  Our 
fathers believed that neither the Americans nor the Indians knew 
who fired the fatal shot. 
</p><p>
My father, Leopold Pokagon, had been a Pottawattamie chief 
thirteen years before this battle, and so remained until his death, 
twenty-seven years after.  Most of his band were sent West in 1837.  
He and some five hundred of his people, having embraced 
Christianity, were permitted to remain in Michigan.  In 1866, they 
numbered three hundred and fifty: nearly all were of pure Indian 
blood.  At the present time, they number two hundred and seventy-one: nearly one-half are of mixed blood.</p></note> 
<note id="n4"><seg type="note-symbol">Certain</seg> <p>it is that the families of Harrison, Rolings, 
Rogers, and many others tinctured with the Indian blood of 
Pocahontas are superior in health to, and fully as strong 
intellectually and morally as, those families from the same branch 
of pure white blood.  John Randolph of Roanoke, a near descendant of 
this Indian woman, and strongly marked with our race lines, was 
several times Congressman from Virginia, once United States 
Senator, and minister to Russia.  In his time his speeches were 
more read than any others.  His masterly arguments were the pride 
of his party and the terror of his opponents.</p></note> 

</div1> 
</back>
</text> 
</TEI.2> 
