<?xml version="1.0"?>

<?dlps id="PopRace"?>
<?dlps page-images="none" figure-images="no"?>
<?dlps transcription="other"?>

<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/tei-p4/tei2.dtd" [
<!ENTITY % POSTKB "INCLUDE">
<!ENTITY % TEI.extensions.ent SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.ent">
<!ENTITY % TEI.extensions.dtd SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.dtd">
<!ENTITY % ISOnum SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/charent/iso-num.ent"> %ISOnum;
<!ENTITY % ISOpub SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/charent/iso-pub.ent"> %ISOpub;
]> 
 
<TEI.2 id="PopRace"> 
<teiHeader type="migrated" creator="Etext">
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title type="main">"The North American Indian&mdash;The Disappearance of the Race A 
Popular Fallacy"</title>
<title type="sort">the north american indian&mdash;the disappearance of the race a popular fallacy</title>
<author>Pope, J. Worden</author>
<respStmt>
<resp>Creation of machine-readable version:</resp> 
<name>Judy Boss</name> 
<resp>Conversion to TEI.2-conformant markup:</resp>  
<name>Jennifer Hanna, University of Virginia Library Electronic Text 
Center</name>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt> 
<extent>ca. <num type="kilobytes">47</num> kilobytes</extent> 
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>University of Virginia Library</publisher>
<pubPlace>Charlottesville, Virginia</pubPlace> 
<idno type="ETC">PopRace</idno> 
<date value="1995">1995</date>
<availability status="public">
<p n="copyright">Copyright &copy; 1995 by the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia</p>
<p n="access">Publicly accessible</p>
</availability>
<idno type="uva-pid">uva-lib:476328</idno>
</publicationStmt>
<seriesStmt>
<title>University of Virginia Library, Text collection</title>
<idno type="uva-set">UVA-LIB-Text</idno>
</seriesStmt> 
<notesStmt>
<note>
<p>This article appeared in <hi rend="italic">The Arena</hi> 16 (Nov. 1896): 945-959.</p>
</note> 
<note>
<p>UVa. Library call number: AP 2 .A6</p>
</note>
</notesStmt> 
<sourceDesc>
<biblFull>
<titleStmt>
<title type="main">"The North American Indian&mdash;The Disappearance of the Race A Popular Fallacy</title>
<title>
<hi rend="italic">The Arena</hi> 16 (Nov. 1896)</title>
<title type="sort">the north american indian&mdash;the disappearance of the race a popular fallacy</title>
<author>J. Worden Pope</author>
</titleStmt> 
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>Arena Publishing Co.</publisher> 
<pubPlace>Boston, MA</pubPlace> 
<date value="1896-11">November, 1896</date>
</publicationStmt> 
</biblFull>
</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc> 
<encodingDesc>
<projectDesc>
<p>Prepared for the University of Virginia Library Electronic Text Center</p>
</projectDesc> 
<editorialDecl>
<p>All quotation marks retained as data</p> 
<p>All unambiguous end-of-line hyphens have been removed, and the 
trailing part of a word has been joined to the preceding line.</p> 
<p id="ETC">Keywords in the header are a local Electronic Text Center scheme  
to aid in establishing analytical groupings</p>
</editorialDecl> 
<refsDecl>
<p>ID elements are given for each page element and are composed of the text's 
unique cryptogram and the given page number, as in AusEmma1 for page one of  
Jane Austen's Emma.</p>
</refsDecl>
</encodingDesc> 
<profileDesc>
<creation>
<date value="1896-11">November, 1896</date>
</creation> 
<langUsage>
<language id="eng" usage="main">English</language>
</langUsage> 
<textClass>
<keywords>
<term>non-fiction; prose</term> 
<term>Native American</term>
</keywords>
</textClass>
</profileDesc> 
<revisionDesc>
<change>
<date value="1995-11-27">November 27, 1995</date> 
<respStmt>
<resp>corrector</resp> 
<name>Jennifer Hanna</name>
</respStmt> 
<item>Added TEI compatible header and tags.</item>
</change> 
<change>
<date value="2005-07">July 2005</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>Corrector</resp>
<name>John Ivor Carlson</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Converted SGML to XML and/or corrected tagging.</item>
</change>
<change>
<date value="2007-09">September 2007</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>Migration</resp>
<name>Ethan Gruber, University of Virginia Library</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Converted XML markup from TEI Lite to uva-dl-tei (TEI P4 with local customizations).</item>
</change>
<change>
<date value="2008-01">January 2008</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>Migration</resp>
<name>Greg Murray, University of Virginia Library</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Programmatically updated TEI header markup (but not header content) for minimal compliance with current QA requirements.</item>
</change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader> 
 
<text id="d1">  
<body id="d2"> 
<div1 type="essay" id="d3"> <pb n="945"/>  
<head> 
THE NORTH AMERICAN INDIAN&mdash;THE DISAPPEARANCE<lb/> 
OF THE RACE A POPULAR<lb/> 
FALLACY.<lb/> 
&mdash;<lb/> 
BY J. WORDEN POPE, U. S. ARMY.<lb/> 
&mdash; 
</head> 
 
<p>There undoubtedly exists a deeply-rooted conviction, supposed 
to rest upon a firm historical basis, that the race of North 
American Indians is rapidly disappearing before the advance of 
civilization; and this conviction, coupled with the twin conception 
that the noble red man has been the victim of the abuse of the 
European conqueror, has long formed a theme for the writers of 
poetry, romance, and history.  For so many generations has this 
theme formed part of the traditions of our race, and so firm a hold 
has it taken upon the imagination, the sympathy, and the sentiments 
of the populace, that any attempt to dislodge it would doubtless be 
regarded with complete incredulity, and any data adduced to 
disprove the belief would be disbelieved as absurd by the average 
well-read American.  To assert, therefore, that there is no proof 
to sustain the popular belief, that on the contrary there is reason 
to doubt that the Indian race has materially diminished, would be 
considered by such persons simply as an iconoclastic attempt to 
subvert the basal facts of history.  It may therefore be startling, 
but it is true, not only that there exists no substantial proof 
that the red man is disappearing before the encroachments of 
civilization, but that many solid facts indicate that there has 
been no material diminution of the Indian population, or at least 
in the quantity of Indian blood, within the historic period. 
</p><p>Were this regarded a moot question, it would require that the 
burden of proof should fall upon those asserting a decrease in 
population under improved conditions of food supply; but as such a 
status of the question had passed long before the existence of the 
present generation, it will be necessary to marshal a formidable 
array of evidence in favor of the opposing view, and this article 
is penned with the intention, in the interest of historic truth, of 
presenting <pb n="946"/>  some of this evidence, with various reasons for 
disbelieving the imaginary dying out of the American aborigines. 
</p><p>The reasons for the belief in the lessening of the Indian 
population certainly seem to rest upon a substantial basis so long 
as the statistics are not critically examined, and numerous 
authorities might be quoted in its favor.  For instance, the 
Encyclopaedia Britannica says: 
 
</p><p>At the date of the European settlement in the American 
Continent, the Indian population of the present area of the United 
States was variously estimated, and as low as 1,000,000.  In Mr. 
Jefferson's time, it was thought that there were 600,000 to 
1,000,000.  In 1822 Rev. J. D. Morse estimated them at 471,136.  In 
1832 Drake placed the number at 313,000, and in 1840 at 400,000.  
In 1855 the Commissioner of Indian Affairs reported 350,000 then in 
the United States; 306,475 in 1866.  By the census of 1870 there 
were 383,577, and by that of 1880, 255,938.  In 1887 the 
Commissioner of Indian Affairs estimated the number at 247,761.  
The conclusion is that the Indians are gradually decreasing in 
numbers.  For the last eighteen years the average decrease of the 
"civilized" or "partially civilized" Indians has been a little less 
than 2,000 a year.  The number of Indians in Canada at the present 
time is estimated at 130,000. 
 
</p><p>Again, "Ballaert estimated the number existing in 1863 as 
follows: United States, 500,000."  Such views are also held by 
Catlin, Hubert Bancroft, Baron de la Hontan, and Bartram. 
</p><p>Despite such authorities, it must be evident, in the first 
place, that any estimate of the early Indian population must have 
been based upon very flimsy evidence, no census being possible of 
a wild population scattered over a vast unknown and largely 
unvisited region, inhabited by scattered bands of roaving savage 
tribes&mdash;mere guesswork, in truth, complicated by the invariable 
tendency to exaggerate numbers. 
</p><p>If there is thus reason to doubt the accuracy of the estimates 
of writers on the numbers of Indians inhabiting the territory of 
the United States in early times, there are more substantial 
reasons for doubting the enumerations of the Indian population 
previous to recent really accurate censuses, say from 1886.  Much 
gross exaggeration is known to exist in these reports by reason of 
the direct pecuniary gain accruing to Indian agents from 
multiplying numbers.  The supplies so much coveted by these agents 
depended largely upon the number of individuals returned, and it is 
well established that many corrupt agents rapidly enriched 
themselves by exaggerations in the enumerations of their charges 
and pocketing the proceeds.  These causes undoubtedly made the 
enumerations of Indian tribes entirely unreliable, and are 
sufficient to account for the supposed decrease <pb n="947"/>  within 
recent years, especially as the estimates vary in so unaccountable 
a manner at short intervals.  The following are the estimates of 
the Indian Bureau for most of the years from 1860 to 1886:</p> 
 
<list> 
<item>1860......250,300     1872......265,900     1880......256,127</item> 
<item>1864......294,574     1873......295,084     1881......261,851</item> 
<item>1865......294,574     1874......275,003     1882......259,632</item> 
<item>1866......295,774     1875......305,068     1883......265,565</item> 
<item>1867......295,899     1876......291,151     1884......264,369</item> 
<item>1869......289,778     1877......250,882     1885......259,244</item> 
<item>1870......313,371     1878......250,864     1886......247,761</item> 
<item>1871......350,000     1879......252,897</item> 
</list> 
 
<p>As the census of 1890 shows 250,483, it would indicate that the 
Indian population, after so many strange oscillations, had returned 
nearly to that of 1860. 
</p><p>Recurring to the early estimates of the numbers of Indians, it 
must appear marvellous to any one acquainted with the mode of life 
of the various tribes subsisting chiefly by hunting and fishing, 
with their constant and destructive warfare, tending to the 
extermination or decimation of weaker tribes, with their roving 
life over vast tracts of territory, with the difficulty of raising 
and maintaining large families&mdash;it must appear strange indeed that 
even so vast a territory as that of the United States could support 
the large numbers of savages estimated by early writers, rising 
above the million mark. 
</p><p>The chief reason which causes the persistence of the notion of 
the decrease of Indians in modern times, and prevents proper 
inspection into the accounts of early writers, is the enormously 
rapid increase of the whites upon this continent, which makes the 
large numbers of Indians estimated seem insignificant in 
proportion.  The knowledge that not only most of the states, but 
even several cities, contain more population than the total of the 
highest estimated number of Indians in the United States 
territories, makes even such largely exaggerated numbers seem 
reasonable, and reasoning is always largely, though unconsciously, 
affected by such comparisons. 
</p><p>Again, it would appear extraordinary that the small early 
settlements of whites could have maintained themselves against the 
large numbers of predatory savages trained throughout life to 
warfare had their numbers been equal to the lowest estimates of 
numbers which early writers ascribe to the Indians.  The acceptance 
of such exaggerations by our early forefathers may not unfairly be 
accredited to the tribute that such numbers would pay to their 
prowess in overcoming them.  It is doubtless true that should one 
ac-<pb n="948"/> cept without the classic grain of salt the accounts of 
the numberless Indians killed in early combats, the numbers of 
Indians must be acknowledged to be fairly estimated at many 
hundreds of thousands; but if human nature has not greatly altered, 
a large allowance must be made in these accounts for the boastful 
disposition to exaggerate the savage forces overcome, common to all 
warriors, especially of the unorganized class of our forefathers.  
Had the numbers of Indians been so large, is it possible that the 
few followers of Daniel Boone would have been able to wrest the 
fair lands of Kentucky from such formidable and numerous foes? 
</p><p>To the readers of Parkman, the most careful of American 
historians, it would certainly appear strange that such small bands 
as he describes should be scattered over so vast an area had the 
Indian population amounted to so large numbers as were generally 
estimated. 
</p><p>After the numbers of eastern tribes became comparatively well 
known, the upholders of the theories of exaggerated numbers of 
Indians found a vast unknown field in the boundless plains of the 
western territories in which to plant numerous hordes of savages; 
but here Lewis and Clark and other travellers found only 
comparatively small, scattered bands roaming over endless wastes, 
leaving small basis for the work of the ever active imagination.  
With the exception of the Sioux, which tribe are and have always 
been comparatively numerous, few Western tribes attained to any 
significant numbers. 
</p><p>When any one calls for proof of the large numbers of Indians 
claimed to people this land and the reason for such large decrease 
as is alleged, he is usually met by statements of the decimation of 
Indians caused by smallpox, ardent spirits, and other evils 
introduced by the whites, attributing to these causes the large 
increase of the death-rate.  It will be vain to look for any proof 
of any such effects produced by the whites.  With the exception of 
the Canadian Indians of the Huron tribe, some 20,000, described by 
Parkman as becoming exterminated through the combined effects of 
smallpox and the warfare of the terrible Iroquois, no statistics 
are forthcoming to prove that the whites have been responsible for 
any large decimation of the Indian race.  According to Col. Garrick 
Mallory, part of these Hurons survive under the name of Wyandots. 
</p><p>The writer was first led to a doubt of the accepted theory of 
the decimation of the Indian race by seeing the remarkable increase 
among the Sioux and Cheyenne Indian prisoners held at Fort Keogh in 
1878, where these Indians came <pb n="949"/>  under the direct charge of 
the government.  The frequent marriages of young Indians, the rapid 
increase in the number of children, and the small death-rate, told 
very decidedly against the notion of their decimation through the 
agency of the whites, and an examination into the birth and death 
rates reported by the Indian Department made the dying out theory 
equally anomalous.  Take the following birth and death rates, as 
given by the Indian Bureau from 1874 to 1886, thirteen of the 
eighteen years included in the estimate of the Encyclopaedia 
Britannica:</p> 
<list> 
<item>                                    Births.  Deaths.  Increase.</item> 
<item>1874............................    2,152    1,490        662</item> 
<item>1875............................    1,889    1,601        388</item> 
<item>1876............................    2,401    2,215        186</item> 
<item>1877............................    3,442    2,781        661</item> 
<item>1878............................    2,941    2,219        722</item> 
<item>1879............................    2,352    2,025        327</item> 
<item>1880............................    3,430    2,020      1,410</item> 
<item>1881............................    2,339    1,989        350</item> 
<item>1882............................    2,998    2,478        520</item> 
<item>1883............................    4,751    4,508        243</item> 
<item>1884............................    4,069    3,787        282</item> 
<item>1885............................    4,145    3,754        391</item> 
<item>1886............................    4,419    3,929        490</item> 
</list> 
 
<p>Meeting an old gentleman who had passed his life chiefly as a 
missionary among the Indians, from New York west to the Rocky 
Mountains, and stating the idea that it seemed in the probabilities 
that the Indians should have increased rather than diminished, the 
old gentleman unhesitatingly affirmed that his knowledge led him to 
believe in an increase rather than a loss in Indian population.  
This man knew a large percentage of the individual Indians among 
all the tribes from New York, where he began his vocation, to the 
Rocky Mountains, where he promised to end his existence among Sioux 
and Northern Cheyennes.  With these ideas growing up, chance placed 
in the hands of the writer a newspaper account of an estimate of 
Indians compiled from the Notes of Thomas Jefferson, which of 
course applies only to the Indians then known, all of whom 
inhabited the country east of the Rocky Mountains.  The following 
is the compilation which that writer compared with the census of 
1887, by which time an accurate enumeration became possible.  
</p><pb n="950"/>  
<list> 
<item> <hi rend="bold">1782</hi> 
<hi rend="bold">1887</hi></item> 
<item>Jefferson's Census.          Indian Commissioner's Census.</item> 
<item>Oswegatchies   .   .   .     100</item> 
<item>Connafedagoes )</item> 
<item>Conhunnewagoes)    .   .     300</item> 
<item>Orondoes   .   .   .   .     100</item> 
<item>Abenakies  .   .   .   .     350</item> 
<item>Little Algonkins   .   .     100</item> 
<item>Mickmacs   .   .   .   .     700</item> 
<item>Amelistes  .   .   .   .     550</item> 
<item>Chalas .   .   .   .   .     130</item> 
<item>Nipissins  .   .   .   .     400</item> 
<item>Algonkins  .   .   .   .     300</item> 
<item>Roundheads .   .   .   .   2,500</item> 
<item>Missasagues.   .   .   .   2,000</item> 
<item>Christenauxkris.   .   .   3,000</item> 
<item>Assinaboes .   .   .   .   1,500  Assinaboines .   .   .   .  1,689</item> 
<item>Blancs or Barbus   .   .   1,500</item> 
<item>Mohawks.   .   .   .   .     160</item> 
<item>Oneidas.   .   .   .   .     300  Oneidas  .   .   .   .   .  1,800</item> 
<item>Tuscaroras .   .   .   .     200  Tuscaroras   .   .   .   .  4,154</item> 
<item>Onondagoes .   .   .   .     260  Onondagoes   .   .   .   .  4,841</item> 
<item>Cayugas.   .   .   .   .     220  Cayugas  .   .   .   .   .    172</item> 
<item>Senecas.   .   .   .   .   1,000  Senecas  .   .   .   .   .  2,949</item> 
<item>Aughguagahs    .   .   .     150</item> 
<item>Nanticoes  .   .   .   .     100</item> 
<item>Mohicans   .   .   .   .     100</item> 
<item>Conoies.   .   .   .   .      30</item> 
<item>Sapoonies  .   .   .   .      30</item> 
<item>Munsies.   .   .   .   .     150</item> 
<item>Delawares or Linnalinopies,  750  Delawares    .   .   .   .     44</item> 
<item>Shawanios  .   .   .   .     300  Shawnees .   .   .   .   .    855</item> 
<item>Mingoes.   .   .   .   .      60</item> 
<item>Wyandots   .   .   .   .     300  Wyandottes   .   .   .   .    264</item> 
<item>Twightwees .   .   .   .     250</item> 
<item>Miamis .   .   .   .   .     300  Miamis   .   .   .   .   .     58</item> 
<item>Ouitanons  .   .   .   .     300</item> 
<item>Peankishas .   .   .   .     400  Plankishas   .   .   .   .    207</item> 
<item>Sioux of the Meadows)</item> 
<item>  Sioux of the Woods).   .  10,000  Sioux    .   .   .   .   . 29,716</item> 
<item>       Eastern Sioux)</item> 
<item>Ajones .   .   .   .   .   1,100</item> 
<item>Panis, White   .   .   .   2,000</item> 
<item>Panis, Freckled.   .   .   1,700  Pawnees  .   .   .   .   .    998</item> 
<item>Padoucas   .   .   .   .   5,000</item> 
<item>Grandeaux  .   .   .   .   1,000</item> 
<item>Canses .   .   .   .   .   1,600  Kansas or Kaw    .   .   .    206</item> 
<item>Osages .   .   .   .   .     600  Osages   .   .   .   .   .    582</item> 
<item>Missouris  .   .   .   .   3,000</item> 
<item>Arkansas   .   .   .   .   2,000</item> 
<item>Caonitas   .   .   .   .     700</item> 
<item>Shakirs    .   .   .   .     200</item> 
<item>Kaskaskias .   .   .   .     300</item> 
<item>Piorcas    .   .   .   .     800  Peorias  .   .   .   .   .    144</item> 
<item>Ponteotamies   .   .   .     450  Pottawatamies.   .   .   .  1,056</item> 
<item>Ottawas    .   .   .   .     300  Ottawas  )</item> 
<item>Chippewas  .   .   .   .   5,900  Chippewas)   .   .   .   . 16,816</item> 
<item>Mynonamies .   .   .   .     550  Menominees   .   .   .   .  1,306</item> 
 
<pb n="951"/>  
 
<item>     1782                             1887</item> 
<item>Jefferson's Census.          Indian Commissioner's Census.</item> 
<item>Onisconsuigs   .   .   .     550</item> 
<item>Kickapous )</item> 
<item>Otagamios )</item> 
<item>Mascoutins)</item> 
<item>Mescuthins)    .   .   .   4,000  Kickapoos    .   .   .   .    567</item> 
<item>Outimacs  )</item> 
<item>Musquakies)</item> 
<item>Cherokees  .   .   .   .   3,000  Cherokees    .   .   .   . 25,000</item> 
<item>Chicasaws  .   .   .   .     500  Chicasaws    .   .   .   .  6,000</item> 
<item>Catawbas   .   .   .   .     150</item> 
<item>Chacktaws  .   .   .   .   6,000  Choctaws     .   .   .   . 16,000</item> 
<item>Upper Creeks)</item> 
<item>Lower Creeks)  .   .   .   3,000  Creeks   .   .   .   .   . 14,000</item> 
<item>Natchez    .   .   .   .     150</item> 
<item>Alibamous  .   .   .   .     600  Alabamas .   .   .   .   .    290</item> 
<item>                                    Indians not enumerated  125,040</item> 
</list> 
 
<p>The numbers and names of the tribes enumerated, many of whom 
have passed out of existence or have been absorbed into other 
tribes or survive under other names, prove that whatever may be 
thought of the accuracy of the enumeration, the compilation was 
intended to be complete and gave the best information then 
obtainable, especially as all the information that could be 
obtained was available to that statesman; and it is an important 
fact to note that there could have been no object in any 
underestimation. 
</p><p>This compilation from Jefferson's Notes was based chiefly upon 
the reports of four authorities: first, that of George Croghan in 
1779, who was deputy agent of Indian affairs under Sir William 
Johnson; second, by a French trader annexed to Colonel Bouquet's 
account of his expedition in 1768; third, by Captain Hutchins, who 
visited most of the tribes by order in 1768 for the purpose of 
learning their numbers; fourth, by John Dodge, an Indian trader, in 
1779.  These seem to be good authorities, and while many tribes may 
be omitted or underestimated, it seems impossible that such 
authorities could have made mistakes that could multiply their 
inaccuracies by more than two or three without discovery; and this 
multiplication could only have been possible with tribes then 
little known, such as the Sioux, which, it may be noted, are set 
down at 10,000 against the present 30,000. 
</p><p>It will be noticed that the great increase which has since 
occurred, except in the case of the Sioux, is found among the so-called civilized tribes, such as the Cherokees, Chicasaws, 
Choctaws, and Creeks, which accessions may be largely due to the 
white and negro blood blended with them. <pb n="952"/>  
</p><p>It is doubtless true that such blending of white and Indian 
blood among those tribes is fully overbalanced by half and quarter 
bloods who have passed into the vast white population who make up 
a portion of our western population and are not counted among the 
Indian population.  Thus some of the best people of Saint Paul and 
probably other Western cities have Indian blood in their veins, 
just as many of the proudest of the F. F. V.s of Virginia claim 
descent from Pocahontas. 
</p><p>It is certain that only recently can it be claimed that any 
account of the number of Indians can be relied upon as strictly 
accurate, and it is a fair question whether within recent historic 
times, say from 1700, the Indians have not actually increased in 
numbers. 
</p><p>Thus the following birth and death rates, together with the 
enumeration of Indian population, from 1887 to 1893, during which 
time much attention has been given to obtaining really accurate 
statistics, is compiled from the reports of the Commissioners of 
Indian Affairs: 
 
</p> 
 
<list> 
<item>               Population.  Births.  Deaths.  Increase.  Decrease.</item> 
<item>1887...........  242,299    4,594    3,850        744        ...</item> 
<item>1888...........  246,036    4,028    3,606        422        ...</item> 
<item>1889...........  250,483    5,181    4,719        462        ...</item> 
<item>1890...........  243,534    4,908    5,208        ...        300</item> 
<item>1891...........  246,834    4,128    4,762        ...        634</item> 
<item>1892...........  248,340    3,508    3,660        ...        152</item> 
<item>1893...........  249,366    3,559    3,741        ...        182</item> 
<item>                                                 _____      _____</item> 
<item>                                                 1,628      1,268</item> 
</list> 
 
<p>The reduction in population in 1890 below that of the 
preceding year is explained as due mainly to reduced estimates of 
the numbers of Pimas, Popagoes, and Navajoes. 
</p><p>It will be noted that in each case of decrease of births over 
deaths, except in the case of 1890 explained above, the Indian 
population shows an increase over the preceding year.  This may 
probably be explained by the fact that the births pass unnoted, 
while the deaths, involving the burial ceremony, will be brought to 
the notice of the agent and be noted.  At any rate, these 
statistics, which are the most exact of any obtained by the Indian 
Department regarding Indian population, decidedly indicate an 
increase in the last seven years. 
</p><p>It is equally certain that before 1880 the census of Indians 
was seriously affected from interested motives, and that no very 
great diminution of the Indian population has taken place within, 
say, twenty-five years.  That the Indian wars of recent date have 
not seriously reduced the Indian popu-<pb n="953"/> lation is capable of 
proof.  In view of these facts, it is difficult to account for the 
numbers of Indians given in the Encyclopaedia Britannica&mdash;1,000,000 
on the appearance of the whites, 600,000 in the days of Thomas 
Jefferson. 
</p><p>If such numbers existed in the days of Jefferson, how could he 
have made such egregious mistakes as shown by the enumeration 
before given?  Such numbers might be accounted for through the 
exaggeration of combatants in their boastful accounts of their 
deeds, through ignorance and want of judgment, but on no known 
facts.  It is well recognized what a power and terror the Six 
Nations became to all tribes within their sphere of activity, as 
well as to the colonists, but they certainly in historic times 
never until recently greatly exceeded 10,000, and probably should 
have been estimated at a less number in early history. 
</p><p>The Five Nations, increased to Six by the conquest and 
incorporation of the Tuscaroras, formed one of the most remarkable 
confederacies of savages ever known, and it would be interesting to 
speculate upon the course of so powerful a confederacy had the 
Europeans not interfered by their appearance.  But however great 
the vital force of this wondrous confederated nation planted among 
the scattered tribes of aborigines, it does not seem possible that 
it could have exerted so terrific a power had the American Indians 
amounted to such numbers as we are accustomed to fancy peopled this 
continent.  It is well known how great use was made of Indians by 
the French and British in their early wars, and had such numbers of 
savages as are estimated by early writers been at their disposal, 
a different history might have awaited this country. 
</p>
<p>Some of the tribes generally considered decreased or almost 
extinct have considerable numbers remaining in British America, as, 
for instance, we find in those territories: 1,249 Abnakis, 4,767 
Algonquins, 17,386 Crees, 553 Delawares, 200 Kickapoos (in Mexico), 
1,311 Menominees, 4,108 Mecinoes, 16,289 Ojibwas and Chippewas, 938 
Ottawas, 166 Pottawatomies, 774 Mesesaugas, 1,673 Coghuawaugas, 972 
Cayugas, 376 Iroquois, 2,352 Mohawks, 1,014 Oneidas, 346 Onondagas, 
206 Senecas, 329 Tuscaroras, 377 Wyandots (Hurons); and this is 
probably true of some of the tribes of the Pacific Slope. 
</p><p>A few of such tribes are also incorporated with other tribes; 
thus 1,000 Delawares are with the Cherokees, 3 with the Senecas, 36 
with the Onondagas and Senecas, 23 with the Stockbridges, and 37 
with the Chippewas. 
</p><p>After penning the above reflections, the writer was, by the 

<pb n="954"/>  

kindness of Major Powell, Chief of the Bureau of Ethnology, 
furnished a copy of the annual report of that bureau for 1885-86, 
which contains the most complete and accurate study of the North 
American Indian extant; and in it is to be found ample proof of the 
truth of the views herein expressed.  Though the report pertains 
chiefly to a study of the languages of the primitive tribes, an 
estimate, the most accurate in existence, is there given of the 
Indian population.  Page 33 of the above report reads: "As a result 
of an investigation of the subject of early Indian population, Col. 
Garrick Mallory long ago arrived at the conclusion that their 
settlements were not numerous, and that the population, compared 
with the enormous territory occupied, was extremely small." 
 
</p><p>Careful examination since the publication of the above tends 
to corroborate the soundness of the conclusions then first 
formulated. . . .  Over-estimates of population resulted from the 
fact that the same body of Indians visited different points during 
the year, and not infrequently were counted two or three times; 
change of permanent village sites also tended to augment estimates 
of population. . . .  For these and other reasons a greatly 
exaggerated idea of Indian population was obtained, and the 
impressions so derived have been dissipated only in comparatively 
recent times. 
 
</p><p>Again, on page 38: 
 
</p><p>Nor is there anything in the accounts of any of the early 
visitors to the Columbia valley to authorize the belief that the 
population there was a very large one. . . .  The Dalles was the 
best fishing station on the river, and the settled population there 
may be taken as a fair index of that of other favorable locations.  
The Dalles was visited by Ross in July, 1811, and the following is 
his statement in regard to the population: "The main camp of the 
Indians is situated at the head of the narrows, and may contain, 
during the salmon season, 3,000 souls or more; but the constant 
inhabitants of the place do not exceed 100 persons." 
</p><p>And as it was on the Columbia, with its numerous supply of 
fish, so was it elsewhere in the United States. . . .  The effect 
of wars in decimating the people has often been greatly 
exaggerated. 
 
</p><p>Again, on pages 44 and 45: 
 
</p><p>Second, the early Indian population of North America was 
greatly exaggerated by other writers, and, instead of being large, 
was, in reality, small as compared with the vast territory occupied 
and the abundant food supply; and furthermore, the population had 
nowhere augmented sufficiently, except in California, to press upon 
the food supply. 
 
</p><p>On page 45 appears this statement, which will be equally a 
surprise with the conclusions against the exaggerated ideas of the 
numbers of the Indians: 
 
</p><p>Fourth, prior to the advent of the European, the tribes were 
probably nearly in a state of equilibrium, and were in the main 
sedentary; <pb n="955"/>  and those tribes which can be said with 
propriety to have been nomadic, became so only after the advent of 
the European, and largely as a result of the acquisition of the 
horse and the introduction of fire-arms. 
 
</p><p>On the same page finally we read: 
 
</p><p>Fifth, while agriculture was general among the tribes of the 
United States, and while it was spreading among the western tribes, 
its products were nowhere sufficient wholly to emancipate the 
Indian from the hunter state. 
 
</p><p>The treatise of Col. Mallory referred to in the above report 
has come into the possession of the writer and is conclusive of the 
general views herein adopted.  After showing the entire lack of 
facts on which early estimates were based and their numerous 
contradictions, he goes on to give such facts as are known by the 
best and most reliable authorities.  These authorities conclude 
that the Indian race started from the Columbia River and spread 
east along the borders of streams where game chiefly abounded, 
leaving vast regions unoccupied; that travellers going along these 
streams and finding numerous bodies of Indians, supposed the whole 
country likewise occupied, though other travellers who journeyed 
through those regions found vast areas wholly unoccupied; that 
tribes wandering around were counted many times under different 
names; that the exaggeration of numbers was a trick of the savages 
themselves to increase their importance; that the many names given 
the different tribes augmented the mistakes of travellers; that 
many tribes supposed to be extinct exist under other names.  For 
instance, the supposed extinct Mohicans of Cooper have descendants 
surviving as Mensees, Brothertons, and Stockbridges, originally 
known as Pequods. 
</p><p>He shows also that tribes supposed to be decimated by smallpox 
and other diseases simply migrated and continued to exist under 
altered names unknown to travellers and uncorrected, no records 
being kept by the tribes themselves.  He shows that Europeans did 
not add to the destructive character of wars, the early Indian wars 
being equally or more destructive.  Taking the instance of the 
Iroquois, he proves that there existed 13,668 in 1877, and less 
than 12,000 in 1763.  He also proves that the alleged destruction 
of Indians in California through the barbarities of the gold-seekers of 1849 was greatly exaggerated, being less than 7,000 out 
of 30,000, while double this number was supposed to have been 
destroyed; that the reports of the Indian Bureau of births and 
deaths show an increase; and that <pb n="956"/>  there is no truth in the 
theory that Indians necessarily from any inherent weakness die off 
by contact with civilization. 
</p><p>His conclusions are: 
 
</p><p>That the native population of the territory occupied by the 
United States at its discovery has been wildly over-estimated&mdash;that 
while many of its opponent bodies have been diminished, or been 
destroyed, by oppression and violence, their loss has been in large 
part compensated by gains among others; that though some temporary 
retrogradation must always be expected among individual tribes at 
the crisis of their transition from savagery or barbarism to more 
civilized habits, yet now the number of our Indians is on the 
increase. 
 
</p><p>Probably the most complete data on this subject are given in 
a report of Major S. M. Clark, who was charged by the Bureau of 
Education to investigate the subject, and whose report is published 
in the Report of the Indian Commissioner for 1877.  He gives the 
following estimates:</p> 
<list> 
<item> 1  1780     Estimate of Secretary of War Knox......    76,000</item> 
<item> 2  1790-91  Estimate of General Imlay..............    60,000</item> 
<item> 3  1820     Report of Dr. Morse on Indian Affairs..   471,000</item> 
<item> 4  1825       "    "  Secretary of War.............   129,366</item> 
<item> 5  1829       "    "      "        "  .............   312,934</item> 
<item> 6  1834       "    "      "        "  .............   312,610</item> 
<item> 7  1836       "    "  Supt. of Indian Affairs......   253,464</item> 
<item> 8  1837       "    "      "       "     "    ......   302,498</item> 
<item> 9  1850       "    "  H. R. Schoolcraft............   379,264</item> 
<item>10  1853       "    "  U. S. Census, 1850...........   400,764</item> 
<item>11  1855       "    "  Indian Office................   314,622</item> 
<item>12  1857       "    "  H. R. Schoolcraft............   379,204</item> 
<item>13  1860       "    "  Indian Office................   254,300</item> 
<item>14  1865       "    "    "      "   ................   294,574</item> 
<item>15  1870       "    "  U. S. Census.................   313,712</item> 
<item>16  1870       "    "  Indian Office................   313,371</item> 
</list> 
 
<p>     Of the estimates from 1790 to 1876, this writer says: 
 
</p><p>1.  It is entirely impracticable to present any trustworthy 
statement of the number of Indians in the whole territory comprised 
within the present limits of the United States.  All enumerations 
and estimates were based on fragmentary and otherwise insufficient 
data.  Our official intercourse with the Indian tribes at the 
beginning of this century did not extend much beyond the Ohio River 
and the Mississippi from its confluence with the Ohio to the Gulf 
of mexico; and our information respecting the number of Indian 
tribes beyond, and their numerical strength, was extremely meagre 
and indefinite.  The number of Indian tribes in official relations 
with the United States steadily increased from 1778, the date of 
our first Indian treaty, to within a few years. 
</p><p>2.  Such estimates and enumerations as have been presented do 
not coincide (except in two instances, 1820 and 1870) in date with 
the years in which the regular census of the United States was 
taken; nor do they appear at regular intervals. 
</p><p>3.  It is almost invariably true that estimates of the numbers 
of our Indian tribes exceed the real numbers; and from the nature 
of the case, all official enumerations, until within a very recent 
period, <pb n="957"/>  have necessarily included many estimates, and are, 
for that reason, inaccurate. 
</p><p>4.  The United States census returns before 1850 did not 
include Indians. 
 
</p><p>A footnote states that the estimates of Knox and Imlay may 
represent warriors only, in which case the total number would be 
380,000 and 300,000, warriors being estimated at one-fifth of the 
population.  Dr. Morse made his estimate under an appointment to 
make a report on the condition of the Indians, which ended in 1822. 
</p><p>The estimate of 1825 did not include Indians in or west of the 
Missouri valley, and is therefore incomplete.  The estimate of 1829 
noted the geographical distribution; that of 1834 did not include 
tribes north of Virginia and east of Ohio; and that of 1836 did not 
include Indians west of the Rocky Mountains nor those of Texas.  
That of 1837 is taken from Schoolcraft's history and includes all 
Indian tribes in the estimate stated by him to have been made up by 
the Indian Office. 
</p><p>The enumeration by Schoolcraft was the first real attempt to 
accurately count the Indians, and cost $130,000, appropriated by 
Congress.  The investigations were never completed, and the 
enumeration was made up partly of estimates, some exaggerated, as, 
for instance, the tribes in Texas and the new territories being put 
at 183,042.  The census of 1850 was chiefly estimated, one estimate 
being 271,930.  The California Indians were placed at 100,000, 
whereas Schoolcraft had three years before placed them at 32,231, 
which was also doubtless an overestimate.  The estimate of 1855 was 
admitted to be largely conjectural, also that of Schoolcraft of 
1857. 
</p><p>From 1860 the Indian Office published statements of 
population, schools, etc., of tribes connected with the Government 
of the United States, which became of value after 1870. 
</p><p>This writer gives the following substantial reasons for the 
exaggerations in the estimates of Indians since 1790: 
 
</p><p>1.  The estimates of the Spanish adventurers, whose 
explorations were more extensive than those of any other nation in 
the sixteenth century, were accepted and seldom questioned for a 
long period; some of them are still accepted.  The Spanish 
estimates were largely based on their previous experience in the 
more densely populated countries of Mexico and Peru: besides, they 
warred with the natives, and it has never been a Spanish trait to 
underrate the numerical strength of an enemy. 
</p><p>2.  The French explorers were largely composed of 
ecclesiastics whose imaginations were kindled by a contemplation of 
the heathen multitudes they were to win to the cross.  The 
extravagance of many of their estimates has been shown, and yet 
they are to a considerable extent accepted to-day. <pb n="958"/>  
</p><p>3.  The early English colonists formed permanent settlements.  
Their little towns were naturally seated on water-courses which 
were the great highways of Indian travel, and at points on the 
coast to which the Indians had long resorted.  They thus came in 
contact with a very large proportion, relatively, of the Indian 
population.  They were also engaged in hostilities with the 
Indians, and were naturally misled as to the number of their foes 
by the ubiquity of the savages, whose mode of warfare enabled them 
to strike a hamlet here to-day and another fifty miles away to-morrow. 
</p><p>4.  There were other reasons more general why estimates were 
exaggerated.  Trade brought to the points of exchange large numbers 
of Indians from great distances.  The Indians naturally, for 
purposes of their own, magnified their own numbers and importance. 
</p><p>The vast extent of country, compared with the more limited 
areas to which the English, French, and Spaniards were accustomed, 
and which were densely populated, led them to magnify the actual 
population of the new world. 
 
</p><p>The most perfect illustration of the effect of European 
civilization upon the American aborigines is to be found in the 
history of the Iroquois Confederacy, of which we fortunately 
possess complete and accurate accounts from an early date, which 
nation of Indians has come into contact in more various ways and 
has figured more largely in our early history than any other.  The 
estimates below are from Major Clark's treatise: </p>
<list> 
<item>Date.    Authority.</item> 
<item>1660  Jesuit Relation.......................................     11,000</item> 
<item>1665  Jesuit Relation.......................................     11,750</item> 
<item>1665  French Expedition.....................................     11,700</item> 
<item>1671  Wentworth Greenhalgh..................................     10,750</item> 
<item>1677  Col. Coursey..........................................     17,000</item> 
<item>1681  Du Chesneau...........................................     10,000</item> 
<item>1682  Governor de la Barre..................................     13,000</item> 
<item>1685  French Memoir of Canada...............................     10,250</item> 
<item>1687  French Memoir of Canada...............................     10,000</item> 
<item>1689  Governor Bellemont....................................     12,850</item> 
<item>1698  Governor Bellemont....................................      6,150</item> 
<item>1720  Governor Hunter.......................................     10,000</item> 
<item>1736  Joncaire (including Tuscaroras).......................      7,350</item> 
<item>1738 Indian Commissioners of New York (including Tuscaroras)      8,825</item> 
<item>1763  Sir William Johnson...................................     11,650</item> 
<item>1768  Capt. Thomas Hutchins.................................     14,150</item> 
<item>1770  Sir William Johnson...................................     10,000</item> 
<item>1774  Sir William Johnson...................................     12,500</item> 
<item>1779  John Dodge, Indian Trader.............................      8,000</item> 
<item>1791  General Imlay.........................................      7,430</item> 
<item>1796  Dr. Morse.............................................      3,748</item> 
<item>1818  Jaspar Parrish, Indian Sub-Agent......................      4,575</item> 
<item>1819  Report to New York Legislature........................      4,538</item> 
<item>1821  Rev. Jedidiah Morse...................................      4,056</item> 
<item>1825  Secretary of War......................................      5,061</item> 
<item>1829  Secretary of War......................................      5,100</item> 
<item>1845  H. R. Schoolcraft.....................................      6,942</item> 
<item>1850  Indian Office.........................................      5,225</item> 
 
<pb n="959"/>  
 
<item>Date.    Authority.</item> 
<item>1855  Indian Office.........................................      5,778</item> 
<item>1860  Indian Office.........................................      3,953</item> 
<item>1865  Indian Office.........................................      5,300</item> 
<item>1870  U. S. Census..........................................      4,962</item> 
<item>1870  Indian Office.........................................      4,804</item> 
<item>1875  N. Y. Census..........................................      4,672</item> 
<item>1875  Indian Office.........................................      4,804</item> 
<item>1877  Indian Office.........................................      5,881</item> 
<item>      If to these are added the Iroquois in Canada..........     13,068</item> 
</list> 
 
<p>The figures from 1796 do not include the Iroquois who had
moved into Canada.  The number estimated in 1877, which is said to 
be an underestimate (13,068), considerably exceeded any trustworthy 
estimate of their numerical strength for more than one hundred 
years, and proves a certain increase.  The wars of the French and 
Indians, the Revolutionary War, and the War of 1812, probably the 
most destructive wars to which Indians have been subjected, 
undoubtedly decreased the numbers of the Iroquois, but it is seen 
that they have more than recovered their earlier numbers. 
</p><p>Major Clark concludes: 
 
</p><p>It may not be impertinent for the writer to observe that the 
above, and a multitude of other facts that have come to his 
knowledge during several years of study of the question of Indian 
civilization, have convinced him that the usual theory that the 
Indian population is destined to decline and finally disappear, as 
a result of contact with white civilization, must be greatly 
modified, probably abandoned altogether. 
 
</p><p>The above-mentioned reports were the result of vast research 
after an exhaustive consulting of the best authorities by the most 
painstaking inquirers, and their conclusions are absolutely 
decisive of the question so far as they extend.  No amount of loose 
compilation by guesswork, indulged in by ordinary writers, can 
stand before the perfect method and unprejudiced study given by 
these honest government inquirers, and their deductions will 
undoubtedly be accepted as conclusive by all unprejudiced students. 
</p><p>It may therefore be claimed with confidence that the notion of 
the dying-out of the Indian race on this continent is a popular 
fallacy which the painstaking system of modern research has 
exploded; though it will long remain in the minds of the people as 
a tradition rendered sacred by many generations of believers, and 
will still hold its place as an historic fact to be worked up by 
sentimentalists in story, song, and romance. 
</p><p>It is time, however, that future historians should, in the 
interest of truth, relegate the theory of the disappearance of the 
race of North American Indians to its proper place among the 
disproved fallacies of history. 
</p> 
 
</div1> 
</body> 
</text> 
</TEI.2> 
