<?xml version="1.0"?>

<?dlps id="PouHago"?>
<?dlps page-images="none" figure-images="no"?>
<?dlps transcription="other"?>

<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/tei-p4/tei2.dtd" [
<!ENTITY % POSTKB "INCLUDE">
<!ENTITY % TEI.extensions.ent SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.ent">
<!ENTITY % TEI.extensions.dtd SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.dtd">
<!ENTITY % ISOnum SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/charent/iso-num.ent"> %ISOnum;
<!ENTITY % ISOpub SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/charent/iso-pub.ent"> %ISOpub;
  
]>  
<TEI.2 id="PouHago">  
<teiHeader type="migrated" creator="Etext">
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title type="main">Hagoromo</title>
<title type="sort">hagoromo</title>
<author>Pound, Ezra and Fenollosa, Ernest</author>
<respStmt>
<resp>Creation of machine-readable version:</resp>   
<name>Winnie Chan</name>   
<resp>Creation of digital images:</resp>   
<name/>   
<resp>Conversion to TEI.2-conformant markup:</resp>   
<name>University of Virginia Library Electronic Text Center.</name>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt>   
<extent>ca. <num type="kilobytes">19</num> kilobytes</extent>   
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>University of Virginia Library</publisher>
<pubPlace>Charlottesville, Virginia</pubPlace>   
<idno type="ETC">PouHago</idno>   
<date value="1996">1996</date>
<availability status="public">
<p n="copyright">Copyright &copy; 1996 by the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia</p>
<p n="access">Publicly accessible</p>
</availability>
<idno type="uva-pid">uva-lib:476330</idno>
</publicationStmt>
<seriesStmt>
<title>University of Virginia Library, Text collection</title>
<idno type="uva-set">UVA-LIB-Text</idno>
</seriesStmt>   
<seriesStmt>
<p>Japanese Text Initiative</p>
</seriesStmt>   
<notesStmt>   
<note>
<p>Footnotes in the print source have been moved to the end of the  
document. For descriptive purposes, words or phrases preceding footnote  
markers in the print source have been added to footnotes at the end of  
the electronic document.</p>
</note>
</notesStmt>   
<sourceDesc>
<biblFull>
<titleStmt>
<title type="main">Hagoromo</title>
<title level="m">"Noh" or Accomplishment: a Study of the Classical Stage in Japan</title>
<title type="sort">hagoromo</title>
<author>Ezra Pound and Ernest Fenollosa</author>
</titleStmt>   
<extent>pp. 165-176</extent>   
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>MacMillan</publisher>   
<pubPlace>London</pubPlace>   
<date value="1916">1916</date>   
<idno type="callNo">Print copy consulted: UVa Library call number PL 735 .F4 1916</idno>
</publicationStmt>   
</biblFull>
</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc>   
<encodingDesc>
<projectDesc>
<p>Prepared for the University of Virginia Library Electronic Text Center.</p>
</projectDesc>   
<editorialDecl>
<p>All quotation marks retained as data.</p>   
<p>All unambiguous end-of-line hyphens have been removed, and the trailing part of a word has been joined to the preceding line.</p>   
<p>Keywords in the header are a local Electronic Text Center scheme to aid in establishing analytical groupings.</p>
</editorialDecl>   
</encodingDesc>   
<profileDesc>
<creation>
<date value="1916">1916</date>
</creation>   
<langUsage>
<language id="eng" usage="main">English</language>
</langUsage>   
<textClass>
<keywords>
<term>drama; poetry; prose</term>
</keywords>   
</textClass>
</profileDesc>   
<revisionDesc>
<change>
<date value="1997-09">September 1997</date>   
<respStmt>
<resp>corrector</resp>   
<name>Catherine Tousignant, Electronic Text Center</name>
</respStmt>   
<item>Added milestones to correspond with TylHago</item>
</change>   
<change>
<date value="1996-12">December 1996</date>   
<respStmt>
<resp>corrector</resp>   
<name>Winnie Chan</name>
</respStmt>   
<item>Added TEI header and tags</item>
</change>   
<change>
<date value="2005-07">July 2005</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>Corrector</resp>
<name>John Ivor Carlson</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Converted SGML to XML and/or corrected tagging.</item>
</change>
<change>
<date value="2007-09">September 2007</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>Migration</resp>
<name>Ethan Gruber, University of Virginia Library</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Converted XML markup from TEI Lite to uva-dl-tei (TEI P4 with local customizations).</item>
</change>
<change>
<date value="2008-01">January 2008</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>Migration</resp>
<name>Greg Murray, University of Virginia Library</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Programmatically updated TEI header markup (but not header content) for minimal compliance with current QA requirements.</item>
</change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>   
  
<text id="d1">
<front id="d2">
<div1 type="play" id="d3"><pb n="165"/>
<head>Hagoromo<lb/>  
A Play in one Act</head>  


<list>
<head>Characters</head>
<item>Chief Fisherman, Hakuryo.</item>   
<item>A Fisherman.</item>   
<item>A Tennin.</item>   
<item>Chorus.</item>
</list>


<p>The plot of the play Hagoromo, the Feather-mantle, is as follows: The  
priest finds the Hagoromo, the magical feather-mantle of a Tennin, an 
aerial spirit or celestial dancer, hanging upon a bough. She demands its 
return. He argues with her, and finally promises to return it, if she 
will teach him her dance or part of it. She accepts the offer. The 
Chorus explains the dance as symbolical of the daily changes of the 
moon. The words about "three, five, and fifteen" refer to the number of 
nights in the moon's changes. In the finale, the Tennin is supposed to 
disappear like a mountain slowly hidden in mist. The 

<pb n="166"/>   
play shows the relation of the early Noh to the God-dance.  
</p>
</div1>
</front>

<body id="d4">
<div1 type="play" id="d5">
<milestone unit="speech" n="Hago1"/>  
<sp>
<speaker>Hakuryo</speaker>  
<lg type="poem">  
<l>Windy road of the waves by Miwo,</l>  
<l>Swift with ships, loud over steersmen's voices.</l>  
<milestone unit="speech" n="Hago2"/>
<l rend="indent">Hakuryo, taker of fish, head of his house, dwells upon  
the barren pine-waste of Miwo.</l>  
</lg>  
</sp>  

<milestone unit="speech" n="Hago3"/>  
<sp>  
<speaker>A Fisherman</speaker>  
<p>  
Upon a thousand heights had gathered the inexplicable cloud. Swept by the  
rain, the moon is just come to light the high house.  
</p>  
  
<p>  
A clean and pleasant time surely. There comes the breath-colour of spring;  
the waves rise in a line below the early mist; the moon is still delaying  
above, though we've no skill to grasp it. Here is a beauty to set the mind  
above itself.  
</p>  
</sp>  

<milestone unit="speech" n="Hago4"/>  
<sp>  
<speaker>Chorus</speaker>  
<lg type="poem">  
<l>I shall not be out of memory</l>  
<l>Of the mountain road by Kiyomi,</l>  
<l>Nor of the parted grass by that bay,</l>  
<l>Nor of the far seen pine-waste</l>  
<l>Of Miwo of wheat stalks.</l>  
</lg>  

<milestone unit="speech" n="Hago5"/>  
<p>  
Let us go according to custom. Take hands against the wind here, for it  
presses the clouds and the sea. Those men who were going to fish are about  
to return without   
    
  
 <pb n="167"/>   
launching. Wait a little, is it not spring? will not the wind be quiet?  
This wind is only the voice of the lasting pine-trees, ready for  
stillness. See how the air is soundless, or would be, were it not for the  
waves. There now, the fishermen are putting out with even the smallest  
boats.  
</p>  
</sp>  

<milestone unit="speech" n="Hago6"/>  
<sp>  
<speaker>Hakuryo</speaker>  
<p>  
I am come to shore at Miwo-no; I disembark in Matsubara; I see all that  
they speak of on the shore. An empty sky with music, a rain of flowers,  
strange fragrance on every side; all these are no common things, nor is  
this cloak that hangs upon the pine-tree. As I approach to inhale its  
colour, I am aware of mystery. Its colour-smell is mysterious. I see that  
it is surely no common dress. I will take it now and return and make it a  
treasure in my house, to show to the aged.  
</p>  
</sp>  

<milestone unit="speech" n="Hago7"/>  
<sp>  
<speaker>Tennin</speaker>  
<p>  
That cloak belongs to some one on this side. What are you proposing to do  
with it?  
</p>  
</sp>  
  
<milestone unit="speech" n="Hago8"/>
<sp>  
<speaker>Hakuryo</speaker>  
<p>  
This? this is a cloak picked up. I am taking it home, I tell you.  
</p>  
</sp>  
    
  
 <pb n="168"/>   
<milestone unit="speech" n="Hago9"/>
<sp>  
<speaker>Tennin</speaker>  
<lg type="poem">  
<l>That is a feather-mantle not fit for a mortal to bear,</l>  
<l>Not easily wrested from the sky-traversing spirit,</l>  
<l>Not easily taken or given.</l>  
<l>I ask you to leave it where you found it.</l>  
</lg>  
</sp>  

<milestone unit="speech" n="Hago10"/>  
<sp>  
<speaker>Hakuryo</speaker>  
<p>  
How! Is the owner of this cloak a Tennin? So be it. In this downcast age I  
should keep it, a rare thing, and make it a treasure in the country, a  
thing respected. Then I should not return it.  
</p>  
</sp>  

<milestone unit="speech" n="Hago11"/>  
<sp>  
<speaker>Tennin</speaker>  
<p>  
Pitiful, there is no flying without the cloak of feathers, no return  
through the ether. I pray you return me the mantle.  
</p>  
</sp>  

<milestone unit="speech" n="Hago12"/>  
<sp>  
<speaker>Hakuryo</speaker>  
<p>  
Just from hearing these high words, I, Hakuryo, have gathered more and yet  
more force. You think, because I was too stupid to recognize it, that I  
shall be unable to take and keep hid the feather-robe, that I shall give  
it back for merely being told to stand and withdraw?  
</p>  
</sp>
    
  
 <pb n="169"/>   
<milestone unit="speech" n="Hago13"/>
<sp>  
<speaker>Tennin</speaker>  
<lg type="poem">  
<l>A Tennin without her robe,</l>  
<l>A bird without wings,</l>  
<l>How shall she climb the air?</l>  
</lg>  
</sp>  

<milestone unit="speech" n="Hago14"/>  
<sp>  
<speaker>Hakuryo</speaker>  
<p>  
And this world would be a sorry place for her to dwell in?  
</p>  
</sp>  

<milestone unit="speech" n="Hago15"/>  
<sp>  
<speaker>Tennin</speaker>  
<p>  
I am caught, I struggle, how shall I . . .?  
</p>  
</sp>  
  
<milestone unit="speech" n="Hago16"/>
<sp>  
<speaker>Hakuryo</speaker>  
<p>  
No, Hakuryo is not one to give back the robe.  
</p>  
</sp>  

<milestone unit="speech" n="Hago17"/>  
<sp>  
<speaker>Tennin</speaker>  
<p>  
Power does not attain . . .  
</p>  
</sp>  
  
<milestone unit="speech" n="Hago18"/>
<sp>  
<speaker>Hakuryo</speaker>  
<p>  
. . . to get back the robe . . .  
</p>  
</sp>  

<milestone unit="speech" n="Hago19"/>  
<sp>  
<speaker>Chorus</speaker>  
<p>  
Her coronet,  
<ref target="n169.1">[1]</ref>  
 jewelled as with the dew of tears, even the flowers that decorated her  
hair, drooping and fading, the whole chain of weaknesses  
<ref target="n169.2">[2]</ref>  
 of the dying Tennin can be seen actually before the eyes. Sorrow!  
</p>  
</sp>
    
  
 <pb n="170"/>   
<milestone unit="speech" n="Hago20"/>
<sp>  
<speaker>Tennin</speaker>  
<p>  
I look into the flat of heaven, peering; the cloud-road is all hidden and  
uncertain; we are lost in the rising mist; I have lost the knowledge of  
the road. Strange, a strange sorrow!  
</p>  
</sp>  

<milestone unit="speech" n="Hago21"/>  
<sp>  
<speaker>Chorus</speaker>  
<p>  
Enviable colour of breath, wonder of clouds that fade along the sky that  
was our accustomed dwelling; 
<milestone unit="speech" n="Hago22"/> 
hearing the sky-bird, accustomed, and well  
accustomed, hearing the voices grow fewer, the wild geese fewer and fewer,  
along the highways of air, how deep her longing to return! Plover and  
seagull are on the waves in the offing. Do they go or do they return? She  
reaches out for the very blowing of the spring wind against heaven.  
</p>  
</sp>  
  
<milestone unit="speech" n="Hago23"/>
<sp>  
<speaker>Hakuryo</speaker>  
<stage>  
to the Tennin  
</stage>  
<p>  
What do you say? Now that I can see you in your sorrow, gracious, of  
heaven, I bend and would return you your mantle.  
</p>  
</sp>  

<milestone unit="speech" n="Hago24"/>  
<sp>  
<speaker>Tennin</speaker>  
<p>  
It grows clearer. No, give it this side.  
</p>  
</sp>  
    
  
 <pb n="171"/>   
<milestone unit="speech" n="Hago25"/>
<sp>  
<speaker>Hakuryo</speaker>  
<p>  
First tell me your nature, who are you, Tennin? Give payment with the  
dance of the Tennin, and I will return you your mantle.  
</p>  
</sp>  

<milestone unit="speech" n="Hago26"/>  
<sp>  
<speaker>Tennin</speaker>  
<p>  
Readily and gladly, and then I return into heaven. You shall have what  
pleasure you will, and I will leave a dance here, a joy to be new among  
men and to be memorial dancing. Learn then this dance that can turn the  
palace of the moon. No, come here to learn it. For the sorrows of the  
world I will leave this new dancing with you for sorrowful people. But  
give me my mantle, I cannot do the dance rightly without it.  
</p>  
</sp>  
  
<milestone unit="speech" n="Hago27"/>
<sp>  
<speaker>Hakuryo</speaker>  
<p>  
Not yet, for if you should get it, how do I know you'll not be off to your  
palace without even beginning your dance, not even a measure?  
</p>  
</sp>  

<milestone unit="speech" n="Hago28"/>  
<sp>  
<speaker>Tennin</speaker>  
<p>  
Doubt is fitting for mortals; with us there is no deceit.  
</p>  
</sp>  

<milestone unit="speech" n="Hago29"/>  
<sp>  
<speaker>Hakuryo</speaker>  
<p>  
I am again ashamed. I give you your mantle.  
</p>  
</sp>  
    
  
 <pb n="172"/>   
<milestone unit="speech" n="Hago30"/>
<sp>  
<speaker>Chorus</speaker>  
<p>  
The young sprite now is arrayed, she assumes the curious mantle; watch how  
she moves in the dance of the rainbow-feathered garment.  
</p>  
</sp>  
  
<milestone unit="speech" n="Hago31"/>
<sp>  
<speaker>Hakuryo</speaker>  
<p>  
The heavenly feather-robe moves in accord with the wind.  
</p>  
</sp>  

<milestone unit="speech" n="Hago32"/>  
<sp>  
<speaker>Tennin</speaker>  
<p>  
The sleeves of flowers are being wet with the rain.  
</p>  
</sp>  

<milestone unit="speech" n="Hago34"/>  
<sp>  
<speaker>Hakuryo</speaker>  
<p>  
All three are doing one step.  
</p>  
</sp>  

<milestone unit="speech" n="Hago35"/>  
<sp>  
<speaker>Chorus</speaker>  
<lg type="poem">  
<l>It seems that she dances.</l>  
<l>Thus was the dance of pleasure,</l>  
<l>Suruga dancing, brought to the sacred east.</l>  
<milestone unit="speech" n="Hago36"/>
<l>Thus was it when the lords of the everlasting</l>  
<l>Trod the world,</l>  
<l>They being of old our friends.</l>  
<l>Upon ten sides their sky is without limit,</l>  
<l>They have named it, on this account, the enduring.</l>  
</lg>  
</sp>  

<milestone unit="speech" n="Hago37"/>  
<sp>  
<speaker>Tennin</speaker>  
<p>  
The jewelled axe takes up the eternal renewing, the palace of the moon-god  
is being renewed with the jewelled axe, and this is always recurring.  
</p>  
</sp>  
    
  
 <pb n="173"/>   
<milestone unit="speech" n="Hago38"/>
<sp>  
<speaker>Chorus</speaker>  
  
<stage>  
commenting on the dance  
</stage>  
  
<lg type="poem">  
<l>The white kiromo, the black kiromo,</l>  
<l>Three, five into fifteen,</l>  
<l>The figure that the Tennin is dividing.</l>  
<l>There are heavenly nymphs, Amaotome,  
<ref target="n173.1">[3]</ref></l>  
<l>One for each night of the month,</l>  
<l>And each with her deed assigned.</l>  
</lg>  
</sp>  

<milestone unit="speech" n="Hago39"/>  
<sp>  
<speaker>Tennin</speaker>  
<p>  
I also am heaven-born and a maid, Amaotome. Of them there are many. 
<milestone unit="speech" n="Hago40"/> 
This  is the dividing of my body, that is fruit of the moon's tree, Katsura.  
<ref target="n173.2">[4]</ref>  
 This is one part of our dance that I leave to you here in your world.  
</p>  
</sp>  

<milestone unit="speech" n="Hago41"/>  
<sp>  
<speaker>Chorus</speaker>  
<p>  
The spring mist is widespread abroad; so perhaps the wild olive's flower  
will blossom in the infinitely unreachable moon. Her flowery head-ornament  
is putting on colour; this truly is sign of the spring. Not sky is here,  
but the beauty; and even here comes the heavenly, wonderful wind. O blow,  
shut the accustomed path of the clouds. O, you  
    
  
 <pb n="174"/>   
in the form of a maid, grant us the favour of your delaying. The  
pine-waste of Miwo puts on the colour of spring. The bay of Kiyomi lies  
clear before the snow upon Fuji. Are not all these presages of the spring?  
There are but few ripples beneath the piny wind. It is quiet along the  
shore. There is naught but a fence of jewels between the earth and the  
sky, and the gods within and without,  
<ref target="n174.1">[5]</ref>  
 beyond and beneath the stars, and the moon unclouded by her lord, and we  
who are born of the sun. This alone intervenes, here where the moon is  
unshadowed, here in Nippon, the sun's field.  
</p>  
</sp>  

<milestone unit="speech" n="Hago42"/>  
<sp>  
<speaker>Tennin</speaker>  
<p>  
The plumage of heaven drops neither feather nor flame to its own  
diminution.  
</p>  
</sp>  

<milestone unit="speech" n="Hago43"/>  
<sp>  
<speaker>Chorus</speaker>  
<p>  
Nor is this rock of earth overmuch worn by the brushing of that  
feather-mantle, the feathery skirt of the stars: rarely, how rarely. There  
is a magic song from the east, the voices of many and many: and flute and  
sho, filling the space beyond the cloud's edge, seven-stringed; dance  
filling and filling. The red sun blots on the sky the line of the colour-drenched 
    
  
 <pb n="175"/>   
 mountains. The flowers rain in a gust; it is no racking storm  
that comes over this green moor, which is afloat, as it would seem, in  
these waves.  
</p>  
  
<p>  
Wonderful is the sleeve of the white cloud, whirling such snow here.  
</p>  
</sp>  
  
<milestone unit="speech" n="Hago44"/>
<sp>  
<speaker>Tennin</speaker>  
<p>  
Plain of life, field of the sun, true foundation, great power!  
</p>  
</sp>  
  
<milestone unit="speech" n="Hago45"/>
<sp>  
<speaker>Chorus</speaker>  
<p>  
Hence and for ever this dancing shall be called "a revel in the East."  
Many are the robes thou hast, now of the sky's colour itself, and now a  
green garment.  
</p>  
</sp>  

<milestone unit="speech" n="Hago46"/>
<milestone unit="speech" n="Hago47"/>
<milestone unit="speech" n="Hago48"/>  
<sp>  
<speaker>Semi-Chorus</speaker>  
<p>  
And now the robe of mist, presaging spring, a colour-smell as this  
wonderful maiden's skirt   &mdash;   left, right, left! The rustling of flowers,  
the putting on of the feathery sleeve; they bend in air with the dancing.  
</p>  
</sp>  

<milestone unit="speech" n="Hago49"/>  
<sp>  
<speaker>Semi-Chorus</speaker>  
<p>  
Many are the joys in the east. She who is the colour-person of the moon  
takes her middle-night in the sky. She marks her three fives with this  
dancing, as a shadow of all fulfilments.  
    
  
 <pb n="176"/>   
The circled vows are at full. Give the seven jewels of rain and all of the  
treasure, you who go from us. After a little time, only a little time, can  
the mantle be upon the wind that was spread over Matsubara or over   
Ashitaka the mountain, though the clouds lie in its heaven like a  
plain awash with sea. Fuji is gone; the great peak of Fuji is blotted out  
little by little. It melts into the upper mist. In this way she (the  
Tennin) is lost to sight.  
</p>  
</sp>  
</div1>  
</body>  
  
<back id="d6">  
<div1 type="notes" id="d7">  
<head>Footnotes</head>  
<note id="n169.1"><seg type="note-symbol">[1:</seg> <p>Her coronet] Vide examples of state head-dress of  
kingfisher feathers in the South Kensington Museum.</p></note>  
  
<note id="n169.2"><seg type="note-symbol">[2:</seg> <p>the chain of weaknesses] The chain of weaknesses, or  
the five ills, diseases of the Tennin: namely, the Tamakadzura withers;  
the Hagoromo is stained; sweat comes from the body; both eyes wink  
frequently; she feels very weary  
of her palace in heaven.</p></note>  
  
<note id="n173.1"><seg type="note-symbol">[3:</seg> <p>There are heavenly nymphs, Amaotome] Cf. 
"Paradiso," xxiii. 25: 
<q><lg type="poem"><l>"Quale nei plenilunii sereni</l>  
<l>Trivia ride tra le ninfe eterne."</l></lg></q>  
</p></note>  
  
<note id="n173.2"><seg type="note-symbol">[4:</seg> <p>Katsura] A tree something like the laurel.</p></note>  
  
<note id="n174.1"><seg type="note-symbol">[5:</seg> <p>the gods within and without] "Within and without,"  
gei, gu, two parts of the temple.</p></note>  

</div1>  
</back>  
  
</text>  
</TEI.2>  
  
 
