<?xml version="1.0"?>

<?dlps id="PouKuma"?>
<?dlps page-images="none" figure-images="no"?>
<?dlps transcription="other"?>

<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/tei-p4/tei2.dtd" [
<!ENTITY % POSTKB "INCLUDE">
<!ENTITY % TEI.extensions.ent SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.ent">
<!ENTITY % TEI.extensions.dtd SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.dtd">
<!ENTITY % ISOnum SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/charent/iso-num.ent"> %ISOnum;
<!ENTITY % ISOlat1 SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/charent/iso-lat1.ent"> %ISOlat1;
<!ENTITY % ISOpub SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/charent/iso-pub.ent"> %ISOpub;
 
]> 
<TEI.2 id="PouKuma"> 
<teiHeader type="migrated" creator="Etext">
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title type="main">Kumasaka</title>
<title type="sort">kumasaka</title>
<author>Pound, Ezra and Fenollosa, Ernest</author>
<respStmt>
<resp>Creation of machine-readable version:</resp>  
<name>Winnie Chan</name>  
<resp>Creation of digital images:</resp>  
<name/>  
<resp>Conversion to TEI.2-conformant markup:</resp>  
<name>University of Virginia Library Electronic Text Center.</name>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt>  
<extent>ca. <num type="kilobytes">18</num> kilobytes</extent>  
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>University of Virginia Library</publisher>
<pubPlace>Charlottesville, Virginia</pubPlace>  
<idno type="ETC">PouKuma</idno>  
<date value="1997">1997</date>
<availability status="public">
<p n="copyright">Copyright &copy; 1997 by the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia</p>
<p n="access">Publicly accessible</p>
</availability>
<idno type="uva-pid">uva-lib:476332</idno>
</publicationStmt>
<seriesStmt>
<title>University of Virginia Library, Text collection</title>
<idno type="uva-set">UVA-LIB-Text</idno>
</seriesStmt>  
<seriesStmt>
<p>Japanese Text Initiative</p>
</seriesStmt>  
<notesStmt>
<note>
<p>Footnotes in the print source have been moved to the end of the 
electronic document and numbered consecutively. For descriptive 
purposes, words or phrases preceding footnote markers in the print 
source have been added to the notes at the end of the electronic 
document.</p>
</note>
</notesStmt>  
<sourceDesc>
<biblFull>
<titleStmt>
<title type="main">Kumasaka</title>
<title level="m">"Noh" or Accomplishment: a Study of the Classical Stage in Japan</title>
<title type="sort">kumasaka</title>
<author>Ezra Pound and Ernest Fenollosa</author>
</titleStmt>  
<editionStmt>
<p>1st Edition</p>
</editionStmt>  
<extent>pp. 63-78</extent>  
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>MacMillan</publisher>  
<pubPlace>London</pubPlace>  
<date value="1916">1916</date>  
<idno type="callNo">Print copy consulted: UVa Library call number PL 735 .F4 1916</idno>
</publicationStmt>  
</biblFull>
</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc>  
<encodingDesc>
<projectDesc>
<p>Prepared for the University of Virginia Library Electronic Text Center.</p>
</projectDesc>  
<editorialDecl>
<p>All quotation marks retained as data.</p>  
<p>All unambiguous end-of-line hyphens have been removed, and the trailing part of a word has been joined to the preceding line.</p>  
<p>Keywords in the header are a local Electronic Text Center scheme to aid in establishing analytical groupings.</p>
</editorialDecl>  
</encodingDesc>  
<profileDesc>
<creation>
<date value="1916">1916</date>
</creation>  
<langUsage>
<language id="eng" usage="main">English</language>
</langUsage>  
<textClass>
<keywords>
<term>drama; poetry; prose</term>
</keywords>  
</textClass>
</profileDesc>  
<revisionDesc>
<change>
<date value="1997-09">September 1997</date>  
<respStmt>
<resp>corrector</resp>  
<name>Catherine Tousignant, Electronic Text Center</name>
</respStmt>  
<item>Added milestones to correspond with WalKuma.</item>
</change>  
<change>
<date value="1997-01">January 1997</date>  
<respStmt>
<resp>corrector</resp>  
<name>Winnie Chan</name>
</respStmt>  
<item>Added TEI header and tags</item>
</change>  
<change>
<date value="2005-07">July 2005</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>Corrector</resp>
<name>John Ivor Carlson</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Converted SGML to XML and/or corrected tagging.</item>
</change>
<change>
<date value="2007-09">September 2007</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>Migration</resp>
<name>Ethan Gruber, University of Virginia Library</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Converted XML markup from TEI Lite to uva-dl-tei (TEI P4 with local customizations).</item>
</change>
<change>
<date value="2008-01">January 2008</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>Migration</resp>
<name>Greg Murray, University of Virginia Library</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Programmatically updated TEI header markup (but not header content) for minimal compliance with current QA requirements.</item>
</change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>  
 
<text id="d1"> 
<body id="d2"> 
<div1 type="play" id="d3"> <pb n="67"/>  
<head> 
KUMASAKA<lb/> 
A Play in two Acts, by Ujinobu, adopted son of Motokiyo 
</head> 
 

<list> 
<head>CHARACTERS</head> 

<item>A Priest.</item> 
 
<item>First Shite, or Hero, the apparition of Kumasaka in the form of an old priest.</item> 
 
<item>Second Shite, the apparition of Kumasaka in his true 
form.</item>
 
<item>Chorus. This chorus sometimes speaks what the chief characters are 
thinking, sometimes it describes or interprets the meaning of their 
movements.</item></list>

<div2 type="section" id="d4"><p> 
PLOT.   &mdash;   The ghost of Kumasaka makes reparation for his brigandage by 
protecting the country. He comes back to praise the bravery of the young 
man who had killed him in single combat. 
</p>  
</div2> 
<div2 type="part" n="1" id="d5"> 

<milestone unit="speech" n="Kuma1-1"/>  
<sp> 
<speaker>Priest</speaker> 
<p> 
Where shall I rest, wandering weary of the world? 
<milestone unit="speech" n="Kuma1-2"/> 
I am a city-bred priest, 
I have not  
 
 
<pb n="68"/>  
seen the east counties, and I've a mind to go there. 
<milestone unit="speech" n="Kuma1-3"/> 
Crossing the hills, I 
look on the lake of Omi, on the woods of Awatsu. Going over the long 
bridge at Seta, I rested a night at Noji, and another at Shinohara, and at 
the dawn I came to the green field, Awono in Miwo. I now pass Akasaka at 
sunset. 
</p> 
</sp> 

<milestone unit="speech" n="Kuma1-4"/> 
<sp> 
<speaker>Shite</speaker> 
<stage> 
in the form of an old priest 
</stage> 
 
<p> 
I could tell that priest a thing or two. 
</p> 
</sp> 
 
<milestone unit="speech" n="Kuma1-5"/> 
<sp> 
<speaker>Priest</speaker> 
<p> 
Do you mean me? What is it? 
</p> 
</sp> 

<milestone unit="speech" n="Kuma1-6"/>  
<sp> 
<speaker>Shite</speaker> 
<p> 
A certain man died on this day. I ask you to pray for him. 
</p> 
</sp> 
 
<milestone unit="speech" n="Kuma1-7"/> 
<sp> 
<speaker>Priest</speaker> 
<p> 
All right; but whom shall I pray for? 
</p> 
</sp> 

<milestone unit="speech" n="Kuma1-8"/>  
<sp> 
<speaker>Shite</speaker> 
<p> 
I will not tell you his name, but his grave lies in the green field beyond 
that tall pine tree. He cannot enter the gates of Paradise, and so I ask 
you to pray. 
</p> 
</sp> 
 
 
<pb n="69"/>  
<milestone unit="speech" n="Kuma1-9"/> 
<sp> 
<speaker>Priest</speaker> 
<p> 
But I do not think it is right for me to pray unless you tell me his name. 
</p> 
</sp> 
 
<milestone unit="speech" n="Kuma1-10"/> 
<sp> 
<speaker>Shite</speaker> 
<p> 
No, no; you can pray the prayer, Ho kai shujo biodo ri aku; that would do. 
</p> 
</sp> 

<milestone unit="speech" n="Kuma1-11"/>  
<sp> 
<speaker>Priest</speaker> 
 
<stage> 
praying 
</stage> 
 
<p> 
Unto all mortals let there be equal grace, to pass from this life of agony 
by the gates of death into law; into the peaceful kingdom. 
</p> 
</sp> 

<milestone unit="speech" n="Kuma1-12"/>  
<sp> 
<speaker>Shite</speaker> 
 
<stage> 
saying first a word or two 
</stage> 
 
<p> 
If you pray for him,   &mdash;    
</p> 
</sp> 

<milestone unit="speech" n="Kuma1-13"/>  
<sp> 
<speaker>Chorus</speaker> 
 
<stage> 
continuing the sentence 
</stage> 
 
<p> 
   &mdash;   If you pray with the prayer of "Exeat" he will be thankful, and you 
need not then know his name. They say that prayer can be heard for even 
the grass and the plants, for even the sand and the soil here; and they 
will surely hear it, if you pray for an unknown man. 
 
</p> 
</sp> 
 
 
<pb n="70"/>  
<milestone unit="speech" n="Kuma1-14"/> 
<sp> 
<speaker>Shite</speaker> 
<p> 
Will you come in? This is my cottage. 
</p> 
</sp> 
 
<milestone unit="speech" n="Kuma1-15"/> 
<sp> 
<speaker>Priest</speaker> 
<p> 
This is your house? Very well, I will hold the service in your house; but 
I see no picture of Buddha nor any wooden image in this 
cottage   &mdash;   nothing but a long spear on one wall and an iron stick in 
place of a priest's wand, and many arrows. What are these for? 
</p> 
</sp> 
 
<milestone unit="speech" n="Kuma1-16"/> 
<sp> 
<speaker>Shite</speaker> 
 
<stage> 
thinking 
</stage> 
 
<p> 
Yes, this priest is still in the first stage of faith. 
 
<stage> 
Aloud. 
</stage> 
 
As you see, there are many villages here: Tarui, Awohaka, and Akasaka. But 
the tall grass of Awo-no-gahara grows round the roads between them, and 
the forest is thick at Koyasu and Awohaka, and many robbers come out under 
the rains. They attack the baggage on horseback, and take the clothing of 
maids and servants who pass here. So I go out with his spear. 
</p> 
</sp> 
 
<milestone unit="speech" n="Kuma1-17"/> 
<sp> 
<speaker>Priest</speaker> 
<p> 
That's very fine, isn't it ? 
</p> 
</sp> 
 
 
<pb n="71"/>  
<milestone unit="speech" n="Kuma1-18"/> 
<sp> 
<speaker>Chorus</speaker> 
<p> 
You will think it very strange for a priest to do this, but even Buddha 
has the sharp sword of Mida, and Aizen Miowo has arrows, and Tamon, taking 
his long spear, throws down the evil spirits. 
</p> 
</sp> 

<milestone unit="speech" n="Kuma1-19"/>  
<sp> 
<speaker>Shite</speaker> 
<p> 
The deep love   &mdash;    
</p> 
</sp> 

<milestone unit="speech" n="Kuma1-20"/>  
<sp> 
<speaker>Chorus</speaker> 
<p> 
   &mdash;   is excellent. Good feeling and keeping order are much more 
excellent than the love of Bosatsu. "I think of these matters and know 
little of anything else. It is from my own heart that I am lost, 
wandering. But if I begin talking I shall keep on talking until dawn. Go 
to bed, good father, I will sleep too." 
</p> 
 
<p> 
He seemed to be going to his bedroom, but suddenly his figure disappeared, 
and the cottage became a field of grass. The priest passes the night under 
the pine trees. 
</p> 
</sp> 

<milestone unit="speech" n="Kuma2-1"/> 
<sp> 
<speaker>Priest</speaker> 
<p> 
I cannot sleep out the night. Perhaps if I held my service during the 
night under this pine tree   &mdash;    
</p> 
</sp> 
 
<stage> 
He begins his service for the dead man. 
</stage> 
 
 
<pb n="73"/>  
 
</div2><div2 type="part" n="2" id="d6"> 
<head>PART SECOND</head> 

<milestone unit="speech" n="Kuma2-2"/>  
<sp> 
<speaker>Second Shite</speaker> 
<p> 
There are winds in the east and south; the clouds are not calm in the 
west; and in the north the wind of the dark evening blusters; and under 
the shade of the mountain   &mdash;    
</p> 
</sp> 

<milestone unit="speech" n="Kuma2-3"/>  
<sp> 
<speaker>Chorus</speaker> 
<p> 
   &mdash;   there is a rustling of boughs and leaves. 
</p> 
</sp> 

<milestone unit="speech" n="Kuma2-4"/>  
<sp> 
<speaker>Second Shite</speaker> 
<p> 
Perhaps there will be moonshine to-night, but the clouds veil the sky; the 
moon will not break up their shadow. "Have at them!" "Ho, there!" "Dash 
in!" That is the way I would shout, calling and ordering my men before and 
behind, my bowmen and horsemen. I plundered men of their treasure, that 
was my work in the world, and now I must go on; it is sorry work for a 
spirit. 
</p> 
</sp> 

<milestone unit="speech" n="Kuma2-5"/>  
<sp> 
<speaker>Priest</speaker> 
<p> 
Are you Kumasaka Chohan? Tell me the tale of your years. 
</p> 
</sp> 
 
 
<pb n="73"/>  
<milestone unit="speech" n="Kuma2-6"/> 
<sp> 
<speaker>Second Shite</speaker> 
 
<stage> 
now known as Kumasaka 
</stage> 
 
<p> 
There were great merchants in Sanjo, Yoshitsugu, and Nobutaka; they 
collected treasure each year; they sent rich goods up to Oku. It was then 
I assailed their trains. Would you know what men were with me? 
</p> 
</sp> 
 
<milestone unit="speech" n="Kuma2-7"/> 
<sp> 
<speaker>Priest</speaker> 
<p> 
Tell me the chief men; were they from many a province? 
</p> 
</sp> 
 
<milestone unit="speech" n="Kuma2-8"/> 
<sp> 
<speaker>Kumasaka</speaker> 
<p> 
There was Kakusho of Kawachi, 
<milestone unit="speech" n="Kuma2-9"/> 
there were the two brothers Suriharitaro; 
they have no rivals in fencing. 
<ref target="n73.1">[1]</ref> 
</p> 
</sp> 

<milestone unit="speech" n="Kuma2-10"/>  
<sp> 
<speaker>Priest</speaker> 
<p> 
What chiefs came to you from the city? 
</p> 
</sp> 
 
<milestone unit="speech" n="Kuma2-11"/> 
<sp> 
<speaker>Kumasaka</speaker> 
<p> 
Emon of Sanjo, Kozari of Mibu. 
</p> 
</sp> 
 
<milestone unit="speech" n="Kuma2-12"/> 
<sp> 
<speaker>Priest</speaker> 
<p> 
In the fighting with torches and in m&ecirc;l&eacute;e   &mdash;    
</p> 
</sp> 
 
 
<pb n="74"/>  
<milestone unit="speech" n="Kuma2-13"/> 
<sp> 
<speaker>Kumasaka</speaker> 
<p> 
   &mdash;   they had no equals. 
</p> 
</sp> 
 
<milestone unit="speech" n="Kuma2-14"/> 
<sp> 
<speaker>Priest</speaker> 
<p> 
In northern Hakoku? 
</p> 
</sp> 

<milestone unit="speech" n="Kuma2-15"/>  
<sp> 
<speaker>Kumasaka</speaker> 
<p> 
Were Aso no Matsuwaka and Mikune no Kuro. 
</p> 
</sp> 
 
<milestone unit="speech" n="Kuma2-16"/> 
<sp> 
<speaker>Priest</speaker> 
<p> 
In Kaga? 
</p> 
</sp> 

<milestone unit="speech" n="Kuma2-17"/>  
<sp> 
<speaker>Kumasaka</speaker> 
<p> 
No, Chohan was the head there. There were seventy comrades who were very 
strong and skilful. 
</p> 
</sp> 

<milestone unit="speech" n="Kuma2-18"/>  
<sp> 
<speaker>Chorus</speaker> 
<p> 
While Yoshitsugu was going along in the fields and on the mountains, we 
set many spies to take him. 
</p> 
</sp> 

<milestone unit="speech" n="Kuma2-19"/>  
<sp> 
<speaker>Kumasaka</speaker> 
<p> 
Let us say that he is come to the village of Akasaka. This is the best 
place to attack him. There are many ways to escape if we are defeated, and 
he has invited many guests and has had a great feast at the inn. 
</p> 
</sp> 
 
 
<pb n="75"/>  
<milestone unit="speech" n="Kuma2-20"/> 
<sp> 
<speaker>Priest</speaker> 
<p> 
When the night was advanced the brothers Yoshitsugu and Nobutaka fell 
asleep. 
</p> 
</sp> 
 
<milestone unit="speech" n="Kuma2-21"/> 
<sp> 
<speaker>Kumasaka</speaker> 
<p> 
But there was a small boy with keen eyes, about sixteen or seventeen years 
old, and he was looking through a little hole in the partition, alert to 
the slightest noise. 
</p> 
</sp> 

<milestone unit="speech" n="Kuma2-22"/>  
<sp> 
<speaker>Priest</speaker> 
<p> 
He did not sleep even a wink. 
</p> 
</sp> 

<milestone unit="speech" n="Kuma2-23"/>  
<sp> 
<speaker>Kumasaka</speaker> 
<p> 
We did not know it was Ushiwaka. 
</p> 
</sp> 

<milestone unit="speech" n="Kuma2-24"/>  
<sp> 
<speaker>Priest</speaker> 
<p> 
It was fate. 
</p> 
</sp> 

<milestone unit="speech" n="Kuma2-25"/>  
<sp> 
<speaker>Kumasaka</speaker> 
<p> 
The hour had come. 
</p> 
</sp> 

<milestone unit="speech" n="Kuma2-26"/>  
<sp> 
<speaker>Priest</speaker> 
<p> 
Be quick! 
</p> 
</sp> 

<milestone unit="speech" n="Kuma2-27"/>  
<sp> 
<speaker>Kumasaka</speaker> 
<p> 
Have at them! 
</p> 
</sp> 
 
 
<pb n="76"/>  

<milestone unit="speech" n="Kuma2-28"/> 
<sp> 
<speaker>Chorus</speaker> 
 
<stage> 
describing the original combat, now symbolized in the dance 
</stage> 
 
<p> 
At this word they rushed in, one after another. They seized the torches; 
it seemed as if gods could not face them. Ushiwaka stood unafraid; he 
seized a small halberd and fought like a lion in earnest, like a tiger 
rushing, like a bird swooping. He fought so cleverly that he felled the 
thirteen who opposed him; many were wounded besides. They fled without 
swords or arrows. Then Kumasaka said, "Are you the devil? Is it a god who 
has struck down these men with such ease? Perhaps you are not a man. 
However, dead men take no plunder, and I'd rather leave this truck of 
Yoshitsugu's than my corpse." So he took his long spear and was about to 
make off   &mdash;    
</p> 
</sp> 

<milestone unit="speech" n="Kuma2-29"/>  
<sp> 
<speaker>Kumasaka</speaker> 
<p> 
   &mdash;   But Kumasaka thought   &mdash;    
</p> 
</sp> 
 
<milestone unit="speech" n="Kuma2-30"/> 
<sp> 
<speaker>Chorus</speaker> 
<stage> 
taking it up 
</stage> 
 
<p> 
   &mdash;   What can he do, that young chap, if I ply my secret arts freely? Be 
he god or devil, I will grasp him and grind him. I will offer  
 
 
<pb n="77"/>  
his body as sacrifice to those whom he has slain. So he drew back, and 
holding his long spear against his side, he hid himself behind the door 
and stared at the young lad. Ushiwaka beheld him, and holding his bill at 
his side, he crouched at a little distance. Kumasaka waited likewise. They 
both waited, alertly; then Kumasaka stepped forth swiftly with his left 
foot, and struck out with the long spear. It would have run through an 
iron wall. Ushiwaka parried it lightly, swept it away, left volted. 
Kumasaka followed and again lunged out with the spear, and Ushiwaka 
parried the spear-blade quite lightly. Then Kumasaka turned the edge of 
his spear-blade towards Ushiwaka and slashed at him, and Ushiwaka leaped 
to the right. Kumasaka lifted his spear and the two weapons were twisted 
together. Ushiwaka drew back his blade. Kumasaka swung with his spear. 
Ushiwaka led up and stepped in shadow. 
</p> 
<milestone unit="speech" n="Kuma2-31"/>  
<p> 
Kumasaka tried to find him, and Ushiwaka slit through the back-chink of 
his armour; this seemed the end of his course, and he was wroth to be 
slain by such a young boy. 
</p> 
</sp> 

<milestone unit="speech" n="Kuma2-32"/>  
<sp> 
<speaker>Kumasaka</speaker> 
<p> 
Slowly the wound   &mdash;    
</p> 
</sp> 
 
 
<pb n="78"/>  
<milestone unit="speech" n="Kuma2-33"/> 
<sp> 
<speaker>Chorus</speaker> 
<p> 
   &mdash;   seemed to pierce; his heart failed; weakness o'ercame him. 
</p> 
</sp> 

<milestone unit="speech" n="Kuma2-34"/>  
<sp> 
<speaker>Kumasaka</speaker> 
<p> 
At the foot of this pine tree   &mdash;    
</p> 
</sp> 

<milestone unit="speech" n="Kuma2-35"/>  
<sp> 
<speaker>Chorus</speaker> 
<p> 
   &mdash;   he vanished like a dew. 
</p> 
 
<p> 
And so saying, he disappeared among the shades of the pine tree at 
Akasaka, and night fell. 
</p> 
</sp> 
</div2> 
</div1> 
</body> 
 
<back id="d7"> 
<div1 type="notes" id="d8"> 
<head>Footnotes</head> 
<note id="n73.1"><seg type="note-symbol">[1:</seg> <p>fencing] "Omoteuchi," face-to-face attack.</p></note> 
</div1> 
</back> 
 
</text> 
</TEI.2> 
 
 
