<?xml version="1.0"?>

<?dlps id="PreCell"?>
<?dlps page-images="none" figure-images="no"?>
<?dlps transcription="other"?>

<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/tei-p4/tei2.dtd" [
<!ENTITY % POSTKB "INCLUDE">
<!ENTITY % TEI.extensions.ent SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.ent">
<!ENTITY % TEI.extensions.dtd SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.dtd">
<!ENTITY % ISOnum SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/charent/iso-num.ent"> %ISOnum;
<!ENTITY % ISOlat1 SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/charent/iso-lat1.ent"> %ISOlat1;
<!ENTITY % ISOpub SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/charent/iso-pub.ent"> %ISOpub;

]>
 
<TEI.2 id="PreCell"> 
<teiHeader type="migrated" creator="Etext">
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title type="main">In a Cellar</title>
<title type="sort">in a cellar</title>
<author>Prescott, Harriet E.</author>
<respStmt>
<resp>Creation of machine-readable version:</resp> 
<name>Judy Boss ( )</name> 
<resp>Conversion to TEI.2-conformant markup:</resp>  
<name>University of Virginia Library Electronic Text Center</name>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt> 
<extent>ca. <num type="kilobytes">88</num> kilobytes</extent> 
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>University of Virginia Library</publisher>
<pubPlace>Charlottesville, Virginia</pubPlace> 
<idno type="ETC">PreCell</idno> 
<date value="1995">1995</date>
<availability status="public">
<p n="copyright">Copyright &copy; 1995 by the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia</p>
<p n="access">Publicly accessible</p>
</availability>
<idno type="uva-pid">uva-lib:476335</idno>
</publicationStmt>
<seriesStmt>
<title>University of Virginia Library, Text collection</title>
<idno type="uva-set">UVA-LIB-Text</idno>
</seriesStmt> 
<sourceDesc>
<biblFull>
<titleStmt>
<title type="main">In a Cellar</title>
<title type="sort">in a cellar</title>
<author>Harriet Prescott</author>
</titleStmt> 
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>Atlantic Monthly</publisher> 
<pubPlace>Boston</pubPlace> 
<date value="1859">1859</date>
</publicationStmt> 
<seriesStmt>
<p>3</p>
</seriesStmt> 
<notesStmt>
<note>
<p>Prescott, Harriet.  "In a Cellar."  <hi rend="italic">Atlantic Monthly</hi>  
3 (1859): 151-172.</p>
</note>
</notesStmt>
</biblFull>
</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc> 
<encodingDesc>
<projectDesc>
<p>Prepared for the University of Virginia Library Electronic Text Center</p>
</projectDesc> 
<editorialDecl>
<p>All quotation marks retained as data</p> 
<p>All unambiguous end-of-line hyphens have been removed, and the 
trailing part of a word has been joined to the preceding line.</p> 
<p id="ETC">Keywords in the header are a local Electronic Text Center scheme  
to aid in establishing analytical groupings</p>
</editorialDecl> 
<refsDecl>
<p>ID elements are given for each page element and are composed of the text's 
unique cryptogram and the given page number, as in AusEmma1 for page one of  
Jane Austen's Emma.</p>
</refsDecl>
</encodingDesc> 
<profileDesc>
<creation>
<date value="1859">1859</date>
</creation> 
<langUsage>
<language id="eng" usage="main">English</language>
</langUsage> 
<textClass>
<keywords>
<term>fiction ; prose</term> 
<term>Women Writers</term>
</keywords>
</textClass>
</profileDesc> 
<revisionDesc>
<change>
<date value="1995-08">August 1995</date> 
<respStmt>
<resp>corrector</resp> 
<name>Jamie L Spriggs, Electronic Text Center, University of Virginia</name>
</respStmt> 
<item>Added header, Tagged with TEI.2-compatible SGML, Parsed against "teilite" dtd</item>
</change> 
<change>
<date value="2005-07">July 2005</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>Corrector</resp>
<name>John Ivor Carlson</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Converted SGML to XML and/or corrected tagging.</item>
</change>
<change>
<date value="2007-09">September 2007</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>Migration</resp>
<name>Ethan Gruber, University of Virginia Library</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Converted XML markup from TEI Lite to uva-dl-tei (TEI P4 with local customizations).</item>
</change>
<change>
<date value="2008-01">January 2008</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>Migration</resp>
<name>Greg Murray, University of Virginia Library</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Programmatically updated TEI header markup (but not header content) for minimal compliance with current QA requirements.</item>
</change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader> 
 
<text id="d1">  
<body id="d2"> 
<div1 type="chapter" n="1" id="d3"><pb n="151"/>   
<head>I.</head> 
 
<p>IT was the day of Madame de St. Cyr's dinner, an event I never 
missed; for, the mistress of a mansion in the Faubourg St. Germain, 
there still lingered about her the exquisite grace and good-breeding peculiar to the old <hi rend="italic">regime</hi>, that insensibly 
communicates itself to the guests till they move in an atmosphere 
of ease that constitutes the charm of home.  One was always sure of 
meeting desirable and well-assorted people here, and a <hi rend="italic"> contre-temps</hi> was impossible.  Moreover, the house was not at the command 
of all; and Madame de St. Cyr, with the daring strength which, when 
found in a woman at all, should, to be endurable, be combined with 
a sweet but firm restraint, rode rough-shod over the <hi rend="italic">parvenus</hi> 
of the Empire, and was resolute enough to insulate herself even 
among the old <hi rend="italic">noblesse</hi>, who, as all the world knows, insulate 
themselves from the rest of France.  There were rare qualities in 
this woman, and were I to have selected one who with an even hand 
should carry a snuffy candle through a magazine of powder, my 
choice would have devolved upon her; and she would have done it. 
</p><p>I often looked, and not unsuccessfully, to discern what 
heritage her daughter had in these little affairs.  Indeed, to one 
like myself Delphine presented the worthier study.  She wanted the 
airy charm of manner, the suavity and tenderness of her mother,&mdash;a 
deficiency easily to be pardoned in one of such delicate and 
extraordinary beauty.  And perhaps her face was the truest index of 
her mind; not that it ever transparently displayed a genuine 
emotion,&mdash;Delphine was too well-bred for that,&mdash;but the outline of 
her features had a keen, regular precision, as if cut in a gem.  
Her exquisite color seldom varied, her eyes were like blue steel, 
she was statue-like and stony.  But had one paused there, 
pronouncing her hard and impassive, he had committed an error.  She 
had no great capability for passion, but she was not to be 
deceived; one metallic flash of her eye would cut like a sword 
through the whole mesh of entanglements with which you had 
surrounded her; and frequently, when alone with her, you perceived 
cool recesses in her nature, sparkling and pleasant, which 
jealously guarded themselves from a nearer approach.  She was 
infinitely <hi rend="italic">spirituelle</hi>; compared to her, Madame herself was 
heavy. 
</p><p>At the first I had seen that Delphine must be the wife of a 
diplomate.  What <pb n="152"/>  diplomate?  For a time asking myself the 
question seriously, I decided in the negative, which did not, 
however, prevent Delphine from fulfilling her destiny, since there 
were others.  She was, after all, like a draught of rich old wine, 
all fire and sweetness.  These things were not generally seen in 
her; I was more favored than many; and I looked at her with 
pitiless perspicacious eyes.  Nevertheless, I had not the least 
advantage; it was, in fact, between us, diamond cut diamond,&mdash; 
which, oddly enough, brings me back to my story. 
</p><p>Some years previously, I had been sent on a special mission to 
the government at Paris, and having finally executed it, I resigned 
the post, and resolved to make my residence there, since it is the 
only place on earth where one can live.  Every morning I half 
expect to see the country, beyond the city, white with an 
encampment of the nations, who, having peacefully flocked there 
over night, wait till the Rue St. Honore shall run out and greet 
them.  It surprises me, sometimes, that those pretending to 
civilization are content to remain at a distance.  What experience 
have they of life,&mdash;not to mention gayety and pleasure, but of the 
great purpose of life,&mdash;society?  Man evidently is gregarious; 
Fourier's fables are founded on fact; we are nothing without our 
opposites, our fellows, our lights and shadows, colors, relations, 
combinations, our <hi rend="italic"> point d'appui</hi>, and our angle of sight.  An 
isolated man is immensurable; he is also unpicturesque, unnatural, 
untrue.  He is no longer the lord of Nature, animal and vegetable,--but Nature is the lord of him; the trees, skies, flowers, 
predominate, and he is in as bad taste as green and blue, or as an 
oyster in a vase of roses.  The race swings naturally to clusters.  
It being admitted, then, that society is our normal state, where is 
it to be obtained in such perfection as at Paris?  Show me the 
urbanity, the generosity in trifles, better than sacrifice, the 
incuriousness and freedom, the grace, and wit, and honor, that will 
equal such as I find here.  Morality,&mdash;we were not speaking of it,--the intrusion is unnecessary; must that word with Anglo-Saxon 
pertinacity dog us round the world?  A hollow mask, which Vice now 
and then lifts for a breath of air, I grant you this state may be 
called; but since I find the vice elsewhere, countenance my 
preference for the accompanying mask.  But even this is vanishing; 
such drawing-rooms as Mme. de St. Cyr's are less and less frequent.  
Yet, though the delightful spell of the last century daily 
dissipates itself, and we are not now what we were twenty years 
ago, still Paris is, and will be till the end of time, for a 
cosmopolitan, the pivot on which the world revolves. 
</p><p>It was, then, as I have said, the day of Mme. de St. Cyr's 
dinner.  Punctually at the hour, I presented myself,&mdash;for I have 
always esteemed it the least courtesy which a guest can render, 
that he should not cool his hostess's dinner. 
</p><p>The usual choice company waited.  There was the Marquis of G., 
the ambassador from home, Col. Leigh, an <hi rend="italic">attache</hi> of that 
embassy, the Spanish and Belgian ministers,&mdash;all of whom, with 
myself, completed a diplomatic circle.  There were also wits and 
artists, but no ladies whose beauty exceeded that of the St. Cyrs.  
With nearly all of this assemblage I held certain relations, so 
that I was immediately at ease.  G. was the only one whom, perhaps, 
I would rather not have met, although we were the best of friends.  
They awaited but one, the Baron Stahl.  Meanwhile Delphine stood 
coolly taking the measurement of the Marquis of G., while her 
mother entertained one and another guest with a low-toned flattery, 
gentle interest, or lively narration, as the case might demand. 
</p><p>In a country where a <hi rend="italic"> coup d'etat</hi> was as easily given as a 
box on the ear, we all attentively watched for the arrival of one 
who had been sent from a neighboring empire to negotiate a loan for 
the tottering throne of this.  Nor was expectation kept long on 
guard.  In a moment, "His Excellency, the Baron Stahl!" was 
announced. <pb n="153"/>  
</p><p>The exaggeration of his low bow to Mme. de St. Cyr, the gleam 
askance of his black eye, the absurd simplicity of his dress, did 
not particularly please me.  A low forehead, straight black brows, 
a beardless cheek with a fine color which gave him a fictitiously 
youthful appearance, were the most striking traits of his face; his 
person was not to be found fault with; but he boldly evinced his 
admiration for Delphine, and with a wicked eye. 
</p><p>As we were introduced, he assured me, in pure English, that he 
had pleasure in making the acquaintance of a gentleman whose 
services were so distinguished. 
</p><p>I, in turn, assured him of my pleasure in meeting a gentleman 
who appreciated them. 
</p><p>I had arrived at the house of Mme. de St. Cyr with a load on 
my mind, which for four weeks had weighed there; but before I thus 
spoke, it was lifted and gone.  I had seen the Baron Stahl before, 
although not previously aware of it; and now, as he bowed, talked 
my native tongue so smoothly, drew a glove over the handsome hand 
upon whose first finger shone the only incongruity of his attire, 
a broad gold ring, holding a gaudy red stone,&mdash;as he stood smiling 
and expectant before me, a sudden chain of events flashed through 
my mind, an instantaneous heat, like lightning, welded them into 
logic.  A great problem was resolved.  For a second, the breath 
seemed snatched from my lips; the next, a lighter, freer man never 
trod in diplomatic shoes. 
</p><p>I really beg your pardon,&mdash;but perhaps from long usage, it has 
become impossible for me to tell a straight story.  It is 
absolutely necessary to inform you of events already transpired. 
</p><p>In the first place, then, I, at this time, possessed a valet, 
the pink of valets, an Englishman,&mdash;and not the less valuable to me 
in a foreign capital, that, notwithstanding his long residence, he 
was utterly unable to speak one word of French intelligibly.  
Reading and writing it readily, his thick tongue could master 
scarcely a syllable.  The adroitness and perfection with which he 
performed the duties of his place were unsurpassable.  To a certain 
extent I was obliged to admit him into my confidence; I was not at 
all in his.  In dexterity and dispatch he equalled the 
advertisements.  He never condescended to don my cast-off apparel, 
but, disposing of it, always arrayed himself in plain but 
gentlemanly garments.  These do not complete the list of Hay's 
capabilities.  He speculated.  Respectable tenements in London 
called him landlord; in the funds certain sums lay to his order; to 
a profitable farm in Hants he contemplated future retirement; and 
passing upon the Bourse, I have received a grave bow, and have left 
him in conversation with an eminent capitalist respecting consols, 
drafts, exchange, and other erudite mysteries, where I yet find 
myself in the A B C.  Thus not only was my valet a free-born 
Briton, but a landed proprietor.  If the Rothschilds blacked your 
boots or shaved your chin, your emotions might be akin to mine.  
When this man, who had an interest in the India traders, brought 
the hot water into my dressing-room, of a morning, the Antipodes 
were tributary to me; to what extent might any little irascibility 
of mine drive a depression in the market! and I knew, as he brushed 
my hat, whether stocks rose or fell.  In one respect, I was 
essentially like our Saxon ancestors,&mdash;my servant was a villain.  
If I had been merely a civilian, in any purely private capacity, 
having leisure to attend to personal concerns in the midst of the 
delicate specialties intrusted to me from the cabinet at home, the 
possession of so inestimable a valet might have bullied me beyond 
endurance.  As it was, I found it rather agreeable than otherwise.  
He was tacitly my secretary of finance. 
</p><p>Several years ago, a diamond of wonderful size and beauty, 
having wandered from the East, fell into certain imperial coffers 
among our Continental highborn; and at the same time some 
extraordinary intelligence, essential to the existence, so to 
speak, of that government, reached a <pb n="154"/>  person there who fixed 
as its price this diamond.  After a while he obtained it, but, 
judging that prudence lay in departure, took it to England, where 
it was purchased for an enormous sum by the Duke of &mdash;, as he 
will remain an unknown quantity, let us say X.  There are probably 
not a dozen such diamonds in the world,&mdash;certainly not three in 
England.  It rejoiced in such flowery appellatives as the Sea of 
Splendor, the Moon of Milk; and, of course, those who had been 
scarcely better than jewed out of it were determined to obtain it 
again at all hazards;&mdash;they were never famous for scrupulosity.  
The Duke of X. was aware of this, and, for a time, the gem had lain 
idle, its glory muffled in a casket; but finally, on some grand 
occasion, a few months prior to the period of which I have spoken 
above, it was determined to set it in the Duchess's coronet.  
Accordingly, one day, it was given by her son, the Marquis of G., 
into the hands of their solicitor, who should deliver it to her 
Grace's jeweller.  It lay in a small shagreen case, and, before the 
Marquis left, the solicitor placed the case in a flat leathern box, 
where lay a chain of most singular workmanship, the clasp of which 
was deranged.  This chain was very broad, of a style known as the 
brick-work, but every brick was a tiny gem, set in a delicate 
filigree linked with the next, and the whole rainbowed lustrousness 
moving at your will, like the scales of some gorgeous Egyptian 
serpent;&mdash;the solicitor was to take this also to the jeweller.  
Having laid the box in his private desk, Ulster, his confidential 
clerk, locked it, while he bowed the Marquis down.  Returning 
immediately, the solicitor took the flat box and drove to the 
jeweller's.  He found the latter so crowded with customers, it 
being the fashionable hour, as to be unable to attend to him; he, 
however, took the solicitor into his inner room, a dark fire-proof 
place, and there quickly deposited the box within a safe, which 
stood inside another, like a Japanese puzzle, and the solicitor, 
seeing the doors double-locked and secured, departed; the other 
promising to attend to the matter on the morrow. 
</p><p>Early the next morning, the jeweller entered his dark room, 
and proceeded to unlock the safe.  This being concluded, and the 
inner one also thrown open, he found the box in a last and 
entirely, as he had always believed, secret compartment.  Anxious 
to see this wonder, this Eye of Morning, and Heart of Day, he 
eagerly loosened the band and unclosed the box.  It was empty.  
There was no chain there; the diamond was missing.  The sweat 
streamed from his forehead, his clothes were saturated, he believed 
himself the victim of a delusion.  Calling an assistant, every 
article and nook in the dark room was examined.  At last, in an 
extremity of despair, he sent for the solicitor, who arrived in a 
breath.  The jeweller's alarm hardly equalled that of the other.  
In his sudden dismay, he at first forgot the circumstances and 
dates relating to the affair; afterward was doubtful.  The Marquis 
of G. was summoned, the police called in, the jeweller given into 
custody.  Every breath the solicitor continued to draw only built 
up his ruin.  He swallowed laudanum, but, by making it an overdoes, 
frustrated his own design.  He was assured, on his recovery, that 
no suspicion attached to him.  The jeweller now asseverated that 
the diamond had never been given to him; but though this was 
strictly true, the jeweller had, nevertheless, committed perjury.  
Of course, whoever had the stone would not attempt to dispose of it 
at present, and, though communications were opened with the general 
European police, there was very little to work upon.  But by means 
of this last step the former possessors became aware of its loss, 
and I make no doubt had their agents abroad immediately. 
</p><p>Meanwhile, the case hung here, complicated and tantalizing, 
when one morning I woke in London.  No sooner had G. heard of my 
arrival than he called, and, relating the affair, requested my 
assistance.  I confess myself to have been interested,&mdash;foolishly 
so, I thought after-<pb n="155"/> ward; but we all have our weaknesses, 
and diamonds were mine.  In company with the Marquis, I waited upon 
the solicitor, who entered into the few details minutely, calling 
frequently upon Ulster, a young fresh-looking man, for 
corroboration.  We then drove to the jeweller's new quarters, took 
him, under charge of the officers, to his place of business, where 
he nervously showed me every point that could bear upon the 
subject, and ended by exclaiming, that he was ruined, and all for 
a stone he had never seen.  I sat quietly for a few moments.  It 
stood, then, thus:&mdash;G. had given the thing to the solicitor, seen 
it put into the box, seen the box put into the desk; but while the 
confidential clerk, Ulster, locked the desk, the solicitor saw the 
Marquis to the door,&mdash;returning, took the box, without opening it 
again, to the jeweller, who, in the hurry, shut it up in his safe, 
also without opening it.  The case was perfectly clear.  These 
mysterious things are always so simple!  You know now, as well as 
I, who took the diamond. 
</p><p>I did not choose to volunteer, but assented, on being desired.  
The police and I were old friends; they had so often assisted me, 
that I was not afraid to pay them in kind, and accordingly agreed 
to take charge of the case, still retaining their aid, should I 
require it.  The jeweller was now restored to his occupation, 
although still subjected to a rigid surveillance, and I instituted 
inquiries into the recent movements of the young man Ulster.  The 
case seemed to me to have been very blindly conducted.  But, though 
all that was brought to light concerning him in London was 
perfectly fair and aboveboard, it was discovered that not long 
since he had visited Paris,&mdash;on the solicitor's business, of 
course, but gaining thereby an opportunity to transact any little 
affairs of his own.  This was fortunate; for if any one could do 
anything in Paris, it was myself. 
</p><p>It is not often that I act as a detective.  But one 
homogeneous to every situation could hardly play a pleasanter part 
for once.  I have thought that our great masters in theory and 
practice, Machiavel and Talleyrand, were hardly more, on a large 
scale. 
</p><p>I was about to return to Paris, but resolved to call 
previously on the solicitor again.  He welcomed me warmly, although 
my suspicions had not been imparted to him, and, with a more 
cheerful heart than had lately been habitual to him, entered into 
an animated conversation respecting the great case of Biter <hi rend="italic"> v.</hi> 
Bit, then absorbing so much of the public attention, frequently 
addressing Ulster, whose remarks were always pertinent, brief, and 
clear.  As I sat actively discussing the topic, feeling no more 
interest in it than in the end of that cigar I just cut off, and 
noting exactly every look and motion of the unfortunate youth, I 
recollect the curious sentiment that filled me regarding him.  What 
injury had he done me, that I should pursue him with punishment?  
Me?  I am, and every individual is, integral with the commonwealth.  
It was the commonwealth he had injured.  Yet, even then, why was I 
the one to administer justice?  Why not continue with my coffee in 
the morning, my kings and cabinets and national chess at noon, my 
opera at night, and let the poor devil go?  Why, but that justice 
is brought home to every member of society,&mdash;that naked duty 
requires no shirking of such responsibility,&mdash;that, had I failed 
here, the crime might, with reason, lie at my door and multiply, 
the criminal increase himself? 
</p><p>Very possibly you will not unite with me; but these little 
catechisms are, once in a while, indispensable, to vindicate one's 
course to one's-self. 
</p><p>This Ulster was a handsome youth;&mdash;the rogues have generally 
all the good looks.  There was nothing else remarkable about him 
but his quickness; he was perpetually on the alert; by constant 
activity, the rust was never allowed to collect on his faculties; 
his sharpness was distressing,&mdash;he appeared subject to a tense 
strain.  Now his quill scratched over the paper unconcernedly, 
while he could join us easily in his master's conversation; nothing
<pb n="156"/>   seemed to preoccupy him, or he held a mind open at every 
point.  It is pitiful to remember him that morning, sitting quiet, 
unconscious, and free, utterly in the hands of that mighty 
Inquisition, the Metropolitan Police, with its countless arms, its 
cells and myrmidons in the remotest corners of the Continent, at 
the mercy of so merciless a monster, and momently closer involved, 
like some poor prey round which a spider spins its bewildering web.  
It was also curious to observe the sudden suspicion that darkened 
his face at some innocent remark,&mdash;the quick shrinking and 
intrenched retirement, the manifest sting and rancor, as I touched 
his wound with a swift flash of my slender weapon and sheathed it 
again, and, after the thrust, the espionage, and the relief at 
believing it accidental.  He had many threads to gather up and 
hold;&mdash;little electric warnings along them must have been 
constantly shocking him.  He did that part well enough; it was a 
mistake, to begin with; he needed prudence.  At that time I owede 
this Ulster nothing; now, however, I owe him a grudge, for some of 
the most harassing hours of my life were occasioned me by him.  But 
I shall not cherish enmity on that account.  With so promising a 
beginning, he will graduate and take his degree from the loftiest 
altitude in his line.  Hemp is a narcotic; let it bring me 
forgetfulness. 
</p><p>In Paris I found it not difficult to trace such a person, 
since he was both foreign and unaccustomed.  It was ascertained 
that he had posted several letters.  A person of his description 
had been seen to drop a letter, the superscription of which had 
been read by the one who picked it up for him.  This superscription 
was the address of the very person who was likely to be the agent 
of the former possessors of the diamond, and had attracted 
attention.  After all,&mdash;you know the Secret Force,&mdash;it was not so 
impossible to imagine what this letter contained, despite of its 
cipher.  Such a person also had been met among the Jews, and at 
certain shops whose reputation was not of the clearest.  He had 
called once or twice on Mme. de St. Cyr, on business relative to a 
vineyard adjoining her chateau in the Gironde, which she had sold 
to a wine-merchant of England.  I found a zest in the affair, as I 
pursued it. 
</p><p>We were now fairly at sea, but before long I found we were 
likely to remain there; in fact, nothing of consequence eventuated.  
I began to regret having taken the affair from the hands in which 
I had found it, and one day, it being a gala or some insatiable 
saint's day, I was riding, perplexed with that and other matters, 
and paying small attention to the passing crowd.  I was vexed and 
mortified, and had fully decided to throw up the whole,&mdash;on such 
hairs do things hang,&mdash;when, suddenly turning a corner, my bridle-reins became entangled in the snaffle of another rider.  I loosened 
them abstractedly, and not till it was necessary to bow to my 
strange antagonist, on parting, did I glance up.  The person before 
me was evidently not accustomed to play the dandy; he wore his 
clothes ill, and his horse worse, and was uneasy in the saddle.  
The unmistakable air of the <hi rend="italic">gamin</hi> was apparent beneath the 
superficies of the gentleman.  Conspicuous on his costume, and 
wound like an order of merit upon his breast, glittered a chain, 
<hi rend="italic"> the</hi> chain,&mdash;each tiny brick-like gem spiked with a hundred sparks, 
and building a fabric of sturdy probabilities with the celerity of 
the genii in constructing Aladdin's palace.  There, a cable to haul 
up the treasure, was the chain;&mdash;where was the diamond?  I need not 
tell you how I followed this young friend, with what assiduity I 
kept him in sight, up and down, all day long, till, weary at last 
of his fine sport, as I certainly was of mine, he left his steed in 
stall and fared on his way a-foot.  Still pursuing, now I threaded 
quay and square, street and alley, till he disappeared in a small 
shop, in one of those dark crowded lanes leading eastward from the 
Pont Neuf, in the city.  It was the sign of a <hi rend="italic"> marchand des 
armures</hi>, 
<pb n="157"/>  and, having provided myself with those persuasive 
arguments a <hi rend="italic"> sergent-de-ville</hi> and a <hi rend="italic">gendarme</hi>, I entered. 
</p><p>A place more characteristic it would be impossible to find.  
Here were piled bows of every material, ash, and horn, and tougher 
fibres, with slackened strings, and among them peered a rusty 
clarion and battle-axe, while the quivers that should have 
accompanied lay in a distant corner, their arrows serving to pin 
long, dusty, torn banners to the wall.  Opposite the entrance, an 
archer in bronze hung on tiptoe, and levelled a steel bow, whose 
piercing <hi rend="italic">fleche</hi> seemed sparkling with impatience to spring from 
his finger and flesh itself in the heart of the intruder.  The 
hauberk and halberd, lance and casque, arquebuse and sword, were 
suspended in friendly congeries; and fragments of costly stuff 
swept from ceiling to floor, crushed and soiled by the heaps of 
rusty firelocks, cutlasses, and gauntlets thrown upon them.  In one 
place, a little antique bust was half hid in the folds of some 
pennon, still dyed with battle-stains; in another, scattered 
treasures of Dresden and Sevres brought the drawing-room into the 
campaign; and all around bivouacked rifles, whose polished barrels 
glittered full of death,&mdash;pistols, variously mounted, for an 
insurgent at the barricades, or fot a lost millionnaire at the 
gaming-table,&mdash;foils, with buttoned bluntness,&mdash;and rapiers, whose 
even edges were viewless, as if filed into air.  Destruction lay 
everywhere, at the command of the owner of this place, and, had he 
possessed a particle of vivacity, it would have been hazardous to 
bow beneath his doorway.  It did not, I must say, look like a place 
where I should find a diamond.  As the owner came forward, I 
determined on my plan of action. 
</p><p>"You have, Sir," I said, handing him a bit of paper, on which 
were scrawled some numbers, "a diamond in your possession, of such 
and so many carats, size, and value, belonging to the Duke of X., 
and left with you by an Englishman, Mr. Arthur Ulster.  You will 
deliver it to me, if you please." 
</p><p>"Monsieur!" exclaimed the man, lifting his hands, and 
surveying me with the widest eyes I ever saw.  "A diamond!  In my 
possession!  So immense a thing!  It is impossible.  I have not 
even seen one of the kind.  It is a mistake.  Jacques Noailles, the 
vender of jewels, <hi rend="italic">en gros</hi>, second door below, must be the man.  
One should perceive that my business is with arms, not diamonds.  
I have it not; it would ruin me." 
</p><p>Here he paused for a reply, but, meeting none, resumed.  "M. 
Arthur Ulster!&mdash;I have heard of no such person.  I never spoke with 
an Englishman.  Bah!  I detest them!  I have no dealings with them.  
I repeat, I have not your jewel.  Do you wish anything more of me?" 
</p><p>His vehemence only convinced me of the truth of my suspicions. 
</p><p>"These heroics are out of place," I answered.  "I demand the 
article in question." 
</p><p>"Monsieur doubts me?" he asked, with a rueful face,&mdash; 
"questions my word, which is incontrovertible?"  Here he clapped 
his hand upon a <hi rend="italic"> couteau-de-chasse</hi> lying near, but, appearing to 
think better of it, drew himself up, and, with a shower of nods 
flung at me, added, "I deny your accusation!"  I had not accused 
him. 
</p><p>"You are at too much pains to convict yourself.  I charge you 
with nothing," I said.  "But this diamond must be surrendered." 
</p><p>"Monsieur is mad!" he exclaimed, "mad! he dreams!  Do I look 
like one who possesses such a trophy?  Does my shop resemble a 
mind?  Look about!  See!  All that is here would not bring a 
hundredth of its price.  I beseech Monsieur to believe me; he has 
mistaken the number, or has been misinformed." 
</p><p>"We waste words.  I know this diamond is here, as well as a 
costly chain"&mdash; 
</p><p>"On my soul, on my life, on my honor," he cried, clasping his 
hands and turning up his eyes, "there is here nothing of the kind.  
I do not deal in gems.  A little silk, a few weapons, a curiosity, 
a <pb n="158"/>  nicknack, comprise my stock.  I have not the diamond.  I 
do not know the thing.  I am poor.  I am honest.  Suspicion 
destroys me!" 
</p><p>"As you will find, should I be longer troubled by your 
denials." 
</p><p>He was inflexible, and, having exhausted every artifice of 
innocence, wiped the tears from his eyes,&mdash;oh, these French! life 
is their theatre,&mdash;and remained quiet.  It was getting dark.  There 
was no gas in the place; but in the pause a distant street-lamp 
swung its light dimly round. 
</p><p>"Unless one desires to purchase, allow me to say that it is my 
hour for closing," he remarked, blandly, rubbing his black-bearded 
chin. 
</p><p>"My time is valuable," I returned.  "It is late and dark.  
When your shop-boy lights up"&mdash; 
</p><p>"Pardon,&mdash;we do not light." 
</p><p>"Permit me, then, to perform that office for you.  In this 
blaze you may perceive my companions, whom you have not appeared to 
recognize." 
</p><p>So saying, I scratched a match upon the floor, and, as the <hi rend="italic"> 
sergent-de-ville</hi> and the <hi rend="italic">gendarme</hi> advanced, threw the light of 
the blue spirt of sulphurous flame upon them.  In a moment more the 
match went out, and we remained in the demi-twilight of the distant 
lantern.  The <hi rend="italic"> marchand des armures</hi> stood petrified and aghast.  
Had he seen the imps of Satan in that instant, it could have had no 
greater effect. 
</p><p>"You have seen them?" I asked.  "I regret to inconvenience 
you; but unless this diamond is produced at once, my friends will 
put their seal on your goods, your property will be confiscated, 
yourself in a dungeon.  In other words, I allow you five minutes; 
at the close of that time you will have chosen between restitution 
and ruin." 
</p><p>He remained apparently lost in thought.  He was a big, stout 
man, and with one blow of his powerful fist could easily have 
settled me.  It was the last thing in his mind.  At length he 
lifted his head,&mdash;"Rosalie!" he called. 
</p><p>At the word, a light foot pattered along a stone floor within, 
and in a moment a little woman stood in an arch raised by two steps 
from our own level.  Carrying a candle, she descended and tripped 
toward him.  She was not pretty, but sprightly and keen, as the 
perpetual attrition of life must needs make her, and wore the 
everlasting grisette costume, which displays the neatest of ankles, 
and whose cap is more becoming than wreaths of garden millinery.  
I am too minute, I see, but it is second nature.  The two commenced 
a vigorous whispering amid sundry gestures and glances.  Suddenly 
the woman turned, and, laying the prettiest of little hands on my 
sleeve, said, with a winning smile,&mdash; 
</p><p>"Is it a crime of <hi rend="italic"> lese-majeste</hi>?" 
</p><p>This was a new idea, but might be useful. 
</p><p>"Not yet," I said; "two minutes more, and I will not answer 
for the consequence." 
</p><p>Other whispers ensued. 
</p><p>"Monsieur," said the man, leaning on one arm over the counter, 
and looking up in my face, with the most engaging frankness,&mdash;"it 
is true that I have such a diamond; but it is not mine.  It is left 
with me to be delivered to the Baron Stahl, who comes as an agent 
from his court for its purchase." 
</p><p>"Yes,&mdash;I know." 
</p><p>"He was to have paid me half a million francs,&mdash;not half its 
worth,&mdash;in trust for the person who left it, who is not M. Arthur 
Ulster, but Mme. de St. Cyr." 
</p><p>Madame de St. Cyr!  How under the sun&mdash;No,&mdash;it could not be 
possible.  The case stood as it stood before.  The rogue was in 
deeper water than I had thought; he had merely employed Mme. de St. 
Cyr.  I ran this over in my mind, while I said, "Yes." 
</p><p>"Now, Sir," I continued, "you will state the terms of this 
transaction." 
</p><p>"With pleasure.  For my trouble I was myself to receive 
patronage and five thousand francs.  The Baron is to be here 
directly, on other and public business.  <hi rend="italic"> Reine du ciel</hi>, 
Monsieur! how shall I meet him?" <pb n="159"/>  
</p><p>"He is powerless in Paris; your fear is idle." 
</p><p>"True.  There were no other terms." 
</p><p>"Nor papers?" 
</p><p>"The lady thought it safest to be without them.  She took 
merely my receipt, which the Baron Stahl will bring to me from her 
before receiving this." 
</p><p>"I will trouble you for it now." 
</p><p>He bowed and shuffled away.  At a glance from me, the <hi rend="italic"> 
gendarme</hi> slipped to the rear of the building, where three others 
were stationed at the two exits in that direction, to caution them 
of the critical moment, and returned.  Ten minutes passed,&mdash;the 
merchant did not appear.  If, after all, he had made off with it!  
There had been the click of a bolt, the half-stifled rattle of 
arms, as if a door had been opened and rapidly closed again, but 
nothing more. 
</p><p>"I will see what detains my friend," said Mademoiselle, the 
little woman. 
</p><p>We suffered her to withdraw.  In a moment more a quick 
expostulation was to be heard. 
</p><p>"They are there, the <hi rend="italic">gendarmes</hi>, my little one!  I should 
have run, but they caught me, the villains! and replaced me in the 
house.  <hi rend="italic"> Oh, sacre!"</hi>&mdash;and rolling this word between his teeth, 
he came down and laid a little box on the counter.  I opened it.  
There was within a large, glittering, curiously-cut piece of glass.  
I threw it aside. 
</p><p>"The diamond!" I exclaimed. 
</p><p>"Monsieur had it," he replied, stooping to pick up the glass 
with every appearance of surprise and care. 
</p><p>"Do you mean to say you endeavored to escape with that bawble?  
Produce the diamond instantly, or you shall hang as high as Haman!" 
I roared. 
</p><p>Whether he knew the individual in question or not, the threat 
was efficient; he trembled and hesitated, and finally drew the 
identical shagreen case from his bosom. 
</p><p>"I but jested," he said.  "Monsieur will witness that I 
relinquish it with reluctance." 
</p><p>"I will witness that you receive stolen goods!" I cried, in 
wrath. 
</p><p>He placed it in my hands. 
</p><p>"Oh!" he groaned, from the bottom of his heart, hanging his 
head, and laying both hands on the counter before him,&mdash;"it pains, 
it grieves me to part with it!" 
</p><p>"And the chain," I said. 
</p><p>"Monsieur did not demand that!" 
</p><p>"I demand it now." 
</p><p>In a moment, the chain also was given me. 
</p><p>"And now will Monsieur do me a favor?  Will he inform me by 
what means he ascertained these facts?" 
</p><p>I glanced at the <hi rend="italic">gar&ccedil;on</hi>, who had probably supplied himself 
with his master's finery illicitly;&mdash;he was the means;&mdash;we have 
some generosity;&mdash;I thought I should prefer doing him the favor, 
and declined. 
</p><p>I unclasped the shagreen case; the <hi rend="italic"> sergent-de-ville</hi> and 
the <hi rend="italic">gendarme</hi> stole up and looked over my shoulder; the <hi rend="italic"> 
gar&ccedil;on</hi> drew near with round eyes; the little woman peeped across; 
the merchant, with tears streaming over his face, gazed as if it 
had been a loadstone; finally, I looked myself.  There it lay, the 
glowing, resplendent thing! flashing in affluence of splendor, 
throbbing and palpitant with life, drawing all the light from the 
little woman's candle, from the sparkling armor around, from the 
steel barbs, and the distant lantern, into its bosom.  It was 
scarcely so large as I had expected to see it, but more brilliant 
than anything I could conceive of.  I do not believe there is 
another such in the world.  One saw clearly that the Oriental 
superstition of the sex of stones was no fable; this was 
essentially the female of diamonds, the queen herself, the 
principle of life, the rejoicing creative force.  It was not 
radiant, as the term literally taken implies; it seemed rather to 
retain its wealth,&mdash;instead of emitting its glorious rays, to curl 
them back like the fringe of a madrepore, and lie there with 
redoubled quivering scintillations, a mass of white magnificence, 
not prismatic, but a vast milky lustre.  I closed the case; on re-opening it, I could scarcely believe that <pb n="160"/>  the beautiful 
sleepless eye would again flash upon me.  I did not comprehend how 
it could afford such perpetual richness, such sheets of lustre. 
</p><p>At last we compelled ourselves to be satisfied.  I left the 
shop, dismissed my attendants, and, fresh from the contemplation of 
this miracle, again trod the dirty, reeking streets, crossed the 
bridge, with its lights, its warehouses midway, its living torrents 
who poured on unconscious of the beauty within their reach.  The 
thought of their ignorance of the treasure, not a dozen yards 
distant, has often made me question if we all are not equally 
unaware of other and greater processes of life, of more perfect, 
sublimed, and, as it were, spiritual crystallizations going on 
invisibly about us.  But had these been told of the thing clutched 
in the hand of a passer, how many of them would have known where to 
turn? and we,&mdash;are we any better? </p>
 
</div1><div1 type="chapter" n="2" id="d4"> 
<head>                           II.</head> 
 
<p>FOR a few days I carried the diamond about my person, and did 
not mention its recovery even to my valet, who knew that I sought 
it, but communicated only with the Marquis of G., who replied, that 
he would be in Paris on a certain day, when I could safely deliver 
it to him. 
</p><p>It was now generally rumored that the neighboring government 
was about to send us the Baron Stahl, ambassador concerning 
arrangements for a loan to maintain the sinking monarchy in 
supremacy at Paris, the usual synecdoche for France. 
</p><p>The weather being fine, I proceeded to call on Mme. de St. 
Cyr.  She received me in her boudoir, and on my way thither I could 
not but observe the perfect quiet and cloistered seclusion that 
pervaded the whole house,&mdash;the house itself seeming only an adjunct 
of the still and sunny garden, of which one caught a glimpse 
through the long open hall-windows beyond.  This boudoir did not 
differ from others to which I have been admitted: the same delicate 
shades; all the dainty appliances of Art for beauty; the lavish 
profusion of <hi rend="italic">bijouterie</hi>; and the usual statuettes of innocence, 
to indicate, perhaps, the presence of that commodity which might 
not be guessed at otherwise; and burning in a silver cup, a rich 
perfume loaded the air with voluptuous sweetness.  Through a half-open door an inner boudoir was to be seen, which must have been 
Delphine's; it looked like her; the prevailing hue was a soft 
purple, or gray; a <hi rend="italic"> prie-dieu</hi>, a book-shelf, and desk, of a dark 
West Indian wood, were just visible.  There was but one picture,&mdash;a 
sad-eyed, beautiful Fate.  It was the type of her nation.  I think 
she worshipped it.  And how apt is misfortune to degenerate into 
Fate!&mdash;not that the girl had ever experienced the former, but, 
dissatisfied with life, and seeing no outlet, she accepted it 
stoically and waited till it should be over.  She needed to be 
aroused;&mdash;the station of an <hi rend="italic">ambassadrice</hi>, which I desired for 
her, might kindle the spark.  There were no flowers, no perfumes, 
no busts, in this ascetic place.  Delphine herself, in some faint 
rosy gauze, her fair hair streaming round her, as she lay on a 
white-draped couch, half-risen on one arm, while she read the 
morning's <hi rend="italic">feuilleton</hi>, was the most perfect statuary of which a 
room could boast,&mdash;illumined, as I saw her, by the gay beams that 
entered at the loftily-arched window, broken only by the flickering 
of the vine-leaves that clustered the curiously-latticed panes 
without.  She resembled in kind a Nymph or Aphrodite just bursting 
from the sea. 
</p><p>Madame de St. Cyr received me with <hi rend="italic">empressement</hi>, and, so 
doing, closed the door of this shrine.  We spoke of various 
things,&mdash;of the court, the theatre, the weather, the world,&mdash; 
skating lightly round the slender edges of her secret, till finally 
she invited me to lunch with her in the garden.  Here, on a rustic 
table, stood wine and a few delicacies,&mdash;while, by extending a 
hand, we could grasp the hanging pears and nectarines still warm to 
the lip and luscious with sunshine, as <pb n="161"/>  we disputed 
possession with the envious wasp who had established a priority of 
claim. 
</p><p>"It is to be hoped," I said, sipping the <hi rend="italic"> Haut-Brion</hi>, whose 
fine and brittle smack contrasted rarely with the delicious 
juiciness of the fruit, "that you have laid in a supply of this 
treasure that neither moth nor rust doth corrupt, before parting 
with that little gem in the Gironde." 
</p><p>"Ah?  You know, then, that I have sold it?" 
</p><p>"Yes," I replied.  "I have the pleasure of Mr. Ulster's 
acquaintance." 
</p><p>"He arranged the terms for me," she said, with restraint,&mdash; 
adding, "I could almost wish now that it had not been." 
</p><p>This was probably true; for the sum which she hoped to receive 
from Ulster for standing sponsor to his jewel was possibly equal to 
the price of her vineyard. 
</p><p>"It was indispensable at the time, this sale; I thought best 
to hazard it on one more season,&mdash;If, after such advantages, 
Delphine will not marry, why&mdash;it remains to retire into the country 
and end our days with the barbarians!" she continued, shrugging her 
shoulders; "I have a house there." 
</p><p>"But you will not be obliged to throw us all into despair by 
such a step now," I replied. 
</p><p>She looked quickly, as if to see how nearly I had approached 
her citadel,&mdash;then, finding in my face no expression but a 
complimentary one, "No," she said, "I hope that my affairs have 
brightened a little.  One never knows what is in store." 
</p><p>Before long I had assured myself that Mme. de St. Cyr was not 
a party to the theft, but had merely been hired by Ulster, who, 
discovering the state of her affairs, had not, therefore, revealed 
his own,&mdash;and this without in the least implying any knowledge on 
my part of the transaction.  Ulster must have seen the necessity of 
leaving the business in the hands of a competent person, and Mme. 
de St. Cyr's financial talent was patent.  There were few ladies in 
Paris who would have rejected the opportunity.  Of these things I 
felt a tolerable certainty. 
</p><p>"We throng with foreigners," said Madame, archly, as I reached 
this point.  "Diplomates, too.  The Baron Stahl arrives in a day." 
</p><p>"I have heard," I responded.  "You are acquainted?" 
</p><p>"Alas! no," she said.  "I knew his father well, though he 
himself is not young.  Indeed, the families thought once of 
intermarriage.  But nothing has been said on the subject for many 
years.  His Excellency, I hear, will strengthen himself at home by 
an alliance with the young Countess, the natural daughter of the 
Emperor." 
</p><p>"He surely will never be so imprudent as to rivet his chain by 
such a link!" 
</p><p>"It is impossible to compute the dice in those despotic 
countries," she rejoined,&mdash;which was pretty well, considering the 
freedom enjoyed by France at that period. 
</p><p>"It may be," I suggested, "that the Baron hopes to open this 
delicate subject with you himself, Madame." 
</p><p>"It is unlikely," she said, sighing.  "And for Delphine, 
should I tell her his Excellency preferred scarlet, she would 
infallibly wear blue.  Imagine her, Monsieur, in fine scarlet, with 
a scarf of gold gauze, and rustling grasses in that unruly gold 
hair of hers!  She would be divine!" 
</p><p>The maternal instinct as we have it here at Paris confounds 
me.  I do not comprehend it.  Here was a mother who did not 
particularly love her child, who would not be inconsolable at her 
loss, would not ruin her own complexion by care of her during 
illness, would send her through fire and water and every torture to 
secure or maintain a desirable rank, who yet would entangle herself 
deeply in intrigue, would not hesitate to tarnish her own 
reputation, and would, in fact, raise heaven and earth to&mdash;endow 
this child with a brilliant match.  And Mme. de St. Cyr seemed to 
regard Delphine, still further, as a cool matter of Art. 
</p><p>These little confidences, moreover, are <pb n="162"/>  provoking.  
They put you yourself so entirely out of the question. 
</p><p>"Mlle. de St. Cyr's beauty is peerless," I said, slightly 
chagrined, and at a loss.  "If hearts were trumps, instead of 
diamonds!" 
</p><p>"We are poor," resumed Madame, pathetically.  "Delphine is not 
an heiress.  Delphine is proud.  She will not stoop to charm.  Her 
coquetry is that of an Amazon.  Her kisses are arrows.  She is 
Medusa!"  And Madame, her mother, shivered. 
</p><p>Here, with her hair knotted up and secured by a tiny dagger, 
her gauzy drapery gathered in her arm, Delphine floated down the 
green alley toward us, as if in a rosy cloud.  But this soft aspect 
never could have been more widely contradicted than by the stony 
repose and cutting calm of her beautiful face. 
</p><p>"The Marquis of G.," said her mother, "he also arrives 
ambassador.  Has he talent?  Is he brilliant?  Wealthy, of course,--but <hi rend="italic">gauche</hi>?" 
</p><p>Therewith I sketched for them the Marquis and his 
surroundings. 
</p><p>"It is charming," said Madame.  "Delphine, do you attend?" 
</p><p>"And why?" asked Delphine, half concealing a yawn with her 
dazzling hand.  "It is wearisome; it matters not to me." 
</p><p>"But he will not go to marry himself in France," said her 
mother.  "Oh, these English," she added, with a laugh, "yourself, 
Monsieur, being proof of it, will not mingle blood, lest the 
Channel should still flow between the little red globules!  You 
will go? but to return shortly?  You will dine with me soon?  <hi rend="italic"> Au 
revoir!"</hi> and she gave me her hand graciously, while Delphine bowed 
as if I were already gone, threw herself into a garden-chair, and 
commenced pouring the wine on a stone for a little tame snake which 
came out and lapped it. 
</p><p>Such women as Mme. de St. Cyr have a species of magnetism 
about them.  It is difficult to retain one's self-respect before 
them,&mdash;for no other reason than that one is, at the moment, 
absorbed into their individuality, and thinks and acts with them.  
Delphine must have had a strong will, and perpetual antagonism did 
not weaken it.  As for me, Madame had, doubtless, reasons of her 
own for tearing aside these customary bands of reserve,&mdash;reasons 
which, if you do not perceive, I shall not enumerate. 
 
</p><p>"Have you met with anything further in your search, Sir?" 
asked my valet, next morning. 
</p><p>"Oh, yes, Hay," I returned, in a very good humor,&mdash;"with great 
success.  You have assisted me so much, that I am sure I owe it to 
you to say that I have found the diamond." 
</p><p>"Indeed, Sir, you are very kind.  I have been interested, but 
my assistance is not worth mentioning.  I thought likely it might 
be, you appeared so quiet."&mdash;The cunning dog!&mdash;"How did you find 
it, Sir, may I ask?" 
</p><p>I briefly related the leading facts, since he had been aware 
of the progress of the case to that point,&mdash;without, however, 
mentioning Mme. de St. Cyr's name. 
</p><p>"And Monsieur did not inform me!" a French valet would have 
cried. 
</p><p>"You were prudent not to mention it, Sir," said Hay.  "These 
walls must have better ears than ordinary; for a family has moved 
in on the first floor recently, whose actions are extremely 
suspicious.  But is this precious affair to be seen?" 
</p><p>I took it from an inner pocket and displayed it, having 
discarded the shagreen case as inconvenient. 
</p><p>"His Excellency must return as he came," said I. 
</p><p>Hay's eyes sparkled. 
</p><p>"And do you carry it there, Sir?" he asked, with surprise, as 
I restored it to my waistcoat-pocket. 
</p><p>"I shall take it to the bank," I said.  "I do not like the 
responsibility." 
</p><p>"It is very unsafe," was the warning of this cautious fellow.  
"Why, Sir! any of these swells, these pickpockets, might meet you, 
run against you,&mdash;so!" said Hay, suiting the action to the word, 
"and, with the little sharp knife conceal-<pb n="163"/> ed in just such a 
ring as this I wear, give a light tap, and there's a slit in your 
vest, Sir, but no diamond!"&mdash;and instantly resuming his former 
respectful deportment, Hay handed me my gloves and stick, and 
smoothed my hat. 
</p><p>"Nonsense!" I replied, drawing on the gloves, "I should like 
to see the man who could be too quick for me.  Any news from India, 
Hay?" 
</p><p>"None of consequence, Sir.  The indigo crop is said to have 
failed, which advances the figure of that on hand, so that one or 
two fortunes will be made to-day.  Your hat, Sir?&mdash;your lunettes?  
Here they are, Sir." 
</p><p>"Good morning, Hay." 
</p><p>"Good morning, Sir." 
</p><p>I descended the stairs, buttoning my gloves, paused a moment 
at the door to look about, and proceeded down the street, which was 
not more than usually thronged.  At the bank I paused to assure 
myself that the diamond was safe.  My fingers caught in a singular 
slit.  I started.  As Hay had prophesied, there was a fine 
longitudinal cut in my waistcoat, but the pocket was empty.  My 
God! the thing was gone.  I never can forget the blank nihility of 
all existence that dreadful moment when I stood fumbling for what 
was not.  Calm as I sit here and tell of it, I vow to you a shiver 
courses through me at the very thought.  I had circumvented Stahl 
only to destroy myself.  The diamond was lost again.  My mind flew 
like lightning over every chance, and a thousand started up like 
steel spikes to snatch the bolt.  For a moment I was stunned, but, 
never being very subject to despair, on my recovery, which was 
almost at once, took every measure that could be devised.  Who had 
touched me?  Whom had I met?  Through what streets had I come?  In 
ten minutes the Prefect had the matter in hand.  My injunctions 
were strict privacy.  I sincerely hoped the mishap would not reach 
England; and if the diamond were not recovered before the Marquis 
of G. arrived,&mdash;why, there was the Seine.  It is all very well to 
talk,&mdash;yet suicide is so French an affair, that an Englishman does 
not take to it naturally, and, except in November, the Seine is too 
cold and damp for comfort, but during that month I suppose it does 
not greatly differ in these respects from our own atmosphere. 
</p><p>A preternatural activity now possessed me.  I slept none, ate 
little, worked immoderately.  I spared no efforts, for everything 
was at stake.  In the midst of all G. arrived.  Hay also exerted 
himself to the utmost; I promised him a hundred pounds, if I found 
it.  He never told me that he said how it would be, never intruded 
the state of the market, never resented my irritating conduct, but 
watched me with narrow yet kind solicitude, and frequently offered 
valuable suggestions, which, however, as everything else did, led 
to nothing.  I did not call on G., but in a week or so his card was 
brought up one morning to me.  "Deny me," I groaned.  It yet wanted 
a week of the day on which I had promised to deliver him the 
diamond.  Meanwhile the Baron Stahl had reached Paris, but he still 
remained in private,&mdash;few had seen him. 
</p><p>The police were forever on the wrong track.  To-day they 
stopped the old Comptesse du Quesne and her jewels, at the 
Barriere; to-morrow, with their long needles, they riddled a 
package of lace destined for the Duchess of X. herself; the Secret 
Service was doubled; and to crown all, a splendid new star of the 
testy Prince de Ligne was examined and proclaimed to be paste,&mdash;the 
Prince swearing vengeance, if he could discover the cause,&mdash;while 
half Paris must have been under arrest.  My own hotel was ransacked 
thoroughly,&mdash;Hay begging that his traps might be included,&mdash;but 
nothing resulted, and I expected nothing, for, of course, I could 
swear that the stone was in my pocket when I stepped into the 
street.  I confess I never was nearer madness,&mdash;every word and 
gesture stung me like asps,&mdash;I walked on burning coals.  Enduring 
all this torment, I must yet meet my daily comrades, eat ices at 
Tortoni's, stroll on the Boulevards, call on <pb n="164"/>  my 
acquaintance, with the same equanimity as before.  I believe I was 
equal to it.  Only by contrast with that blessed time when Ulster 
and diamonds were unknown, could I imagine my past happiness, my 
present wretchedness.  Rather than suffer it again, I would be 
stretched on the rack till every bone in my skin was broken.  I 
cursed Mr. Arthur Ulster every hour in the day; myself, as well; 
and even now the word diamond sends a cold blast to my heart.  I 
often met my friend, the <hi rend="italic"> marchand des armures</hi>.  It was his turn 
to triumph; I fancied there must be a hang-dog kind of air about 
me, as about every sharp man who has been outwitted.  It wanted 
finally but two days of that on which I was to deliver the diamond. 
</p><p>One midnight, armed with a dark lantern and a cloak, I was 
traversing the streets along,&mdash;unsuccessful, as usual, just now 
solitary, and almost in despair.  As I turned a corner, two men  
were but scarcely visible a step before me.  It was a badly-lighted 
part of the town.  Unseen and noiseless I followed.  They spoke in 
low tones,&mdash;almost whispers; or rather, one spoke,&mdash;the other 
seemed to nod assent. 
</p><p>"On the day but one after to-morrow," I heard spoken in 
English.  Great Heavens! was it possible? had I arrived at a clue?  
That was the day of days for me.  "You have given it, you say, in 
this billet,&mdash;I wish to be exact, you see," continued the voice,&mdash; 
"to prevent detection, you gave it, ten minutes after it came into 
your hands, to the butler of Madame &mdash;," (here the speaker 
stumbled on the rough pavement, and I lost the name,) "who," he 
continued, "will put it in the &mdash;" (a second stumble acted like 
a hiccough) "cellar." 
</p><p>"Wine-cellar," I thought; "and what then?" 
</p><p>"In the &mdash;."  A third stumble was followed by a round 
German oath.  How easy it is for me now to fill up the little 
blanks which that unhappy pavement caused! 
</p><p>"You share your receipts with this butler.  On the day I 
obtain it," he added, and I now perceived his foreign accent, "I 
hand you one hundred thousand francs; afterward, monthly payments 
till you have received the stipulated sum.  But how will this 
butler know me, in season to prevent a mistake?  Hem!&mdash;he might 
give it to the other!" 
</p><p>My hearing had been trained to such a degree that I would have 
promised to overhear any given dialogue of the spirits themselves, 
but the whisper that answered him eluded me.  I caught nothing but 
a faint sibillation.  "Your ring?" was the rejoinder.  "He shall be 
instructed to recognize it?  Very well.  It is too large,&mdash;no, that 
will do, it fits the first finger.  There is nothing more.  I am 
under infinite obligations, Sir; they shall be remembered.  Adieu!" 
</p><p>The two parted; which should I pursue?  In desperation I 
turned my lantern upon one, and illumined a face fresh with color, 
whose black eyes sparkled askance after the retreating figure, 
under straight black brows.  In a moment more he was lost in a 
false <hi rend="italic"> cul-de-sac</hi>, and I found it impossible to trace the other. 
</p><p>I was scarcely better off than before; but it seemed to me 
that I had obtained something, and that now it was wisest to work 
this vein.  "The butler of Madame &mdash;."  There were hundreds of 
thousands of Madames in town.  I might call on all, and be as old 
as the Wandering Jew at the last call.  The cellar.  Wine-cellar, 
of course,&mdash;that came by a natural connection with butler,&mdash;but 
whose?  There was one under my own abode; certainly I would explore 
it.  Meanwhile, let us see the entertainments for Wednesday.  The 
Prefect had a list of these.  For some I found I had cards; I 
determined to allot a fraction of time to as many as possible; my 
friends in the Secret Service would divide the labor.  Among 
others, Madame de St. Cyr gave a dinner, and, as she had been in 
the affair, I determined not to neglect her on this occasion, 
although having no definite idea of what had been, or plan of what 
should be done.  I decided not to speak of this oc-<pb n="165"/> currence 
to Hay, since it might only bring him off some trail that he had 
struck. 
</p><p>Having been provided with keys, early on the following evening 
I entered the wine-cellar, and, concealed in an empty cask that 
would have held a dozen of me, waited for something to turn up.  
Really, when I think of myself, a diplomate, a courtier, a man-about-town, curled in a dusty, musty wine-barrel, I am moved with 
vexation and laughter.  Nothing, however, turned up,&mdash;and at length 
I retired, baffled.  The next night came,&mdash;no news, no 
identification of my black-browed man, no success; but I felt 
certain that something must transpire in that cellar.  I don't know 
why I had pitched upon that one in particular, but, at an earlier 
hour than on the previous night, I again donned the cask.  A long 
time must have elapsed; dead silence filled the spacious vaults, 
except where now and then some Sillery cracked the air with a quick 
explosion, or some newer wine bubbled round the bung of its barrel 
with a faint effervescence.  I had no intention of leaving this 
place till morning, but it suddenly appeared like the most woful 
waste of time.  The master of this tremendous affair should be 
abroad and active; who knew what his keen eyes might detect, what 
loss his absence might occasion in this nick of time?  And here he 
was, shut up and locked in a wine-cellar!  I began to be very 
nervous; I had already, with aid, searched every crevice of the 
cellar; and now I thought it would be some consolation to discover 
the thief, if I never regained the diamond.  A distant clock tolled 
midnight.  There was a faint noise,&mdash;a mouse?&mdash;no, it was too 
prolonged;&mdash;nor did it sound like the fiz of Champagne;&mdash;a great 
iron door was turning on its hinges; a man with a lantern was 
entering; another followed, and another.  They seated themselves.  
In a few moments, appearing one by one and at intervals, some 
thirty people were in the cellar.  Were they all to share in the 
proceeds of the diamond?  With what jaundiced eyes we behold 
things!  I myself saw all that was only through the lens of this 
diamond, of which not one of these men had ever heard.  As the 
lantern threw its feeble glimmer on this group, and I surveyed them 
through my loophole, I thought I had never seen so wild and savage 
a picture, such enormous shadows, such bold outline, such a 
startling flash on the fact of their leader, such light retreating 
up the threatening arches.  More resolute brows, more determined 
words, more unshrinking hearts, I had not met.  In fact, I found 
myself in the centre of a conspiracy, a society as vindictive as 
the Jacobins, as unknown and terrible as the Marianne of to-day.  
I was thunderstruck, too, at the countenances on which the light 
fell,&mdash;men the loyalest in estimation, ministers and senators, 
millionnaires who had no reason for discontent, dandies whose 
reason was supposed to be devoted to their tailors, poets and 
artists of generous aspiration and suspected tendencies, and one 
woman,&mdash;Delphine de St. Cyr.  Their plans were brave, their 
determination lofty, their conclave serious and fine; yet as slowly 
they shut up their hopes and fears in the black masks, one man bent 
toward the lantern to adjust his.  When he lifted his face before 
concealing it, I recognized him also.  I had met him frequently at 
the Bureau of Police; he was, I believe, Secretary of the Secret 
Service. 
</p><p>I had no sympathy with these people.  I had liberty enough 
myself, I was well enough satisfied with the world, I did not care 
to revolutionize France; but my heart rebelled at the mockery, as 
this traitor and spy, this creature of a system by which I gained 
my fame, showed his revolting face and veiled it again.  And 
Delphine, what had she to do with them?  One by one, as they 
entered, they withdrew, and I was left alone again.  But all this 
was not my diamond. 
</p><p>Another hour elapsed.  Again the door opened, and remained 
ajar.  Some one entered, whom I could not see.  There was a pause,--then a rustle,&mdash;the door creaked ever so little.  "Art thou 
there?" <pb n="166"/>  lisped a shrill whisper,&mdash;a woman, as I could 
guess. 
</p><p>"My angel, it is I," was returned, a semitone lower.  She 
approached, he advanced, and the consequence was a salute resonant 
as the smack with which a Dutch burgomaster may be supposed to set 
down his mug.  I was prepared for anything.  Ye gods! if it should 
be Delphine!  But the base suspicion was birth-strangled as they 
spoke again.  The conversation which now ensued between these 
lovers under difficulties was tender and affecting beyond 
expression.  I had felt guilty enough when an unwilling auditor of 
the conspirators,&mdash;since, though one employs spies, one does not 
therefore act that part one's-self, but on emergencies,&mdash;an 
unwillingness which would not, however, prevent my turning to 
advantage the information gained; but here, to listen to this 
rehearsal of woes and blisses, this <hi rend="italic"> ah mon Fernand</hi>, this aria 
in an area, growing momently more fervent, was too much.  I 
overturned the cask, scrambled upon my feet, and fled from the 
cellar, leaving the astounded lovers to follow, while, agreeably to 
my instincts, and regardless of the diamond, I escaped the 
embarrassing predicament. 
</p><p>At length it grew to be noon of the appointed day.  Nothing 
had transpired; all our labor was idle.  I felt, nevertheless, more 
buoyant than usual,&mdash;whether because I was now to put my fate to 
the test, or that to-day was the one of which my black-browed man 
had spoken, and I therefore entertained a presentiment of good-fortune, I cannot say.  But when, in unexceptionable toilet, I 
stood on Mme. de St. Cyr's steps, my heart sunk.  G. was doubtless 
already within, and I thought of the <hi rend="italic"> marchand des armures'</hi> 
exclamation, "Queen of Heaven, Monsieur! how shall I meet him!"  I 
was plunged at once into the profoundest gloom.  Why had I 
undertaken the business at all?  This interference, this good-humor, this readiness to oblige,&mdash;it would ruin me yet!  I forswore 
it, as Falstaff forswore honor.  Why needed I to meddle in the <hi rend="italic"> 
melee</hi>?  Why&mdash;  But I was no catechumen.  Questions were useless 
now.  My emotions are not chronicled on my face, I flatter myself; 
and with my usual repose I saluted our hostess.  Greeting G. 
without any allusion to the diamond, the absence of which allusion 
he received as a point of etiquette, I was conversing with Mrs. 
Leigh, when the Baron Stahl was announced.  I turned to look at his 
Excellency.  A glance electrified me.  There was my dark-browed man 
of the midnight streets.  It must, then, have been concerning the 
diamond that I had heard him speak.  His countenance, his eager, 
glittering eye, told that to-day was as eventful to him as to me.  
If he were here, I could well afford to be.  As he addressed me in 
English, my certainty was confirmed; and the instant in which I 
observed the ring, gaudy and coarse, upon his finger, made 
confirmation doubly sure.  I own I was surprised that anything 
could induce the Baron to wear such an ornament.  Here he was 
actually risking his reputation as a man of taste, as an exquisite, 
a leader of <hi rend="italic">haut ton</hi>, a gentleman, by the detestable vulgarity 
of this ring.  But why do I speak so of the trinket?  Do I not owe 
it a thrill of as fine joy as I ever knew?  Faith! it was not 
unfamiliar to me.  It had been a daily sight for years.  In meeting 
the Baron Stahl I had found the diamond. 
</p><p>The Baron Stahl was, then, the thief?  Not at all.  My valet, 
as of course you have been all along aware, was the thief. 
</p><p>The Marquis of G. took down Mme. de St. Cyr; Stahl preceded 
me, with Delphine.  As we sat at table, G. was at the right, I at 
the left of our hostess.  Next G. sat Delphine; below her, the 
Baron; so that we were nearly <hi rend="italic"> vis-a-vis</hi>.  I was now as fully 
convinced that Mme. de St. Cyr's cellar was the one, as the day 
before I had been that the other was; I longed to reach it.  Hay 
had given the stone to a butler&mdash;doubtless this&mdash;the moment of its 
theft; but, not being aware of Mme. de St. Cyr's previous share in 
the adventure, had probably not afforded her another.  And thus I 
con-<pb n="167"/> cluded her to be ignorant of the game we were about to 
play; and I imagined, with the interest that one carries into a 
romance, the little preliminary scene between the Baron and Madame 
that must have already taken place, being charmed by the 
cheerfulness with which she endured the loss of the promised 
reward. 
</p><p>As the Baron entered the dining-room, I saw him withdraw his 
glove, and move the jewelled hand across his hair while passing the 
solemn butler, who gave it a quick recognition;&mdash;the next moment we 
were seated.  It was a dinner <hi rend="italic"> a la Russe</hi>; that is, only wines 
were on the table, clustered around a central ornament,&mdash;a bunch of 
tall silver rushes and flag-leaves, on whose airy tip danced <hi rend="italic"> 
fleurs-de-lis</hi> of frosted silver, a design of Delphine's,&mdash;the 
dishes being on side-tables, from which the guests were served as 
they signified their choice of the variety on their cards.  Our 
number not being large, and the custom so informal, rendered it 
pleasant. 
</p><p>I had just finished my oysters and was pouring out a glass of 
Chablis, when another plate was set before the Baron. 
</p><p>"His Excellency has no salt," murmured the butler,&mdash;at the 
same time placing one beside him.  A glance, at entrance, had 
taught me that most of the service was uniform; this dainty little 
<hi rend="italic">saliere</hi> I had noticed on the buffet, solitary, and unlike the 
others.  What a fool had I been!  Those gaps in the Baron's remarks 
caused by the paving-stones, how easily were they to be supplied! 
</p><p>"Madame?" 
</p><p>Madame de St. Cyr. 
</p><p>"The cellar?" 
</p><p>A salt-cellar. 
</p><p>How quick the flash that enlightened me while I surveyed the 
<hi rend="italic">saliere</hi>! 
</p><p>"It is exquisite!  Am I never to sit at your table but some 
new device charms me?" I exclaimed.  "Is it your design, 
Mademoiselle?" I said, turning to Delphine. 
</p><p>Delphine, who had been ice to all the Baron's advances, only 
curled her lip.  <hi rend="italic">" De babioles!"</hi> she said. 
</p><p>"Yes, indeed," cried Mme. de St. Cyr, extending her hand for 
it.  "But none the less her taste.  Is it not a fairy thing?  A <hi rend="italic"> 
Cellini</hi>!  Observe this curve, these lines! but one man could have 
drawn them!"&mdash;and she held it for our scrutiny.  It was a tiny hand 
and arm of ivory, parting the foam of a wave and holding a golden 
shell, in which the salt seemed to have crusted itself as if in 
some secretest ocean-hollow.  I looked at the Baron a moment; his 
eyes were fastened upon the <hi rend="italic">saliere</hi>, and all the color had 
forsaken his cheeks,&mdash;his face counted his years.  The diamond was 
in that little shell.  But how to obtain it?  I had no novice to 
deal with; nothing but delicate <hi rend="italic">finesse</hi> would answer. 
</p><p>"Permit me to examine it," I said.  She passed it to her left 
hand for me to take.  The butler made a step forward. 
</p><p>"Meanwhile, Madame," said the Baron, smiling, "I have no 
salt." 
</p><p>The instinct of hospitality prevailed;&mdash;she was about to 
return it.  Might I do an awkward thing?  Unhesitatingly.  
Reversing my glass, I gave my arm a wider sweep than necessary, 
and, as it met her hand with violence, the <hi rend="italic">saliere</hi> fell.  
Before it touched the floor I caught it.  There was still a pinch 
of salt left,&mdash;nothing more. 
</p><p>"A thousand pardons!" I said, and restored it to the Baron. 
</p><p>His Excellency beheld it with dismay; it was rare to see him 
bend over and scrutinize it with staring eyes. 
</p><p>"Do you find there what Count Arnaldos begs in the song," 
asked Delphine,&mdash;"the secret of the sea, Monsieur?" 
</p><p>He handed it to the butler, observing, "I find here no"&mdash; 
</p><p>"Salt, Monsieur?" replied the man, who did not doubt but all 
had gone right, and replenished it. 
</p><p>Had one told me in the morning that no intricate manoeuvres, 
but a simple blunder, would effect this, I might have met him in 
the Bois de Boulogne. 
</p><p>"We will not quarrel," said my neigh-<pb n="168"/> bor, lightly, with 
reference to the popular superstition. 
</p><p>"Rather propitiate the offended deities by a crumb tossed over 
the shoulder," added I. 
</p><p>"Over the left?" asked the Baron, to intimate his knowledge of 
another idion, together with a reproof for my <hi rend="italic">gaucherie</hi>. 
</p><p><hi rend="italic">" A gauche,&mdash;quelquefois c'est justement a droit</hi>," I 
replied. 
</p><p>"Salt in any pottage," said Madame, a little uneasily, "is 
like surprise in an individual; it brings out the flavor of every 
ingredient, so my cook tells me." 
</p><p>"It is a preventive of palsy," I remarked, as the slight 
trembling of my adversary's finger caught my eye. 
</p><p>"And I have noticed that a taste for it is peculiar to those 
who trace their blood to Galitzin," continued Madame. 
</p><p>"Let us, therefore, elect a deputation to those mines near 
Cracow," said Delphine. 
</p><p>"To our cousins, the slaves there?" laughed her mother. 
</p><p>"I must vote to lay your bill on the table, Mademoiselle," I 
rejoined. 
</p><p>"But with a <hi rend="italic">boule blanche</hi>, Monsieur?" 
</p><p>"As the salt has been laid on the floor," said the Baron. 
</p><p>Meanwhile, as this light skirmishing proceeded, my sleeve and 
Mme. de St. Cyr's dress were slightly powdered, but I had not seen 
the diamond.  The Baron, bolder than I, looked under the table, but 
made no discovery.  I was on the point of dropping my napkin to 
accomplish a similar movement, when my accomodating neighbor 
dropped hers.  To restore it, I stooped.  There it lay, large and 
glowing, the Sea of Splendor, the Moon of Milk, the Torment of my 
Life, on the carpet, within half an inch of a lady's slipper.  
Mademoiselle de St. Cyr's foot had prevented the Baron from seeing 
it; now it moved and unconsciously covered it.  All was as I 
wished.  I hastily restored the napkin, and looked steadily at 
Delphine,&mdash;so steadily, that she perceived some meaning, as she had 
already suspected a game.  By my sign she understood me, pressed 
her foot upon the stone and drew it nearer.  In France we do not 
remain at table until unfit for a lady's society,&mdash;we rise with 
them.  Delphine needed to drop neither napkin nor handkerchief; she 
composedly stooped and picked up the stone, so quickly that no one 
saw what it was. 
</p><p>"And the diamond?" said the Baron to the butler, rapidly, as 
he passed. 
</p><p>"It was in the <hi rend="italic">saliere</hi>!" whispered the astonished 
creature. 
 
</p><p>In the drawing-room I sought the Marquis. 
</p><p>"To-day I was to surrender you your property," I said; "it is 
here." 
</p><p>"Do you know," he replied, "I thought I must have been 
mistaken?" 
</p><p>"Any of our volatile friends here might have been," I resumed; 
"for us it is impossible.  Concerning this, when you return to 
France, I will relate the incidents; at present, there are those 
who will not hesitate to take life to obtain its possession.  The 
<hi rend="italic">diligence</hi> leaves in twenty minutes; and if I owned the diamond, 
it should not leave me behind.  Moreover, who knows what a day may 
bring forth?  To-morrow there may be an <hi rend="italic">emeute</hi>.  Let me restore 
the thing as you withdraw." 
</p><p>The Marquis, who is not, after all, the Lion of England, 
pausing a moment to transmit my words from his ear to his brain, 
did not afterward delay to make inquiries or adieux, but went to 
seek Mme. de St. Cyr and wish her good-night, on his departure from 
Paris.  As I awaited his return, which I knew would not be 
immediate, Delphine left the Baron and joined me. 
</p><p>"You beckoned me?" she asked. 
</p><p>"No, I did not." 
</p><p>"Nevertheless, I come by your desire, I am sure." 
</p><p>"Mademoiselle," I said, "I am not in the custom of doing 
favors; I have forsworn them.  But before you return me my jewel, 
I risk my head and render one last one, and to you." 
</p><p>"Do not, Monsieur, at such price," <pb n="169"/>  she responded, with 
a slight mocking motion of her hand. 
</p><p>"Delphine! those resolves, last night, in the cellar, were 
daring; they were noble, yet they were useless." 
</p><p>She had not started, but a slight tremor ran over her person 
and vanished while I spoke. 
</p><p>"They will be allowed to proceed no farther,&mdash;the axe is 
sharpened; for the last man who adjusted his mask was a spy,&mdash;was 
the Secretary of the Secret Service." 
</p><p>Delphine could not have grown paler than was usual with her of 
late.  She flashed her eye upon me. 
</p><p>"He was, it may be, Monsieur himself," she said. 
</p><p>"I do not claim the honor of that post." 
</p><p>"But you were there, nevertheless,&mdash;a spy!" 
</p><p>"Hush, Delphine!  It would be absurd to quarrel.  I was there 
for the recovery of this stone, having heard that it was in a 
cellar,&mdash;which, stupidly enough, I had insisted should be a wine-cellar." 
</p><p>"It was, then"&mdash; 
</p><p>"In a salt-cellar,&mdash;a blunder which, as you do not speak 
English, you cannot comprehend.  I never mix with treason, and did 
not wish to assist at your patimes.  I speak now, that you may 
escape." 
</p><p>"If Monsieur betrays his friends, the police, why should I 
expect a kinder fate?" 
</p><p>"When I use the police, they are my servants, not my friends.  
I simply warn you, that, before sunrise, you will be safer 
travelling than sleeping,&mdash;safer next week in Vienna than in 
Paris." 
</p><p>"Thank you!  And the intelligence is the price of the diamond?  
If I had not chanced to pick it up, my throat," and she clasped it 
with her fingers, "had been no slenderer than the others?" 
</p><p>"Delphine, will you remember, should you have occasion to do 
so in Vienna, that it is just possible for an Englishman to have 
affections, and sentiments, and, in fact, sensations? that, with 
him, friendship can be inviolate, and to betray it an 
impossibility?  And even were it not, I, Mademoiselle, have not the 
pleasure to be classed by you as a friend." 
</p><p>"You err.  I esteem Monsieur highly." 
</p><p>I was impressed by her coolness. 
</p><p>"Let me see if you comprehend the matter," I demanded. 
</p><p>"Perfectly.  The arrest will be used to-night, the guillotine 
to-morrow." 
</p><p>"You will take immediate measures for flight?" 
</p><p>"No,&mdash;I do not see that life has value.  I shall be the debtor 
of him who takes it." 
</p><p>"A large debt.  Delphine, I exact a promise of you.  I do not 
care to have endangered myself for nothing.  It is not worth while 
to make your mother unhappy.  Life is not yours to throw away.  I 
appeal to your magnanimity." 
</p><p>"'Affections, sentiments, sensations!'" she quoted.  "Your own 
danger for the affection,&mdash;it is an affair of the heart!  Mme. de 
St. Cyr's unhappiness,&mdash;there is the sentiment.  You are angry, 
Monsieur,&mdash;that must be the sensation." 
</p><p>"Delphine, I am waiting." 
</p><p>"Ah, well.  You have mentioned Vienna, and why?  Liberals are 
countenanced there?" 
</p><p>"Not in the least.  But Madame l'Ambassadrice will be 
countenanced." 
</p><p>"I do not know her." 
</p><p>"We are not apt to know ourselves." 
</p><p>"Monsieur, how idle are these cross-purposes!" she said, 
folding her fan. 
</p><p>"Delphine," I continued, taking the fan, "tell me frankly 
which of these two men you prefer,&mdash;the Marquis or his Excellency." 
</p><p>"The Marquis?  He is antiphlogistic,&mdash;he is ice.  Why should 
I freeze myself?  I am frozen now,&mdash;I need fire!" 
</p><p>Her eyes burned as she spoke, and a faint red flushed her 
cheek. 
</p><p>"Mademoiselle, you demonstrate to me that life has yet a value 
to you." 
</p><p>"I find no fire," she said, as the flush fell away. 
</p><p>"The Baron?" <pb n="169"/>  
</p><p>"I do not affect him." 
</p><p>"You will conquer your prejudice in Vienna." 
</p><p>"I do not comprehend you, Monsieur;&mdash;you speak in riddles, 
which I do not like." 
</p><p>"I will speak plainer.  But first let me ask you for the 
diamond." 
</p><p>"The diamond?  It is yours?  How am I certified of it?  I find 
it on the floor; you say it was in my mother's <hi rend="italic">saliere</hi>; it is 
her affair, not mine.  No, Monsieur, I do not see that the thing is 
yours." 
</p><p>Certainly there was nothing to be done but to relate the 
story, which I did, carefully omitting the Baron's name.  At its 
conclusion, she placed the prize in my hand. 
</p><p>"Pardon, Monsieur," she said; "without doubt you should 
receive it.  And this agent of the government,&mdash;one could turn him 
like hot iron in this vice,&mdash;who was he?" 
</p><p>"The Baron Stahl." 
</p><p>All this time G. had been waiting on thorns, and, leaving her 
now, I approached him, displayed for an instant the treasure on my 
palm, and slipped it into his.  It was done.  I bade farewell to 
this Eye of Morning and Heart of Day, this thing that had caused me 
such pain and perplexity and pleasure, with less envy and more joy 
than I thought myself capable of.  The relief and buoyancy that 
seized me, as his hand closed upon it, I shall not attempt to 
portray.  An abdicated king was not freer. 
</p><p>The Marquis departed, and I, wandering round the <hi rend="italic">salon</hi>, 
was next stranded upon the Baron.  He was yet hardly sure of 
himself.  We talked indifferently for a few moments, and then I 
ventured on the great loan.  He was, as became him, not 
communicative, but scarcely thought it would be arranged.  I then 
spoke of Delphine. 
</p><p>"She is superb!" said the Baron, staring at her boldly. 
</p><p>She stood opposite, and, in her white attire on the background 
of the blue curtain, appeared like an impersonation of Greek genius 
relieved upon the blue of an Athenian heaven.  Her severe and 
classic outline, her pallor, her downcast lids, her absorbed look, 
only heightened the resemblance.  Her reverie seemed to end 
abruptly, the same red stained her cheek again, her lips curved in 
a proud smile, she raised her glowing eyes and observed us 
regarding her.  At too great distance to hear our words, she 
quietly repaid our glances in the strength of her new decision, and 
then, turning, began to entertain those next her with an unwonted 
spirit. 
</p><p>"She has needed," I replied to the Baron, "but one thing,&mdash;to 
be aroused, to be kindled.  See, it is done!  I have thought that 
a life of cabinets and policy might achieve this, for her talent is 
second not even to her beauty." 
</p><p>"It is unhappy that both should be wasted," said the Baron.  
"She, of course, will never marry." 
</p><p>"Why not?" 
</p><p>"For various reasons." 
</p><p>"One?" 
</p><p>"She is poor." 
</p><p>"Which will not signify to your Excellency.  Another?" 
</p><p>"She is too beautiful.  One would fall in love with her.  And 
to love one's own wife&mdash;it is ridiculous!" 
</p><p>"Who should know?" I asked. 
</p><p>"All the world would suspect and laugh." 
</p><p>"Let those laugh that win." 
</p><p>"No,&mdash;she would never do as a wife; but then as"&mdash; 
</p><p>"But then in France we do not insult hospitality!" 
</p><p>The Baron transferred his gaze to me for a moment, then tapped 
his snuff-box, and approached the circle round Delphine. 
</p><p>It was odd that we, the arch enemies of the hour, could speak 
without the intervention of seconds; but I hoped that the Baron's 
conversation might be diverting,&mdash;the Baron hoped that mine might 
be didactic. 
</p><p>They were very gay with Delphine.  He leaned on the back of a 
chair and <pb n="171"/>  listened.  One spoke of the new gallery of the 
Tuileries, and the five pavilions,&mdash;a remark which led us to 
architecture. 
</p><p>"We all build our own houses," said Delphine, at last, "and 
then complain that they cramp us here, and the wind blows in there, 
while the fault is not in the order, but in us, who increase here 
and shrink there without reason." 
</p><p>"You speak in metaphors," said the Baron. 
</p><p>"Precisely.  A truth is often more visible veiled than nude." 
</p><p>"We should soon exhaust the orders," I interposed; "for who 
builds like his neighbor?" 
</p><p>"Slight variations, Monsieur!  Though we take such pains to 
conceal the style, it is not difficult to tell the order of 
architecture chosen by the builders in this room.  My mother, for 
instance,&mdash;you perceive that her pavilion would be the florid 
Gothic." 
</p><p>"Mademoiselle's is the Doric," I said. 
</p><p>"Has been," she murmured, with a quick glance. 
</p><p>"And mine, Mademoiselle?" asked the Baron, indifferently. 
</p><p>"Ah, Monsieur," she returned, looking serenely upon him, "when 
one has all the winning cards in hand and yet loses the stake, we 
allot him <hi rend="italic"> un pavillon chinois</hi>,"&mdash;which was the polite way of 
dubbing him Court Fool. 
</p><p>The Baron's eyes fell.  Vexation and alarm were visible on his 
contracted brow.  He stood in meditation for some time.  It must 
have been evident to him that Delphine knew of the recent 
occurrences,&mdash;that here in Paris she could denounce him as the 
agenty of a felony, the participant of a theft.  What might prevent 
it?  Plainly but one thing: no woman would denounce her husband.  
He had scarcely contemplated this step on arrival. 
</p><p>The guests were again scattered in groups round the room.  I 
examined an engraving on an adjacent table.  Delphine reclined as 
lazily in a <hi rend="italic">fauteuil</hi> as if her life did not hang in the 
balance.  The Baron drew near. 
</p><p>"Mademoiselle," said he, "you allotted me just now a cap and 
bells.  If two should wear it?&mdash;if I should invite another into my 
<hi rend="italic">pavillon chinois</hi>?&mdash;if I should propose to complete an alliance, 
desired by my father, with the ancient family of St. Cyr?&mdash;if, in 
short, Mademoiselle, I should request you to become my wife?" 
</p><p><hi rend="italic">" Eh, bien, Monsieur</hi>,&mdash;and if you should?" I heard her 
coolly reply. 
</p><p>But it was no longer any business of mine.  I rose and sought 
Mme. de St. Cyr, who, I thought, was slightly uneasy, perceiving 
some mystery to be afloat.  After a few words, I retired. 
</p><p>Archimedes, as perhaps you have never heard, needed only a 
lever to move the world.  Such a lever I had put into the hands of 
Delphine, with which she might move, not indeed the grand globe, 
with its multiplied attractions, relations, and affinities, but the 
lesser world of circumstances, of friends and enemies, the circle 
of hopes, fears, ambitions.  There is no woman, as I believe, but 
could have used it. 
 
</p><p>The next day was scarcely so quiet in the city as usual.  The 
great loan had not been negotiated.  Both the Baron Stahl and the 
English minister had left Paris,&mdash;and there was a <hi rend="italic"> coup d'etat</hi>. 
</p><p>But the Baron did not travel alone.  There had been a ceremony 
at midnight in the Church of St. Sulpice, and her Excellency the 
Baroness Stahl, <hi rend="italic">nee</hi> de St. Cyr, accompanied him. 
</p><p>It is a good many years since.  I have seen the diamond in the 
Duchess of X.'s coronet, at the drawing-room, often,&mdash;but I have 
never seen Delphine.  The Marquis begged me to retain the chain, 
and I gave myself the pleasure of presenting it, through her 
mother, to the Baroness Stahl.  I hear, that, whenever she desires 
to effect any cherished object which the Baron opposes, she has 
only to wear this chain, and effect it.  It appears to possess a 
magical power, and its potent spell enslaves the Baron as the lamp 
and ring of Eastern tales enslaved the Afrites. <pb n="172"/>  The life 
she leads has aroused her.  She is no longer the impassive Silence; 
she has found her fire.  I hear of her as the charm of a brilliant 
court, as the soul of a nation of intrigue.  Of her beauty one does 
not speak, but her talent is called prodigious.  What impels me to 
ask the idle question, If it were well to save her life for this?  
Undoubtedly she fills a station which, in that empire, must be the 
summit of a woman's ambition.  Delphine's Liberty was not a 
principle, but a dissatisfaction.  The Baroness Stahl is vehement, 
is Imperialist, is successful.  While she lives, it is on the top 
of the wave; when she dies,&mdash;ah! what business has Death in such a 
world? 
</p><p>As I said, I have never seen Delphine since her marriage.  The 
beautiful statuesque girl occupies a niche into which the blazing 
and magnificent <hi rend="italic">intrigante</hi> cannot crowd.  I do not wish to be 
disillusioned.  She has read me a riddle,&mdash;Delphine is my Sphinx. 
 
</p><p>As for Mr. Hay,&mdash;I once said the Antipodes were tributary to 
me, not thinking that I should ever become tributary to the 
Antipodes.  But such is the case; since, partly through my 
instrumentality, that enterprising individual has been located in 
their vicinity, where diamonds are not to be had for the asking, 
and the greatest rogue is not a Baron. 
</p> 
</div1>
 
</body> 
</text> 
</TEI.2> 
 
 
