<?xml version="1.0"?>

<?dlps id="RagPush"?>
<?dlps page-images="none" figure-images="no"?>
<?dlps transcription="other"?>

<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/tei-p4/tei2.dtd" [
<!ENTITY % POSTKB "INCLUDE">
<!ENTITY % TEI.extensions.ent SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.ent">
<!ENTITY % TEI.extensions.dtd SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.dtd">
<!ENTITY % ISOnum SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/charent/iso-num.ent"> %ISOnum;
<!ENTITY % ISOlat1 SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/charent/iso-lat1.ent"> %ISOlat1;
<!ENTITY % ISOpub SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/charent/iso-pub.ent"> %ISOpub;
 
]> 
<TEI.2 id="RagPush"> 
<teiHeader type="migrated" creator="Etext">
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title type="main">Pushkin and His Work</title>
<title type="sort">pushkin and his work</title>
<author>Ragozin, Zenide A.</author>
<respStmt>
<resp>Creation of machine-readable version:</resp>  
<name>Judy Boss</name>  
<resp>Conversion to TEI.2-conformant markup:</resp>  
<name>University of Virginia Library Electronic Text Center.</name>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt>  
<extent>ca. <num type="kilobytes">40</num> kilobytes</extent>  
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>University of Virginia Library</publisher>
<pubPlace>Charlottesville, Virginia</pubPlace>  
<idno type="ETC">RagPush</idno>  
<date value="1996">1996</date>
<availability status="public">
<p n="copyright">Copyright &copy; 1996 by the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia</p>
<p n="access">Publicly accessible</p>
</availability>
<idno type="uva-pid">uva-lib:476342</idno>
</publicationStmt>
<seriesStmt>
<title>University of Virginia Library, Text collection</title>
<idno type="uva-set">UVA-LIB-Text</idno>
</seriesStmt>  
<sourceDesc>
<biblFull>
<titleStmt>
<title type="main">Pushkin and His Work</title>
<title level="j">Cosmopolitan</title>
<title type="sort">pushkin and his work</title>
<author>Zena&iuml;de A. Ragozin</author>
</titleStmt>  
<extent>pp 307-314.</extent>  
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>Cosmopolitan Publishing Company</publisher>  
<pubPlace>Irvington on the Hudson (NY)</pubPlace>  
<date value="1900-01">January 1900</date>
</publicationStmt>  
<notesStmt>
<note>
<p>The Cosmopolitan, Vol. 28, No.3, January 1900. Copy consulted: UVA Library Call Number AP2 .C8</p>
</note>
</notesStmt>
</biblFull>
</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc>  
<encodingDesc>
<projectDesc>
<p>Prepared for the University of Virginia Library Electronic Text Center.</p>
</projectDesc>  
<editorialDecl>
<p>All quotation marks retained as data.</p>  
<p>All unambiguous end-of-line hyphens have been removed, and the trailing part of a word has been joined to the preceding line.</p>  
<p>Keywords in the header are a local Electronic Text Center scheme to aid in establishing analytical groupings.</p>
</editorialDecl>  
<refsDecl>
<p>ID elements are given for each page element and are composed of the  
text's unique cryptogram and the given page number, as in AusEmma1 for  
page one of Jane Austen's Emma.</p>
</refsDecl>  
</encodingDesc>  
<profileDesc>
<creation>
<date value="1900">1900</date>
</creation>  
<langUsage>
<language id="eng" usage="main">English</language>
</langUsage>  
<textClass>
<keywords>
<term>non-fiction; prose</term>
</keywords>  
</textClass>
</profileDesc>  
<revisionDesc>
<change>
<date value="1996-09">September 1996</date>  
<respStmt>
<resp>corrector</resp>  
<name>Stephen Ramsay, Electronic Text Center</name>
</respStmt>  
<item>Added TEI header and tags.</item>
</change>  
<change>
<date value="2005-07">July 2005</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>Corrector</resp>
<name>John Ivor Carlson</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Converted SGML to XML and/or corrected tagging.</item>
</change>
<change>
<date value="2007-09">September 2007</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>Migration</resp>
<name>Ethan Gruber, University of Virginia Library</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Converted XML markup from TEI Lite to uva-dl-tei (TEI P4 with local customizations).</item>
</change>
<change>
<date value="2008-01">January 2008</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>Migration</resp>
<name>Greg Murray, University of Virginia Library</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Programmatically updated TEI header markup (but not header content) for minimal compliance with current QA requirements.</item>
</change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>  
 
 
<text id="d1">  
<body id="d2">
	<div1 type="essay" id="d3">  <pb n="307"/>  
<head>Ragozin, Zena&iuml;de A.  "Pushkin and His Work." 
     <hi rend="italic">Cosmopolitan</hi> 28 (Jan. 1900): 307-314.</head> 

<p>IT may be a long time yet before Russian poetry is anything more 
than a word to the great bulk of the English-reading public, and 
the name of Kalid&acirc;sa or Fird&ucirc;si would convey to the 
average mind a far more definite impression than the name of 
Ma&iuml;kof, Polonsky or Nekr&agrave;ssof&mdash;because every one who is 
at all on familiar terms with books has met at least the names of 
the Hindoo and the Persian poet, while it is absolutely certain 
that not one in a thousand habitual readers, or even students of 
literature, ever comes across those of the Russians.  Yet one name 
there is, which has pierced through the barrier raised by race 
difference and an exceedingly difficult language, and is at least 
as familiar to English and American ears as those of the two 
Orientals: the name of Pushkin, the centennial anniversary of whose 
birth was celebrated last year all over Russia. 
</p><p>There is in this a certain unconscious justice; in this sense, 
that if ever there was a representative national writer, who 
absorbed all the vital sap of his native soil, who embodied all the 
elements of which his nation was composed, and reflected every side 
and aspect of that nation's life, that writer was Pushkin.  He even 
enacted in his own person, in the brief thirty-seven years of his 
life, the process of evolution through which his country has passed 
within this century.  He was born the Russia of the end of the 
eighteenth century; he died the Russia of to-day. 
</p><p>There are many currents in Russian thought: the philosophical, 
the cosmopolitan, the patriotic, the conservative, the opposition 
(the latter embodied in what is called "denunciatory literature"); 
to gain a knowledge of all, and from them to form a faithful 
picture of the country's spiritual and material life, one would 
have to read the several writers, each of whom represents some 
particular fraction of the whole.  But if ever the complete works 
of Pushkin are presented in a worthy translation, a thorough study 
of them will bring before the reader Russia "in her habit as she 
lives"&mdash;with her greatness and her faults, her large-hearted 
lovableness and her foibles, her passionate patriotism and as 
passionate protest&mdash;the "large and liberal discontent" which 
William Watson counts among "the things that are more excellent"&mdash; 
her pregnant possibilities and all-embracing humanity.  Yes, 
Pushkin is Russia, all Russia, the national poet in the widest 
sense, as was strikingly shown during his centennial when each of 
the numerous political and intellectual fractions, from the highest 
official circles to the "reddest" radical cliques, claimed him for 
its own and could support its claim from passages in his works and 
in his life. 
</p><p>And yet he was, ethnologically, not all Russian.  He had, on 
his mother's side, a generous admixture of foreign blood&mdash;African 
blood.  His great-grandfather, Abraham (Ibrahim) Petrovitch 
Hannibal, was a full-blood Abyssinian princeling who had been 
stolen in infancy by slave dealers and brought to Constantinople.  
The Russian ambassador saw him there in a pasha's household, and 
was so delighted with the child's pretty antics that the pasha gave 
him the boy to take home.  The ambassador, in turn, presented 
little Ibrahim to his imperial master, Peter the Great, who took a 
great fancy to him, stood godfather at his baptism, and kept him 
about his person.  Always bright, the boy now developed exceptional 
cleverness, and Peter, who was not the man to neglect any 
intellectual promise, had him carefully taught under his own eyes.  
In 1716 he took young Ibrahim with him on his European journey, and 
left him in Paris to complete his education with several other 
young noblemen, under the surveillance of the Russian legation.  
There he was petted and lionized and had altogether such a good 
time that he could with difficulty be prevailed upon to return to 
Petersburg; in fact, it was only a personal appeal from Peter to 
his godson's good feeling and affection which brought him back 
post-haste, at the cost of much regret and even heartache.  After 
Peter's death he joined the party opposed to the tyranny of the  
<pb n="308"/>   
all-powerful favorite, Prince Menshikof, and was removed to 
Siberia, on garrison duty which amounted to polite exile, but was 
promptly called back when his benefactor's daughter Elizabeth 
ascended the throne.  He then rose from grade to grade at court and 
in the army until he retired to his estates in the rank of general-en-chef.   
He died, at a very advanced age, in 1781.  His eldest son 
distinguished himself in the naval war against Turkey under Orlof, 
and founded the city of Kherson.  His granddaughter Nadejda was 
Pushkin's mother. 
</p><p>Pushkin's father belonged to the old noblesse.  One of his 
ancestors played a prominent part in the reign of Ivan IV. (the 
Terrible), and in the eventful inter-regnum and civil wars which 
ended in the election of Michael Romanof to the throne.  He was an 
aristocrat of a type produced by the complex influences of a court 
presided over by the imperial philosopher and philanthropist who, 
by her genius and personal charm, achieved the incredible feat of 
reconciling a craze for Rousseau, Voltaire and the Encyclopedists 
with the most loyal absolutism.  Catherine II. loved Russia with a 
patriotic fervor, and a rare appreciation of the national 
character, to which her private correspondence alone would bear 
sufficient witness.  Her enthusiasm for the language of her adopted 
country was almost prophetic, for in her time it was only beginning 
to unfold its literary possibilities; it was reserved for our poet 
to bring out all its richness and flexibility, all the music of its 
infinite variety.  Yet one of the most direct effects of her 
influence upon her immediate surroundings&mdash;the court, and thence 
upon the ruling minority known as "society"&mdash;was to complete what 
had been begun by Peter's foreign importations and continued by his 
daughter Elizabeth's French predilections, i.e., to denationalize, 
to a certain extent and superficially only, the upper ten thousand, 
to estrange them from their own people, and to give them an 
artificial veneer of French culture which only the tenacity of 
ineradicable race qualities prevented from going deep enough to 
vitiate the vital spring of nationality.  The most dangerous 
symptom of this disease was a contempt for all things native and 
for the intelligence of the masses&mdash;in other words, for all who did 
not speak French words, think French thoughts and wear French 
dress. 
</p><p>Such was the atmosphere in which little Alexander grew and 
developed&mdash;very much at his own sweet will; for his mother&mdash;a 
clever, cold, worldly woman&mdash;was not fond of him, finding him 
unsociable and undemonstrative.  She did not conceal her preference 
for his sister Olga and his brother Leo, and it does credit to all 
the children that their mutual affection was not impaired by these 
unnatural conditions.  Alexander's loving, ardent nature might have 
suffered, but he had a haven of refuge in the room of his 
grandmother Hannibal.  Thither he fled from the persecutions of the 
French governesses who were the bane of his existence, and once 
ensconced in the old lady's huge workbasket he was inviolable. 
</p><p>His other good fairy was his peasant nurse, Arina 
Rodi&oacute;novna, to whom Russia owes a monument by the side of 
her nursling's.  But the time of her saving influence was yet to 
come.  Just now the boy made his headquarters in his father's 
library, with the result that, at eleven, "he knew French 
literature by heart," as his brother said later with only 
pardonable exaggeration, and was beginning to try his hand at 
clever little poems&mdash;vers d'occasion&mdash;and even a bit of comedy 
inspired by Moli&egrave;re, an author in whom his father especially 
delighted and whose works he frequently read to his family with 
masterly elocution. 
</p><p>Alexander was twelve years old when the school question came 
up, and he barely escaped being sent to the Jesuit College, a 
fashionable and high-toned institution very popular at the time 
among the Petersburg aristocracy.  It was through the efforts and 
influence of a patriotic friend of the family.  A. F. 
Tourgu&eacute;nief, that he was received instead into the newly 
opened Lyceum at Ts&aacute;rskoy&eacute;-Sel&ograve;.  Here the boy 
found most favorable conditions for the free development of his 
character.  The hitherto repressed genial side of his nature 
expanded and blossomed out in the atmosphere of warm-hearted 
comradeship, which in some cases matured into serious, lifelong 
friendships.  The Lyceum, a very exclusive, <pb n="309"/>  aristocratic 
institution, was conducted on exceptionally liberal lines, possibly 
too liberal in some ways.  A rather dangerous margin of liberty was 
left to the young fellows, and it was not strange that they should 
be wild.  Pushkin's particular set was not the soberest, but it was 
the most talented, enthusiastic and generous.  His popularity, 
however, was not limited to a few; he soon became the poet-laureate 
of the school.  At first he was nicknamed "the Frenchman"; but the 
general spirit of the place was rather more Russian than his 
environment at home had been, and he was gradually drawn into using 
his native language.  The artist's creative chord was touched, and 
we have sundry short poems of this early period, written for 
special festive occasions, which are little gems.  His fame, 
indeed, spread far beyond the Lyceum walls, and the best literary 
men of the time began to expect great things of him.  The regular 
studies did not fare so well.  The masters, while loving and 
admiring him, were compelled to mark him down as indolent and 
careless, and he was graduated the nineteenth on the list. 
</p><p>This poor showing, however, does not seem to have greatly 
affected him, nor did it prevent his being the hero of his class, 
the pride of both faculty and students.  For he was, of course, the 
poet of the occasion, and the poem, "Reminiscences of 
Ts&aacute;rskoy&eacute;-Sel&ograve;," which he delivered from the 
platform before the most select, the most representative audience 
which court and city could have mustered, was a strangely mature 
production&mdash;a loving retrospect on the boundary-line between the 
beautiful dreamland which school had been to him and his chosen 
circle of friends, and the mysterious reality beyond, the whole 
instinct with that prophetic sadness which all true poets have 
known in the very flush of youthful spirits and joyousness.  The 
young poet knew that among the audience sat Derj&aacute;vin, the 
eagle of the preceding literary era, the creator of the Russian 
ode, to whom the great Catherine had been "Felicia," as Elizabeth 
had been "Gloriana" to Spenser, and the consciousness almost robbed 
Pushkin of his voice, especially when he addressed the aged poet 
with his last strophe, which as a homage to "Russia's inspired 
bard."  Derj&aacute;vin, making his way through the congratulating 
throng, stood before his youthful successor with markedly inclined 
head, in reverential attitude, about to bestow on him a warm 
embrace.  This was too much for the emotional boy of sixteen, and&mdash; 
he ran away.  That same day Pushkin's father was present at a 
dinner given by Count Razumofsky, Minister of Public Instruction, 
and Alexander's quick talent, present success and future promise 
formed the main theme of conversation.  Derj&aacute;vin was 
present, and, as was his wont, silent, if not glum.  But when the 
Minister, courteously addressing Pushkin, said, "And yet, I should 
like to train your son for prose work," the old lion growled, "Let 
the boy alone; he is a poet."  This was his consecration. 
</p><p>The following four years of Alexander's life may be summed up 
in three words: study, writing, society life.  Equally eager, 
equally indefatigable, in all, he spent himself so recklessly that, 
before he was twenty-one, he had twice worked and danced himself 
into brain-fever.  Society always exercised a fascinating&mdash;and in 
the end, alas! fatal-influence over him.  This was an exciting 
time, too, with many serious, and even dangerous, elements seething 
and fermenting under the frivolous surface.  There were other 
things than society gossip and love-making going on under cover of 
all the banqueting and dancing, and the young men who feasted most 
wildly and danced most assiduously were those whom, five years 
later, the ill-advised, ill-fated outbreak of the 14th of December 
sent to the gallows or the mines, or, at the best, into Siberian 
exile.  For it is well known that only the flower of the capital's 
aristocracy was concerned in the conspiracy ostensibly directed 
against the accession of Nicholas I.  And they were, most of them, 
Pushkin's intimates.  It was impossible, with his impulsive nature 
and facile pen, that he should not become implicated, and there 
were verses of his, written between two cups of champagne and 
circulated in manuscript copies, which of course found their way 
into the Emperor's hands and sorely puzzled him as to what he 
should do with the author. 
</p><p>Nicholas was proud of Russian talent and honestly desirous of 
furthering the <pb n="310"/>  progress of Russian literature, to the 
extent of stretching important points in its favor.  Thus, when 
Karamz&eacute;n undertook his colossal work, "The History of the 
Russian Empire," he was granted access to the most secret state 
archives and exempted from the control of the Censor's office.  In 
young Pushkin's case the Emperor was naturally inclined to 
leniency, and the poet's friends fought a battle half won already 
when they interceded in his favor.  Karamz&eacute;n undertook to 
give him a parental talking-to and obtained from him the promise 
that he would not again swamp Russia with subversive poetry.  So, 
instead of being sent to some Siberian city or to a remote 
monastery, he was given some good advice and one thousand roubles 
traveling money, and ordered to Ekaterinoslav in the south of 
Russia, there to join the staff of Governor Inzof, one of the 
wisest and kindest old generals in the service, who received him 
with open arms, settled him in his own house to keep him out of 
harm's way, and treated him altogether as a son. 
</p><p>Although Pushkin appreciated this kindness and became warmly 
attached to his gentle mentor, he was not happy.  Moody and 
restless, he often gave the old general, who was in a way 
responsible for him, a good deal of anxiety.  The poet's health 
broke down again; he was sent on a trip to the Caucasus and the 
Crimea, in the company of a friendly and reliable family.  His 
letters betray low spirits, at times even temper; but there is no 
trace of either in the wonderful poems&mdash;"The Captive of the 
Caucasus" and "The Fountain of Baktchi-Sarae"&mdash;for which 
inspiration was supplied by the magnificent scenery and the 
romantic memories of those semi-Eastern countries. 
</p><p>So much traveling, if anything, increased the spirit of 
restlessness which would not suffer Pushkin to settle down 
contentedly.  He was seized with a violent longing for the sea, and 
with some difficulty persuaded General Inzof to transfer him to 
Odessa.  On the way thither he stumbled on some encamped gipsies 
and wandered off with them, making himself perfectly at home and a 
great favorite.  To this whim we owe a charming poem, "The 
Gipsies," somewhat in the Byronian vein. 
 
</p><p>Odessa was the most European of Russian cities after St. 
Petersburg.  There he found again a brilliant society, Italian 
opera, and was delighted.  But not for long.  The Governor, Count 
Vorontsof, was kind, but&mdash;wanted him to work, setting him various 
official tasks.  The poet grew restless, and, it must be confessed, 
tried his chief's patience almost beyond endurance.  The south was 
visited that year with the locust plague, and Vorontsof sent 
Pushkin as special commissioner to study the plague on the spot and 
report on the damage done, possible remedies, et cetera, et cetera.  
The report came in due time; it read as follows:&mdash;</p> 
 
<lg type="poem"><l>"The locusts came amain,</l> 
<l>And settled on the plain;</l> 
<l>They ate up all the grain,</l> 
<l>And flew away again."</l></lg> 
 
<p>No one will blame Vorontsof for urgently requesting to be 
relieved of such a subordinate. 
</p><p>The poet in May, 1824, was ordered home, to his parents' 
estate of Mikh&aacute;&iuml;lofskoy&eacute; in the government of 
Pskof (a couple of days from Petersburg; now, by rail, a few 
hours), and was placed under his own father's surveillance.  The 
old gentleman was not overmuch pleased to have the custody of his 
wayward son, and did not make things very easy for him.  Yet the 
two years of his forced retirement were probably the most fruitful 
and altogether beneficial of Pushkin's career.  In this peaceful 
retreat, with his time all his own, with all his faculties well 
centered and in healthy working order, free from the disturbing 
claims and influences of social life, once for all he "found 
himself," to use a truly profound German expression.  In this work 
of moral recuperation his main help and solace was the 
companionship of his old peasant nurse, Arina Rodi&oacute;novna.  
She was a superior woman, without being in the least aware of it, 
of a rural type which is fast dying out&mdash;if not already dead&mdash;in 
all countries: an inexhaustible mine of folk-lore.  In his early 
boyhood, surfeited with the cold artificialities of the late and 
contemporary French school, Pushkin had unconsciously enjoyed his 
nurse's songs and stories as a drink from a pure, cold spring, and 
in the Lyceum days he had begun his fantastic tale, "Rusl&aacute;n 
<pb n="311"/>  and Ludmila," on folk-lore motives from the national 
heroic-ballad cycle.  Now he turned to her consciously to draw 
through her the unalloyed vigor of his native soil, the uncorrupted 
national spirit, the undiluted richness, raciness and grace of his 
native language&mdash;in short, as he said himself, to get rid of the 
last vestige of what he called his "confounded French education." 
</p><p>The external routine of Pushkin's life at 
Mikh&aacute;&iuml;lofskoy&eacute; was that of any society man from 
the capital thrown for a time on the resources of nature and a 
country neighborhood, as described with masterly vividness in his 
novel (in verse), "Eugene Oni&eacute;gin."  But many hours of each 
day were given to work in his own plain sitting-room, where he 
mostly spent his evenings in the company of his old nurse, always 
as eager to listen as she was willing to talk.  The folk-tales 
which Pushkin put into verse directly from her words, preserving 
with marvelous tact the characteristic turns and epic forms of the 
narrative, are among the most charming productions of his lighter 
vein. 
</p><p>Thus the terrible year 1825 came and went.  Pushkin, in his 
position of semi-exile, was spared many perplexities, many 
temptations.  That he could not have kept out of the trouble had he 
been entirely at liberty, he freely admitted to the Emperor himself 
in a confidential audience to which he was summoned by imperial 
order in September, 1826.  Nicholas was gracious. 
</p><p>"Pushkin," he suddenly asked, at the end of a long talk, 
"should you have taken part in the 14th of December if you had been 
in Petersburg?" 
</p><p>"Most undoubtedly I should, sire," promptly replied the poet.  
"All my friends were in it, and I could not have kept away.  Only 
absence saved me, for which I thank God." 
</p><p>"Well," said the Emperor, "you have had enough fooling.  I 
hope that you will be sensible after this, and that we shall not 
quarrel any more.  You shall send me all you write; I myself will 
be your censor." 
</p><p>From this day to that of the poet's premature death Nicholas 
never wavered in his kindly disposition, to which he gave 
expression openly on more than one occasion, although there were 
petty jealousies enough at work, always on hand with slanderous 
insinuations&mdash;the usual thing, never absent at any court. 
</p><p>It might have been better for Pushkin in every way could he 
have kept away from court circles and so-called society life 
generally.  But that life with its luxurious setting appealed to 
the beauty-loving and excitable side of his poet's nature, and he 
never could resist its glamour.  His marriage in 1830 with an 
extremely beautiful but rather shallow-minded and pleasure-loving 
young girl, Natalie Gontchar&oacute;f, only drew him deeper into 
the vortex, from which no escape was possible thereafter.  His 
wife's tastes, and partly his own, necessitated a style of living 
far beyond his means, and the pressure of debt and various 
entanglements made itself felt from year to year, even though the 
very considerable income from his writings, added to his own 
fortune, should have afforded him a more than comfortable 
competency.  But he was, of course, an indifferent business man.  
His estates were ill managed and yielded irregular returns.  Add to 
all this occasional losses at the card-table&mdash;an inevitable 
standing feature of Russian high life at that time, and much later, 
too&mdash;and it will be seen that our poet had more than his share of 
those petty, nagging material cares which were so particularly 
distasteful to him. 
</p><p>About this time, too, a change was taking place in his 
heretofore open and genial nature.  The criticism with which each 
of his forthcoming works was met, upset and irritated him.  For it 
was ignorant, or at least incompetent, criticism.  The trouble was 
that there <hi rend="italic">could</hi> be no critics for him.  His most important 
works were appearing in quick succession just in these years and&mdash; 
they puzzled their readers.  He was innovating, creating, in every 
direction, and the editors of the critical departments in the 
contemporary magazines, with the best will, handled him either 
roughly or awkwardly, because they had no standards by which to 
judge him: <hi rend="italic">he was creating the standards</hi>.  He had to educate 
a generation capable of criticising him, and it may be asserted 
that it is only the great men who may be called his spiritual 
posterity&mdash;the great modern Russian writers&mdash;who have grown up to 
the task.  He <pb n="312"/>  felt that he was misapprehended or not 
understood at all.  Modest as all true genius is, he was at first 
staggered; in a moment of despondency he went so far as to write 
(in a letter to a friend): "Perhaps, after all, innovations are 
unnecessary."  But the weakness was momentary; the rebound of self-consciousness  
prompt and vigorous.  The genius in him asserted its 
supreme rights, its inviolable majesty.  He <hi rend="italic">knew</hi> he was 
right, though he could have given no reason&mdash;he never was good at 
arguing.  The revulsion was complete and final, and left him a 
sterner, more unbending man than he had been naturally inclined to 
be.  It was when he had arrived at this last phase of his 
intellectual development that he wrote a brief and pithy profession 
of faith of which the following claims at least to be a true 
rendering:&mdash;</p> 
 
<lg type="poem"><l>"Poet! court not the favor of the many!</l> 
<l>For short-lived are the transports of applause,</l> 
<l>And fools shall sit in judgment over thee,</l> 
<l>And thou shalt hear the world's unfeeling laugh.</l> 
<l>Be thou through all impassive, strong and stern.</l> 
<l>Thou art a king: so live&mdash;alone.  The path</l> 
<l>Freely pursue where thy free genius calls,</l> 
<l>Maturing ever the fruits of loving thought,</l> 
<l>Demanding no reward for work achieved.</l> 
<l>'Tis in thyself.  Thyself thy judge supreme;</l> 
<l>No critic's censure more severe than thine.</l> 
<l>Fastidious artist, look upon thy work:</l> 
<l>Art thou content?  Then let the world abuse it,</l> 
<l>The altar spurn which holds thy sacred flame,</l> 
<l>And try in childish, mischief-loving glee</l> 
<l>Thy tripod to o'erturn, thy throne divine."</l></lg> 
 
<p>The immediate occasion of this hardening transformation was 
the unfavorable reception awarded to the best-loved child of his 
Muse, the work he knew to be most perfect, most mature&mdash;his 
national historical tragedy of "Boris Godun&oacute;f."  He had 
written it entirely during those fruitful years at 
Mikh&aacute;&iuml;lofskoy&eacute;, and had kept it six years in his 
portfolio, shrinking to the last from actual publication.  For he 
knew it was too novel to please the general public, who object to 
being startled; he felt it to be beyond his contemporaries, with 
the exception of his own small chosen circle.  He foresaw the 
result; yet, when it came, it hurt him sorely, and, for a time, 
upset his mental balance. 
</p><p>The great innovation in Pushkin's tragedy was that he did not 
treat it on the lines of French pseudo-classicism, but on those of 
the Shakespearean histories.  He had been for a time, like all his 
contemporaries, under the spell of Byron's magnificent poetry and 
morbid views of life and men.  But this influence was dispelled 
like mist before the morning sun when Shakespeare's glory burst on 
him.  He studied him closely and lovingly; how searchingly and 
understandingly is shown by many stray bits of criticism scattered 
through his letters. 
</p><p>"I never read either Calderon or Lope de Vega," Pushkin 
writes, in a precious letter in which he opens a glimpse into the 
sanctum of his work, "but what a man is Shakespeare!  I cannot get 
over him.  How paltry Byron is by his side&mdash;Byron the dramatist, 
who in all his life understood only one character&mdash;his own. . . .  
To one of his personages he gave his pride, to another his hatred, 
to a third his moody melancholy.  Thus out of one complete, gloomy 
and powerful character he made several insignificant ones.  That is 
not tragedy. . . .  There is another common error.  Having 
conceived a character, everything the author makes him say, even to 
the most indifferent, becomes distinctive and typical&mdash;like the 
pedants and sailors in Fielding's old novels.  A conspirator asks 
for a glass of water in the manner of a conspirator&mdash;and makes 
himself ridiculous. . . .  Now take Shakespeare.  He lets his 
characters speak and act with all the careless naturalness of real 
life, because he is sure, at the right moment, to make them strike 
the right note." 
</p><p>To Pushkin's admiration and knowledge of Shakespeare we owe 
two more productions in two very different veins: a translation, or 
rather adaptation, under the title of "Angelo," of "Measure for 
Measure," grave and stern, and wholly worthy of the original; and 
a story in light, frolicsome verse, a charming bit of fun, which 
may be called a parody on "Lucretia"&mdash;in this way: Pushkin happened 
to read the tale of the Roman matron's woes while in a particularly 
jocose mood, and the mad thought struck him, as he laid it down, 
"What if she had not taken things so tragically, but had simply&mdash; 
boxed Tarquin's ears!"  The idea amused him so much that he allowed 
it to take tangible shape in "Count Noolin," a modern version  
<pb n="313"/>  of the ancient story, enacted between a young and beautiful 
chatelaine and a young city Lovelace, bored and idle, her neighbor 
in the country, with just the d&eacute;nouement he had imagined. 
</p><p>A list of Pushkin's works would be dry reading.  Suffice it to 
say that his "Eugene Oni&eacute;gin" may possibly be accounted his 
greatest work.  It is, in the highest sense, a society novel, which 
can be likened only to Thackeray's "Vanity Fair."  It rivals 
Thackeray's masterpiece in scope, in power and grace, in vividness 
and depth, and as a wholly representative picture of the time and 
society it portrays, with an undercurrent of pensiveness and 
pathos, which belongs to the race, irrespective of time and 
setting.  Add to all this the charm of matchless versification, 
sprightly, abundant, spontaneous and musical as a mountain spring, 
and you will have a gem of a water and cut which would be hard to 
match in any literature. 
</p><p>A historical novel in prose, "The Captain's Daughter," 
depicting scenes from the terrible peasant uprising under 
Pugatch&oacute;f, in Catherine's reign; a history of the same; 
journalistic work (critical essays, traveling notes, et cetera); 
short stories; folk-tales in verse; ballads&mdash;there is hardly a 
literary form of which he has not left at least one specimen: and 
it is always a perfect one, a model of its kind. 
</p><p>The quantity of historical notes, fragmentary material, 
jottings of all kinds, which was found in his papers, gave heart-breaking  
evidence that when, at only thirty-seven, on that bleak 
January morning, he fell in a most unnecessary duel, he was 
snatched away in the very prime of his powers.  It is hardly 
orthodox to admit the necessity of <hi rend="italic">any</hi> duel; but this one 
surely was <hi rend="italic">most</hi> unnecessary, since there was no cause for it 
but society gossip, which should have been ignored and would then 
have quickly died out, or found some new pabulum.  But it was 
Pushkin's great misfortune to be extremely sensitive to what people 
said of him and his, and gossip had been busy for some time with 
his young wife's innocent, though possibly somewhat imprudent, 
conduct&mdash;and this was his most vulnerable point.  He became morose, 
irritable, entirely unlike his old warm-hearted, genial self. 
</p><p>The man around whom the gossip had centered, Baron 
d'Anth&egrave;s-Heckeren, a French officer in the Russian service, 
married Madame Pushkin's sister.  Pushkin's fierce African blood 
asserted itself in this affair, and the bloodthirsty spirit he 
showed on the field, insisting on his right to fire once more when 
already lying on the ground fatally hurt, as well as the regret he 
expressed at not having killed his adversary, greatly astonished 
his friends.  But the unholy feeling could not be of long duration 
in so noble a spirit.  Even as they were placing him in the 
carriage, he said: "Just now I thought it would have given me 
pleasure to kill him.  Now I don't care any more."  He lingered two 
days in unspeakable agony, heroically endured, and his one thought 
was to shield his wife.  "Poor girl," he kept repeating, "she 
suffers for no fault of hers." 
</p><p>Every Russian writer of any account has had occasion to 
express an opinion of Pushkin and his work.  Naturally, a good deal 
has been said that is unjust, or wide of the mark.  At one time it 
was rather the fashion, among a certain literary and political 
small fry, to speak of him disparagingly as of a mere society poet, 
and because, forsooth, he was no partisan, little dreaming that 
such an accusation against a thinker, a poet, a spirit which looks 
on the things of this world from its throne among the stars, is 
highest praise.  G&oacute;gol, Pushkin's friend and disciple, knew 
better when he wrote: "Pushkin was given to the world to show it 
what a poet is&mdash;one who is a poet and nothing else&mdash;a poet not 
influenced by any particular time or conditions, not even by his 
own personal character as a man, but independent of all things."  
Tourgu&eacute;nief, too, had a word to say which hit the mark: 
"Pushkin was a <hi rend="italic">central</hi> artist, a man who lived at the very 
core of Russian life."  That which is perfectly centered cannot 
incline to one side or the other.  "The core of his nation's life."  
What a place for a poet! with his ear to its heart, at the source 
whence spring all the manifold currents which underlie with their 
steadfast, directing reality the seemingly random play of the waves 
on the more or less troubled surface!  And another great voice now 
hushed in death, that of Michael Dostoy&eacute;fsky, spoke 
<pb n="314"/>  
of Pushkin as one in whose personality and work there was something 
undoubtedly prophetic of Russia's future destinies, her place among 
the nations&mdash;who first reflected one of our chief national 
characteristics: the longing for a large, a universal humanity, for 
a regeneration which should include not our race alone, but all 
mankind, for a solution of the contradictions and animosities which 
distract the European nations through the broad tolerance and 
generous sympathies of the Russian soul.  And, even apart from such 
world-wide aspirations and glimpses of a remote future, was he not 
a prophet, the man who, at a time when serfdom was considered a 
natural and necessary, indeed rather benign, institution, could 
give vent to his indignant feelings in such words as the 
following:&mdash;
 
<q>"A horrible thought fills my soul with gloom: 
here, in the midst of flourishing fields and hills, the lover of 
humanity sorrowfully notes everywhere the pernicious signs of shameful 
ignorance.  Blind to tears and deaf to moans, a scourge of men decreed 
by fate, a ruling class, unfeeling, lawless, wild, appropriates with 
ruthless rod the husbandman's labor, property and time."</q>
</p> 

<p><ref target="n314">[note]</ref> </p>

<p>And is not the following an inspired prophecy:&mdash;

<q><lg type="poem"><l>O friends! shall I behold a people 
unoppressed,</l><l>And serfdom fallen, abolished at our Czar's behest?
</l><l>And shall the dawning of enlightened freedom rise
</l><l>O'er this our land before my gladdened eyes?"</l></lg></q>
</p> 
<p>Less than thirty years later, Pushkin would have been in the 
front of the laborers for the cause which he was the first to 
herald.  Truly it had been a noble sight for the world! 
</p><p>Simple-minded and modest as Pushkin was in his maturity, he 
knew his own worth far better than any of his contemporaries could 
know it; and this his legitimate self-consciousness he recorded, 
with majestic assurance, without false humility, in the famous 
lines entitled "A Monument":&mdash; 
 
<q><lg type="stanza" n="1"><l>I have erected to myself a monument
</l><l>Such as was never raised by human hands.
</l><l>O'er Alexander's column towering high,
</l><l>It lifts its haughty crest o'er all the lands;
</l><l>Nor shall the path to it made by a people's feet
</l><l>In future times be grass-grown and untrod!
</l><l>Not all of me shall perish!  In my sacred lyre
</l><l>My spirit shall survive and still defy decay,
</l><l>And in this world my name with honor shall be spoken
</l><l>So long as but one poet sees the light of day. . . .
</l></lg><lg type="stanza" n="2"><l>
"To none but noble feelings did my lyre appeal;
</l><l>I sang of freedom's glory in a cruel age,
</l><l>And gentle mercy for the fallen I invoked:
</l><l>For this my people long will love their poet's page."
</l></lg></q> 
</p> 
<p>One of the numerous&mdash;too-numerous&mdash;articles and studies on 
Pushkin which his centennial anniversary has called forth likens 
him, the father of modern Russian literature, to a mighty tree, 
which plunges its roots far into Russia's past, and with its 
powerful branches supports the entire structure of that literature.  
The image can be improved upon.  Modern Russian literature may be 
likened to one of the banian forests in India, which are the growth 
of a single tree.  Pushkin is the parent trunk&mdash;with its roots in 
the past and its leafy crown in the blue ether&mdash;from which great 
limbs branch out, which in their turn take root, and each of 
which&mdash;G&oacute;gol, Tourgu&eacute;nief, Gontchar&ograve;f, 
Dostoy&eacute;fsky, Tolstoy&mdash;is a mighty tree.  And the numberless 
smaller shoots and saplings, which form the body of the forest, 
still live on the same sap, even while absorbing much nourishment 
directly from the native soil. 
 
</p><p>And yet, after all, the glory of Russia's national poet but 
reflects that of Russia herself.  For if it is true, as 
Tourgu&eacute;nief hopefully said, that such a language as the 
Russian could have been given to none but a great people, it may be 
said with equal truth that none but a great people could have given 
a Pushkin to the world.</p> 
 
<note id="n314"><seg type="note-symbol">[note]</seg> <p>It has never yet, to my knowledge, been 
pointed out how very significant it is, historically, that utterances 
like these and the lines which follow should have been allowed in 
print in the very heyday of muzzling censorship&mdash;especially when one 
remembers that Emperor Nicholas kept his word to the poet, and was, to 
his death, his only censor.  If the Emperor had not entertained and 
been maturing the project of emancipation which he bequeathed his son 
on his deathbed as a sacred duty, is it likely that he should have 
sanctioned the publication of such sentiments?  By the way, there is 
this to say for Russian censorship&mdash;that it always has shown respect 
and given great latitude to writers of real talent, serious thinkers. 
The works of our great writers teem with things for which any of the 
journalistic small fry would be severely disciplined.  Not to go any 
farther, we can see that in Tolstoy's novels.</p></note> 
 
</div1> 
 
</body> 
</text> 
</TEI.2> 
