<?xml version="1.0"?>

<?dlps id="RemWhit"?>
<?dlps page-images="none" figure-images="no"?>
<?dlps transcription="other"?>

<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/tei-p4/tei2.dtd" [
<!ENTITY % POSTKB "INCLUDE">
<!ENTITY % TEI.extensions.ent SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.ent">
<!ENTITY % TEI.extensions.dtd SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.dtd">
<!ENTITY % ISOnum SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/charent/iso-num.ent"> %ISOnum;
<!ENTITY % ISOpub SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/charent/iso-pub.ent"> %ISOpub;
 
]> 
<TEI.2 id="RemWhit"> 
<teiHeader type="migrated" creator="Etext">
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title type="main">A White Heart</title>
<title type="sort">white heart</title>
<author>Remizov, Aleksei</author>
<respStmt>
<resp>Creation of machine-readable version:</resp>  
<name>Judy Boss</name>  
<resp>Creation of digital images:</resp>  
<name/>  
<resp>Conversion to TEI.2-conformant markup:</resp>  
<name>University of Virginia Library Electronic Text Center.</name>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt>  
<extent>ca. <num type="kilobytes">12</num> kilobytes</extent>  
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>University of Virginia Library</publisher>
<pubPlace>Charlottesville, Virginia</pubPlace>  
<idno type="ETC">RemWhit</idno>  
<date value="1997">1997</date>
<availability status="public">
<p n="copyright">Copyright &copy; 1997 by the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia</p>
<p n="access">Publicly accessible</p>
</availability>
<idno type="uva-pid">uva-lib:476345</idno>
</publicationStmt>
<seriesStmt>
<title>University of Virginia Library, Text collection</title>
<idno type="uva-set">UVA-LIB-Text</idno>
</seriesStmt>  
<sourceDesc>
<biblFull>
<titleStmt>
<title type="main">A White Heart</title>
<title level="j">The Dial, vol. 70</title>
<title type="sort">white heart</title>
<author>Aleksei Remizov</author>
<respStmt>
<resp>Translator</resp>  
<name>John Cournos</name>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt>  
<extent>pp 65-68</extent>  
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>The Dial Publishing Company, Inc.</publisher>  
<pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>  
<date value="1921-01">January-June, 1921</date>  
<idno type="callNo">Print copy consulted: UVa Library AP2.D48</idno>
</publicationStmt>  
</biblFull>
</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc>  
<encodingDesc>
<projectDesc>
<p>Prepared for the University of Virginia Library Electronic Text Center.</p>
</projectDesc>  
<editorialDecl>
<p>All quotation marks retained as data.</p>  
<p>All unambiguous end-of-line hyphens have been removed, and the trailing part of a word has been joined to the preceding line.</p>  
<p>The images exist as archived TIFF images, one or more JPEG versions for general use, and thumbnail GIFs.</p>  
<p>Keywords in the header are a local Electronic Text Center scheme to aid in establishing analytical groupings.</p>
</editorialDecl>  
</encodingDesc>  
<profileDesc>
<creation>
<date value="1921">1921</date>
</creation>  
<langUsage>
<language id="eng" usage="main">English</language>
</langUsage>  
<textClass>
<keywords>
<term>prose; fiction</term>  
<term>Literature in Translation</term>
</keywords>  
</textClass>
</profileDesc>  
<revisionDesc>
<change>
<date value="1997-05">May, 1997</date>  
<respStmt>
<resp>corrector</resp>  
<name>Christine Ruotolo</name>
</respStmt>  
<item>Added TEI header and tags.</item>
</change>  
<change>
<date value="2005-07">July 2005</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>Corrector</resp>
<name>John Ivor Carlson</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Converted SGML to XML and/or corrected tagging.</item>
</change>
<change>
<date value="2007-09">September 2007</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>Migration</resp>
<name>Ethan Gruber, University of Virginia Library</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Converted XML markup from TEI Lite to uva-dl-tei (TEI P4 with local customizations).</item>
</change>
<change>
<date value="2008-01">January 2008</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>Migration</resp>
<name>Greg Murray, University of Virginia Library</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Programmatically updated TEI header markup (but not header content) for minimal compliance with current QA requirements.</item>
</change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>  
 
<text id="d1">  
<body id="d2"> 

<div1 type="story" id="d3"><pb n="65"/>   
<head> 
A WHITE HEART<lb/> 
BY ALEKSEI REMIZOV<lb/> 
<hi rend="italic">Translated from the Russian by John Cournos</hi><lb/> 
</head> 
<p>I WAS waiting for a tram-car.  There was no way of getting on; 
people were hanging on, jostling one another.  Well, simply 
like wild beasts.  Ten tram-cars I let go past.  I saw an old woman 
standing there, like myself, waiting.  An ancient grandmother.  To 
look at her face you would have thought that it had always been 
like that, that she had always been a grandmother; her wrinkles 
were so minute; she was toothless, and goodness was in her face. 
I looked more intently; she was standing patiently; did her tired 
eyes see anything?  Yes, they saw. 
 
</p><p>"Don't leave me to myself," said to me the grandmother.  "Let 
us go on the tram together.  I simply can't manage to crowd in." 
 
</p><p>"All right," said I.  "We'll go together.  Only we'll have to 
wait here for some time; I'm no good for pushing, or hanging on." 
 
</p><p>"God preserve us from that!" the grandmother interrupted me. 
 
</p><p>Yes, the grandmother saw that she was not alone. 
 
</p><p>A young woman was standing near us, and it was quite clear that 
she was with us; but the young woman could hold out no longer, 
and when the eleventh tram came up she suddenly changed&mdash;what 
had become of her gentleness!  She joined the tram crowd and hung 
on with the rest. 
 
</p><p>The matter had become desperate for us.  Nothing seemed left 
for us to do but to go on foot. 
 
</p><p>"Let us go, grandmother; it's all the same." 
 
</p><p>"I'll never get so far." 
 
</p><p>It was true.  The old woman could have never got there.  We 
were standing on a corner of the Ninth Line, and the grandmother's 
destination was the New Village. 
 
</p><p>I conquered my despair, and it was evident that the grandmother 
had conquered hers long ago.  At last, with God's help, we got a 
tram and pushed in. 
 
</p><p>The tram was full; it was useless to even think of a seat.  They 
   <pb n="66"/>   
were all soldiers.  As for me, I'm not good at hanging on; still, I 
managed to stand somehow.  It was different with the old woman; 
she bent quite in two, and her legs refused to obey her&mdash;she was 
like a blade of grass at every jolt. 
 
</p><p>"Won't some one give grandmother a seat!" said I to the passengers. 
 
</p><p>That was not the first time I had spoken like that; so I did not 
expect any mercy.  But this time it seemed to work; two sailors 
rose from their seats. 
 
</p><p>"There are good people in this world&mdash;please sit down." 
 
</p><p>I seated the grandmother. 
 
</p><p>It is good for a man to be like these sailors.  I looked at them 
and, perhaps, even standing, they felt at that instant as happy as 
the grandmother. 
 
</p><p>As for her, having rested a while, she began to talk.  Though she 
did not speak loudly, every word of hers was audible; there was 
something in her voice which cheered even the sailors, who had given 
up their place to her; her harshest words came from a white heart. 
 
</p><p>The old grandmother told about herself, of the place she had 
come from, and of her hard and lonely life.  And in the course of 
her story she recalled the present, as it were, and, raising her eyes 
to me, repeated: 
 
</p><p>"Don't leave me to myself.  We'll get off together." 
 
</p><p>"Together, together, grandmother!" repeated I, as well as the 
two sailors, rocking from the jolts.  Without words, they seemed 
to say as they rocked&mdash;"together, together!" 
 
</p><p>It was hard for the grandmother in the white world; that was 
the word she used&mdash;"hard."  The grandmother was not a native 
here; her own country was at the other end of the world; some-where  
near Kovno.  Many times she had been driven out; they 
always told her that the Germans were coming.  Nothing was certain  
for some time; she would gather up her goods and get ready 
to go; then one day would pass, then another, and everything would 
be as it was before; and she would remain. 
 
</p><p>"In the end they made it hard for me, and I had to go." 
 
</p><p>"Who made it hard for you&mdash;the Germans?" 
 
</p><p>"No!" said the grandmother, as she remembered something very 
bitter, but she added, in a voice without bitterness: "My own 
children."</p> 
 
   <pb n="67"/>   
<p>The soldier passengers exchanged glances.  And the voice of the 
old woman became even more audible.  For some reason the whole 
car grew quiet, and no one went out.  Did they all go the same 
way&mdash;grandmother's way? 
 
</p><p>"I had a little house.  I thought I'd die there.  I was quite alone 
in the white world.  I had had a daughter of about sixteen; she 
died.  Another daughter married, lived a year, and died.  I had 
three sons, who worked in a factory here in St Petersburg.  When 
my old man died, I held up the funeral for three days, thinking 
they would come.  But they didn't come.  I suppose they never 
got my telegram.  Then, when the war began, all my sons were 
taken as soldiers.  And no matter how many times I wrote and inquired,  
they could tell me nothing about them.  Just like a stone 
thrown into the water." 
 
</p><p>"Perhaps they are in prison?" 
 
</p><p>"No; I think they are gone." 
 
</p><p>Again the grandmother remembered something bitter; again spoke 
in her good voice: 
 
</p><p>"And when the children came, they set fire to my little house, 
and left only the ashes.  I wept and I said to them: 'Oh, don't 
set it on fire&mdash;do let it alone!'  'So you want to live with the Germans!   
You're a German woman!  We'll throw you into the fire!' 
I thought to myself: Let them throw me in; as it is, mine is a hard 
life, and all of God's Saints have been burnt.  I stand there and 
think to myself, and they are arguing.  One says: 'Let's throw 
her into the fire!' and the other says: 'No, let her alone!'  Then, 
when the house burnt down, I went away.  It took me three months, 
going on foot." 
 
</p><p>The grandmother became lost in thought; was she thinking of 
her house&mdash;there at the end of the world, where charred bits of 
wood alone remained under the snow?  Or was she thinking of her 
sons, who had worked in the factory here, and were now out there 
&mdash;there under the snow? 
 
</p><p>And I thought, as I lookd [sic] at the bowed grandmother, who had 
grown silent (the whole car was now looking at her): 
 
</p><p>"Grandmother, you with your heart, which has suffered bitter 
loss; with your white heart you have accepted your bitter fate&mdash;otherwise  
how could you speak of your spoilers as your children? 
&mdash;and now you are alone in the white world with your white heart, 
   <pb n="68"/>   
and your life is hard; you are living your last days and who is there 
to comfort you?  Who will comfort us?  Grandmother, it is hard 
for us too; I speak for all, and to all, all, all.  Who feels at ease, 
who can feel happy at the sight of the white ruins of your house, 
at the sight of the white grave of your lost world?  What wild 
beast, or what leering, shaggy soul; or what soul, crushed, like a 
rotten, worm-eaten mushroom, or heart resembling a begnawed dry 
bone?  No; here we are, all of us; and if there is any one who had 
not understood with his mind, then he has felt it with his heart&mdash;every  
one of us&mdash;your oppressive burden . . . the whole cross is 
ours to bear!" 
 
</p><p>"Don't be uneasy," said the grandmother, "a woman in Moscow 
had a dream.  She dreamt of Virgin Mary, who said to her: 'The 
Russian kingdom is in my hand; go and seek such an ikon as will 
show me as I am now.'  That same woman went all over Moscow, 
through all the churches and into all the houses&mdash;and she couldn't 
find it.  At last she went to the village of Kolomensk, near Moscow, 
and went into a church that had been built in the times of Ivan 
the Terrible.  It was full of ikons&mdash;they were lying there below, one 
on top the other, like slabs of the dead.  She picked up one after 
the other, one after the other and suddenly exclaimed: 'That's 
the very one!' and now this ikon is being taken all over Moscow, 
and prayers are being offered it for salvation.  And I saw it.  At 
the top a kind of rainbow and Sabaoth, then clouds, and then Virgin 
Mary in porphyry and crown&mdash;in one hand the sceptre, in the other 
the earth." 
 
</p><p>It was now time for the grandmother to leave the tram. 
 
</p><p>We left together; it was easy for us to leave, for every one made 
way for us. 
 
</p><p>I led the old grandmother to a stopping-place, saw her into another  
tram, and said good-bye. 
 
</p><p>"Good-bye, grandmother!" 
 
</p><p>"Christ be with you!" 
 
</p><p>And I went my way, through the St Petersburg darkness, and in 
the darkness bore along with me in a white heart&mdash;a tranquil light.</p> 
   
</div1> 
</body> 
</text> 
</TEI.2> 
 
