<?xml version="1.0"?>

<?dlps id="RouProf"?>
<?dlps page-images="none" figure-images="no"?>
<?dlps transcription="other"?>

<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/tei-p4/tei2.dtd" [
<!ENTITY % POSTKB "INCLUDE">
<!ENTITY % TEI.extensions.ent SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.ent">
<!ENTITY % TEI.extensions.dtd SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.dtd">
<!ENTITY % ISOnum SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/charent/iso-num.ent"> %ISOnum;
]> 
<TEI.2 id="RouProf"> 
<teiHeader type="migrated" creator="Etext">
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title type="main">Profession of Faith of a Savoyard Vicar</title>
<title type="sort">profession of faith of a savoyard vicar</title>
<author>Rousseau, Jean-Jacques, 1712-1778</author>
<editor>Eliot, LL D Charles W.</editor>
<respStmt> 
<resp>Creation of machine-readable version:</resp> 
<name>Modern History Sourcebook, www.fordham.edu/halsall/mod/modsbook.html</name> 
<resp>Conversion to TEI.2-conformant markup:</resp> 
<name>University of Virginia Library Electronic Text Center.</name>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt> 
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>University of Virginia Library</publisher>
<pubPlace>Charlottesville, Virginia</pubPlace> 
<idno type="ETC">RouProf</idno> 
<date value="2001">2001</date>
<availability status="public">
<p n="copyright">Copyright &copy; 2001 by the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia</p>
<p n="access">Publicly accessible</p>
</availability>
<idno type="uva-pid">uva-lib:476352</idno>
</publicationStmt>
<seriesStmt>
<title>University of Virginia Library, Text collection</title>
<idno type="uva-set">UVA-LIB-Text</idno>
</seriesStmt> 
<sourceDesc>
<biblFull>
<titleStmt>
<title type="main">Profession of Faith of a Savoyard Vicar</title>
<title type="parallel">French and English philosophers: Descartes, Rousseau, Voltaire, Hobbes; with introductions and notes</title>
<title type="sort">profession of faith of a savoyard vicar</title>
<author>Jean-Jacques Rousseau</author>
<editor>Charles W. Eliot, LL.D.</editor>
</titleStmt> 
<extent>76 pages (selection)</extent> 
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>P.F. Collier and Son, Company</publisher> 
<pubPlace>New York</pubPlace> 
<date value="1910">1910</date> 
<idno type="callNo">Source copy consulted:  Alderman Library, Call Number AC 1. A4 1910 v. 34</idno>
</publicationStmt> 
<seriesStmt>
<p>The Harvard Classics</p>
</seriesStmt> 
<notesStmt>
<note>
<p>Profession of Faith of a Savoyard Vicar appears as one of several writings included in this volume.</p>
</note>
</notesStmt>
</biblFull>
</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc> 
<encodingDesc>
<projectDesc>
<p>Prepared for the University of Virginia Library Electronic Text Center.</p>
</projectDesc> 
<editorialDecl>
<p>All unambiguous end-of-line hyphens have been removed, and the  trailing part of a word has been joined to the preceding line.</p> 
<p id="ETC">Some keywords in the header are a local Electronic Text Center scheme  to aid in establishing analytical groupings.</p>
</editorialDecl> 
</encodingDesc> 
<profileDesc>
<langUsage>
<language id="eng" usage="main">English</language> 
<language id="fre">French</language> 
<language id="ger">German</language>
</langUsage> 
<textClass>
<keywords>
<term>CORD</term> 
<term>philosophy</term> 
<term>religion</term>
</keywords> 
<keywords>
<term>nonfiction</term> 
<term>prose</term> 
<term>masculine/feminine</term> 
<term>Literature in Translation</term>
</keywords> 
</textClass>
</profileDesc> 
<revisionDesc>
<change>
<date value="2002-07">July, 2002</date> 
<respStmt>
<resp>corrector</resp> 
<name>Jason Smick, The Electronic Text Center</name>
</respStmt> 
<item/>
</change> 
<change>
<date value="2005-07">July 2005</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>Corrector</resp>
<name>John Ivor Carlson</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Converted SGML to XML and/or corrected tagging.</item>
</change>
<change>
<date value="2007-09">September 2007</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>Migration</resp>
<name>Ethan Gruber, University of Virginia Library</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Converted XML markup from TEI Lite to uva-dl-tei (TEI P4 with local customizations).</item>
</change>
<change>
<date value="2008-01">January 2008</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>Migration</resp>
<name>Greg Murray, University of Virginia Library</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Programmatically updated TEI header markup (but not header content) for minimal compliance with current QA requirements.</item>
</change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader> 
 
<text id="d1"> 
 
<front id="d2"> 
<titlePage id="d3"> 
	<pb/>
<titlePart type="main"> 
PROFESSION OF FAITH OF A <lb/> 
SAVOYARD VICAR 
</titlePart> 
 
<byline> 
By <lb/> 
<docAuthor> 
Jean-Jacques Rousseau 
</docAuthor> 
</byline> 
 
<docImprint> 
<pubPlace> 
<hi rend="italic">New York</hi> 
</pubPlace> 
P.F. Collier &amp; Son Company 
</docImprint> 
</titlePage> 
 
<div1 type="preface" id="d4"> 
 
<head>Introductory Note</head> 
<p>Jean Jacques Rousseau was born at Geneva, June 28, 1712, the son of a watchmaker of French origin. His education was 
irregular, and though he tried many professions - including engraving, music, and teaching - 
he found it difficult to support himself in any of them. The discovery of his talent as a 
writer came with the winning of a prize offered by the Academy of Dijon for a discourse on 
the question, <q>Whether the progress of the sciences and of letters has tended to 
corrupt or to elevate morals.</q> He argued so brilliantly that the tendency of 
civilization was degrading that he became at once famous. The discourse here printed on the 
causes of inequality among men was written in a similar competition.</p> 
<p>He now concentrated his powers upon literature, producing two novels, <foreign lang="fre">"La Nouvelle 
Heloise,"</foreign> the forerunner and parent of endless sentimental and picturesque fictions; 
and <foreign lang="fre">"Emile, ou l'Education,"</foreign> a work which has had enormous influence on the theory 
and practise of pedagogy down to out own time and in which the Savoyard Vicar appears, who 
is used as the mouthpiece for Rousseau's own religious ideas. <foreign lang="fre">Le Contrat Social</foreign> 
(1762) elaborated the doctrine of the discourse on inequality. Both historically and 
philosophically it is unsound; but it was the chief literary source of the enthusiasm for 
liberty, fraternity, and equality, which inspired the leaders of the French Revolution, and 
its effects passed far beyond France.</p> 
<p>His most famous work, the "Confessions," was published after his death. This book is a mine of information 
as to his life, but it is far from trustworthy; and the picture it gives of the author's 
personality and conduct, though painted in such a way as to make it absorbingly interesting, 
is often unpleasing in the highest degree. But it is one of the great autobiographies of the 
world.</p> 
<p>During Rousseau's later years he was the victim of the delusion of 
persecution; and although he was protected by a succession of good friends, he came to 
distrust and quarrel with each in turn. He died at Ermenonville, near Paris, July 2, 1778, 
the most widely influential French writer of his age.</p> 
<p>The Savoyard Vicar and his <q>Profession of Faith</q> are introduced into <q>Emile</q> not, according to 
the author, because he wishes to exhibit his principles as those which should be taught, but 
to give an example of the way in which religious matters should be discussed with the young. 
Nevertheless, it is universally recognized that these opinions are Rousseau's own, and 
represent in short form his characteristic attitude toward religious belief. The Vicar 
himself is believed to combine the traits of two Savoyard priests whom Rosseaue knew in his 
youth. The more important was the Abbe Gaime, whom he had known at Turin; the other, the 
Abbe Gatier, who had taught him at Annecy.</p> 
</div1> 
 
<div1 type="introduction" id="d5"> 
<head>Introduction</head> 
 
<p>About thirty years ago a young man, who had forsaken his own country and rambled into Italy, found 
himself reduced to a condition of great poverty and distress. He had been bred a Calvinist; but in consequence of his 
misconduct and of being unhappily a fugitive in a foreign country, without money or friends, 
he was induced to change his religion for the sake of subsistence. To this end he procured 
admittance into a <hi rend="italic">hospice</hi> for catechumens, that is to say, a house established for the 
reception of proselytes. The instructions he here received concerning some controversial 
points excited doubts he had not before entertained, and first caused him to realize the 
evil of the step he had taken. He was taught strange dogmas, and was eye-witness to stranger 
manners; and to these he saw himself a destined victim. He now sought to make his escape, 
but was prevented and more closely confined. If he complained, he was punished for 
complaining; and, lying at the mercy of his tyrannical oppressors, found himself treated as 
criminal because he could not without reluctance submit to be so.</p> 
<p>Let those who are sensible how much the first acts of violence and injustice irritate young and inexperienced 
minds, judge of the situation of this unfortunate youth. Swollen with indignation, the tears 
of rage burst from his eyes. He implored the assistance of heaven and earth in vain; he 
appealed to the whole world, but no one attended to his plea. His complaints could reach the 
ears only of a number of servile domestics, - slaves to the wretch by whom he was thus 
treated, or accomplices in the same crime, - who ridiculed his non-conformity and endeavored 
to secure his imitation. He would doubtless have been entirely ruined had it not been for 
the good offices of an honest ecclesiastic, who came to the hospital on some business, and 
with whom he found an opportunity for a private conference. The good priest was himself 
poor, and stood in need of every one's assistance; the oppressed proselyte, however, stood 
yet in greater need of him. The former did not hesitate, therefore, to favor his escape, 
even at the risk of making a powerful enemy.</p> 
<p>Having escaped from vice only to return to indigence, this young adventurer struggled against his destiny without success. For a 
moment, indeed, he thought himself above it, and at the first prospect of good fortune, his 
former distresses and his protector were forgotten together. He was soon punished, however, 
for his ingratitude, as his groundless hopes soon vanished. His youth stood in vain on his 
side; his romantic notions proving destructive to all his designs. Having neither capacity 
nor address to surmount the difficulties that fell in his way, and being a stranger to the 
virtues of moderation and the arts of knavery, he attempted so many things that he could 
bring none to perfection, Hence, having fallen into his former distress, and being not only 
in want of clothes and lodging, but even in danger of perishing with hunger, he recollected 
his former benefactor.</p> 
<p>To him he returned, and was well received. The sight of the 
unhappy youth brought to the poor vicar's mind the remembrance of a good action; - a 
remembrance always grateful to an honest mind. This good priest was naturally humane and 
compassionate. His own misfortunes had taught him to feel for those of others, nor had 
prosperity hardened his heart. In a word, the maxims of true wisdom and conscious virtue had 
confirmed the kindness of his natural disposition. He cordially embraced the young wanderer, 
provided for him a lodging, and shared with him the slender means of his own subsistence. 
Nor was this all: he went still farther, freely giving him both instruction and consolation, 
and also endeavoring to teach him the difficult art of supporting adversity with patience. 
Could you believe, ye sons of prejudice! that a priest, and a priest in Italy too, could be 
capable of this?</p> 
<p>This honest ecclesiastic was a poor Savoyard, who having in his 
younger days incurred the displeasure of his bishop, was obliged to pass the mountains in 
order to seek that provision which was denied him in his own country. He was neither 
deficient in literature nor understanding; his talents, therefore, joined with an engaging 
appearance, soon procured him a patron, who recommended him as tutor to a young man of 
quality. He preferred poverty, however, to dependence; and, being a stranger to the manners 
and behavior of the great, he remained but a short time in that situation. In quitting this 
service, however, he fortunately did not lose the esteem of his friend; and, as he behaved 
with great prudence and was universally beloved, he flattered himself that he shoud in time 
regain the good opinion of his bishop also, and be rewarded with some little benefice in the 
mountains, where he hoped to spend in tranquillity and peace the remainder of his days. This 
was the height of his ambition.</p> 
<p>Interested by a natural affinity in favor of the 
young fugitive, he examined very carefully into his character and disposition. In this 
examination, he saw that his misfortunes had already debased his heart; - that the shame and 
contempt to which he had been exposed had depressed his ambition, and that his disappointed 
pride, converted into indignation, had deduced, from the injustice and cruelty of mankind, 
the depravity of human nature and the emptiness of virtue. He had observed religion made use 
of as a mask to self-interest, and its worship as a cloak to hypocrisy. He had seen the 
terms heaven and hell prostituted in the subtility of vain disputes; the joys of the one and 
the pains of the other being annexed to a mere repetition of words. He had observed the 
sublime and primitive idea of the Divinity disfigured by the fantastical imaginations of 
men; and, finding that in order to believe in God it was necessary to give up that 
understanding he hath bestowed on us, he held in the same disdain as well the sacred object 
of our idle reveries as those idle reveries themselves. Without knowing anything of natural 
causes, or giving himself any trouble to investigate them, he remained in a condition of the 
most stupid ignorance, mixed with profound contempt for those who pretended to greater 
knowledge than his own.</p> 
<p>A neglect of all religious duties leads to a neglect of all 
moral obligations. The heart of this young vagabond had already made a great progress from 
one toward the other. Not that he was constitutionally vicious; but misfortune and 
incredulity, having stifled by degrees the propensities of his natural disposition, were 
hurrying him on to ruin, adding to the manners of a beggar the principles of an atheist.</p> 
<p>His ruin, however, though almost inevitable, was not absolutely completed. His education 
not having been neglected, he was not without knowledge. He had not yet exceeded that happy 
term of life, wherein the youthful blood serves to stimulate the mind without inflaming the 
passions, which were as yet unrelaxed and unexcited. A natural modesty and timidity of 
disposition had hitherto supplied the place of restraint, and prolonged the term of youthful 
innocence. The odious example of brutal depravity, and of vices without temptation, so far 
from animating his imagination, had mortified it. Disgust had long supplied the place of 
virtue in the preservation of his innocence, and to corrupt this required more powerful 
seductions.</p> 
<p>The good priest saw the danger and the remedy. The difficulties that 
appeared in the application did not deter him from the attempt. He took a pleasure in the 
design, and resolved to complete it by restoring to virtue the victim he had snatched from 
infamy.</p> 
<p>To this end he set out resolutely in the execution of his project. The merit 
of the motive increased his hopes, and inspired means worthy of his zeal. Whatever might be 
the success, he was sure that he should not tow away his labor: - we are always sure so 
far to succeed in well doing.</p> 
<p>He began with striving to gain the confidence of the 
proselyte by conferring on him his favors disinterestedly, - by never importuning him with 
exhortations, and by descending always to a level with his ideas and manner of thinking. It 
must have been all affecting sight to see a grave divine become the comrade of a young 
libertine - to see virtue affect the air of licentiousness - in order to triumph the more 
certainly over it. Whenever the heedless youth made him the confidant of his follies, and 
unbosomed himself freely to his benefactor, the good priest listened attentively to his 
stories; and, without approving the evil, interested himself in the consequences. No 
ill-timed censure ever indiscreetly checked the pupil's communicative temper. The pleasure 
with which he thought himself heard increased that which he took in telling all his secrets. 
Thus he was induced to make a free and general confession without thinking he was confessing 
anything.</p> 
<p>Having thus made himself master of the youth's sentiments and character, 
the priest was enabled to see clearly that, without being ignorant for his years, he had 
forgotten almost everything of importance for him to know, and that the state of meanness 
into which he had fallen had almost stifled in him the sense of good and evil. There is a 
degree of low stupidity which deprives the soul as it were of life; the voice of conscience 
is also but little heard by those who think of nothing but the means of subsistence. To 
rescue this unfortunate youth from the moral death that so nearly teatened him, he began, 
therefore, by awakening his self-love and exciting in him a due regard for himself. He 
represented to his imagination a more happy success, from the future employment of his 
talents; he inspired him with a generous ardor by a recital of the commendable actions of 
others, and by raising his admiration of those who performed them. In order to detach him 
insensibly from an idle and vagabond life, he employed him in copying books; and under 
pretence of having occasion for such extracts, cherished in him the noble sentiment of 
gratitude for his benefactor. By this method he also instructed him indirectly by the books 
he employed him to copy; and induced him to entertain so good an opinion of himself as to 
think he was not absolutely good for nothing, and to hold himself not quite so despicable in 
his own esteem as he had formerly done.</p> 
<p>A trifling circumstance may serve to show the art which this benevolent instructor made use of to insensibly elevate the heart of his 
disciple, without appearing to think of giving him instruction. This good ecclesiastic was 
so well known and esteemed for his probity and discernment, that many persons chose rather 
to entrust him with the distribution of their alms than the richer clergy of the cities. Now 
it happened that receiving one day a sum of money in charge for the poor, the young man had 
the meanness to desire some of it, under that title, for himself. <q>No,</q> replied 
his kind benefactor, <q>you and I are breten; you belong to me, and I should not apply 
the charity entrusted with me to my own use.</q> He then gave him the desired sum from his 
private funds. Lessons of this kind are hardly ever town away on young people, whose 
hearts are not entirely corrupted.</p> 
<p>But I will continue to speak no longer in the third person, which is indeed a superfluous caution; as you, my dear countrymen, are very 
sensible that the unhappy fugitive I have been speaking of is myself. I believe that I am 
now so far removed from the irregularities of my youth as to dare to avow them, and think 
that the hand which extricated me from them is too well deserving of my gratitude for me not 
to do it honour even at the expense of a little shame.</p> 
<p>The most striking circumstance of all was to observe in the retired life of my worthy master virtue without hypocrisy and 
humanity without weakness. His conversation was always honest and simple, and his conduct 
ever conformable to his discourse. I never found him troubling himself whether the persons 
he assisted went constantly to vespers-whether they went frequently to confession - or 
fasted on certain days of the week. Nor did I ever know him to impose on them any of those 
conditions without which a man might perish from want, and have no hope of relief from the 
devout.</p> 
<p>Encouraged by these observations, so far was I from affecting in his presence the forward zeal of a new proselyte, that I took no pains to conceal my thoughts, nor did I 
ever remark his being scandalized at this freedom. Hence, I have sometimes said to myself, 
he certainly overlooks my indifference for the new mode of worship I have embraced, in 
consideration of the disregard which he sees I have for that in which I was educated; as he 
finds my indifference is not partial to either. But what could I think when I heard him 
sometimes approve dogmas contrary to those of the Romish church, and appear to hold its 
ceremonies in little esteem? I should have been apt to consider him a protestant in 
disguise, had I seen him less observant of those very ceremonies which he seemed to think of 
so little account; but knowing that he acquitted himself as punctually of his duties as a 
priest in private as in public, I knew not how to judge of these seeming contradictions. If 
we except the failing which first brought him into disgrace with his superior, and of which 
he was not altogether corrected, his life was exemplary, his manners irreproachable, and his 
conversation prudent and sensible. As I lived with him in the greatest intimacy, I learned 
every day to respect him more and more; and as he had entirely won my heart by so many acts 
of kindness, I waited with an impatient curiosity to know the principles on which a life and 
conduct so singular and uniform could be founded.</p> 
<p>It was some time, however, before this curiosity was satisfied, as he endeavoured to cultivate those seeds of reason and 
goodness which he had endeavoured to instill, before he would disclose himself to his 
disciple. The greatest difficulty he met with was to eradicate from my heart a proud 
misantopy, a certain rancorous hatred which I bore to the wealthy and fortunate, as if 
they were made so at my expense, and had usurped apparent happiness from what should have 
been my own. The idle vanity of youth, which is opposed to all constraint and humiliation, 
encouraged but too much my propensity to indulge this splenetic humor; whilst that 
self-love, which my mentor strove so earnestly to cherish, by increasing my pride, rendered 
mankind, in my opinion, still more detestable, and only added to my hatred of them the most 
egregious contempt.</p> 
<p>Without directly attacking this pride, he yet strove to prevent it from degenerating into barbarity, and without diminishing my self-esteem, made me less 
disdainful of my neighbors. In withdrawing the gaudy veil of external appearances, and 
presenting to my view the real evils it concealed, he taught me to lament the failings of my 
fellow creatures, to sympathize with their miseries, and to pity instead of envying them. 
Moved to compassion for human frailties from a deep sense of his own, he saw mankind 
everywhere the victims of either their own vices or of the vices of others, - he saw the 
poor groan beneath the yoke of the rich, and the rich beneath the tyranny of their own idle 
habits and prejudices.</p> 
<p><q>Believe me,</q> said he, <q>our mistaken notions of things are so far from hiding our misfortunes from our view, that they augment those evils 
by rendering trifles of importance, and making us sensible of a thousand wants which we 
should never have known but for our prejudices. Peace of mind consists in a contempt for 
everything that may disturb it. The man who gives himself the greatest concern about life is 
he who enjoys it least; and he who aspires the most earnestly after happiness is always the 
one who is the most miserable.</q></p> 
<p><q>Alas!</q> cried I, with all the bitterness of discontent, <q>what a deplorable picture do you present of human life! If 
we may indulge ourselves in nothing, to what purpose were we born? If we must despise even 
happiness itself, who is there that can know what it is to be happy?</q></p> 
<p><q>I know,</q> replied the good priest, in a tone and manner that struck me.</p> 
<p><q>You!</q> said I, <q>so little favored by fortune! so poor! exiled! persecuted! 
can you be happy? And if you are, what have you done to purchase happiness?</q></p> 
<p><q>My dear child,</q> he replied, embracing me, <q>I will willingly tell you. As you have freely confessed to me, I will do the same to you. I will disclose to you all the 
sentiments of my heart. You shall see me, if not such as I really am, at least such as I 
believe myself to be: and when you have heard my whole <hi rend="italic">Profession of Faith</hi>--when you know 
fully the situation of my heart--you will know why I think myself happy; and, if you agree 
with me, what course you should pursue in order to become so likewise.</q></p> 
<p><q>But this profession is not to be made in a moment. It will require some time to disclose to you my 
thoughts on the situation of mankind and on the real value of human life. We will therefore 
take a suitable opportunity for a few hours' uninterrupted conversation on this subject.</q></p> 
<p>As I expressed an earnest desire for such an opportunity, an appointment was made for the next morning. We rose at the break of day and prepared for the 
journey. Leaving the town, he led me to the top of a hill, at the foot of which ran the 
river Po, watering in its course the fertile vales. That immense chain of mountains, called 
the Alps, terminated the distant view. The rising sun cast its welcome rays over the gilded 
plains, and, by projecting the long shadows of the trees, the houses, and adjacent hills, 
formed the most beautiful scene ever mortal eye beheld. One might have been almost tempted 
to think that nature had at this moment displayed all this grandeur and beauty as a subject 
for our conversation. Here it was that, after contemplating for a short time the surrounding 
objects in silence, my teacher and benefactor confided to me with impressive earnestness the 
principles and faith which governed his life and conduct.</p> 
</div1> 
</front> 
 
<body id="d6"> 
 
<div1 type="essay" id="d7"> 
 
<head><hi rend="bold">PROFESSION OF FAITH OF A SAVOYARD VICAR</hi></head> 
 
<p>Expect from me neither learned declamations nor profound arguments. I am no great philosopher, and give myself but little trouble in regard to becoming such. 
Still I perceive sometimes the glimmering of good sense, and have always a regard for the 
truth. I will not enter into any disputation, or endeavor to refute you; but only lay down 
my own sentiments in simplicity of heart. Consult your own during this recital: this is all 
I require of you. If I am mistaken, it is undesignedly, which is sufficient to absolve me of 
all criminal error; and if I am right, reason, which is common to us both, shall decide. We 
are equally interested in listening to it, and why should not our views agree?</p> 
<p>I was born a poor peasant, destined by my situation to the business of husbandry. It was thought, 
however, much more advisable for me to learn to get my bread by the profession of a priest, 
and means were found to give me a proper education. In this, most certainly, neither my 
parents nor I consulted what was really good, true, or useful for me to know; but only that 
I should learn what was necessary to my ordination. I learned, therefore, what was required 
of me to learn, -- I said what was required of me to say -- and, accordingly, was made a 
priest. It was not long, however, before I perceived too plainly that, in laying myself 
under an obligation to be no longer a man, I had engaged for more than I could possibly 
perform.</p> 
<p>Some will tell us that conscience is founded merely on our prejudices, but I 
know from my own experience that its dictates constantly follow the order of nature, in 
contradiction to all human laws and institutions. We are in vain forbidden to do this thing 
or the other--we shall feel but little remorse for doing any thing to which a well-regulated 
natural instinct excites us, how strongly soever prohibited by reason. Nature, my dear 
youth, hath hitherto in this respect been silent in you. May you continue long in that happy 
state wherein her voice is the voice of innocence! Remember that you offend her more by 
anticipating her instructions than by refusing to hear them. In order to know when to listen 
to her without a crime, you should begin by learning to check her insinuations.</p> 
<p>I had always a due respect for marriage as the first and most sacred institution of nature. Having 
given up my right to enter into such an engagement, I resolved, therefore, not to profane 
it: for, notwithstanding my manner of education, as I had always led a simple and uniform 
life, I had preserved all that clearness of understanding in which my first ideas were 
cultivated. The maxims of the world had not obscured my primitive notions, and my poverty 
kept me at a sufficient distance from those temptations that teach us the sophistry of 
vice.</p> 
<p>The virtuous resolution I had formed, was, however, the very cause of my ruin, as my determination not to violate the rights of others, left my faults exposed to 
detection. To expiate the offence, I was suspended and banished; falling a sacrifice to my 
scruples rather than to my incontinence. From the reproaches made me on my disgrace, I found 
that the way to escape punishment for an offence is often by committing a greater.</p> 
<p>A few instances of this kind go far with persons capable of reflection. Finding by sorrowful 
experience that the ideas I had formed of justice, honesty, and other moral obligations were 
contradicted in practice, I began to give up most of the opinions I had received, until at 
length the few which I retained being no longer sufficient to support themselves, I called 
in question the evidence on which they were established. Thus, knowing hardly what to think, 
I found myself at last reduced to your own situation of mind, with this difference only, 
that my unbelief being the later fruit of a maturer age, it was a work of greater difficulty 
to remove it.</p> 
<p>I was in that state of doubt and uncertainty in which Descartes requires the mind to be involved, in order to enable it to investigate truth. This 
disposition of mind, however, is too disquieting to long continue, its duration being owing 
only to indolence or vice. My heart was not so corrupt as to seek fresh indulgence; and 
nothing preserves so well the habit of reflection as to be more content with ourselves than 
with our fortune.</p> 
<p>I reflected, therefore, on the unhappy lot of mortals floating always on the ocean of human opinions, without compass or rudder-left to the mercy of their 
tempestuous passions, with no other guide than an inexperienced pilot, ignorant of his 
course, as well as from whence he came, and whither he is going. I often said to myself: I 
love the truth - I seek, yet cannot find it. Let any one show it to me and I will readily 
embrace it. Why doth it hide its charms from a heart formed to adore them?</p> 
<p>I have frequently experienced at times much greater evils; and yet no part of my life was ever so 
constantly disagreeable to me as that interval of scruples and anxiety. Running perpetually 
from one doubt and uncertainty to another, all that I could deduce from my long and painful 
meditations was incertitude, obscurity, and contradiction; as well with regard to my 
existence as to my duty.</p> 
<p>I cannot comprehend how any man can be sincerely a skeptic on principle. Such philosophers either do not exist, or they are certainly the most 
miserable of men. To be in doubt, about things which it is important for us to know, is a 
situation too perplexing for the human mind; it cannot long support such incertitude; but 
will, in spite of itself, determine one way or the other, rather deceiving itself than being 
content to believe nothing of the matter.</p> 
<p>What added further to my perplexity was, that as the authority of the church in which I was educated was decisive, and tolerated not 
the slightest doubt, in rejecting one point, I thereby rejected in a manner all the others. 
The impossibility of admitting so many absurd decisions, tew doubt over those more 
reasonable. In being told I must believe all, I was prevented from believing anything, and I 
knew not what course to pursue.</p> 
<p>In this situation I consulted the philosophers. I turned over their books, and examined their several opinions. I found them vain, dogmatical 
and dictatorial-even in their pretended skepticism. Ignorant of nothing, yet proving 
nothing; but ridiculing one another instead; and in this last particular only, in which they 
were all agreed, they seemed to be in the right. Affecting to triumph whenever they attacked 
their opponents, they lacked everything to make them capable of a vigorous defence. If you 
examine their reasons, you will find them calculated only to refute: If you number voices, 
every one is reduced to his own suffrage. They agree in nothing but in disputing, and to 
attend to these was certainly not the way to remove my uncertainty.</p> 
<p>I conceived that the weakness of the human understanding was the first cause of the prodigious variety I 
found in their sentiments, and that pride was the second. We have no standard with which to 
measure this immense machine; we cannot calculate its various relations; we neither know the 
first cause nor the final effects; we are ignorant even of ourselves; we neither know our 
own nature nor principle of action; nay, we hardly know whether man be a simple or compound 
being. Impenetrable mysteries surround us on every side; they extend beyond the region of 
sense; we imagine ourselves possessed of understanding to penetrate them, and we have only 
imagination. Every one strikes out a way of his own across this imaginary world; but no one 
knows whether it will lead him to the point he aims at. We are yet desirous to penetrate, to 
know, everything. The only thing we know not is to contentedly remain ignorant of what it is 
impossible for us to know. We had much rather determine at random, and believe the thing 
which is not, than to confess that none of us is capable of seeing the thing that is. Being 
ourselves but a small part of that great whole, whose limits surpass our most extensive 
views, and concerning which its creator leaves us to make our idle conjectures, we are vain 
enough to decide what that whole is in itself, and what we are in relation to it.</p> 
<p>But were the philosophers in a situation to discover the truth, which of them would be 
interested in so doing? Each knows very well that his system is no better founded that the 
systems of others; he defends it, nevertheless, because it is his own. There is not one of 
them, who, really knowing truth from falsehood, would not prefer the latter, if of his own 
invention, to the former, discovered by any one else. Where is the philosopher who would not 
readily deceive mankind, to increase his own reputation? Where is he who secretly proposes 
any other object than that of distinguishing himself from the rest of mankind? Provided he 
raises himself above the vulgar, and carries away the prize of fame from his competitors, 
what doth he require more? The most essential point is to think differently from the rest of 
the world. Among believers he is an atheist, and among atheists he affects to be a 
believer.</p> 
<p>The first fruit I gathered from these meditations was to learn to confine my enquiries to those things in which I was immediately interested, - to remain contended in 
a profound ignorance of the rest; and not to trouble myself so far as even to doubt about 
what it did not concern me to know.</p> 
<p>I could further see that instead of clearing up any unnecessary doubts, the philosophers only contributed to multiply those which most 
tormented me, and that they resolved absolutely none. I therefore applied to another guide, 
and said to myself, let me consult my innate instructor, who will deceive me less than I may 
be deceived by others; or at least the errors I fall into will be my own, and I shall grow 
less depraved in the pursuit of my own illusions, than in giving myself up to the deceptions 
of others.</p> 
<p>Taking a retrospect, then, of the several opinions which had successively prevailed with me from my infancy, I found that, although none of them were so evident as to 
produce immediate conviction, they had nevertheless different degrees of probability, and 
that my innate sense of truth and falsehood leaned more or less to each. On this first 
observation, proceeding to compare impartially and without prejudice these different 
opinions with each other, I found that the first and most common was also the most simple 
and most rational; and that it wanted nothing more to secure universal suffrage, than the 
circumstance of having been last proposed. Let us suppose that all our philosophers, ancient 
and modern, had exhausted all their whimsical systems of power, chance, fate, necessity, 
atoms, an animated world, sensitive matter, materialism, and of every other kind; and after 
them let us imagine the celebrated Dr. Clarke enlightening the world by displaying the being 
of beings - the supreme and sovereign disposer of all things. With what universal 
admiration, - with what unanimous applause would not the world receive this new system, - so 
great, so consolatory, so sublime, - so proper to elevate the soul, to lay the foundations 
of virtue, - and at the same time so striking, so enlightened, so simple, - and, as it 
appears to me, pregnant with less incomprehensibilities and absurdities than all other 
systems whatever! I reflected that unanswerable objections might be made to all, because the 
human understanding is incapable of resolving them, no proof therefore could be brought 
exclusively of any: but what difference is there in proofs! Ought not that system then, 
which explains everything, to be preferred, when attended with no greater difficulties than 
the rest?</p> 
<p>The love of truth then comprises all my philosophy; and my method of research being the simple and easy rule of common sense, which dispenses with the vain 
subtilty of argumentation, I reexamined by this principle all the knowledge of which I was 
possessed, resolved to admit as evident everything to which I could not in the sincerity of 
my heart refuse to assent, to admit also as true all that seemed to have a necessary 
connection with it, and to leave everything else as uncertain, without either rejecting or 
admitting, being determined not to trouble myself about clearing up any point which did not 
tend to utility in practice.</p> 
<p>But, after all, who am I? What right have I to judge of these things? And what is it that determines my conclusions? If, subject to the impressions 
I receive, these are formed in direct consequence of those impressions, I trouble myself to 
no purpose in these investigations. It is necessary, therefore, to examine myself, to know 
what instruments are made use of in such researches, and how far I may confide in their 
use.</p> 
<p>In the first place, I know that I exist, and have senses whereby I am affected. 
This is a truth so striking that I am compelled to acquiesce in it. But have I properly a 
distinct sense of my existence, or do I only know it from my various sensations? This is my 
first doubt; which, at present, it is impossible for me to resolve: for, being continually 
affected by sensations, either directly from the objects or from the memory; how can I tell 
whether my self-consciousness be, or be not, something foreign to those sensations, and 
independent of them.</p> 
<p>My sensations are all internal, as they make me sensible of my own existence; but the cause of them is external and independent, as they affect me without 
my consent, and do not depend on my will for their production or annihilation. I conceive 
very clearly, therefore, that the sensation which is internal, and its cause or object which 
is external, are not one and the same thing.</p> 
<p>Thus I know that I not only exist but that other beings exists as well as as myself; to with, the objects of my sensations; and 
though these objects should be nothing but ideas, it is very certain that these ideas are no 
part of myself.</p> 
<p>Now everything that I perceive out of myself, and which acts upon my senses, I call matter; and those portions of matter which I conceive are united in 
individual beings, I call bodies. Thus all the disputes between Idealists and Materialists 
signify nothing to me; their distinctions between the appearance and reality of bodies being 
chimerical.</p> 
<p>Hence I have acquired as certain knowledge of the existence of the universe as of my own. I next reflect on the objects of my sensations; and, finding in 
myself the faculty of comparing them with each other, I perceive myself endowed with an 
active power with which I was before unacquainted.</p> 
<p>To perceive is only to feel or be sensible of things; to compare them is to judge of their existence. To judge of things and 
to be sensible of them are very different. Things present themselves to our sensations as 
single and detached from each other, such as they barely exist in nature; but in our 
intellectual comparison of them they are removed, transported as it were, from place to 
place, disposed on and beside each other, to enable us to pronounce concerning their 
difference and similitude. The characteristic faculty of an intelligent, active being is, in 
my opinion, that of giving a sense to the world <hi rend="italic">exist.</hi> In beings merely sensitive, I have 
searched in vain to discover the like force of intellect; nor can I conceive it to be in 
their nature. Such passive beings perceive every object singly or by itself; or if two 
objects present themselves, they are perceived as united into one. Such beings having no 
power to place one in competition with, beside, or upon the other, they cannot compare 
them,or judge of their separate existence.</p> 
<p>To see two objects at once, is not to see their relations to each other, nor to judge of their difference; as to see many objects, 
though distinct from one another, is not to reckon their number. I may possibly have in my 
mind the ideas of a large stick and a small one, without comparing those ideas together, or 
judging that one is less than the other; as I may look at my hand without counting my 
fingers. 
<ref target="n1">[1]</ref> 
The comparative ideas of greater and less, as well as numerical ideas 
of one, two, etc., are certainly not sensations, although the understanding produces them 
only from our sensatione.</p> 
<p>It has been pretended that sensitive beings distinguish sensations one from the other, by the actual difference there is between those sensations: 
this, however, demands an explanation. When such sensations are different, a sensitive begin 
is supposed to distinguish them by their difference; but when they are alike, they can then 
only distinguish them because they perceive one without the other; for, otherwise, how can 
two objects exactly alike be distinguished in a simultaneous sensation? Such objects must 
necessarily be blended together and taken for one and the same; particularly according to 
that system of philosophy in which it is pretended that the sensations, representative of 
extension, are not extended.</p> 
<p>When two comparative sensations are perceived, they make both a joint and separate impression; but their relation to each other is not necessarily 
perceived in consequence of either. If the judgment we form of this relation were indeed a 
mere sensation, excited by the objects, we should never be deceived in it, for it can never 
be denied that I truly perceive what I feel.</p> 
<p>How, therefore, can I be deceived in the relation between these two sticks, particularly, if they are not parallel? Why do I say, for 
instance, that the little one is a third part as long as the great one, when it is in 
reality only a fourth? Why is not the image, which is the sensation, conformable to its 
model, which is the object? It is because I am active when I judge, the operation which 
forms the comparison is defective, and my understanding, which judges of relations, mixes 
its errors with the truth of those sensations which are representative of objects.</p> 
<p>Add to this the reflection, which I am certain you will think striking after duly weighing it, that if we were merely passive in the use of 
our senses, there would be no communication between them:</p> <p>so that it would be 
impossible for us to know that the body we touched with our hands and the object we saw with 
our eyes were one and the same. Either we should not be able to perceive external objects at 
all, or they would appear to exist as five perceptible substances of which we should have no 
method of ascertaining the identity.</p> 
<p>Whatever name be given to that power of the mind which assembles and compares my 
sensations, - call it attention, meditation, reflection, or whatever you please, - certain 
it is that it exists in me, and not in the objects of those sensations. It is I alone who 
produce it, although it is displayed only in consequence of the impressions made on me by 
those objects. Without being so far master over myself as to perceive or not to perceive at 
pleasure, I am still more or less capable of making an examination into the objects 
perceived.</p> 
<p>I am not, therefore, a mere sensitive and passive, but an active and intelligent being; and, whatever philosophers may pretend, lay claim to the honor of 
thinking. I know only that truth depends on the existence of things, and not on my 
understanding which judges of them; and that the less such judgment depends on me, the 
nearer I am certain of approaching the truth. Hence my rule of confiding more on sentiment 
than reason is confirmed by reason itself.</p> 
<p>Being thus far assured of my own nature and capacity, I begin to consider the objects about me; ragarding myself, with a kind of 
shuddering, as a creature town on the wide world of the universe, and as it were lost in 
an infinite variety of other beings, without knowing anything of what they are, either among 
themselves or with regard to me.</p> 
<p>Everything that is perceptible to my senses is matter, and I deduce all the essential properties of matter from those sensible qualities, 
which cause it to be perceptible, and which are inseparable from it. I see it sometimes in 
motion and at other times at rest. This rest may be said to be only relative; but as we 
perceive degrees in motion, we can very clearly conceive one of the two extremes which is 
rest; and this we conceive so distinctly, that we are even induced to take that for absolute 
rest which is only relative. Now motion cannot be essential to matter, if matter can be 
conceived at rest. Hence I infer that neither motion nor rest are essential to it; but 
motion being an action, is clearly the effect of cause, of which rest is only the absence. 
When nothing acts on matter, it does not move; it is equally indifferent to motion and rest; 
its natural state, therefore, is to be at rest.</p> 
<p>Again, I perceive in bodies two kinds of motion; that is a mechanical or communicated motion, and a spontaneous or voluntary one. 
In the first case, the moving cause is out of the body moved, and in the last, exists within 
it. I shall not hence conclude, however, that the motion of a watch, for example, is 
spontaneous; for if nothing should act upon it but the spring, that spring would not wind 
itself up again when once down. For the same reason, also, I should as little accede to the 
spontaneous motion of fluids, nor even to heat itself, the cause of their fluidity.</p> 
<p>You will ask me if the motions of animals are spontaneous? I will freely answer, I cannot 
positively tell, but analogy speaks in the affirmative. You may ask me further, how I know 
there is such a thing as spontaneous motion? I answer, because I feel it. I <hi rend="italic">will</hi> to move my 
arm, and, accordingly, it moves without the intervention of any other immediate cause. It is 
in vain to attempt to reason me out of this sentiment; it is more powerful than any rational 
evidence. You might as well attempt to convince me that I do not exist.</p> 
<p>If the actions of men are not spontaneous, and there be no such spontaneous action in what passes 
on earth, we are only the more embarrassed to conceive what is the first cause of all 
motion. For my part I am so fully persuaded that the natural state of matter is a state of 
rest, and that it has in itself no principle of activity, that whenever I see a body in 
motion, I instantly conclude that it is either an animated body or that its motion is 
communicated to it. My understanding will by no means acquiesce in the notion that 
unorganized matter can move of itself, or be productive of any kind of action.</p> 
<p>The visible universe, however, is composed of inanimate matter, which appears to have nothing in 
its composition of organization, or that sensation which is common to the parts of an 
animated body, as it is certain that we ourselves, being parts thereof, do not perceive our 
existence in the whole. The universe, also, is in motion; and its movements being all 
regular, uniform, and subjected to constant laws, nothing appears therein similar to that 
liberty which is remarkable in the spontaneous motion of men and animals. The world, 
therefore, is not a huge self-moving animal, but receives its motions from some foreign 
cause, which we do not perceive: but I am so strongly persuaded within myself of the 
existence of this cause, that it is impossible for me to observe the apparent diurnal 
revolution of the sun, without conceiving that some force must urge it forward; or if it is 
the earth itself that turns, I cannot but conceive that some hand must turn it.</p> 
<p>If it be necessary to admit general laws that have no apparent relation to matter, from what fixed 
point must that enquiry set out? Those laws, being nothing real or substantial, have some 
prior foundation equally unknown and occult. Experience and observation have taught us the 
laws of motion; these laws, however, determine effects only without; these laws, however, 
determine effects only without displaying their causes; and, therefore, are not sufficient 
to explain the system of the universe. Descartes could form a model of the heavens and earth 
with dice; but he could not give their motions to those dice, nor bring into play his 
centrifugal force without the assistance of a rotary motion. Newton discovered the law of 
attraction; but attraction alone would soon have reduced the universe into one solid mass: 
to this law, therefore, he found it necessary to add a projectile force, in order to account 
for the revolution of the heavenly bodies. Could Descartes tell us by what physical law his 
vortices were put and kept in motion? Could Newton produce the hand that first impelled the 
planets in the tangent of their respective orbits?</p> 
<p>The first causes of motion do not exist in matter; bodies receive from and communicate motion to each other, but they cannot 
originally produce it. The more I observe the action and reaction of the powers of nature 
acting on each other, the more I am convinced that they are merely effects; and we must ever 
recur to some volition as the first cause: for to suppose there is a progression of causes 
to infinity, is to suppose there is no first cause at all. In a word, every motion that is 
not produced by some other, must be the effect of spontaneous, voluntary act. Inanimate 
bodies have no action but motion; and there can be no real action without volition. Such is 
my first principle. I believe, therefore, that a <hi rend="italic">Will</hi> gives motion to the universe, and 
animates all nature. This is my first article of faith.</p> 
<p>In what manner volition is productive of physical and corporeal action I know not, but I experience within myself that 
it is productive of it. I <hi rend="italic">will</hi> to act, and the action immediately follows; I <hi rend="italic">will</hi> to move my 
body, and my body instantly moves; but, that an inanimate body lying at rest, should move 
itself, or produce motion, is incomprehensible and unprecedented. The <hi rend="italic">Will</hi> also is known by 
its effects and not by its essence. I know it as the cause of motion; but to conceive matter 
producing motion, would be evidently to conceive an effect without a cause, or rather not to 
conceive any thing at all.</p> 
<p>It is no more possible for me to conceive how the will moves the body, than how the sensations affect the soul. I even know not why one of these 
mysteries ever appeared more explicable than the other. For my own part, whether at the time 
I am active or passive, the means of union between the two substances appear to me 
absolutely incomprehensible. Is it not strange that the philosophers have town off this 
incomprehensibility, merely to confound the two substances together, as if operations so 
different could be better explained as the effects of one subject than of two.</p> 
<p>The principle which I have here laid down, is undoubtedly something obscure; it is however 
intelligible, and contains nothing repugnant to reason or observation. Can we say as much as 
the doctrines of materialism? It is very certain that, if motion be essential to matter, it 
would be inseparable from it; it would be always the same in every portion of it, 
incommunicable, and incapable of increase or diminution; it would be impossible for us even 
to conceive matter at rest. Again, when I am told that motion is not indeed essential to 
matter, but necessary to its existence, I see tough the attempt to impose on me by a form 
of words, which it would be more easy to refute, if more intelligible. For, whether the 
motion of matter arises from itself, and is therefore essential to it, or whether it is 
derived from some external cause, it is not further necessary to it than as the moving cause 
acting thereon: so that we still remain under the first difficulty.</p> 
<p>General and abstract ideas form the source of our greatest errors. The jargon of metaphysics never 
discovered one truth; but it has filled philosophy with absurdities, of which we are ashamed 
as soon as they are stripped of their pompous expressions. Tell me truly, my friend if any 
precise idea is conveyed to your understanding when you are told of a blind, unintelligent 
power being diffused toughout all nature? It is imagined that something is meant by those 
vague terms, Universal force and Necessary motion; and yet they convey no meaning. The idea 
of motion is nothing more than the idea of passing from one place to another, nor can there 
be any motion without some particular direction; for no individual being can move several 
ways at once. In what manner then is it that matter necessarily moves? Has all the matter of 
which bodies are composed a general and uniform motion, or has each atom a particular motion 
of its own? If we give assent to the first notion, the whole universe will appear to be one 
solid and indivisible mass; and according to the second, it should constitute a diffused and 
incoherent fluid, without a possibility that two atoms ever could be united. What can be the 
direction of this motion common to all matter? Is it in a right line upwards or downwards, 
to the right or to the left? Again, if every particle of matter has its particular 
direction, what can be the cause of all those directions and their variations? If every atom 
or particle of matter revolved only on its axis, none of them would change their place, and 
there would be no motion communicated; and even in this case it is necessary that such a 
revolving motion should be carried on one way. To ascribe to matter motion in the abstract, 
is to make use of terms without a meaning; and in giving it any determine motion, we must of 
necessity suppose the cause that determines it. The more I multiply particular forces, the 
more new causes have I to explain, without ever finding one common agent that directs them. 
So far from being able to conceive any regularity or order in the fortuitous concourse of 
elements, I cannot even conceive the nature of their concurrence; and an universal chaos is 
more inconceivable than universal harmony. I easily comprehend that the mechanism of the 
world cannot be perfectly known to the human understanding, but whenever men undertake to 
explain it, they ought at least to speak in such a manner that others may understand 
them.</p> 
<p>If from matter being put in motion I discover the existence of a <hi rend="italic">Will</hi> as the 
first active cause, the subjugation of this matter to certain regular laws of motion 
displays also intelligence. This is my second article of faith. To act, to compare, to 
prefer, are the operations of an active, thinking being: such a being, therefore, exists. Do 
you proceed to ask me, where I discover its existence? I answer, not only in the revolutions 
of the celestial bodies; not only in myself; but in the flocks that feed on the plain, in 
the birds that fly in the air, in the stone that falls to the ground, and in the leaf that 
trembles in the wind.</p> 
<p>I am enabled to judge of the physical order of things, although ignorant of their final cause; because to be able to form such a judgment it is sufficient 
for me to compare the several parts of the visible universe with each other, to study their 
mutual concurrence, their reciprocal relations, and to observe the general result of the 
whole. I am ignorant why the universe exists, but I am enabled nevertheless to see how it is 
modified. I cannot fail to perceive that intimate connection by which the several beings it 
is composed of afford each other mutual assistance. I resemble, in this respect, a man who 
sees the inside of a watch for the first time, and is captivated with the beauty of the 
work, although ignorant of its use. I know not, he may say, what this machine is good for, 
but I perceive that each part is made to fit some other. I admire the artist for every part 
of his performance, and am certain that all these wheels act thus in concert to some common 
end, which as yet I fail to comprehend.</p> 
<p>But let us compare the partial and particular ends, the means whereby they are effected, and their constant relations of every kind; then 
let us appeal to our innate sense of conviction; and what man in his senses can refuse to 
acquiesce in such testimony? To what unprejudiced view does not the visible arrangement of 
the universe display the supreme intelligence of its author? How much sophistry does it not 
require to disavow the harmony of created beings, and that admirable order in which all the 
parts of the system concur to the preservation of each other? You may talk to me as much as 
you please of combinations and chances: what end will it answer to reduce me to silence, if 
you can persuade me into the truth of what you advance? and how will you divest me of that 
involuntary sentiment which continually contradicts you? If organized bodies are 
fortuitously combined in a thousand ways before they assume settled and constant forms; if 
at first they are formed stomachs without mouths, feet without heads, hands without arms, 
and imperfect organs of every kind, which have perished for want of the necessary faculties 
of self-preservation; how comes it that none of these imperfect essays have engaged our 
attention? Why hath nature at length confined herself to laws to which she was not at first 
subjected? I confess that I ought not to be surprised that any possible thing should happen, 
when the rarity of the event is compensated by the great odds that it did not happen. And 
yet if any one were to tell me that a number of printer's types, jumbled promiscuously 
together, had arranged themselves in the order of the letters composing the Aeneid, I 
certainly should not deign to take one step to verify or disprove such a story. It may be 
said, I forget the number of chances: but pray how many must I suppose to render such a 
combination in any degree probable? I, who see only the one, must conclude that there is an 
infinite number against it, and that it is not the effect of chance. Add to this that the 
product of these combinations must be always of the same nature with the combined elements; 
hence life and organization never can result from a blind concourse of atoms, nor will the 
chemist, with all his art in compounds, ever find sensation and thought at the bottom of his 
crucible.</p> 
<p>I have been frequently surprised and sometimes scandalized in the reading 
of <foreign lang="ger">Nieuwentheit</foreign>. What a presumption was it to set down to make a book of those wonders of 
nature that display the wisdom of their author? Had his book been as big as the whole world, 
he would not have exhausted his subject; and no sooner do we enter into the minutiae of 
things than the greatest wonder of all escapes us; - that is, the harmony and connection of 
the whole. The generation of living and organized bodies alone baffles all the efforts of 
the human understanding. That insurmountable barrier which nature hath placed between the 
various species of animals, that they might not be confounded with each other, makes her 
intentions sufficiently evident. Not contended only to establish order, she has taken 
effectual methods to prevent its being disturbed.</p> 
<p>There is not a being in the universe which may not, in some respect, be regarded as the common center of all others, 
which are ranged around it in such a manner that they serve reciprocally as cause and effect 
to one another. The imagination is lost and the understanding confounded in such an infinite 
diversity of relations, of which, however, not one of them is either lost or confounded in 
the crowd. How absurd the attempt to deduce this wonderful harmony from the blind mechanism 
of a fortuitous jumble of atoms! Those who deny the unity of design, so manifest in the 
relation of all the parts of this grand system, may endeavor as much as they will to conceal 
their absurdities with abstract ideas, coordinations, general principles, and emblematical 
terms. Whatever they may advance, it is impossible for me to conceive that a system of 
beings can be so wisely regulated, without the existence of some intelligent cause which 
effects such regulation. It is not in my power to believe that passive inanimate matter 
could ever have produced living and sensible creatures, - that a blind fatality should be 
productive of intelligent beings, - or that a cause, incapable itself of thinking, should 
produce the faculty of thinking in its effects.</p> 
<p>I believe, therefore, that the world is governed by a wise and powerful <hi rend="italic">Will.</hi> I see it, or rather I feel it; and this is of 
importance for me to know. But is the world eternal, or is it created? Are things derived 
from one selfexistent principle, or are there two or more, and what is their essence? Of all 
this I know nothing, nor do I see that it is necessary I should. In proportion as such 
knowledge may become interesting I will endeavor to acquire it: but further than this I give 
up all such idle disquisitions, which serve only to make me discontended with myself, which 
are useless in practice, and are above my understanding.</p> 
<p>You will remember, however, that I am not dictating my sentiments to you, but only explaining what they are. Whether 
matter be eternal or only created, whether it have a passive principle or not, certain it is 
that the whole universe is one design, and sufficiently displays one intelligent agent: for 
I see no part of this system that is not under regulation, or that does not concur to one 
and the same end; viz. that of preserving the present and established order of things. That 
Being, whose will is his deed, whose principle of action is in himself, - that Being, in a 
word, whatever it be, that gives motion to all parts of the universe, and governs all 
things, I call God.</p> 
<p>To this term I affix the ideas of intelligence, power, and will, which I have collected from the order of things; and to these I add that of goodness, which 
is a necessary consequence of their union. But I am not at all the wiser concerning the 
essence of the Being to which I give these attributes. He remains at an equal distance from 
my senses and my understanding. The more I think of him, the more I am confounded. I know of 
a certainty that he exists, and that his existence is independent of any of his creatures. I 
know also that my existence is dependent on his, and that every being I know is in the same 
situation as myself. I perceive the deity in all his works, I feel him within me, and behold 
him in every object around me: but I no sooner endeavor to contemplate what he is in 
himself, - I no sooner enquire where he is, and what is his substance, than he eludes the 
strongest efforts of my imagination; and my bewildered understanding is convinced of its own 
weakness.</p> 
<p>For this reason I shall never take upon me to argue about the nature of God further than I am obliged to do by the relation he appears to stand in to myself. There is 
so great a temerity in such disquisitions that a wise man will never enter on them without 
trembling, and feeling fully assured of his incapacity to proceed far on so sublime a 
subject: for it is less injurious to entertain no ideas of the deity at all, than to harbor 
those which are unworthy and unjust.</p> 
<p>After having discovered those of his attributes by which I am convinced of his existence, I return to myself and consider the place I occupy 
in that order of things, which is directed by him and subjected to my examination. Here I 
find my species stand incontestibly in the first rank; as man, by virtue of his will and the 
instruments he is possessed of to put it in execution,has a greater power over the bodies by 
which he is surrounded than they, by mere physical impulse, have over him. By virtue of his 
intelligence, I also find, he is the only created being here below that can take a general 
survey of the whole system. Is there one among them, except man, who knows how to observe 
all others?-to weigh, to calculate, to foresee their motions, their effects, and to join, if 
I may so express myself, the sentiment of a general existence to that of the individual? 
What is there so very ridiculous then in supposing every thing made for man, when he is the 
only created being who knows how to consider the relation in which all things stand to 
himself?</p> 
<p>It is then true that man is lord of the creation, - that he is, at least, sovereign over the habitable earth; for it is certain that he not only subdues all other 
animals, and even disposes by his industry of the elements at his pleasure, but he alone of 
all terrestrial beings knows how to subject to his convenience, and even by contemplation to 
appropriate to his use, the very stars and planets he cannot approach. Let any one produce 
me an animal of another species who knows how to make use of fire, or hath faculties to 
admire the sun. What! am I able to observe, to know other beings and their relations, - am I 
capable of discovering what is order, beauty, virtue, - of contemplating the universe, - of 
elevating my ideas to the hand which governs the whole, - am I capable of loving what is 
good and doing it, and shall I compare myself to the brutes? Abject soul! it is your gloomy 
philosophy alone that renders you at all like them. Or, rather, it is vain you would debase 
yourself. Your own genius rises up against your principles;-your benevolent heart gives the 
lie to your absurd doctrines, - and even the abuse of your faculties demonstrates their 
excellence in spite of yourself.</p> 
<p>For my part, who have no system to maintain, who am only a simple, honest man, attached to no party, unambitious of being the founder of any 
sect, and contended with the situation in which God hath placed me, I see nothing in the 
world, except the deity, better than my own species; and were I left to choose my place in 
the order of created beings, I see none that I could prefer to that of man.</p> 
<p>This reflection, however, is less vain than affecting; for my state is not the effect of choice, 
and could not be due to the merit of a being that did not before exist. Can I behold myself, 
nevertheless thus distinguished, without thinking myself happy in occupying so honorable a 
post; or without blessing the hand that placed me here? From the first view I thus took of 
myself, my heart began to glow with a sense of gratitude towards the author of our being; 
and hence arose my first idea of the worship due to a beneficent deity. I adore the supreme 
power, and melt into tenderness at his goodness. I have no need to be taught artificial 
forms of worship; the dictates of nature are sufficient. Is it not a natural consequence of 
self-love to honor those who protect us, and to love such as do us good?</p> 
<p>But when I come afterwards to take a view of the particular rank and relation in which I stand, as an 
individual, among the fellow-creatures of my species; to consider the different ranks of 
society and the persons by whom they are filled; what a scene is presented to me! Where is 
that order and regularity before observed? The scenes of nature present to my view the most 
perfect harmony and proportion: those of mankind nothing but confusion and disorder. The 
physical elements of things act in concert with each other; the moral world alone is a chaos 
of discord. Mere animals are happy; but man, their lord and sovereign, is miserable! Where, 
Supreme Wisdom! are thy laws? Is it thus, O Providence! thou governest the world? What is 
become of thy power, thou Supreme Beneficence! when I behold evil thus prevailing upon the 
earth?</p> 
<p>Would you believe, my good friend, that from such gloomy reflections and apparent contradictions, I should form to myself more sublime ideas of the soul than ever 
resulted from my former researches? In meditating on the nature of man, I conceived that I 
discovered two distinct principles; the one raising him to the study of eternal truth, the 
love of justice and moral beauty-bearing him aloft to the regions of the intellectual world, 
the contemplation of which yields the truest delight to the philosopher; the other debasing 
him even below himself, subjecting him to the slavery of sense, the tyranny of the passions, 
and exciting these to counteract every noble and generous sentiment inspired by the former. 
When I perceived myself hurried away by two such contrary powers, I naturally concluded that 
man is not one simple and individual substance. I will, and I will not; I perceive myself at 
once free, and a slave; I see what is good, I admire it, and yet I do the evil: I am active 
when I listen to my reason, and passive when hurried away by my passions; while my greatest 
uneasiness is to find, when fallen under temptations, that I had the power of resisting 
them.</p> 
<p>Attend, young man, with confidence to what I say; you will find I shall never 
deceive you. If conscience be the offspring of our prejudices, I am doubtless in the wrong, 
and moral virtue is not to be demonstrated; but if self-love, which makes us prefer 
ourselves to every thing else, be natural to man, and if nevertheless an innate sense of 
justice be found in his heart, let those who imagine him to be a simple uncompounded being 
reconcile these contradictions, and I will give up my opinion and acknowledge him to be one 
substance.</p> 
<p>You will please to observe that by the word substance I here mean, in general, a being possessed of some primitive 
quality, abstracted from all particular or secondary modifications. Now, if all known 
primitive qualities may be united in one and the same being, we have no need to admit of 
more than one substance; but if some of these qualities are incompatible with, and 
necessarily exclusive of each other, we must admit of the existence of as many different 
substances as there are such incompatible qualities. You will do well to reflect on this 
subject. For my part, notwithstanding what Mr. Locke hath said on this head, I need only to 
know that matter is extended and divisible, to be assured that it cannot think; and when a 
philosopher comes and tells me that trees and rocks have thought and perception, he may, 
perhaps, embarrass me with the subtlety of his arguments, but I cannot help regarding him as 
a disingenuous sophist, who had rather attribute sentiment to stocks and stones than 
acknowledge men to have a soul.</p> 
<p>Let us suppose that a man, born deaf, should deny the reality of sounds, because his ears were never sensible of them. To convince him of his 
error, I place a violin before his eyes; and, by playing on another, concealed from him, 
give a vibration to the strings of the former. This motion, I tell him, is effected by 
sound.</p> 
<p><q>Not at all,</q> says he; <q>the cause of the vibration of the string, is in the string itself; it is a common quality in all bodies so to 
vibrate.</q></p> 
<p><q>Show me then,</q> I reply, <q>the same vibration in other bodies; or at least, the cause of it in this string.</q></p> 
<p><q>I cannot,</q> the deaf man may reply, <q>but wherefore must I, because I do not conceive how this string 
vibrates, attribute the cause to your pretended sounds, of which I cannot entertain the 
least idea? This would be to attempt an explanation of one obscurity by another still 
greater. Either make your sounds perceptible to me, or I shall continue to doubt their 
existence.</q></p> 
<p>The more I reflect on our capacity of thinking, and the nature of the human understanding, the greater is the resemblance I find between the arguments of our 
materialists and that of such a deaf man. They are, in effect, equally deaf to that internal 
voice which, nevertheless, calls to them so loud and emphatically. A mere machine is 
evidently incapable of thinking, it has neither motion nor figure productive of reflection: 
whereas in man there exists something perpetually prone to expand, and to burst the fetters 
by which it is confined. Space itself affords not bounds to the human mind: the whole 
universe is not extensive enough for man; his sentiments, his desires, his anxieties, and 
even his pride, take rise from a principle different from that body within which he 
perceives himself confined.</p> 
<p>No material being can be self-active, and I perceive that I am so. It is in vain to dispute with me so clear a point. My own sentiment carries with it 
a stronger conviction than any reason which can ever be brought against it. I have a body on 
which other bodies act, and which acts reciprocally upon them. This reciprocal action is 
indubitable; but my will is independent of my senses. I can either consent to, or resist 
their impressions. I am either vanquished or victor, and perceive clearly within myself when 
I act according to my will, and when I submit to be governed by my passions. I have always 
the power to will, though not the force to execute it. When I give myself up to any 
temptation, I act from the impulse of external objects. When I reproach myself for my 
weakness in so doing, I listen only to the dictates of my will. I am a slave in my vices, 
and free in my repentance. The sentiment of my liberty is effaced only by my depravation, 
and when I prevent the voice of the soul from being heard in opposition to the laws of the 
body.</p> 
<p>All the knowledge I have of volition, is deduced from a sense of my own; and, 
of the understanding, my knowledge is no greater. When I am asked what is the cause that 
determines my will, I ask in my turn, what is the cause that determines my judgment? for it 
is clear that these two causes make but one; and if we conceive that man is active in 
forming his judgment of things - that his understanding is only a power of comparing and 
judging, we shall see that his liberty is only a similar power, or one derived from this-he 
chooses the good as he judges of the true, and for the same reason as he deduces a false 
judgment, he makes a bad choice. What then is the cause that determines his will? It is his 
judgment. And what is the cause that determines his judgment? It is his intelligent faculty, 
- his power of judging. The determining cause lies in himself. If we proceed beyond this 
point, I know nothing of the matter.</p> 
<p>Not that I suppose myself at liberty not to will my own good, or to will my own evil: but my liberty consists in this very circumstance, that 
I am incapable to will any thing but what is useful to me, or at least what appears so, 
without any foreign object interfering in my determination. Does it follow from hence that I 
am not my own master because I am incapable of assuming another being, or of divesting 
myself of what is essential to my existence?</p> 
<p>The principle of all action lies in the will of a free being. We can go no farther in search of its source. It is not the word 
liberty that has no signification; it is that of necessity. To suppose any act or effect, 
which is not derived from an active principle, is indeed to suppose effects without a cause. 
Either there is no first impulse, or every first impulse can have no prior cause; nor can 
there be any such thing as will without liberty. Man is, therefore, a free agent, and as 
such animated by an immaterial substance. This is my third article of faith. From these 
tee first you may easily deduce all the rest, without my continuing to number them.</p> 
<p>If man be an active and free being, he acts of himself. None of his spontaneous actions, 
therefore, enter into the general system of Providence, nor can be imputed to it. Providence 
doth not contrive the evil, which is the consequence of man's abusing the liberty his 
creator gave him; it only doth not prevent it, either because the evil which so impotent a 
being is capable of doing is beneath its notice, or because it cannot prevent it without 
laying a restraint upon his liberty, and causing a greater evil by debasing his nature. 
Providence hath left man at liberty, not that he should do evil, but good, by choice,. It 
hath capacitated him to make such choice, in making a proper use of the faculties it hath 
bestowed on him. His powers, however, are at the same time so limited and confined, that the 
use he makes of his liberty is not of importance enough to disturb the general order of the 
universe. The evil done by man falls upon his own head, without making any change in the 
system of the world, - without hindering the human species from being preserved in spite of 
themselves. To complain, therefore, that God doth not prevent man from doing evil is, in 
fact, to complain that he hath given a superior excellence to human nature, - that he hath 
ennobled our actions by annexing to them the merit of virtue.</p> 
<p>The highest enjoyment is that of being contented with ourselves. It is in order to deserve this contentment that 
we are placed here on earth and endowed with liberty, - that we are tempted by our passions, 
and restrained by conscience. What could Omnipotence itself do more in our favor? Could it 
have established a contradiction in our nature, or have allotted a reward for well-doing to 
a being incapable of doing ill? Is it necessary, in order to prevent man from being wicked, 
to reduce all his faculties to a simple instinct and make him a mere brute? No! never can I 
reproach the Deity for having given me a soul made in his own image, that I might be free, 
good, and happy like himself.</p> 
<p>It is the abuse of our faculties which makes us wicked and miserable. Our cares, our anxieties, our griefs, are all owing to ourselves. Moral evil 
is incontestibly our own work, and physical evil would in fact be nothing, did not our vices 
render us sensible of it. Is it not for our preservation that nature make us sensible of our 
wants? Is not pain of body an indication that the machine is out of order, and a caution for 
us to provide a remedy? And as to death, do not the wicked render both our lives and their 
own miserable? Who can be desirous of living here forever? Death is a remedy for all the 
evils we inflict on ourselves. Nature will not let us suffer perpetually. To how few evils 
are men subject who live in primeval simplicity! They hardly know any disease, and are 
irritated by scarcely any passions. They neither foresee death, nor suffer by the 
apprehensions of it. When it approaches, their miseries render it desirable, and it is to 
them no evil. If we could be contented with being what we are, we should have no inducement 
to lament our fate; but we inflict on ourselves a thousand real evils in seeking after an 
imaginary happiness. Those who are impatient under trifling inconveniences, must expect to 
suffer much greater. In our endeavors to reestablish by medicines a constitution impaired by 
irregularities, we always add to the evil we feel, the greater one which we fear. Our 
apprehensions of death anticipate its horrors and hasten its approach. The faster we 
endeavor to fly, the swifter it pursues us. Thus we are terrified as long as we live, and 
die murmuring against nature on account of those evils which we bring on ourselves by doing 
outrage to her laws.</p> 
<p>Enquire no longer then, who is the author of evil. Behold him in yourself. There exists no other evil in nature than what you either do or suffer, and you 
are equally the author of both. A general evil could exist only in disorder, but in the 
system of nature I see an established order, which is never disturbed. Particular evil 
exists only in the sentiment of the suffering being; and this sentiment is not given to man 
by nature, but is of his own acquisition. Pain and sorrow have but little hold on those who, 
unaccustomed to reflection, have neither memory nor foresight. Take away our fatal 
improvements-take away our errors and our vices-take away, in short, every thing that is the 
work of man, and all that remains is good.</p> 
<p>Where every thing is good, nothing can be unjust, justice being inseparable from goodness. Now goodness is the necessary effect of 
infinite power and self-love essential to every being conscious of its existence. An 
omnipotent Being extends its existence also, if I may so express myself, with that of its 
creatures. Production and preservation follow from the constant exertion of its power: it 
does not act on non-existence. God is not the God of the dead, but of the living. He cannot 
be mischievous or wicked without hurting himself. A being capable of doing every thing 
cannot <hi rend="italic">will</hi> to do any thing but what is good. He who is infinitely good, therefore, because 
he is infinitely powerful, must also be supremely just, otherwise he would be inconsistent 
with himself. For that love of order which produces it we call goodness, and that love of 
order which preserves it is called justice.</p> 
<p>God, it is said, owes nothing to his creatures. For my part, I believe he owes them every thing he promised them when he gave 
them being. Now what is less than to promise them a blessing, if he gives them an idea of 
it, and has so constituted them as to feel the want of it? The more I look into myself, the 
more plainly I read these words written in my soul:<hi rend="italic">Be just and thou wilt be happy.</hi> I see 
not the truth of this, however, in the present state of things, wherein the wicked triumph 
and the just are trampled on and oppressed. What indignation, hence, arises within us to 
find that our hopes are frustrated! Conscience itself rises up and complains of its maker. 
It cries out to him lamenting, <hi rend="italic">thou has deceived me!</hi></p> 
<p><q>I have deceived thee! rash man? Who hath told thee so? Is thy soul annihilated? Dost thou cease to exist? Oh, Brutus! 
stain not a life of glory in the end. Leave not thy honor and thy hopes with thy body in the 
fields of Philippi. Wherefore dost thou say, virtue is a shadow, when thou wilt yet enjoy 
the reward to thine own? Dost thou imagine thou art going to die? No! thou art going to 
live! and then will I make good every promise I have made to thee.</q></p> 
<p>One would be apt to think, from the murmurs of impatient mortals, that God owed them a recompense before 
they had deserved it; and that he was obliged to reward their virtue beforehand. No; let us 
first be virtuous, and rest assured we shall sooner or later be happy. Let us not require 
the prize before we have won the victory, nor demand the price of our labor before the work 
be finished. <q>It is not in the lists,</q> says Plutarch, <q>that the victors at 
our games are crowned, but after the contests are over.</q></p> 
<p>If the soul be immaterial, it may survive the body, and if so, Providence is justified. Had I no other 
proof of the immateriality of the soul, than the oppression of the just and the triumph of 
the wicked in this world, this alone would prevent my having the least doubt of it. So 
shocking a discord amidst the general harmony of things, would make me naturally look out 
for the cause. I should say to myself, we do not cease to exist with this life, - every 
thing reassumes its order after death. I should indeed, be embarrassed to tell where man was 
to be found, when all his perceptible properties were destroyed. At present, however, there 
appears to me no difficulty in this point, as I acknowledge the existence of two different 
substances. It is very plain that during my corporeal life, as I perceive nothing but by 
means of my senses, whatever is not submitted, to their cognizance must escape me. When the 
union of the body and the soul is broken, I conceive that the one may be dissolved, and the 
other preserved entire. Why should the dissolution of the one necessarily bring on that of 
the other? On the contrary, being so different in their natures, their state of union is a 
state of violence, and when it is broken and they both return to their natural situation. 
The active and living substance regains all the force it had employed in giving motion to 
the passive and dead substance to which it had been united. Alas! my failings make me but 
too sensible that man is but half alive in this life, and that the life of the soul 
commences at the death of the body.</p> 
<p>But what is that life? Is the soul immortal in its own nature? My limited comprehension is incapable of conceiving any thing that is 
unlimited. Whatever we call infinite is beyond my conception. What can I deny or 
affirm?-what arguments can I employ on a subject I cannot conceive? I believe that the soul 
survives the body so long as is necessary to justify Providence in the good order of things; 
but who knows that this will be forever? I can readily conceive how material bodies wear 
away and are destroyed by the separation of their parts, but I cannot conceive a like 
dissolution of a thinking being; and hence, as I cannot imagine how it can die, I presume it 
cannot die at all. This presumption, also, being consolatory and not unreasonable, why 
should I be fearful to indulge it?</p> 
<p>I feel that I have a soul: I know it both from thought and sentiment: I know that it exists, without knowing its essence: I cannot reason, 
therefore, on ideas which I have not. One thing, indeed, I know very well, which is, that 
the identity of my being can be preserved only by the memory, and that to be in fact the 
same person, I must remember to have previously existed. Now I cannot recollect, after my 
death, what I was during life, without also recollecting my perceptions, and consequently my 
actions: and I doubt not but this remembrance will one day constitute the happiness of the 
just and the torments of the wicked. Here below, the violence of our passions absorbs the 
innate sentiment of right and wrong, and stifles remorse. The mortification and obloquy 
which virtue often suffers in the world may prevent our being sensible of its charms. But 
when, delivered from the delusions of sense, we shall enjoy the contemplation of the Supreme 
Being, and those eternal truths of which he is the source;-when the beauty of the natural 
order of things shall strike all the faculties of the soul, and when we shall be employed 
solely in comparing what we have really done with what we ought to have done, then will the 
voice of conscience reassume its tone and strength; then will that pure delight, which 
arises from a consciousness of virtue, and the bitter regret of having debased ourselves by 
vice, determine the lot which is severally prepared for us. Ask me not, my good friend, if 
there may not be some other causes of future happiness and misery. I confess I am ignorant. 
These however, which I conceive, are sufficient to console me under the inconveniences of 
this life and give me hopes of another. I do not pretend to say that the virtuous will 
receive any peculiar rewards; for what other advantage can a being, excellent in its own 
nature, expect than to exist in a manner agreeable to the excellence of its constitution? I 
dare affirm, nevertheless, that they will be happy: because their Creator, the author of all 
justice, having given them sensibility, cannot have made them to be miserable; and as they 
have not abused their liberty on earth, they have not perverted the design of their creation 
by their own fault: yet, as they have suffered evils in his life, they will certainly be 
indemnified in another. This opinion is not so much founded on the merits of a man, as on 
the notion of that goodness which appears to me inseparable from the divine nature. I only 
suppose the order of things strictly maintained, and that the Deity is ever consistent with 
himself.</p> 
<p>It would be to as little purpose to ask me whether the torments of the wicked will be eternal. On this subject I am entirely ignorant, and have not the vain 
curiosity to perplex myself with such useless disquisitions. Indeed, why should I interest 
myself to discover their ultimate fate and destiny? I can never believe, however, that they 
will be condemned to everlasting torments.</p> 
<p>If supreme justice avenges itself on the 
wicked, it avenges itself on them here below. It is you and your errors, ye nations! that 
are its ministers of vengeance. It employs the evils you bring on each other, to punish the 
crimes for which you deserve them. It is in the insatiable hearts of mankind, - corroding 
with envy, avarice, and ambition, - that their avenging passions punish them for their 
vices, amidst all the false appearances of prosperity. Where is the necessity of seeking a 
hell in another life, when it is to be found even in this, - in the hearts of the 
wicked.</p> 
<p>Where our momentary necessities or senseless desires have an end, there ought 
our passions and our vices to end also. Of what perversity can pure spirits be susceptible? 
As they stand in need of nothing, to what end should they be vicious? If destitute of our 
grosser senses, can they be desirous of any thing but good? Doth not their happiness consist 
principally in contemplation, and is it possible that those who cease to be wicked should be 
eternally miserable?</p> 
<p>This is what I am inclined to believe on this head, without giving myself the trouble to determine positively concerning the matter.</p> 
<p>O righteous and merciful being! whatever be thy decrees, I acknowledge their rectitude. If thou 
punishest the wicked, my weak reason is dumb before thy justice. But if the remorse of those 
unfortunate wretches is to have an end, - if the same fate is one day to attend us all, - my 
soul exults in thy praise. Is not the wicked man, after all, my brother? How often have I 
been tempted to resemble him in partaking of his vices. O! may he be delivered from his 
misery; may he cast off, also, that malignity which accompanies it; may he be ever as happy 
as myself; so far from exciting my jealousy, his happiness will only add to my own.</p> 
<p>It is thus by contemplating God in his works, and studying him in those attributes which 
it imports me to know, that I learn by degrees to extend that imperfect and confined idea I 
had at first formed of the Supreme Being. But, if this idea becomes thus more grand and 
noble, it is proportionably less adapted to the weakness of the human understanding. In 
proportion as my mind approaches eternal light its brightness dazzles and confounds me: so 
that I am forced to give up all those mean and earthly images which assist my imagination. 
God is no longer a corporeal and perceptible being: the supreme Intelligence which governs 
the world, is no longer the world itself: but in vain I endeavour to elevate my thoughts to 
a conception of his essence. When I reflect that it is he who gives life and activity to 
that living and active substance which moves and governs animated bodies, - when I am told 
that my soul is a spiritual being, and that God is also a spirit, I am incensed at this 
debasement of the divine essence, as if God and my soul were of the same nature, as if God 
was not the only absolute, the only truly active being, - perceiving, thinking and willing 
of himself, - from whom his creatures derive thought, activity, will, liberty, and 
existence. We are free only because it is his will that we should be so; his inexplicable 
substance being, with respect to our souls, such as our souls are in regard to our bodies. I 
know nothing of his having created matter, bodies, spirits, or the world. The idea of 
creation confounds me and surpasses my conception, though I believe as much of it as I am 
able to conceive. But I know that God hath formed the universe and all that exists, in the 
most consummate order. He is doubtless eternal, but I am incapacitated to conceive an idea 
of eternity. Why then should I amuse myself with words? All that I conceive is, that he 
existed before all things, that he exists with them, and will exist after them, if they 
should ever have an end. That a being, whose essence is inconceivable, should give existence 
to other beings, is at best obscure and incomprehensible to our ideas; but that something 
and nothing should be reciprocally converted into each other is a palpable contradiction, a 
most manifest absurdity.</p> 
<p>God is intelligent; but in what manner? Man is intelligent by the act of reasoning, but the supreme intelligence lies under no necessity to reason. He 
requires neither premises nor consequences; nor even the simple form of a proposition. His 
knowledge is purely intuitive. He beholds equally what is and will be. All truths are to him 
as one idea, as all places are but one point, and all times one moment. Human power acts by 
the use of means, the divine power in and of itself. God is powerful because he is willing, 
his will constituting his power. God is good. Nothing is more manifest than this truth. 
Goodness in man, however, consists in a love to his fellow-creatures, and the goodness of 
God in a love of order; for it is on such order that the connexion and preservation of all 
things depend. Again, God is just. This I am fully convinced of, as justice is the natural 
consequence of goodness. The injustice of men is their own work, not his; and that moral 
disorder, which in the judgment of some philosophers makes against the system of providence, 
is in mine the strongest argument for it. Justice in man, indeed, is to render every one his 
due: but the justice of God requires at the hands of every one an account of the talents 
with which he has entrusted them.</p> 
<p>In the discovery by the force of reason, however, of those divine attributes of which I have no absolute idea, I only affirm what I do not 
clearly comprehend; which is in effect to affirm nothing. I may say, it is true that, God is 
this or that; I may be sensible of it and fully convinced within myself, but I may yet be 
unable to conceive how, or in what manner he is so.</p> 
<p>In short, the greater efforts I make to contemplate his infinite essence, the less I am able to conceive it. But I am 
certain that he is, and that is sufficient. The more he surpasses my conceptions, the more I 
adore him. I humble myself before him, and say:</p> 
<p><q>Being of beings! I am, because thou art. To meditate continually on thee is to elevate my thoughts to the fountain of 
existence. The most meritorious use of my reason is to be annihilated before thee. It is the 
delight of my soul, to feel my weak faculties overcome by the splendor of thy greatness.</q></p> 
<p>After having thus deduced this most important truth, from the impressions of perceptible 
objects and that innate principle which leads me to judge of natural causes from experience, 
it remains for me to inquire what maxims I ought to draw therefrom for my conduct in life, - 
what rules I ought to prescribe to myself, in order to fulfill my destiny on earth agreeably 
to the design of him who placed me here. To pursue my own method, I deduce these rules, not 
from the sublime principles of philosophy, but find them written in indelible characters on 
my heart. I have only to consult myself concerning what I ought to do. All that I feel to be 
right, is right: whatever I feel to be wrong, is wrong. Conscience is the ablest of all 
casuists, and it is only when we are trafficing with her, that we have recourse to the 
subtilties of logical ratiocination. The chief of our concerns is that of ourselves; yet how 
often have we not been told by the monitor within, that to pursue out own interest at the 
expense of others would be to do wrong! We imagine, thus, that we are sometimes obeying the 
impulse of nature, and we are all the while resisting it. In listening to the voice of our 
senses we turn a deaf ear to the dictates of our hearts, - the active being obeys, - the 
passive being commands. Conscience is the voice of the soul, - the passions are the voice of 
the body. Is it surprising that these two voices should sometimes contradict each other, or 
can it be doubted, when they do, which ought to be obeyed? Reason deceives us but too often, 
and has given us a right to distrust her conclusions; but conscience never deceives us. She 
is to the soul what instinct 
<ref target="n2">[2]</ref> 
is to the body, - she is man's truest and safest guide. Whoever puts himself under the conduct of his guide pursues the direct path of 
nature, and need not fear to be mislead. This point is very important, (pursued my 
benefactor, perceiving I was going to interrupt him), permit me to detain you a little 
longer in order to clear it up.</p> 
<p>All the morality of our actions lies in the judgments we ourselves form of them. If virtue be any thing real, it ought to be the same in our 
hearts as in our actions; and one of the first rewards of virtue is to be conscious of our 
putting it in practice. If moral goodness be agreeable to our nature, a man cannot be sound 
of mind or perfectly constituted, unless he be good. On the contrary, if it be not so and 
man is naturally wicked, he cannot become good without a corruption of his nature; goodness 
being contrary to his constitution. Formed for the destruction of his fellow-creatures, as 
the wolf is to devour its prey, an humane and compassionate man would be as depraved an 
animal as a meek and lamb-like wolf, while virtue only would leave behind it the stings of 
remorse.</p> 
<p>Let us examine ourselves, my young friend, all partiality part, and see which way our inclinations tend. Which is most agreeable to us, to contemplate the happiness 
or the miseries of others? Which is the most pleasing for us to do, and leaves the most 
agreeable reflection after it, an act of benevolence or of cruelty? For whom are we the most 
deeply interested at our theatres? Do you take a pleasure in acts of villainy? or do you 
shed tears at seeing the authors of them brought to condign punishment? It has been said 
that every thing is indifferent to us in which we are not interested: the contrary, however, 
is certain; as the soothing endearments of friendship and humanity console us under 
affliction; and even in our pleasures we should be too solitary, too miserable, if we had 
nobody to partake them with us. If there be nothing moral in the heart of man, whence arise 
those transports of admiration and esteem we entertain for heroic actions and great minds? 
What has this virtuous enthusiasm to do with our private interest? Wherefore do I rather 
wish to be an expiring Cato, than a triumphant Caesar? Deprive our hearts of a natural 
affection for the sublime and beautiful, and you deprive us of all the pleasures of life. 
The man whose meaner passions have stifled in his narrow soul such delightful sentiments, - 
he who by dint of concentrating all his affections within himself hath arrived at the pitch 
of having no regard for any one else, is no longer capable of such transports. His frozen 
heart never flutters with joy; no sympathetic tenderness brings the tears into his eyes; he 
is incapable of enjoyment. The unhappy wretch is void of sensibility: he is already 
dead.</p> 
<p>But how great soever may be the number of the wicked, there are but few of these cadaverous souls - but few persons so 
insensible, if their own interest be set aside, to what is just and good. Iniquity never 
pleases unless we profit by it: in every other case it is natural for us to desire the 
protection of the innocent. When we see, for instance, in the street or on the highway, an 
act of injustice or violence committed, an emotion of resentment and indignation immediately 
rises in the heart, and incites us to stand up in defence of the injured and oppressed: but 
a more powerful consideration restrains us, and the laws deprive individuals of the right of 
taking upon themselves to avenge insulted innocence. On the contrary, if we happen to be 
witnesses to any act of compassion or generosity, with what admiration, with what esteem are 
we instantly inspired! Who is there that doth not, on such an occasion, say to himself, 
would that I had done as much! It is certainly of very little consequence to us whether a 
man was good or bad who lived two thousand years ago; and yet we are much affected in this 
respect by the relations we meet with in ancient history, as if the transactions recorded 
had happened in our own times. Of what hurt is the wickedness of a Catiline to me? Am I 
afraid of falling a victim to his villainy? Wherefore, then, do I look upon him with the 
same horror as if he were my contemporary? We hate the wicked not only because their vices 
are hurtful, but also because they are wicked. We are not only desirous of happiness for 
ourselves, but also for the happiness of others; and when that happiness doth not diminish 
ours, it necessarily increases it. In a word, we cannot help sympathizing with the 
unfortunate, and always suffer when we are witnesses to their misery. The most perverse 
natures cannot be altogether divested of this sympathy; though it frequently causes them to 
act in contradiction to themselves. The robber who strips the passenger on the highway, will 
frequently distribute his spoils to cover the nakedness of the poor, and the most barbarous 
assassin may be induced humanely to support a man falling into a fit.</p> 
<p>We hear daily of the cries of remorse for secret crimes, and frequently see remarkable instances of 
conscience bringing these crimes to light. Alas! who is a total stranger to this importunate 
voice? We speak of it from experience, and would be glad to silence so disagreeable a 
monitor. But let us be obedient to nature. We know that her government is very mild and 
gracious, and that nothing is more agreeable than the testimony of a good conscience, which 
ever follows our observance of her laws. The wicked man is afraid of, and shuns himself. He 
turns his eyes on every side in search of objects to amuse him. Without an opportunity for 
satire and raillery he would be always sad. His only pleasure lies in mockery and insult. On 
the contrary, the serenity of the just is internal. His smiles are not those of malignity 
but of joy. The source of them is found in himself, and he is as cheerful when alone as in 
the midst of an assembly. He derives not contentment from those who approach him, but 
communicates it to them.</p> 
<p>Cast your eye over the several nations of the world: take a retrospective view of their various histories. Amidst all the many inhuman and absurd forms 
of worship, - amidst all that prodigious diversity of manners and characters, - you will 
everywhere find the same ideas of justice and honesty, - the same notions of good and evil, 
Ancient paganism adopted the most abominable deities, which it would have punished on earth 
as infamous criminals-deities that presented no other picture of supreme happiness than the 
commission of crimes, and the gratification of their passions. But vice, armed even with 
sacred authority, descended in vain on earth. Moral instinct influenced the human heart to 
rebel against it. Even in celebrating the debaucheries of Jupiter, the world admired and 
respected the continence of Xenocrates. The chaste Lucretia adored the impudent Venus. The 
intrepid Roman sacrificed to Fear. They invoked the god Jupiter who disabled his father 
Saturn, and yet they died without murmuring by the hand of their own. The most contemptible 
divinities were adored by the noblest of men. The voice of nature, more powerful than that 
of the gods, made itself respected on earth, and seemed to have banished vice to heaven.</p> 
<p>There evidently exists, then, in the soul of man, an innate principle of justice and 
goodness, by which, in spite of our own maxims, we approve or condemn the actions of 
ourselves and others. To this principle it is that I give the appellation of conscience.</p> 
<p>At this word, however, I hear the clamor of our pretentious philosophers, who all exclaim 
about the mistakes of infancy and the prejudices of education. There is nothing, they say, 
in the human mind but what is instilled by experience; nor can we judge of anything but from 
the ideas we have acquired. Nay, they go farther, and venture to reject the universal sense 
of all nations; seeking some obscure example known only to themselves, to controvert this 
striking uniformity in the judgment of mankind: as if all the natural inclinations of the 
race were annihilated by the depravation of one people, and as if when monsters appeared the 
species itself were extinct. But what end did it serve to the skeptical Montaigne, to take 
so much trouble to discover in an obscure corner of the world a custom opposed to the common 
notions of justice? What end did it answer for him to place that confidence in the most 
suspicious travellers which he refused to the most celebrated writers? Should a few 
whimsical and uncertain customs, founded on local motives unknown to us, invalidate a 
general induction drawn from the united concurrence of all nations, contradicting each other 
in every other point and agreeing only in this? You pique yourself, Montaigne, on being 
ingenuous and sincere. Give us a proof, if it be in the power of a philosopher, of your 
frankness and veracity. Tell me if there be any country upon earth in which it is deemed a 
crime to be sincere, compassionate beneficent, and generous, - in which an honest man is 
despicable, and knavery held in esteem?</p> 
<p>It is pretended that every one contributes to the public good for his own interest; but whence comes it that the virtuous man contributes 
to it to his prejudice? Can a man lay down his life for his own interest? It is certain all 
our actions are influenced by a view to our own good: but unless we take moral good into the 
account, none but the actions of the wicked can ever be explained by motives of private 
interest. We imagine, indeed, that no more will be attempted; as that would be too 
abominable a kind of philosophy, by which we should be puzzled to account for virtuous 
actions; or could extricate ourselves out of the difficulty only by attributing them to base 
designs and sinister views;-by debasinnable to take any other course. All was done with very 
great speed; and so we made by the sail more than eight miles an hour, free from all other 
fear than that of encountering some vessel of war. We gave the Moors, our prisoners, their 
dinner, and the t is not my design here to enter into such metaphysical investigations, as 
surpass both your capacity and mine, and which in fact are useless. I have already told you 
I would not talk philosophy to you, but only assist you to consult your own heart. Were all 
the philosophers in Europe to prove me in the wrong, yet if you were sensible I was in the 
right, I should desire nothing more.</p> 
<p>To this end you need only to distinguish between our acquired ideas and our natural sentiments, for we are sensible before we are 
intelligent; and as we do not learn to desire our own good and to avoid what is evil, but 
possess this desire immediately from nature so the love of virtue and hatred of vice are as 
natural as the love of ourselves. The operations of conscience are not intellectual, but 
sentimental; for though all our ideas are acquired from without, the sentiments which 
estimate them arise from within; and it is by these alone that we know the agreement or 
disagreement which exists between us and those things which we ought to seek or shun.</p> 
<p>To exist is, with us, to be sensible. Our sensibility is incontestably prior to our 
intelligence, and we were possessed of sentiment before we formed ideas. Whatever was the 
cause of our being, it hath provided for our preservation in furnishing us with sentiments 
agreeable to our constitution, nor can it possibly be denied that these at least are 
innate.</p> 
<p>These sentiments are, in the individual, - the love of himself, aversion to pain, dread of death, and the desire of happiness. But if, as it cannot be doubted, man is 
by nature a social being, or at least formed to become such, his sociability absolutely 
requires that he should be furnished with other innate sentiments relative to his species; 
for to consider only the physical wants of men, it would certainly be better for them to be 
dispersed than assembled.</p> 
<p>Now it is from this moral system, - formed by its duplicate relation to himself and his fellow creatures, that the impulse of conscience arises. To know 
what is virtuous is not to love virtue. Man has no innate knowledge of virtue; but no sooner 
is it made known to him by reason, than conscience induces him to love and admire it. This 
is the innate sentiment I mean.</p> 
<p>I cannot think it impossible therefore to explain, from natural consequences, the immediate principle of conscience independent of reason; and, 
though it were impossible, it is not at all necessary; since those who reject this principle 
(admitted, however, and acknowledged in general by all mankind) do not prove its 
nonexistence, but content themselves with affirming it only. When we affirm that it doth 
exist, we stand at least on as good a footing as they, and have besides that internal 
testimony for us, - the voice of conscience deposing in behalf of itself. If the first 
glimmerings of the understanding dazzle our sight, and make objects appear at first obscure 
or confused, let us wait but a little while till our eyes recover themselves and gather 
strength, and we shall presently see, by the light of reason, those same objects to be such 
as nature first presented them: or rather, let us be more simple and less vain; let us 
confine ourselves to the sentiments we first discovered, as it is to these our 
well-regulated studies must always recur.</p> 
<p>O Conscience! Conscience! thou divine instinct, thou certain guide of an ignorant and confined, though intelligent and free being; 
- thou infallible judge of good and evil, who makest man to resemble the Deity. In thee 
consist the excellence of our nature and the morality of our actions. Without thee I 
perceive nothing in myself that should elevate me above the brutes, except the melancholy 
privilege of wandering from error to error by the assistance of an ill-regulated 
understanding and undisciplined reason.</p> 
<p>Thank heaven, we are delivered from this formidable apparatus of philosophy. We can be men without being sages. Without spending our 
days in the study of morality, we possess at a cheaper rate a more certain guide tough the 
immense and perplexing labyrinth of human opinions. It is not enough, however, that such a 
guide exists, - it is necessary to know and follow her. If she speaks to all hearts, it may 
be said, how comes it that so few understand her? It is, alas! because she speaks to us the 
language of nature, which every thing conspires to make us forget. Conscience is timid, she 
loves peace and retirement. The world and its noises terrify her. The prejudices she has 
been compelled to give rise to are her most cruel enemies, before whom she is silent or 
avoids their presence. Their louder voice entirely overpowers her's, and prevents her being 
heard. Fanaticism counterfeits her nature, and dictates in her name the greatest of crimes. 
Thus, from being often rejected, she at length ceases to speak to us, and answers not our 
inquiries after being long held in contempt; it also costs us as much trouble to recall, as 
it did at first to banish her from our bosoms.</p> 
<p>How often in my researches have I found myself fatigued from my indifference! How often hath uneasiness and disgust, poisoning 
my meditations, rendered them insupportable! My insensible heart was susceptible only of a 
luke-warm and languishing zeal for truth. I said to myself, why should I take the trouble to 
seek after things that have no existence? Virtue is a mere chimera, nor is there any thing 
desirable but the pleasures of sense. When a man hath once lost a taste for the pleasures of 
the mind, how difficult to recover it! How much more difficult it also is for one to acquire 
such a taste who never possessed it! If there be in the world a man so miserable as never in 
his life to have done an action the remembrance of which must make him satisfied with 
himself, that man must be ever incapable of such a taste; and for want of being able to 
perceive that goodness which is conformable to his nature, must of necessity remain wicked 
as he is, and eternally miserable. But can you believe there exists on earth a human 
creature so depraved as never to have given up his heart to the inclination of doing good? 
The temptation is so natural and seductive, that it is impossible always to resist it, and 
the remembrance of the pleasure it hath once given us is sufficient to commend it to us ever 
afterwards. Unhappily, this propensity is at first difficult to gratify. There are a 
thousand reasons for our not complying with the dictates of our hearts. The false prudence 
of the world confines our good inclinations to ourselves, and all our fortitude is necessary 
to cast off the yoke. To take a pleasure in virtue is the reward of having been virtuous, 
nor is this prize to be obtained till it be merited.</p> 
<p>Nothing is more amiable than virtue, but we must possess it, in order to find it such. When we court at first it 
embraces, it assumes, like Proteus in the fable, a thousand terrifying forms, and displays 
at last its own only to those who are tenacious of their hold.</p> 
<p>Wavering perpetually between my natural sentiments, tending to the general good of mankind, and my reason, 
confining everything to my own, I should have remained all my life in this continual 
dilemma, doing evil yet loving good, in constant contradiction with myself, had not new 
knowledge enlightened my heart; had not the truth, which determined my opinions, directed 
also my conduct and rendered me consistent.</p> 
<p>It is in vain to attempt the establishment of virtue on the foundation of reason alone. What solidity is there in such a 
base? Virtue, it is said, is the love of order; but can or ought this love of order to 
prevail over that of my own happiness? Let there be given me a clear and sufficient reason 
for my giving it the preference. This pretended principle is at the bottom only a mere play 
upon words; as I may as well say that vice also consists in the love of order taken in a 
different sense. There is some kind of moral order in every thing that has sentiment and 
intelligence. The difference is that a good being regulates himself according to the general 
order of things, and a wicked being regulates things agreeably to his own private interest: 
the latter makes himself the centre of all things, and the former measures his radius and 
disposes himself in the circumference. Here he is arranged, with respect to the common 
centre, as God, and with respect to all concentric circles, as his fellow creatures. If 
there be no God, the wicked man only reasons right - the good man is a mere fool.</p> 
<p>O my child! may you be one day sensible how great a weight we are relieved from, when, having 
exhausted the vanity of human opinion and tasted of the bitterness of the passions, we see 
ourselves at last so near the path to wisdom, - the reward of our good actions, and the 
source of that happiness we had despaired of obtaining.</p> 
<p>Every duty prescribed by the laws of nature, though almost effaced from my heart by the injustice of mankind, again 
revived at the name of that eternal justice which imposed them,and was a witness to my 
discharged of them. I see in myself nothing more than the work and instrument of a superior 
being desirous of and doing good, desirous also of effecting mine by the concurrence of my 
will to his own, and by my making a right use of my liberty. I acquiesce in the regularity 
and order he hath established, being certain of enjoying one day or other that order in 
myself, and of finding my happiness therein: for what can afford greater felicity than to 
perceive one's self making a part of a system where every thing is constructed aright? On 
every occasion of pain or sorrow I support them with patience, reflecting that they are 
transitory and that they are derived from a body that is detached from myself. If I do a 
good action in secret, I know that it is nevertheless see, and make the consideration of 
another life the rule of my conduct in this. If I am ever dealt with unjustly I say to 
myself, that just Being, who governs all things, knows how to indemnify me. My corporeal 
necessities and the miseries inseparable from this mortal life, make the apprehensions of 
death more supportable. I have hence so many chains the less to break when I am obliged to 
quit this mortal scene.</p> 
<p>For what reason my soul is thus subjected to the organs of sense and chained to a body which lays it under so much restraint, I know not, nor presume 
to enter into the decrees of the Almighty. But I may, without temerity, form a modest 
conjecture or two on this subject. I reflect that,if the mind of man had remained perfectly 
free and pure, what merit could he have pretended to in admiring and pursuing that order 
which he saw already established, and which he would lie under no temptation to disturb? It 
is true he would have been happy, but he could not have attained that most sublime degree of 
felicity - the glory of virtue and the testimony of a good conscience. We should in such a 
case have been no better than the angels, and without doubt a virtuous man will be one day 
much superior. Being united on earth to a mortal body by ties not less powerful than 
incomprehensible, the preservation of that body becomes the great concern of the soul, and 
makes its present apparent interests contrary to the general order of things, which it is 
nevertheless capable of seeing and admiring. It is in this situation that by making a good 
use of his liberty, it becomes at once his merit and his reward; and that he prepares for 
himself eternal happiness in combating his earthly passions, and preserving the primitive 
purity of his will.</p> 
<p>But even supposing that in our present state of depravity our primitive propensities were such as they ought to be, yet if all our vices are derived from 
ourselves, why do we complain that we are subjected by them? Why do we impute to the Creator 
those evils which we bring on ourselves, and those enemies we arm against our own happiness? 
Ah! let us not spoil the man of nature, and he will always be virtuous without constraint, 
and happy without remorse. The criminals who pretend they are compelled to sin, are as false 
as they are wicked. Is it possible for them not to see that the weakness they complain of is 
their own work; that their first depravation was owing to their own will; that by their 
willfully yielding at first to temptations, they at length find them irresistible? It is 
true they now cannot held their being weak and wicked; but it is their fault that they at 
first become so. How easily might men preserve the mastery over themselves and their 
passions even during life if, before their vicious habits are acquired, when the faculties 
of the mind are just beginning to be displayed, they should employ themselves on those 
objects which it is necessary for them to know in order to judge of those which are unknown; 
if they were sincerely desirous of acquiring knowledge, not with a view of making a parade 
in the eyes of other, but in order to render themselves wise, good, and happy in the 
practice of their natural duties! This study appears difficult because we only apply to it 
after being already corrupted by vice, and made slaves to our passions. We place our 
judgment and esteem on objects before we arrive at the knowledge of good and evil, and then 
referring every thing to that false standard, we hold nothing in its due estimation.</p> 
<p>The heart, at a certain age, while it is yet free, eager, restless, and anxious for 
happiness, is ever seeking it with an impatient and uncertain curiosity; when deceived by 
the senses, if fixes on the shadow of it, and imagines it to be found where it doth not 
exist. This illusion hath prevailed too long with me. I discovered it, alas! too late; and 
have not been able entirely to remove it: no, it will remain with me as long as this mortal 
body, which gave rise to it. It may prove as seductive, however, as it will, it can no 
longer deceive me. I know it for what it is, and even while I am misled by it, despise it. 
So far from esteeming it an object of happiness, I see it is an obstacle to it. Hence I long 
for that moment when I shall shake off this incumbrance of body and be myself, without 
inconsistency or participation with matter, and shall depend on myself only to be happy. In 
the mean time I make myself happy in this life, because I hold the evils of life as trifling 
in themselves; as almost foreign to my being; and conceive at the same time that all the 
real good which may thence be deduced depends on myself.</p> 
<p>To anticipate as much as possible that desirable state of happiness, power and liberty, I exercise my mind in sublime 
contemplations. I meditate on the order of the universe, not indeed with a view to explain 
it by vain systems, but to admire it perpetually and to adore its all-wise Creator, whose 
features I trace in his workmanship. With him I am thus enabled to converse, and to exert my 
faculties in the contemplation of his divine essence. I am affected by his beneficence, I 
praise him for his mercies, but never so far forget myself as to pray. For what should I ask 
of him? That he should for my sake pervert the order of things, and work miracles in my 
favor? Shall I, who ought to love and admire above all things that order which is 
established by his wisdom and maintained by his providence, desire that such order should be 
broken for me? No! such a rash petition would rather merit punishment than acceptance. Nor 
can I pray to him for the power of acting aright: for why should I petition for what he hath 
already given me? Hath he not given me conscience to love virtue, reason to know what it is, 
and liberty to make it my choice? If I do evil, I have no excuse: I do it because I will. To 
desire him to change my will, is to require that of him which he requires of me. This would 
be to desire him to do my work, while I receive the reward. Not to be content with my 
situation in the order of things, is to desire to be no longer a man; it is to wish that 
things were otherwise constituted than they are, - to wish for evil and disorder. No, thou 
source of justice and truth, God! merciful and just! placing my confidence in thee, the 
chief desire of my heart is that they will be done. By rendering my will conformable to 
thine, I act as thou dost, - I acquiesce in thy goodness, and conceive myself already a 
partaker of that supreme felicity which is its reward.</p> 
<p>The only thing which, under a just diffidence of myself, I request of him, or rather expect from his justice, is that he 
will correct my errors when I go astray. To be sincere, however, I do not think my judgment 
infallible: such of my opinions as seem to be the best founded may, nevertheless, be false; 
for what man hath not his opinions, and how few are there who agree in every thing? It is to 
no purpose that the illusions by which I am misled arise from myself; it is he alone who can 
dissipate them. I have done every thing in my power to arrive at truth; but its source is 
elevated beyond my reach. If my faculties fail me, in what am I culpable? Is it not then 
necessary for truth to stoop to my capacity?</p> 
<p>The good priest spoke with much earnestness: he was deeply moved, and I was also greatly affected. I imagined myself 
attending to the divine Orpheus singing his hymns and teaching mankind the worship of the 
gods. A number of objections, however, to what he had said, suggested themselves; though I 
did not urge one, as they were less solid than perplexing; and though not convinced, I was 
nevertheless persuaded he was in the right. In proportion as he spoke to me from the 
conviction of his own conscience, mine confirmed me in the truth of what he said.</p> 
<p>The sentiments you have been delivering, said I to him, appear newer to me in what you confess 
yourself ignorant of, than in what you profess to believe. I see in the latter a resemblance 
to that theism or natural religion which Cistians affect to confound with atheism and 
impiety, though in fact diametrically opposite. In the present condition of my mind I find 
it difficult to adopt precisely your opinions and to be as wise as you. To be at least as 
sincere, however, I will consult my own conscience on these points. It is that internal 
sentiment which, according to your example, ought to be my monitor; and you have yourself 
taught me that, after having imposed silence on it for a long time, it is not to be awakened 
again in a moment. I will treasure up your discourse in my heart and meditate thereon. If I 
am as much convinced as you are, after I have duly weighed it, I will trust you as my 
apostle and will be your proselyte till death. Go on, however, to instruct me. You have only 
informed me of half I ought to know. Give me your thoughts on revelation, the scriptures, 
and those mysterious doctrines concerning which I have been in the dark from my infancy, 
without being able to conceive or believe them, and yet not knowing how to either admit or 
reject them.</p> 
<p>Yes, my dear child, (said he), I will proceed to tell you what I think further. I meant not to open my heart to you by halves: but the desire which you express to 
be informed in these particulars, was necessary to authorize me to be totally without 
reserve. I have hitherto told you nothing but what I thought might be useful to you, and in 
the truth of which I am most firmly persuaded. The examination which I am now going to make 
is very different; presenting to my view nothing but perplexity, mysteriousness, and 
obscurity. I enter on it, therefore, with distrust and uncertainty. I almost tremble to 
determine about any thing, and shall, therefore, rather inform you of my doubts than of my 
opinions. Were your own sentiments more confirmed. I should hesitate to acquaint you with 
mine; but in your present skeptical situation, you will be a gainer by thinking as I do. Let 
my discourse, however, carry with it no greater authority than that of reason, for I frankly 
confess myself ignorant as to whether I am in the right or wrong. It is difficult, indeed, 
in all discussions, not to assume sometimes an affirmative tone; but remember that all my 
affirmations, in treating these matters, are only so many rational doubts. I leave you to 
investigate the truth of them. On my part, I can only promise to be sincere.</p> 
<p>You will find that my exposition treats of nothing more than natural religion. It is very strange 
that we should stand in need of any other! By what means can I find out such necessity? In 
what respect can I be culpable for serving God agreeably to the dictates of the 
understanding he hath given me, and the sentiments he hath implanted in my heart? What 
purity of morals, what system of faith useful to man, or honorable to his Creator, can I 
deduce from any positive doctrines, that I cannot deduce equally as well from a good use of 
my natural faculties? Let any one show me what can be added, either for the glory of God, 
the good of society, or my own advantage, to the obligations we are laid under by nature. 
Let him show me what virtue can be produced from any new worship, which is not also the 
consequence of mine. The most sublime ideas of the Deity are inculcated by reason alone. 
Take a view of the works of nature, listen to the voice within, and then tell me what God 
hath omitted to say to your sight, your conscience, your understanding? Where are the men 
who can tell us more of him than he thus tells us of himself? Their revelations only debase 
the Deity, in ascribing to him human passions. So far from giving us enlightened notions of 
the Supreme Being, their particular tenets, in my opinion, give us the most obscure and 
confused ideas. To the inconceivable mysteries by which the Deity is hid from our view, they 
add the most absurb contradictions. They serve to make man proud, persecuting, and cruel. 
Instead of establishing peace on earth, they bring fire and sword. I ask myself what good 
purpose all this contention serves without being able to resolve the question. Artificial 
religion presents to my view only the wickedness and miseries of mankind.</p> 
<p>I am told, indeed, that revelation is necessary to teach mankind the manner in which God should be 
served. As a proof of this, they bring the diversity of whimsical modes of worship which 
prevail in the world; and that without remarking that this very diversity arises from the 
practice of adopting revelations. Ever since men have taken it into their heads to make the 
Deity speak, every people make him speak in their own way, and say what they like best. Had 
they listened only to what the Deity hath said to their hearts, there would have been but 
one religion on earth.</p> 
<p>It is necessary that the worship of God should be uniform; I would have it so: but is this a point so very important that the whole apparatus of divine 
power was necessary to establish it? Let us not confound the ceremonials of religion with 
religion itself. The worship of God demands that of the heart; and this, when it is sincere, 
is ever uniform. Men must entertain very ridiculous notions of the Deity, indeed, if they 
imagine he can interest himself in the gown or cassock of a priest, - in the order of words 
he pronounces, or in the gestures and genuflexions he makes at the altar. Alas! my friend, 
where is the use of kneeling? Stand as upright as you may, you will always be near enough to 
the earth. God requires to be worshipped in spirit and in truth. This is a duty incumbent on 
men of all religions and countries. With regard to exterior forms, if their uniformity be 
expedient for the sake of peace and good order, it is merely an affair of government; the 
administration of which surely requires not the aid of revelation.</p> 
<p>I did not set out at first with these reflections. Hurried on by the prejudices of education, and by that 
dangerous self-conceit which ever elates mankind above their sphere, as I could not raise my 
feeble conceptions to the Supreme Being, I foolishly endeavored to debase him to my ideas. 
Thus I connected relations infinitely distant from each other, comparing the incomprehensible nature of the deity with my own. I require still further a more immediate 
communication with the Divinity, and more particular instructions concerning his will. Not 
content with reducing God to a similitude with man, I wanted to be further distinguished by 
his favor, and to enjoy supernatural lights. I longed for an exclusive and peculiar 
privilege of adoration, and that God should have revealed to me what he had kept secret from 
others, or that others should not understand his revelations so well as myself.</p> 
<p>Looking on the point at which I had arrived, - at that whence all believers set out in 
order to reach an enlightened mode of worship, I regarded natural religion only as the 
elements of all religion. I took a survey of that variety of sects which are scattered over 
the face of the earth, and who mutually accuse each other of falsehood and error. I asked 
which of them was right?</p> 
<p>Every one of them in their turn answered <hi rend="italic">theirs.</hi> I and my partisans only think truly; all the rest are mistaken.</p> 
<p><hi rend="italic">But, how do you know that your sect is in the right?</hi></p> 
<p>Because God hath declared so.</p> 
<p><hi rend="italic">And who tells you that God hath so declared!</hi></p> 
<p>My spiritual guide, who knows it well. My pastor tells me to believe so and so, and accordingly I believe it; he assures me that everyone who says to the 
contrary speaks falsely; and, therefore, I listen to nobody who controverts his 
doctrine.<ref target="n3">[3]</ref> </p> 

<p>If there be only one religion in the world that can prevent our suffering eternal damnation, and there be on any 
part of the earth a single mortal who is sincere, and is not convinced by its evidence, the 
God of that religion must be the most iniquitous and cruel of tyrants. Would we seek the 
truth therefore in sincerity, we must lay no stress on the place or circumstance of our 
birth, nor on the authority of fathers and teachers; but appeal to the dictates of reason 
and conscience concerning every thing is that taught us in our youth. It is to no purpose to 
bid me subject my reason to the truth of things of which it is incapable of judging. The man 
who would impose on me a falsehood, may bid me do the same. It is necessary, therefore, I 
should employ my reason even to know when it ought to submit.</p> 
<p>All the theology I am myself capable of acquiring, by taking a prospect of the universe and by the proper use of 
my faculties, is confined to what I have here laid down. To know more, we must have recourse 
to extraordinary means. These means cannot depend on the authority of men: for as all men 
are of the same species as myself, whatever another can by natural means come to the 
knowledge of, I can do the same; and another man is as liable to be deceived as I am. When I 
believe, therefore, what he says, it is not because he says it, but because he proves it. 
The testimony of mankind, therefore, is really that of my reason, and adds nothing to the 
natural means God hath given me for the discovery of the truth.</p> 
<p>What then can even the apostle of truth have to tell me, of which I am not still to judge?</p> 
<p><hi rend="italic">But God himself hath spoken; listen to the voice of revelation.</hi></p> 
<p>That, indeed, is another thing. God hath spoken! This is saying a great deal: but to whom hath he spoken?</p> 
<p><hi rend="italic">He hath spoken to man.</hi></p> 
<p>How comes it then that I heard nothing of it?</p> 
<p><hi rend="italic">He hath appointed others to teach you his word.</hi></p> 
<p>I understand you. There are certain men who are to tell me what God hath said. I had much rather have heard it from himself. This, had 
he so pleased, he could easily have done; and I should then have run no risk of deception. 
Will it be said I am secured from that by his manifesting the mission of his messengers by 
miracles? Where are those miracles to be seen? Are they related only in books? Pray, who 
wrote those books?</p> 
<p><hi rend="italic">Men.</hi></p> 
<p>Who were witnesses to these miracles?</p> 
<p><hi rend="italic">Men.</hi></p> 
<p>Always human testimony! It is always men who tell me what other men have told them. What 
a number of those are constantly between me and the Deity! We are always reduced to the 
necessity of examining, comparing, and verifying such evidence. O! that God had deigned to 
have saved me all this anxiety! Should I in that case have served him with a less willing 
heart?</p> 
<p>Consider, my friend, in what a terrible discussion I am already engaged; what immense erudition I stand in need of to recur back to the earliest antiquity-to examine, to 
weigh, to confront prophecies, revelations, facts, with all the monuments of faith that have 
made their appearance in all the countries of the world; to ascertain their time, place, 
authors, and occasions. How great the critical sagacity which is requisite to enable me to 
distinguish between pieces that are suppositious, and those which are authentic; to compare 
objections with their replies, translations with their originals; to judge of the 
impartiality of witnesses, of their good sense, of their capacity; to know if nothing be 
suppressed or added to their testimony, if nothing be changed, transposed, or falsified; to 
obviate the contradictions that remain, to judge what weight we ought to ascribe to the 
silence of our opponents in regard to facts alleged against them; to discover whether such 
allegations were known to them; whether they did not disdain them too much to make any 
reply; whether books were common enough for ours to reach them; or, if we were honest enough 
to let them have free circulation among us, and to leave their strongest objections in full 
force.</p> 
<p>Again, supposing that all these monuments of faith are acknowledged to be incontestable, we must proceed to examine the proofs of the mission of their authors. It 
would be necessary for us to be perfectly acquainted with the laws of chance and the 
doctrine of probabilities, to judge correctly what prediction could not be accomplished 
without a miracle; to know the genius of the original languages, in order to distinguish 
what is predictive in these languages and what is only figurative. It would be requisite for 
us to know what facts are agreeable to the established order of nature, and what are not so; 
to be able to say how far an artful man may not fascinate the eyes of the simple, and even 
astonish the most enlightened spectators; to know of what kind a miracle should be, and the 
authenticity it ought to bear, not only to claim our belief, but to make it criminal to 
doubt it; to compare the proofs of false and true miracles, and discover the certain means 
of distinguishing them; and after all to tell why the Deity should choose, in order to 
confirm the truth of his word, to make use of means which in their turn require 
confirmation, as if he took delight in playing upon the credulity of mankind, and had 
purposely avoided the direct means to persuade them.</p> 
<p>Suppose that the divine majesty hath really condescended to make man the organ of promulgating its sacred will, is it 
reasonable, is it just, to require all mankind to obey the voice of such a minister, without 
his making himself known to be such? Where is the equity or propriety in furnishing him, for 
universal credentials, with only a few particular tokens displayed before a handful of 
obscure persons, and of which all the rest of mankind know nothing but by hearsay? In every 
country in the world, if we should believe all the prodigies to be true which the common 
people and the ignorant affirm to have seen, every sect would be in the right; there would 
be more miraculous events than natural ones; and the greatest miracle of all would be to 
find that no miracles had happened where fanaticism had been persecuted.</p> 
<p>The Supreme Being is best displayed by the fixed and unalterable order of nature. If there should happen 
many exceptions to such general laws, I should no longer know what to think; and for my 
part, I must confess I believe too much in God to believe in so many miracles so little 
worthy of him.</p> 
<p>What if a man should come and harangue us in the following manner:</p> 
<p><q>I come, ye mortals, to announce to you the will of the most high. Acknowledge in my 
voice that of him who sent me. I command the sun to move backwards, the stars to change 
their places, the mountains to disappear, the waves to remain fixed on high, and the earth 
to wear a different aspect.</q></p> 
<p>Who would not, at the sight of such miracles, immediately attribute them to the author of nature?</p> <p>Nature is not obedient to 
impostors. Their miracles are always performed in the highways, in the fields, or in 
apartments where they are displayed before a small number of spectators, previously disposed 
to believe every thing they see.</p> 
<p>Who is there that will venture to decide how many eye-witnesses are necessary to render a miracle worthy of credit? If the miracles, intended 
to prove the truth of your doctrine, stand themselves in need of proof, of what use are 
they? Their performance might as well have been omitted.</p> 
<p>The most important examination after all remains to be made into the truth of the doctrines delivered; for as 
those who say that God is pleased to work these miracles, pretend that the devil sometimes 
imitates them, we are no niarer a decision than before, though such miracles should be ever 
so well attested. As the magicians of Pharaoh worked the same miracles, even in the presence 
of Moses, as he himself performed by the express command of God, why might not they, in his 
absence, from the same proofs, pretend to the same authority? Thus after proving the truth 
of the doctrine by the miracle, you are reduced to the necessity of proving the truth of the 
miracle by that of the doctrine, 
<ref target="n4">[4]</ref> 
lest the works of the devil should be mistaken 
for those of the Lord. What think you of this alternative?</p> 
<p>The doctrines coming from God, ought to bear the sacred characters of the divinity; and should not only clear up those confused ideas which 
unenlightened reason excites in the mind, but should also furnish us with a system of 
religion and morals agreeable to those attributes by which only we form a conception of his 
essence. If then they teach us any absurdities, if they inspire us with the sentiments of 
aversion for our fellow-creatures and fear for ourselves; if they describe the Deity as a 
vindictive, partial, jealous and angry being; as a God of war and of battles, always ready 
to thunder and destroy; always teatening slaughter and revenge, and even boasting of 
punishing the innocent, my heart cannot be incited to love so terrible a Deity, and I shall 
take care how I give up my natural religion to embrace such doctrines.</p> 
<p>I should say to the advocates and professors of such a religion:</p> 
<p><q>Your God is not mine! A Being who began his dispensations with partiality, selecting one people 
and proscribing the rest of mankind, is not the common father of the human race; a Being who destines to 
eternal punishment the greater part of his creatures, is not that good and merciful God who is 
pointed out by my reason.</q></p> 
<p>With regard to articles of faith, my reason tells me they should be clear, perspicuous, and evident. If natural religion be insufficient, it is 
owing to the obscurity in which it necessarily leaves those sublime truths it professes to 
teach. It is the business of revelation to exhibit them to the mind in a more clear and 
sensible manner; to adapt them to our understanding, and to enable us to conceive, in order 
that we may be capable of believing them. True faith is assured and confirmed by the 
understanding. The best of all religions is undoubtedly the clearest. That which is clouded 
with mysteries and contradictions, the worship that is to be taught me by preaching, teaches 
me by that very circumstance to distrust it. The God whom I adore is not a God of darkness; 
he hath not given me an understanding to forbid me the use of it. To bid me give up my 
reason, is to insult the author of it. The minister of truth doth not tyrannize over my 
understanding, - he enlightens it.</p> 
<p>We have set aside all human authority, and without it, I cannot see how one man can convince another by preaching top him an unreasonable 
doctrine. Let us suppose two persons engaged in a dispute on this head, and see how they 
will express themselves in the language generally made use of on such occasions.</p> 
 
<sp> 
<speaker> 
<hi rend="italic">Dogmatist.</hi></speaker><p>-Your reason tells you that the whole is greater than a part, but I tell you 
from God, that a part is greater than the whole.</p></sp> 
<sp> 
<speaker> 
<hi rend="italic">Rationalist.</hi></speaker><p>-And who are you, that dare to tell me God contradicts himself? In whom shall I rather believe; in him who 
instructs me in the knowledge of eternal truths by means of reason, or in you who in his 
name would impose on me the greatest absurdities?</p></sp> 
<sp> 
<speaker> 
<hi rend="italic">Dogmatist.</hi></speaker><p>-In me, for my instructions are more positive, and I will prove to you incontestably that he hath sent 
me.</p></sp> 
<sp> 
<speaker> 
<hi rend="italic">Rationalist.</hi></speaker><p>-How! will you prove that God hath sent you to depose against 
himself? What sort of proofs can you bring to convince me it is more certain that God speaks 
by your mouth, than by the understanding he hath given me?</p></sp> 
<sp> 
<speaker> 
<hi rend="italic">Dogmatist.</hi></speaker><p>-The understanding he hath given you! Ridiculous and contemptible man! You talk as if you were 
the first infidel who was ever misled by an understanding depraved by sin.</p></sp> 
<sp> 
<speaker> 
<hi rend="italic">Rationalist.</hi></speaker><p>-Nor may you, man of God! be the first knave whose impudence hath been the 
only proof he could give of his divine mission.</p></sp> 
<sp> 
<speaker> 
<hi rend="italic">Dogmatist.</hi></speaker><p>-How! can Philosophers be thus abusive?</p></sp> 
<sp> 
<speaker> 
<hi rend="italic">Rationalist.</hi></speaker><p>-Sometimes, when Saints set them the example.</p></sp> 
<sp> 
<speaker> 
<hi rend="italic">Dogmatist.</hi></speaker><p>-Oh! but I am authorized to abuse you. I speak on the part of God 
Almighty.</p></sp> 
<sp> 
<speaker> 
<hi rend="italic">Rationalist.</hi></speaker><p>-It would not be improper, however, to produce your 
credentials before you assume your privileges.</p></sp> 
<sp> 
<speaker> 
<hi rend="italic">Dogmatist.</hi></speaker><p>- My credentials are sufficiently authenticated. Both heaven and earth are witnesses in my favor. Attend, I pray 
you, to my arguments.</p></sp> 
<sp> 
<speaker> 
<hi rend="italic">Rationalist.</hi></speaker><p>-Arguments! why, you surely do not pretend to 
any! To tell me that my reason is fallacious, is to refute whatever it may say in your 
favor. Whoever refuses to abide by the dictates of reason, ought to be able to convince 
without making use of it. For, supposing that in the course of your arguments you should 
convince me, how shall I know whether it be not tough the fallacy of reason depraved by 
sin, that I acquiesce in what you affirm? Besides, what proof, what demonstration, can you 
ever employ more evident that the axiom which destroys it? It is fully as credible that a 
just syllogism should be false, as that a part is greater than the whole.</p></sp> 
<sp> 
<speaker> 
<hi rend="italic">Dogmatist.</hi></speaker><p>-What a difference! My proofs admit of no reply; they are of a supernatural kind.</p></sp> 
<sp> 
<speaker> 
<hi rend="italic">Rationalist.</hi></speaker><p>-Supernatural! What is the meaning of that term? I do not understand it.</p></sp> 
<sp> 
<speaker> 
<hi rend="italic">Dogmatist.</hi></speaker><p>-Contraventions of the order of nature; prophecies, miracles, and 
prodigies of every kind.</p></sp> 
<sp> 
<speaker> 
<hi rend="italic">Rationalist.</hi></speaker><p>-Prodigies and miracles! I have never seen any of these things.</p></sp> 
<sp> 
<speaker> 
<hi rend="italic">Dogmatist.</hi></speaker><p>-No matter; others have seen them for you. We can bring 
clouds of witnesses -the testimony of whole nations.</p></sp> 
<sp> 
<speaker> 
<hi rend="italic">Rationalist.</hi></speaker><p>-The testimony of whole nations! Is that a proof of the supernatural kind?</p></sp> 
<sp> 
<speaker> 
<hi rend="italic">Dogmatist.</hi></speaker><p>-No! But when it is unanimous it is incontestable.</p></sp> 
<sp> 
<speaker> 
<hi rend="italic">Rationalist.</hi></speaker><p>-There is nothing more incontestable than the dictates of reason, nor can the testimony of all mankind prove the truth of an 
absurdity. Let us see some of your supernatural truths then, as the attestation of men is 
not so.</p></sp> 
<sp> 
<speaker> 
<hi rend="italic">Dogmatist.</hi></speaker><p>-Infidel wretch! It is plain that the grace of God doth not speak 
to thy understanding.</p></sp> 
<sp> 
<speaker> 
<hi rend="italic">Rationalist.</hi></speaker><p>-Whose fault is that? Not mine; for, according to 
you, it is necessary to be enlightened by grace to know how to ask for it. Begin then, and 
speak to me in its stead.</p></sp> 
<sp> 
<speaker> 
<hi rend="italic">Dogmatist.</hi></speaker><p>-Is not this what I am doing? But you will not hear. What do you say to prophecies?</p></sp> 
<sp> 
<speaker> 
<hi rend="italic">Rationalist.</hi></speaker><p>-As to prophecies; I say, in the first place, I have heard as few of them as I have seen miracles; and in the second, I say 
that no prophecy bears any weight with me.</p></sp> 
<sp> 
<speaker> 
<hi rend="italic">Dogmatist.</hi></speaker><p>-Thou disciple of Satan! And why have prophecies no weight with you?</p></sp> 
<sp> 
<speaker> 
<hi rend="italic">Rationalist.</hi></speaker><p>-Because, to give them such weight requires tee things, the concurrence of which is impossible. These are, that I 
should in the first place be a witness to the delivery of the prophecy; next, that I should 
be witness also to the event; lastly, that it should be clearly demonstrated to me that such 
event could not have occurred by accident. For, though a prophecy were as precise, clear, 
and determinate as an axiom of geometry, yet as the perspicuity of a prediction made at 
random does not render the accomplishment of it impossible, that accomplishment when it 
happens proves nothing in fact concerning the fore-knowledge of him who predicted it. You 
see, therefore, to what your pretended supernatural proofs, your miracles, and your 
prophecies reduce us: - to the folly of believing them all on the credit of others, and of 
submitting the authority of God speaking to our reason, to that of man. If those eternal 
truths, of which my understanding forms the strongest conception, can possibly be false, I 
can have no hope of ever arriving at certitude; and so far from being capable of being 
assured that you speak to me from God, I cannot even be assured of his existence.</p></sp> 
 
<p>You see, my child, how many difficulties must be removed before our disputants can agree; nor 
are these all. Among so many different religions, each of which proscribes and excludes the 
other, one only can be true; if, indeed, there be such a one among them all. Now, to 
discover which this is, it is not enough to examine that one; it is necessary to examine 
them all, as we should not, on any occasion whatever, condemn without a hearing. It is 
necessary to compare objections with proofs, and to know what each objects to in the others, 
as well as what the others have to say in their defence. The more clearly any sentiment or 
opinion appears demonstrated, the more narrowly it behooves us to inquire, what are the 
reasons which prevent its opponents from subscribing to it?</p> 
<p>We must be very simple indeed, to think that an attention to the theologists of our own party sufficient to 
instruct us in what our adversaries have to offer. Where shall we find divines, of any 
persuasion, perfectly candid and honest? Do they not all begin to weaken the arguments of 
their opponents before they proceed to refute them? Each is the oracle of his party, and 
makes a great figure among his own partisans, with such proofs as would expose him to 
ridicule among those of a different persuasion.</p> 
<p>Are you desirous of gaining information from books? What a fund of erudition will not this require! How many languages 
must you learn! How many libraries must you turn over! And who is to direct you in the 
choice of the books? There are hardly to be found in any one country the best books on the 
contrary side of the question, and still less is it to be expected that we should find books 
on all sides. The writings of the adverse and absent party, were they found also, would be 
very easily refuted. The absent are always in the wrong; and the most weak and insufficient 
arguments laid down with a confident assurance, easily efface the most sensible and valid, 
when exposed with contempt. Add to all this, that nothing is more fallacious than books, nor 
exhibit less faithfully the sentiments of their writers. The judgment which you formed, for 
instance, of the Roman Catholic religion, from the treatise of Bossuet, was very different 
from that which you acquired by residing among us. You have seen that the doctrines we 
maintain in our controversies with the Protestants, are not those which are taught the 
common people; and that Bossuet's book by no means resembles the instructions delivered from 
the pulpit.</p> 
<p>To form a proper judgment of any religion, we are not to deduce its 
tenets from the books of its professors; we must go and learn it among the people. Each sect 
have their peculiar traditions, - their customs, prejudices, and modes of acceptation, which 
constitute the peculiar mode of their faith. This should all be taken into consideration 
when we form a judgment of their religion.</p> 
<p>How many considerable nations are there who print no books of their own, and read none of ours? How are they to judge of our 
opinions, or we of theirs? We laugh at them - they despise us; and though our travellers 
have turned them into ridicule, they need only to travel among us, to ridicule us in their 
turn. In what country are there not to be found men of sense and sincerity, friends of 
humanity, who require only to know truth, in order to embrace it? And yet every one imagines 
that truth is confined to his own particular system, and thinks that the religion of all 
other nations in the world is absurd. These foreign modes, therefore, cannot be in reality 
so very absurd as they appear, or the apparent reasonableness of ours is less real.</p> 
<p>We have tee principal religions in Europe. One admits only of one revelation, another 
of two, and the third of tee. Each holds the other in detestation, anathematizes its 
possessors, accuses them of ignorance, obstinacy, and falsehood. What impartial person will 
presume to decide between them, without having first examined their proofs and heard their 
reasons? That which admits only of one revelation is the most ancient and seems the least 
disputable; that which admits of tee is the most modern and seems to be the most 
consistent; that which admits of two and rejects the third, may possibly be the best, but it 
hath certainly every prepossession against it - its inconsistency stares one full in the 
face.</p> 
<p>In all these tee revelations, the sacred books are written in languages unknown to the people who believe in them. The Jews no 
longer understand Hebrew; the Cistians neither Greek nor Hebrew; the Turks and Persians 
understand no Arabic, and even the modern Arabs themselves speak not the language of 
Mahomet. Is not this a very simple manner of instructing mankind, by talking to them always 
in a language which they do not comprehend? But these books, it will be said, are 
translated; a most unsatisfactory answer, indeed! Who can assure me that they are translated 
faithfully, or that it is even possible they should be so? Who can give me a sufficient 
reason why God, when he hath a mind to speak to mankind, should stand in need of an 
interpreter?</p> <p>I can never conceive that what every man is indispensably obliged to 
know can be shut up in these books; or that he who is incapacitated to understand them, or 
the persons who explain them, will be punished for involuntary ignorance. But we are always 
plaguing ourselves with books. What a frenzy! Because Europe is full of books, the Europeans 
conceive them to be indispensable, without reflecting that tee-fourths of the world know 
nothing at all about them. Are not all books written by men? How greatly, therefore, must 
man have stood in need of them, to instruct him in his duty, and by what means did he come 
to the knowledge of such duties, before books were written? Either he must have acquired 
such knowledge of himself, or it must have been totally dispensed with.</p> 
<p>We, Roman Catholics, make a great noise about the authority of the church: but what do we gain by it, 
if it requires as many proofs to establish this authority as other sects also require to 
establish their doctrines? The church determines that the church has a right to determine. 
Is not this a special proof of its authority? And yet, depart from this, and we enter into 
endless discussions.</p> 
<p>Do you know many Cistians who have taken the pains to examine carefully into what the Jews have alleged against us? If there are a few who know something 
of them, it is from what they have met with in the writings of Cistians: a very strange 
manner indeed of instructing themselves in the arguments of their opponents! But what can be 
done? If any one should dare to publish among us such books as openly espouse the cause of 
Judaism, we should punish the author, the editor, and the bookseller. 
<ref target="n5">[5]</ref> 
This policy is very convenient, and very sure to make us always in the right. We can refute at 
pleasure those who are afraid to speak.</p> 
<p>Those among us, also, who have an opportunity to converse with the Jews, have but little advantage. These unhappy people know that they 
are at our mercy. The tyranny we exercise over them, renders them justly timid and reserved. 
They know how far cruelty and injustice are compatible with Cistian charity. What, 
therefore, can they venture to say to us, without running the risk of incurring the charge 
of blasphemy? Avarice inspires us with zeal, and they are too rich not to be ever in the 
wrong. The most sensible and learned among them are the most circumspect and reserved. We 
make a convert, perhaps, of some wretched hireling, to calumniate his sect; we set a parcel 
of pitiful brokers disputing, who give up the point merely to gratify us; but while we 
triumph over the ignorance or meanness of such wretched opponents, the learned among them 
smile in contemptuous silence at our folly. But do you think that in places where they might 
write and speak securely, we should have so much the advantage of them? Among the doctors of 
the Sorbonne, it is as clear as daylight, that the predictions concerning the Messiah relate 
to Jesus Cist. Among the Rabbins at Amsterdam, it is just as evident that they have no 
relation whatever to him. I shall never believe that I have acquired a sufficient 
acquaintance with the arguments of the Jews, till they compose a free and independent State, 
and have their schools and universities, where they may talk and dispute with freedom and 
impunity. Till then we can never really know what arguments they have to offer.</p> 
 
<p>At Constantinople, the Turks make known their reasons, and we dare not publish ours. There it is our turn to submit. If the 
Turks require us to pay to Mahomet, in whom we do not believe, the same respect which we 
require the Jews to pay to Jesus Cist, in whom they believe as little, can the Turks be in 
the wrong and we in the right? On what principle of equity can we resolve that question in 
our own favor?</p> 
<p>Two - thirds of mankind are neither, Jews, Cistians, nor Mahometans. How many millions of men, therefore, must there be who never heard of Moses, of Jesus 
Cist, or of Mahomet? Will this be denied? Will it be said that our missionaries are 
dispersed over the face of the whole earth? This, indeed, is easily affirmed; but are there 
any of them in the interior parts of Africa, where no European hath ever yet penetrated? Do 
they travel tough the inland parts of Tartary, or follow on horseback the wandering 
hordes, whom no stranger ever approaches, and who, so far from having heard of the Pope, 
hardly know any thing of their own Grand Lama? Do our missionaries traverse the immense 
continent of America, where there are whole nations still ignorant that the people of 
another world have set foot on theirs? Are there any missionaries in Japan, from whence 
their ill-behavior hath banished them forever, and where the fame of their predecessors is 
transmitted to succeeding generations as that of artful knaves, who, under cover of a 
religious zeal, wanted to make themselves gradually masters of the empire? Do they penetrate 
into the harems of the Asiatic princes, to preach the gospel to millions of wretched slaves? 
What will become of these secluded women for want of a missionary to preach to them this 
gospel? Must every one of them go to hell for being a recluse?</p> 
<p>But were it true that the gospel is preached in every part of the earth, the difficulty is not removed. On the eve 
preceding the arrival of the first missionary in any country, some one person of that 
country expired without hearing the glad tidings. Now what must we do with this one person? 
If there be but a single individual in the whole universe, to whom the gospel of Cist is 
not made known, the objection which presents itself on account of this one person, is as 
cogent as if it included a fourth part of the human race.</p> 
<p>Again, supposing that the ministers of the gospel are actually present and preaching in those distant nations, how can 
they reasonably hope to be believed on their own word, and expect that their hearers will 
not scrupulously require a confirmation of what is taught? Might not any one of them very 
reasonably say to these preachers:</p> 
<p><q>You tell me of a God who was born and put to death nearly two thousand years ago, in another portion of the world, and in I know not what 
obscure town; assuring me that all those who do not believe in this mysterious tale are 
damned.</q></p> 
<p><q>These are things too strange to be readily credited on the sole authority of a man who is himself a perfect stranger.</q></p> 
<p><q>Why hath your God brought those events to pass, of which he requires me to be instructed, at so great a distance? Is 
it a crime to be ignorant of what passes at the antipodes? Is it possible for me to divine 
that there existed in the other hemisphere a people called Jews, and a city called 
Jerusalem? I might as well be required to know what happens in the moon.</q></p> 
<p><q>You are come, you say, to inform me; but why did you not come soon enough to inform my father, 
or why do you damn that innocent man because he knew nothing of the matter? Must he be 
eternally punished for your delay; he who was so just, so benevolent, and so desirous of 
knowing the truth?</q></p> 
<p><q>Be honest, and suppose yourself in my place. Do you think 
that I can believe, upon your testimony alone, all these incredible things you tell me, or 
that I can reconcile so much injustice with the character of that just God, whom you pretend 
to make known?</q></p> 
<p><q>Let me first, I pray you, go and see this distant country where so many miracles have happened that are totally unknown here. Let me go and be well informed 
why the inhabitants of that Jerusalem you speak of presumed to treat God like a thief or a 
murderer.</q></p> 
<p><q>They did not, you will say, acknowledge his divinity. How then can I, who never have heard of him but from you?</q></p> 
<p><q>You add, that they were punished, dispersed, and led into captivity;-not one of them ever approaching their former city.</q></p> 
<p><q>Assuredly, they deserved all this: but its present inhabitants, - what say they of 
the unbelief and <hi rend="italic">Decide</hi> of their predecessors? Do they not deny it, and acknowledge the 
divinity of the sacred personage just as little as did its ancient inhabitants?</q></p> 
<p><q>What! in the same city in which your God was put to death, neither the ancient nor 
present inhabitants acknowledge his divinity! And yet you would have me believe it, who was 
born nearly two thousand years after the event, and two thousand leagues distant from the 
place!</q></p> 
<p><q>Do you not see that, before I can give credit to this book, which you call sacred and of which I comprehend nothing, I ought to be informed from others as to when 
and by whom it was written; how it hath been preserved and transmitted to you; what is said 
of it in the country where it originated; and what are the reasons of those who reject it, 
although they know as well as you every thing of which you have informed me? You must 
perceive, therefore, the necessity I am under of going first to Europe, then to Asia, and 
lastly into Palestine to investigate and examine this subject for myself, and that I must be 
an absolute idiot to even listen to you before I have completed this investigation.</q></p> 
<p>Such a discourse as this appears to me not only very reasonable, but I affirm that every sensible man ought under such circumstances to speak in the same 
manner, and to send a missionary about his business, who should be in haste to instruct and 
baptize him before he had sufficiently verified the proofs of his mission.</p> 
<p>Now, I maintain that there is no revelation against which the same objections might not be made, 
and that with even greater force than against Cistianity. Hence it follows that if there 
be in the world but one true religion, and if every one is obliged to adopt it under pain of 
damnation, it is necessary to spend our lives in the study of all religions, - to visit the 
countries where they have been established, and examine and compare them with each other. No 
man is exempted from the principal duty of his species, and no one hath a right to confide 
in the judgment of another. The artisan who lives only by his industry, the husbandman who 
cannot read, the timid and delicate virgin, the feeble valetudinarian, all must, without 
exception, study, meditate, dispute, and travel the world over in search of truth. There 
would no longer be any settled inhabitants in a country, the face of the earth being covered 
with pilgrims going from place to place, at great trouble and expense, to verify, examine, 
and compare the several different systems and modes of worship to be met with in different 
countries.</p> 
<p>We must in such a case bid adieu to the arts and sciences, to trade, and to all the civil occupations of life. Every other study must give place to that of religion; 
while the man who should enjoy the greatest share of health and strength, and make the best 
use of his time and reason for the longest term of years allotted to human life, would, in 
his extreme old age, be still perplexed and undecided; and it would be indeed wonderful if, 
after all his researches, he should be able to learn before his death what religion he ought 
to have believed and practiced during his life.</p> 
<p>Do you endeavor to mitigate the severity of this method, and place as little confidence as possible in the authority of your 
fellow men? In so doing, however, you place in them the greatest confidence: for if the son 
of a Cistian does right in adopting, without a scrupulous and impartial examination, the 
religion of his father, how can the son of a Turk do wrong in adopting in the same manner 
the religion of Mahomet?</p> 
<p>I defy all the persecutors in the world to answer this question in a manner satisfactory to any person of common sense. Nay, some of them, when 
hard pressed by such arguments, will sooner admit that God is unjust, and visits the sins of 
the fathers upon the children, than give up their cruel and persecuting principles. Others, 
indeed, strive to elude the force of these reasons by civilly sending an angel to instruct 
those who, under absolute ignorance, lived, nevertheless, good moral lives. A very pretty 
device, truly, is that of the angel! Not contented with subjecting us to this angelic 
hierarchy, they would reduce even the Deity himself to the necessity of employing it.</p> 
<p>See, my son, to what absurdities we are led by pride, and the spirit of persecution, - by 
being puffed up with our own vanity, and conceiving that we possess a greater share of 
reason than the rest of mankind.</p> 
<p>I call to witness that God of peace whom I adore, and whom I would make known to you, that my researches have been always sincere; but seeing 
that they were and always must be unsuccessful, and that I was launched out into a boundless 
ocean of perplexity, I returned the way I came, and confined my creed within the limits of 
my first notions. I could never believe that God required me, under pain of eternal 
damnation, to be so very learned; and, therefore, I shut up all my books.</p> 
<p>The book of nature lies open to every eye. It is from this sublime and wonderful volume that I learn to 
serve and adore its Divine Author. No person is excusable for neglecting to read this book, 
as it is written in an universal language, intelligible to all mankind.</p> 
<p>Had I been born on a desert island, or had never seen a human creature beside myself; had I never been 
informed of what had formerly happened in a certain corner of the world; I might yet have 
learned, by the exercise and cultivation of my reason, and by the proper use of those 
faculties God hath given me, to know and to love him. I might hence have learned to love and 
admire his power and goodness, and to have properly discharged my duty here on earth. What 
can the knowledge of the learned teach me more?</p> 
<p>With regard to revelation: could I reason better or were I better informed, I might be made sensible perhaps of its truth and 
of its utility to those who are so happy as to believe it. But if there are some proofs in 
its favor which I cannot invalidate, there appear also to me many objections against it 
which I cannot resolve. There are so many reasons both for and against its authority that, 
not knowing what to conclude, I neither admit nor reject it. I reject only the obligation of 
submitting to it, because this pretended obligation is incompatible with the justice of God, 
and that, so far from its removing the obstacles to salvation, it raises those which are 
insurmountable by the greater part of mankind, Except in this article, therefore, I remain 
respectfully in doubt concerning the Scriptures. I have not the presumption to think myself 
infallible. More able persons may possibly determine in cases that to me appear 
undeterminable. I reason for myself, not for them. I neither censure nor imitate them. Their 
judgment may possibly be better than mine, but am I to blame that it is not mine?</p> 
<p>I will confess to you further, that the majesty of the Scriptures strikes me with admiration, 
as the purity of the gospel hath its influence on my heart. Peruse the works of our 
philosophers, enriched with all their pomp of diction: how mean, how contemptible are they, 
compared with the Scriptures! Is it possible that a book at once so simple and sublime 
should be merely the work of man? Is it possible that the sacred personage, whose history it 
contains, should be himself a mere man? Do we find that he assumed the tone of an enthusiast 
or ambitious sectary? What purity, what sweetness in his manners! What an affecting 
gracefulness in his delivery! What sublimity in his maxims! What profound wisdom in his 
discourses! What presence of mind, what subtilty, what truth in his replies! How great the 
command over his passions! Where is the man, where the philosopher who could so live and so 
die, without weakness and without ostentation? When Plato described an imaginary good 
man 
<ref target="n6">[6]</ref> 
loaded with all the shame of guilt, yet meriting the highest reward of virtue, he describes exactly the character of Jesus. The resemblance was so striking that 
all the fathers perceived it. What prepossession, what blindness must it be to compare the 
son of Soponiscus to the son of Mary? What an infinite disproportion is there between 
them! Socrates, dying without pain or ignominy, easily supported his character to the last; 
and if his death, however easy, had not crowned his life, it might have been doubted whether 
Socrates, with all his wisdom, was any thing more than a vain sophist. He invented, it is 
said, the theory of morals. Others, however, had already put them in practice; he had only 
to say what they had done, and reduce their examples to precepts. Aristides had been just, 
before Socrates defined justice. Leonidas gave up his life for his country before Socrates 
declared patriotism to be a duty. The Spartans were a sober people before Socrates 
recommended sobriety. Before he had even defined virtue, Greece abounded in virtuous men. 
But where could Jesus learn, among his compatriots, that pure and sublime morality of which 
he only hath given us both precept and example? 
<ref target="n7">[7]</ref> 
The greatest wisdom was made 
known amidst the most bigoted fanaticism; and the simplicity of the most heroic virtues did 
honor to the vilest people on the earth. The death of Socrates, peaceably philosophizing 
with his friends, appears the most agreeable form that could be desired; - that of Jesus, 
expiring in the midst of agonizing pains, abused, insulted, cursed by a whole nation, is the 
most horrible that could be feared. Socrates, in receiving the cup of poison, blessed indeed 
the weeping executioner who administered it; but Jesus, in the midst of excruciating 
tortures, prayed for his merciless tormentors. Yes, if the life and death of Socrates are 
those of a sage, the life and death of Jesus are those of a God.</p> 
<p>Shall we suppose the evangelic history a mere fiction? Indeed, my friend, it bears not the marks of fiction. On the contrary, the history 
of Socrates, which nobody presumes to doubt, is not so well attested as that of Jesus 
Cist. Such a supposition, in fact, only shifts the difficulty without removing it. It is 
more inconceivable that a number of persons should agree to write such a history than that 
one only should furnish the subject of it. The Jewish authors were incapable of the diction, 
and were strangers to the morality contained in the gospel, - the marks of whose truth are 
so striking and inimitable, that the inventor would be a more astonishing character than the 
hero. And yet, with all this, the same gospel abounds with incredible relations, with 
circumstances repugnant to reason, and which it is impossible for a man of sense either to 
conceive of or to admit. What is to be done amidst all these contradictions? Be modest and 
circumspect. Regard in silence what cannot be either disproved or comprehend, and humble 
thyself before the Supreme Being who alone knoweth the truth.</p> 
<p>Such is the involuntary skepticism in which I remain. This skepticism, however, is not painful to me, because it 
extends not to any essential point of practice; and as my mind is firmly settled regarding 
the principles of my duty, I serve God in the sincerity of my heart. In the mean time, I 
seek not to know any thing more than what relates to my moral conduct; and as to those 
dogmas which have no influence over the behavior, and about which so many persons give 
themselves so much trouble, I am not at all solicitous. I look upon the various particular 
religions as so many salutary institutions, prescribing in different countries an uniform 
manner of public worship; and which may all have their respective reasons, peculiar to the 
climate, government, or laws of the people adopting them, or some other motive which renders 
the one preferable to the other according to the circumstance of time and place. I believe 
all that are established to be good when God is served in sincerity of heart. This service 
is all that is essential. He rejects not the homage of the sincere, under whatsoever form 
they present it. Being called to the service of the church, I comply, therefore with a 
scrupulous exactness, to all the forms it prescribes in my duty, and should reproach myself 
for the least wilful neglect of them. After having lain under a long prohibition I obtained, 
tough the interest of M. de Mellerade, a permission to re-assume the functions of the 
priesthood, to procure me a livelihood. I had been accustomed formerly to say mass with all 
that levity and carelessness with which we perform the most serious and important offices 
after having very often repeated them. Since I entertained my new principles, however, I 
celebrate it with greater veneration: - penetrated by reflecting on the majesty of the 
Supreme Being, and the insufficiency of the human mind that is so little able to form 
conceptions relative to its author, I consider that I offer up the prayers of a people under 
a prescribed form of worship, and therefore carefully observe all its rites. I recite 
carefully; and strive not to omit the least word or ceremony. Before going to communicate, I 
first recollect myself, in order to do it with all those dispositions that the church and 
the importance of the sacrament require. I endeavor on this occasion to silence the voice of 
reason before the Supreme Intelligence. I say to myself: who art thou, to presume to set 
bounds to omnipotence? I reverently pronounce the sacramental words, and annex to them all 
the faith that depends on me. Whatever, therefore, be the truth with regard to that 
inconceivable mystery, I am not fearful of being charged at the day of judgment with 
profaning it in my heart.</p> 
<p>Honored with the ministerial office, though of the lowest rank, I will never do or say 
any thing that may make me unworthy to fulfill its sacred functions. I will always inculcate 
virtue, exhort my auditors to pursue it, and as far as it is in my power, set them an 
example. It does not depend on me to make their religion amiable, nor to confine the 
articles of their faith to what is necessary for all to believe: but God forbid that I 
should ever preach up the cruel tenets of persecution, - that I should even induce them to 
hate their neighbors, or to consign others to damnation. 
<ref target="n8">[8]</ref> 
Were I, indeed, in a superior station, this reserve might incur censure; but I am too insignificant to have much 
to fear, and I can never fall lower than I am. But whatever may happen, I shall never 
blaspheme Divine Justice, nor lie against the Spirit of Truth.</p> 
<p>I have long been ambitious of the honor of being a pastor. I am indeed still ambitious, though I have no 
longer any hopes of it. There is no character in the world, my good friend, which appears to 
me so desirable as that of a pastor. A good pastor is a minister of goodness, as a good 
magistrate is a minister of justice. A pastor can have no temptation to evil; and though he 
may not always have it in his power to do good himself, he is really doing his duty when 
soliciting it of others, and very often obtains it when he learns to make himself truly 
worthy of respect.</p> 
<p>O that I enjoyed but some little benefice among the poor people in our mountains! How happy should I then feel! for I cannot but think that I should make my 
parishioners happy! I should never, indeed, make them rich, but I should cheerfully partake 
of their poverty. I would raise them above meanness and contempt, - more insupportable than 
indigence itself. I would induce them to love concord, and to cherish that equality which 
often banishes poverty, and always renders it more supportable. When they should see that I 
was no richer than themselves, and yet lived content, they would learn to console themselves 
under their lot, and to live contented also.</p> 
<p>In the instructions I should give them, I should be less directed by the sense of the church than by that of the gospel; whose 
tenets are more simple, and whose morals are more sublime; - that teaches few religious 
forms and many deeds of charity.</p> 
<p>Before I should teach them their duty, I should always endeavor to practice it myself, in order to let them see that I really thought as I 
spoke.</p> 
<p>Had I any Protestants in my neighborhood, or in my parish I would make no distinction between them and my own flock, in every thing that regarded acts of Cistian 
charity. I would endeavor to make them all love and regard each other as breten-tolerating 
all religions, and peacefully enjoying their own.</p> 
<p>Thus, my young friend, have I given you with my own lips a recital of my creed, such as the Supreme Being reads it in my heart. 
You are the first person to whom I have made this <hi rend="italic">Profession of Faith;</hi> and you are the only 
one, probably, to whom I shall ever make it.</p> 
<p>If I were more positive in myself, I should have assumed a more positive and dogmatic air; but I am a man ignorant and subject to 
error. I have opened to you my heart without reserve. What I have thought certain, I have 
given you as such. My doubts I have declared as doubts; my opinions as opinions; and I have 
honestly given you my reasons for both. What can I do more? It remains now for you to judge. 
Be sincere with yourself. Whether men love or hate, admire or despise you, is of but little 
moment. Speak only what is true, do only what is right; for, after all, the object of 
greatest importance is to faithfully discharge our duty. Adopt only those of my sentiments 
which you believe are true, and reject all the others; and whatever religion you may 
ultimately embrace, remember that its real duties are independent of human institutions - 
that no religion upon earth can dispense with the sacred obligations of morality - that an 
upright heart is the temple of the Divinity - and that, in every country and in every sect, 
to love God above all things, and thy neighbor as thyself, is the substance and summary of 
the law - the end and aim of religious duty.</p> 
 
 
<div2 type="notes" id="d8"> 
<head>Footnotes</head> 
 
<note id="n1"><seg type="note-symbol">[1]</seg><p>M. de la Condamine tells of a people who knew how to reckon only as far as tee. Yet these people must often have seen their fingers without ever 
having counted five.</p></note> 
<note id="n2"><seg type="note-symbol">[2]</seg> <p>Modern philosophy, which affects to admit of nothing but what it can explain, hath nevertheless very unadvisedly admitted of that 
obscure faculty, called instinct, which appears to direct animals to the purposes of their 
being, without any acquisition of knowledge. Instinct, according to one of our greatest 
philosophers, is a habit destitute of reflection, but acquired by reflecting. Thus from the 
manner in which he explains its progress, we are led to conclude that children reflect more 
than grown persons; a paradox singular enough to require some examination. Without entering, 
however, into the discussion of it at present, I would only ask what name I am to give to 
that eagerness which my dog shows to pursue a mole, for instance, which he does not eat when 
he has caught it;-to that patience with which he stands watching for them whole hours, and 
to that expertness with which he makes them a prey the moment they reach the surface of the 
earth; and that in order only to kill them, without ever having been trained to mole 
hunting, or having been taught that moles were beneath the spot? I would ask further, as 
more important, why the first time I teaten the same dog, he tows himself down with is 
back to the ground and his feet raised in a suppliant attitude, the most proper of all 
others to excite my compassion; an attitude in which he would not long remain if I were so 
obdurate as to beat him lying in such a posture? It is possible that a young puppy can have 
already acquired moral ideas? Can he have any notion of clemency and generosity? What 
experience can encourage him to hope he shall appease me, by giving himself up to my mercy? 
Almost all dogs do nearly the same thing in the same circumstances, nor do I advance any 
thing here of which every one may not convince himself. Let the philosophers, who reject so 
disdainfully the term instinct, explain this fact merely by the operation of our senses, and 
the knowledge thereby acquired; let them explain it, I say, in a manner satisfactory to any 
person of common sense, and I have no more to say in favor of instinct.</p></note> 
<note id="n3"><seg type="note-symbol">[3]</seg> <p>All of them, says a certain wise and good priest, pretend that they derive their 
doctrines not from men, nor from any created being, but from God.  But to say truth, without flattery 
or disguise, there is nothing in such pretentions: however they may talk, they owe their religion 
to human means.  Witness the manner in which they first adopt it.  The nation, country and place 
where they are born and bred determine it.  Are we not circumcised or baptized,---made Jews, Turks, 
or Christians before we are men?  Our religion is not the effect of choice; witness our lives and 
manners so little accordant to it; witness how we act contrary to the tenets of it on the most 
trifling occasions.---<hi rend="italic">Charron, on Wisdom.</hi></p></note> 
<note id="n4"><seg type="note-symbol">[4]</seg> <p>This is expressly mentioned in many places in Scripture, particularly in Deuteronomy, chap. 
xiii., where it is said that, if a prophet, teaching the worship of strange Gods, confirm 
his discourse by signs and wonders, and what he foretells really comes to pass, so far from 
paying any regard to his mission, the people should stone him to death. When the Pagans, 
therefore, put the Apostles to death, for preaching up to them the worship of a strange God, 
proving their divine mission by prophesies and miracles, I see not what could be objected to 
them, which they might not with equal justice have retorted upon us. Now, what is to be done 
in this case? There is but one step to be taken, to recur to reason and leave miracles to 
themselves: better indeed had it been never to have had recourse to them, nor to have 
perplexed good sense with such a number of subtle distinctions. What! do I talk of subtle 
distinctions in Christianity? If there are such, our Saviour was in the wrong surely to 
promise the Kingdom of Heaven to the weak and simple! How came he to begin his fine 
discourse on the Mount, with blessing the poor in spirit, if it requires so much ingenuity 
to comprehend and believe his doctrines? When you prove that I ought to subject my reason to 
his dictates, it is very well; but to prove that, you must render them intelligible to my 
understanding; you must adapt your arguments to the poverty of my genius, or I shall not 
acknowledge you to be true disciple of your Master, or think that it is his doctrines which 
you would inculcate.</p></note> 
<note id="n5"><seg type="note-symbol">[5]</seg> <p>Among a thousand known instances, the following stands in no 
need of comment: the Catholic divines of the sixteenth century having condemned all the 
Jewish books without exception to be burnt, a learned and illustrious theologue, who was 
consulted on that occasion, had very nearly involved himself in ruin by being simply of the 
opinion that such of them might be preserved as did not relate to Cistianity, or treated 
of matters foreign to religion.</p></note> 
<note id="n6"><seg type="note-symbol">[6]</seg> <p>De Rep. dial. 1.</p></note> 
<note id="n7"><seg type="note-symbol">[7]</seg> <p>See in his discourse on the Mount the parallel he makes between the morality of Moses and his own. 
Matthew v. 21, &amp;c.</p></note> 
<note id="n8"><seg type="note-symbol">[8]</seg> <p>The duty of adopting and respecting the religion of our country does not extend to such tenets as are contrary to 
moral virtue; such as that of persecution. It is this horrible dogma which arms mankind 
inhumanly against each other, and renders them destructive to the human race. The 
distinction between political and theological toleration is puerile and ridiculous, as they 
are inseparable, so that one cannot be admitted without the other.</p></note> 
</div2> 
</div1> 
</body> 
</text> 
</TEI.2> 
 
 
