<?xml version="1.0"?>

<?dlps id="RunNegr"?>
<?dlps page-images="none" figure-images="no"?>
<?dlps transcription="other"?>

<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/tei-p4/tei2.dtd" [
<!ENTITY % POSTKB "INCLUDE">
<!ENTITY % TEI.extensions.ent SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.ent">
<!ENTITY % TEI.extensions.dtd SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.dtd">
<!ENTITY % ISOnum SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/charent/iso-num.ent"> %ISOnum;
<!ENTITY % ISOpub SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/charent/iso-pub.ent"> %ISOpub;

]>

<TEI.2 id="RunNegr"> 
<teiHeader type="migrated" creator="Etext">
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title type="main">The Negro Exodus</title>
<title type="sort">negro exodus</title>
<author>Runnion, James B.</author>
<respStmt>
<resp>Creation of machine-readable version</resp>
<name>Judy Boss</name>
</respStmt>
<respStmt>
<resp>Conversion to TEI-conformant markup</resp>
<name>University of Virginia Library Electronic Text Center</name>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt> 
<extent>ca. <num type="kilobytes">36</num> kilobytes</extent> 
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>University of Virginia Library</publisher>
<pubPlace>Charlottesville, Virginia</pubPlace> 
<idno type="ETC">RunNegr</idno> 
<date value="1995">1995</date>
<availability status="public">
<p n="copyright">Copyright &copy; 1995 by the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia</p>
<p n="access">Publicly accessible</p>
</availability>
<idno type="uva-pid">uva-lib:476354</idno>
</publicationStmt>
<seriesStmt>
<title>University of Virginia Library, Text collection</title>
<idno type="uva-set">UVA-LIB-Text</idno>
</seriesStmt> 
<sourceDesc>
<biblFull>
<titleStmt>
<title type="main">The Negro Exodus</title>
<title type="sort">negro exodus</title>
<author>James B. Runnion</author>
</titleStmt> 
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>Atlantic Monthly</publisher> 
<pubPlace>New York</pubPlace> 
<date value="1879">1879</date>
</publicationStmt> 
<seriesStmt>
<p>Volume 44</p>
</seriesStmt> 
<notesStmt>
<note>
<p>pp. 222-230</p>
</note>
</notesStmt>
</biblFull>
</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc> 
<encodingDesc>
<projectDesc>
<p>Prepared for the University of Virginia Library Electronic Text Center</p>
</projectDesc> 
<editorialDecl>
<p>All quotation marks retained as data</p> 
<p>All unambiguous end-of-line hyphens have been removed, and the 
trailing part of a word has been joined to the preceding line.</p> 
<p id="ETC">Keywords in the header are a local Electronic Text Center scheme  
to aid in establishing analytical groupings</p>
</editorialDecl> 
<refsDecl>
<p>ID elements are given for each page element and are composed of the text's 
unique cryptogram and the given page number, as in SpeFQue1 for page one of  
Spenser's Faerie Queene.</p>
</refsDecl>
</encodingDesc> 
<profileDesc>
<creation>
<date value="1879">1879</date>
</creation> 
<langUsage>
<language id="eng" usage="main">English</language>
</langUsage> 
<textClass>
<keywords>
<term>nonfiction; prose</term> 
<term>African American</term>
</keywords>
</textClass>
</profileDesc> 
<revisionDesc>
<change>
<date value="1994-08">August 1994</date> 
<respStmt>
<resp>corrector</resp>
<name>Kelly Tetterton</name>
</respStmt>
<item>minimal TEI tagging</item>
</change> 
<change>
<date value="2005-07">July 2005</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>Corrector</resp>
<name>John Ivor Carlson</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Converted SGML to XML and/or corrected tagging.</item>
</change>
<change>
<date value="2007-09">September 2007</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>Migration</resp>
<name>Ethan Gruber, University of Virginia Library</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Converted XML markup from TEI Lite to uva-dl-tei (TEI P4 with local customizations).</item>
</change>
<change>
<date value="2008-01">January 2008</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>Migration</resp>
<name>Greg Murray, University of Virginia Library</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Programmatically updated TEI header markup (but not header content) for minimal compliance with current QA requirements.</item>
</change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader> 

<text id="d1">  
<body id="d2"> 
<div1 type="article" id="d3"><pb n="222"/>  
<head>Runnion, James B. "The Negro Exodus."  <hi rend="italic">Atlantic Monthly</hi> 44 
(1879): 222-230.</head>
 
<p>A RECENT sojourn in the South for a few weeks, chiefly in Louisiana 
and Mississippi, gave the writer an opportunity to inquire into 
what has been so aptly called "the negro exodus."  The emigration 
of blacks to Kansas began early in the spring of this year.  For a 
time there was a stampede from two or three of the river parishes 
in Louisiana and as many counties opposite in Mississippi. 
<pb n="223"/>  
Several thousand negroes (certainly not fewer than five thousand, 
and variously estimated as high as ten thousand) had left their 
cabins before the rush could be stayed or the excitement lulled.  
Early in May most of the negroes who had quit work for the purpose 
of emigrating, but had not succeeded in getting off, were persuaded 
to return to the plantations, and from that time on there have been 
only straggling families and groups that have watched for and 
seized the first opportunity for transportation to the North.  
There is no doubt, however, that there is still a consuming desire 
among the negroes of the cotton districts in these two States to 
seek new homes, and there are the best reasons for believing that 
the exodus will take a new start next spring, after the gathering 
and conversion of the growing crop.  Hundreds of negroes who 
returned from the river-banks for lack of transportation, and 
thousands of others infected with the ruling discontent, are 
working harder in the fields this summer, and practicing more 
economy and self-denial than ever before, in order to have the 
means next winter and spring to pay their way to the "promised 
land." 
</p><p>"We've been working for fourteen long years," said an 
intelligent negro, in reply to a question as to the cause of the 
prevailing discontent, "and we ain't no better off than we was when 
we commenced."  This is the negro version of the trouble, which is 
elaborated on occasion into a harrowing story of oppression and 
plunder. 
</p><p>"I tell you it's all owing to the radical politicians at the 
North," explained a representative of the type known as the 
Bourbons; "they've had their emissaries down here, and deluded the 
'niggers' into a very fever of emigration, with the purpose of 
reducing our basis of representation in Congress and increasing 
that of the Northern States." 
</p><p>These are the two extremes of opinion at the South.  The first 
is certainly the more reasonable and truthful, though it implies 
that all the blame rests upon the whites, which is not the case; 
the second, preposterous as it will appear to Northern readers, is 
religiously believed by large numbers of the "unreconciled."  
Between these two extremes there is an infinite variety of 
theories, all more or less governed by the political faction to 
which the various theorizers belong; there are at least a dozen of 
these factions, such as the Bourbons, the conservatives, the native 
white republicans, the carpet-bag republicans, the negro 
republicans, etc.  There is a political tinge in almost everything 
in the extreme Southern States.  The fact seems to be that the 
emigration movement among the blacks was spontaneous to the extent 
that they were ready and anxious to go.  The immediate notion of 
going may have been inculcated by such circulars, issued by 
railroads and land companies, as are common enough at emigrant 
centres in the North and West, and the exaggeration characteristic 
of such literature may have stimulated the imagination of the 
negroes far beyond anything they are likely to realize in their new 
homes.  Kansas was naturally the favorite goal of the negro <hi rend="italic"> 
emigre</hi>, for it was associated in his mind with the names of Jim 
Lane and John Brown, which are hallowed to him.  The timid learned 
that they could escape what they have come to regard as a second 
bondage, and they flocked together to gain the moral support which 
comes from numbers. 
</p><p>Diligent inquiry among representative men, of all classes and 
from all parts of Louisiana, who were in attendance at the 
constitutional convention in New Orleans, and careful observation 
along the river among the land owners and field hands in both 
Louisiana and Mississippi, left a vivid impression of some material 
and political conditions which fully account for the negro exodus.  
I have dropped the social conditions out of the consideration, 
because I became convinced that the race troubles at the South can 
be solved to the satisfaction of both whites and blacks without 
cultivating any closer social relations than those which now 
prevail.  The material conditions which I have in mind are less 
familiar than the political conditions; they are mainly the land-tenure and credit systems, 
<pb n="224"/>  
and mere modifications (scarcely 
for the better) of the peculiar plantation system of slavery days. 
</p><p>The cotton lands at the South are owned now, as they were 
before the war, in large tracts.  The land was about all that most 
of the Southern whites had left to them after the war, and they 
kept it when they could, at the first, in the hope that it would 
yield them a living through the labor of the blacks; of late years 
they have not been able to sell their plantations at any fair 
price, if they desired to do so.  The white men with capital who 
went to the South from the North after the war seemed to acquire 
the true Southern ambition to be large land owners and planters; 
and when the ante-bellum owners lost their plantations the land 
usually went in bulk to the city factors who had made them advances 
from year to year, and had taken mortgages on their crops and broad 
acres.  As a consequence, the land has never been distributed among 
the people who inhabit and cultivate it, and agricultural labor in 
the Southern States approaches the condition of the factory labor 
in England and the Eastern States more nearly than it does the farm 
labor of the North and West.  Nearly every agricultural laborer 
north of Mason and Dixon's line, if not the actual possessor of the 
land he plows, looks forward to owning a farm some time; at the 
South such an ambition is rare, and small ownership still more an 
exception.  The practice of paying day wages was first tried after 
the war; this practice is still in vogue in the sugar and rice 
districts, where laborers are paid from fifty to seventy cents per 
day, with quarters furnished and living guaranteed them at nine or 
ten cents a day.  In sections where the wages system prevails, and 
where there have been no political disturbances, the negroes seem 
to be perfectly contented; at all events, the emigration fever has 
not spread among them.  But it was found impracticable to maintain 
the wage system in the cotton districts.  The negroes themselves 
fought against it, because it reminded them too much of the slave-gang, driven out at daybreak and home at sundown.  In many cases 
the planters were forced to abandon it, because they had not the 
means to carry on such huge farming, and they could not secure the 
same liberal advances from capitalists as when they were able to 
mortgage a growing "crop of niggers."  Then the system of working 
on shares was tried.  This was reasonably fair, and the negro 
laborers were satisfied as long as it lasted.  The owners of the 
land, under this system, would furnish the indispensable mule and 
the farming implements, and take one half the product.  The 
planters themselves relinquished this system.  Some of them contend 
that the laziness and indifference of the negro made the 
partnership undesirable; many others admit that they were not able 
to advance the negro tenant his supplies pending the growth of the 
year's crop, as it was necessary they should do under the sharing 
system.  Now the renting system is almost universal.  It yields the 
land owner a certainty, endangered only by the death, sickness, or 
desertion of the negro tenant; but it throws the latter upon his 
own responsibility, and frequently makes him the victim of his own 
ignorance and the rapacity of the white man.  The rent of land, on 
a money basis, varies from six to ten dollars an acre per year, 
while the same land can be bought in large quantities all the way 
from fifteen to thirty dollars per acre, according to location, 
clearing, improvement, richness, etc.  When paid in product, the 
rent varies from eighty to one hundred pounds of lint cotton per 
acre for land that produces from two hundred to four hundred pounds 
of cotton per acre; the tenant undertakes to pay from one quarter 
to one half &mdash; perhaps an average of one third &mdash; of his crop for the 
use of the land, without stock, tools, or assistance of any kind.  
The land owners usually claim that they make no money even at these 
exorbitant figures.  If they do not, it is because only a portion 
of their vast possessions is under cultivation, because they do no 
work themselves, and in some cases because the negroes do not 
cultivate and gather as large a crop as they could and ought to 
harvest.  It is very certain that the negro tenants, as a class, 
make no money; if they are out of debt at the end of a season, they 
have reason to rejoice. 
</p><p>The credit system, which is as universal as the renting 
system, is even more illogical and oppressive.  The utter 
viciousness of both systems in their mutual dependence is 
sufficiently illustrated by the single fact that, after fourteen 
years of freedom and labor on their own account, the great mass of 
the negroes depend for their living on an advance of supplies (as 
they need food, clothing, or tools during the year) upon the pledge 
of their growing crop.  This is a generic imitation of the white 
man's improvidence during the slavery times; then the planters 
mortgaged their crops and negroes, and where one used the advances 
to extend his plantation, ten squandered the money.  The negro's 
necessities have developed an offensive race, called merchants by 
courtesy, who keep supply stores at the cross-roads and steamboat 
landings, and live upon extortion.  These people would be called 
sharks, harpies, and vampires in any Northwestern agricultural 
community, and they would not survive more than one season.  The 
country merchant advances the negro tenant such supplies as the 
negro wants up to a certain amount, previously fixed by contract, 
and charges the negro at least double the value of every article 
sold to him.  There is no concealment about the extortion; every 
store-keeper has his cash price and his credit price, and in nearly 
all cases the latter is one hundred per cent. higher than the 
former.  The extortion is justified by those who practice it on the 
ground that their losses by bad debts, though their advances are 
always secured by mortgage on the growing crop, overbalance the 
profits; this assertion is scarcely borne out by the comparative 
opulence of the "merchant" and the pitiful poverty of the laborer.  
Some of the largest and wealthiest planters have sought to protect 
their tenants from the merciless clutches of the contrary merchant, 
who is more frequently than not an Israelite, by advancing supplies 
of necessary articles at reasonable prices.  But the necessities of 
the planter, if not his greed, often betray him into plundering the 
negro.  The planter himself is generally a victim to usury.  He 
still draws on the city factor to the extent of ten dollars a bale 
upon his estimated crop.  He pays this factor two and one half per 
cent. commission for the advance, eight per cent. interest for the 
money, two and one half per cent. more for disposing of the crop 
when consigned to him, and sometimes still another commission for 
the purchase of the supplies.  The planter who furnishes his 
tenants with supplies on credit is usually paying an interest of 
fifteen to eighteen per cent. himself, and necessarily takes some 
risk in advancing upon an uncertain crop and to a laborer whom he 
believes to be neither scrupulous nor industrious; these conditions 
necessitate more than the ordinary profit, and in many cases 
suggest exorbitant and unreasonable charges.  But whether the negro 
deals with the merchant or the land owner, his extravagance almost 
invariably exhausts his credit, even if it be large.  The negro is 
a sensuous creature, and luxurious in his way.  The male is an 
enormous consumer of tobacco and whisky; the female has an 
inordinate love for flummery; both are fond of sardines, potted 
meats, and canned goods generally, and they indulge themselves 
without any other restraint than the refusal of their merchant to 
sell to them.  The man who advances supplies watches his negro 
customers constantly; if they are working well and their crop 
promises to be large, he will permit and even encourage them to 
draw upon him liberally; it is only a partial failure of the crop, 
or some intimation of the negro's intention to shirk his 
obligations, that induces his country factor to preach the virtue 
of self-restraint, or moralize upon the advantages of economy. 
</p><p>The land owner's rent and the merchant's advances are both 
secured by a chattel mortgage on the tenant's personal property, 
and by a pledge of the growing crop.  The hired laborer (for it is 
common for negroes to work for 
<pb n="226"/>  
wages for other negroes who 
rent lands) has also a lien upon the growing crops second only to 
the land owner's; but as the law requires that the liens shall be 
recorded, which the ignorant laborer usually neglects and the 
shrewd merchant never fails to do, the former is generally cheated 
of his security.  Among those who usually work for hire are the 
women, who are expert cotton pickers, and the loss of wages which 
so many of them have suffered by reason of the prior lien gained by 
landlord and merchant has helped to make them earnest and effective 
advocates of emigration.  The Western farmer considers it hard 
enough to struggle under one mortgage at a reasonable interest; the 
negro tenant begins his season with three mortgages, covering all 
he owns, his labor for the coming year, and all he expects to 
acquire during that period.  He pays one third his product for the 
use of the land; he pays double the value of all he consumes; he 
pays an exorbitant fee for recording the contract by which he 
pledges his pound of flesh; he is charged two or three times as 
much as he ought to pay for ginning his cotton; and, finally, he 
turns over his crop to be eaten up in commissions, if anything 
still be left to him.  It is easy to understand why the negro 
rarely gets ahead in the world.  This mortgaging of future 
services, which is practically what a pledge of the growing crop 
amounts to, is in the nature of bondage.  It has a tendency to make 
the negro extravagant, reckless, and unscrupulous; he has become 
convinced from previous experience that nothing will be coming to 
him on the day of settlement, and he is frequently actuated by the 
purpose of getting as much as possible and working as little as 
possible.  Cases are numerous in which the negro abandons his own 
crop at picking time, because he knows that he has already eaten up 
its full value; and so he goes to picking for wages on some other 
plantation.  In other cases, where negroes have acquired mules and 
farming implements upon which a merchant has secured a mortgage in 
the manner described, they are practically bound to that merchant 
from year to year, in order to retain their property; if he removes 
from one section to another, they must follow him, and rent and 
cultivate lands in his neighborhood.  It is only the ignorance, the 
improvidence, and the happy disposition of the negro, under the 
influence of the lazy, drowsy climate, to which he is so well 
adapted physically, that have enabled him to endure these hardships 
so long.  And, though the negro is the loser, the white man is not 
often the gainer, from this false plantation and mercantile system.  
The incidental risk may not be so large as the planter and merchant 
pretend, but the condition of the people is an evidence that the 
extortion they practice yields no better profit in the long run 
than would be gained by competition in fair prices on a cash 
system; and in leading up to a general emigration of the laboring 
population the abuses described will eventually ruin and impoverish 
those who have heretofore been the only beneficiaries thereof.  The 
decay of improvements inevitable under annual rentings, the lack of 
sufficient labor to cultivate all the good land, and the universal 
idleness of the rural whites have kept the land owners 
comparatively poor; the partial failure of crops and the 
unscrupulousness of the negro debtor, engendered by the infamous 
exactions of his creditor, have prevented the merchants, as a 
class, from prospering as much as might be supposed; and, finally, 
the uniform injustice to the laborers induces them to fly to ills 
they know not of, rather than bear those they have.  It is a 
blessing to the negro that the laws do not yet provide for a 
detention of the person in the case of debt, or escape would be 
shut off entirely; as it is, various influences and circumstances 
appertaining to the system in vogue have been used to prevent the 
easy flight of those who desire to go, and have detained thousands 
of blacks for a time who are fretting to quit the country. 
</p><p>Political oppression has contributed largely to the discontent 
which is the prime cause of the exodus.  "Bulldozing" 
<pb n="227"/>  
is 
the term by which all forms of this oppression are known.  The 
native whites are generally indisposed to confess that the negroes 
are quitting the country on account of political injustice and 
persecution; even those who freely admit and fitly characterize the 
abuses already described seek to deny, or at least belittle, the 
political abuses.  The fact that a large number of negroes have 
emigrated from Madison Parish, Louisiana, where there has never 
been any bulldozing, and where the negroes are in full and 
undisputed political control, is cited as proof that political 
disturbances cut no figure in the case.  But the town of Delta, in 
Madison Parish, is at once on the river and the terminus of a 
railroad that runs back through the interior of the State; thus 
Madison Parish would furnish the natural exit for the fugitives 
from the adjoining counties, where there have been political 
disturbances.  It would be just as reasonable to contend that the 
plundering of the negroes has had no influence in driving them 
away, since many of those who have emigrated were among the most 
prosperous of the blacks, as to deny the agency of political 
persecution.  Families that had been able to accumulate a certain 
amount of personal property, in spite of the extortionate 
practices, sold their mules, their implements, their cows, their 
pigs, their sheep, and their household goods for anything they 
would bring, &mdash; frequently as low as one sixth of their value, &mdash; in 
order that they might improve an immediate opportunity to go away; 
it is evident that there must have been some cause outside of 
extortion in their case.  There are candid native whites who do not 
deny, but justify, the violent methods which have been employed to 
disfranchise the negroes, or compel them to vote under white 
dictation, in many parts of Louisiana and Mississippi, on the 
ground that the men who pay the taxes should vote them and control 
the disbursement of the public moneys.  The gentlemen who advance 
this argument seem to ignore the fact that the very Northerner whom 
they are seeking to convert to "the Mississippi plan" may himself 
be a taxpayer in some Northern city, where public affairs are 
controlled by a class of voters in every way as ignorant and 
irresponsible as the blacks, but where bulldozing has never yet 
been suggested as a remedy.  For the rest, the evidences of 
political oppression are abundant and convincing.  The bulldozers 
as a class are more impecunious and irresponsible than the negroes, 
and, unlike the negroes, they will not work.  There has been more 
of the "night-riding," the whippings, the mysterious 
disappearances, the hangings, and the terrorism comprehended in the 
term bulldozing than has been reported by those "abstracts and 
brief chronicles of the time," the Southern newspapers, which are 
now all of one party, and defer to the ruling sentiment among the 
whites.  The exodus has wrung from two or three of the more candid 
and independent journals, however, a virtual confession of the 
fiendish practices of bulldozing in their insistance that these 
practices must be abandoned.  The non-resident land owners and the 
resident planters, the city factors and the country merchants of 
means and respectability, have taken no personal part in the 
terrorizing of the negro, but they have tolerated it, and sometimes 
encouraged it, in order to gratify their preference for "white 
government."  The negroes have suffered the more because they have 
not resisted and defended themselves; now they have begun to 
convince those who have persecuted them that, if they will not 
strike back, they can and will run away.  No one who is at all 
familiar with the freedman can doubt that the abridgment of his 
political rights has been one of the main causes of the exodus.  
Voting is widely regarded at the North as a disagreeable duty, but 
the negro looks upon it as the highest privilege in life; to be 
frightened out of the exercise of this privilege, or compelled to 
exercise it in conflict with his convictions and preferences, is to 
suffer from a cruel injustice, which the negro will now try to 
escape, since he has learned that escape is possible.  The women, 
though free from personal assaults, suffer from the terrorism 
<pb n="228"/>  
that prevails in certain districts as much as the men.  "We 
might as well starve or freeze to death in Kansas," they say, "as 
to be shot-gunned here."  If they talk to you in confidence, they 
declare that the ruling purpose is to escape from the "slaughter-pens" of the South.  Political persecution, and not the extortion 
they suffer, is the refrain of all the speakers at negro meetings 
that are held in encouragement and aid of the emigration.  It is 
idle to deny that the varied injustice which the negroes have 
suffered as voters is accountable for a large part of their 
universal yearning for new homes, and it will be folly for the 
responsible classes at the South to ignore this fact. 
</p><p>As it is the negroes who are fleeing from the South, it is 
natural to look among the dominant class for the injustice which is 
driving them away; but it would be unfair to conclude that the 
blame rests entirely upon the whites, and still more so to leave 
the impression that there is no extenuation for the mistakes and 
abuses for which the whites are responsible.  Much of the 
intimidation of the blacks has been tolerated, if not suggested, by 
a fear of negro uprisings.  The apprehension is a legacy from the 
days of slavery, and is more unreasonable now than it was then; but 
still it exists.  This is not an excuse, but an explanation.  The 
Pharaohs of the time of Moses were in constant dread lest the 
Hebrews under their rule should go over to their enemies, and their 
dread doubtless increased the cruelty of the Egyptians; but, while 
this dread was an extenuation in the eyes of the persecutors, it 
did not prevent the Hebrews from fleeing the persecution.  So the 
blacks are going without regard to the justification which the 
whites may set up for their treatment; the only difference between 
the old and new exodus is that, as the writer heard one negro 
speaker express it, "every black man is his own Moses in this 
exodus."  The negro may be lazy; it seems impossible to be 
otherwise in the Southern climate.  He may not be willing to work 
on Saturdays, no matter how urgent the necessity; the indulgence in 
holidays is said to be one of the chief drawbacks to the 
advancement of the emancipated serfs of Russia.  The blacks are 
certainly extravagant in their way, though the word seems to be 
almost misused in connection with a race who live largely on pork 
and molasses, and rarely wear more than half a dollar's worth of 
clothes at one time.  They have not the instinct of home as it 
prevails among the whites, but incline to a crude and unsystematic 
communism; the negro quarters of the old plantations are all 
huddled together in the centre, and, except where the land owners 
have interfered to encourage a different life, there is still too 
much promiscuousness in the relation of the sexes.  The negro, as 
a rule, has no ambition to become a land owner; he prefers to 
invest his surplus money, when he has any, in personal and movable 
property.  In most cases where the blacks have been given the 
opportunity of buying land on long time, and paying yearly 
installments out of the proceeds of their annual crops, they have 
tired of the bargain after a year or two, and abandoned the 
contract.  The negro politicians and preachers are not all that 
reformers and moralists would have them; the imitative faculty of 
the African has betrayed the black politician into many of the 
vicious ways of the white politician, and the colored preacher is 
frequently not above "the pomps and vanity of this wicked world."  
All this is the more unfortunate, as the blacks have a child-like 
confidence in their chosen leaders, founded partly on their 
primitive character, and partly on their distrust of the native 
whites.  Both their politicians and their preachers have given 
abundant evidence of their insincerity during the excitement of 
emigration by blowing hot and blowing cold; by talking to the 
negroes one way, and to the whites another; and even to the extent, 
in some instances, of taking money to use their influence for 
discouraging and impeding emigration.  These are some of the faults 
and misfortunes on the part of the blacks which enter into the race 
troubles.  The chief blame which attaches to the whites is the 
failure to make a persistent effort, 
<pb n="229"/>  
by education and kind 
treatment, to overcome the distrust and cure the faults of the 
negroes.  The whites control, because they constitute the "property 
and intelligence" of the South, to use the words of a democratic 
statesman; this power should have been used to gain the confidence 
of the blacks.  Had such a course been taken, there would not have 
been the fear of reenslavement, which actually prevails to a 
considerable extent among the negroes.  So long as a portion of the 
whites entertain the conviction that the war of the sections will 
be renewed within a few years, as is the case, the negroes will 
suspect and dread the class who would treat them as enemies in case 
the war should come, and will seek to escape to a section of the 
country where they would not be so treated.  Perhaps, too, there 
would have been a voluntary political division among the black 
voters, had the whites used more pacific means to bring it about, 
and had they themselves set the example.  And last, but not least, 
in making up the sum of blame that the whites must bear, is their 
own unwillingness to labor, which gives the rural population too 
much time for mischief and too little sympathy with the working 
classes. 
</p><p>As we have traced the causes that have led to the exodus, and 
described the conditions which warrant the belief that there will 
be a renewal of the emigration on a more extended scale next 
spring, and endeavored to distribute the responsibility for the 
troubles equitably among whites and blacks, remedies have naturally 
suggested themselves to the reader; in fact, they are more easily 
to be thought out than accomplished.  A few general reflections may 
be added, however, in order to indicate the probable solution of 
the race troubles that have brought about the exodus, if, indeed, 
the whites and blacks of the South are ever going to live together 
in peace. 
</p><p>(1.)  It is certain that negro labor is the best the South can 
have, and equally certain that the climate and natural conditions 
of the South are better suited to the negro than any others on this 
continent.  The alluvial lands, which many persons believe the 
negroes alone can cultivate, on account of climatic conditions, are 
so rich that it might literally be said it is only necessary to 
tickle them with a hoe to make them laugh back a harvest.  The 
common prosperity of the country &mdash; the agricultural interests of the 
South and the commercial interests of the North &mdash; will be best 
served, therefore, by the continued residence and labor of the 
blacks in the cotton States. 
</p><p>(2.)  The fact stated in the foregoing paragraph is so well 
understood at the North that the Southern people should dismiss the 
idea that there is any scheming among the Northern people, 
political or otherwise, to draw the black labor away from its 
natural home.  The same fact should also influence the people at 
the North not to be misled by any professional philanthropists who 
may have some self-interest in soliciting aid to facilitate negro 
emigration from the South.  The duty of the North in this matter is 
simply to extend protection and assure safe-conduct to the negroes, 
if the Southern whites attempt to impede voluntary emigration by 
either law or violence.  Any other course might be cruel to the 
negro in encouraging him to enter on a new life in a strange 
climate, as well as an injustice to the white land owners of the 
South. 
</p><p>(3.)  There is danger that the Southern whites will, as a 
rule, misinterpret the meaning of the exodus.  Many are inclined to 
underrate its importance, and those who appreciate its significance 
are apt to look for temporary and superficial remedies.  The vague 
promises made at the Vicksburg convention, which was controlled by 
the whites, and called to consider the emigration movement, have 
had no influence with the negroes, because they have heard such 
promises before.  Had the convention adopted some definite plan of 
action, such as ex-Governor Foote, of Mississippi, submitted, its 
session might not have been in vain.  This plan was to establish a 
committee in every county, composed of men who have the confidence 
of both whites and blacks, that should be auxiliary to the 
<pb n="230"/>  
public authorities, listen to complaints, and arbitrate, advise, 
conciliate, or prosecute, as each case should demand.  It is short-sighted for the Southern people to make mere temporary concessions, 
such as have been made in some cases this year, for that course 
would establish an annual strike.  It is folly for them to suppose 
they can stem the tide of emigration by influencing the regular 
lines of steamboats not to carry the refugees, for the people of 
the North will see that the blacks shall not be detained in the 
South against their will.  It is unwise for them to devise schemes 
for importing Chinese, or encouraging the immigration of white 
labor as a substitute for negro labor, when they may much better 
bestir themselves to make the present effective labor content. 
</p><p>(4.)  Education will be the most useful agent to employ in the 
permanent harmonizing of the two races, and the redemption of both 
from the faults and follies which constitute their troubles.  It is 
not the education of the negro alone, whose ambition for learning 
is increasing notably with every new generation, but the education 
of the mass of the young whites, that is needed to inculcate more 
tolerance of color and opinion, to give them an aspiration beyond 
that of riding a horse and hanging a "nigger," and to enable them 
to set a better example to the imitative blacks in the way of work 
and frugality.  The blacks need the education to protect them from 
designing white men; the whites need it to teach them that their 
own interests will be best served by abandoning bulldozing of all 
kinds. 
</p><p>(5.)  Reform in the land tenure, by converting the plantation 
monopolies into small holdings; abolition of the credit system, by 
abandoning the laws which sustain it; a diversification of crops; 
and attention to new manufacturing, maritime, and commercial 
enterprises, &mdash; these are the material changes that are most needed.  
They can be secured only through the active and earnest efforts of 
the whites.  The blacks will be found responsive. 
</p><p>(6.)  The hope of the negro exodus at its present stage, or 
even if it shall continue another season, is that the actual loss 
of the valuable labor that has gone, and the prospective loss of 
more labor that is anxious to go, will induce the intelligent and 
responsible classes at the South to overcome their own prejudices, 
and to compel the extremists, irreconcilables, and politicians 
generally, of all parties, to abandon agitation, and give the South 
equal peace and equal chance for black and white. 
</p> 
<signed>                                   <hi rend="italic">James B. Runnion.</hi>
</signed>

 
</div1> 
</body> 
</text> 
</TEI.2> 
