<?xml version="1.0"?>

<?dlps id="TayView"?>
<?dlps page-images="none" figure-images="no"?>
<?dlps transcription="other"?>

<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/tei-p4/tei2.dtd" [
<!ENTITY % POSTKB "INCLUDE">
<!ENTITY % TEI.extensions.ent SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.ent">
<!ENTITY % TEI.extensions.dtd SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.dtd">
<!ENTITY % ISOnum SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/charent/iso-num.ent"> %ISOnum;
<!ENTITY % ISOpub SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/charent/iso-pub.ent"> %ISOpub;
  
]>  
<TEI.2 id="TayView">  
<teiHeader type="migrated" creator="Etext">
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title type="main">Views A-Foot; Europe Seen with Knapsack and Staff</title>
<title type="sort">views a foot europe seen with knapsack and staff</title>
<author>Taylor, Bayard</author>
<respStmt>
<resp>Creation of machine-readable version:</resp>   
<name>Stephen Railton</name>   
<resp>Creation of digital images:</resp>   
<name>Carol Osborne, Electronic Text Center</name>   
<resp>Conversion to TEI.2-conformant markup:</resp>   
<name>University of Virginia Library Electronic Text Center.</name>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt>   
<extent>ca. <num type="kilobytes">10</num> kilobytes</extent>   
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>University of Virginia Library</publisher>
<pubPlace>Charlottesville, Virginia</pubPlace>   
<idno type="ETC">TayView</idno>   
<date value="1997">1997</date>
<availability status="public">
<p n="copyright">Copyright &copy; 1997 by the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia</p>
<p n="access">Publicly accessible</p>
</availability>
<idno type="uva-pid">uva-lib:476387</idno>
</publicationStmt>
<seriesStmt>
<title>University of Virginia Library, Text collection</title>
<idno type="uva-set">UVA-LIB-Text</idno>
</seriesStmt>   
<notesStmt>
<note>
<p>This electronic text represents the following excerpts: from Chapter XIX, "Leipsic and Dresden" (pp. 198-200), from Chapter XXXII, "Scenes in Genoa, Leghorn, and Pisa" (pp. 339-401), from Chapter XXXIII, "Residence in Florence" (pp. 354-55).</p>
</note>   
</notesStmt>   
<sourceDesc>
<biblFull>
<titleStmt>
<title type="main">Views A-Foot; Europe Seen with Knapsack and Staff</title>
<title type="sort">views a foot europe seen with knapsack and staff</title>
<author>Bayard Taylor</author>
</titleStmt>   
<editionStmt>
<p>Household Edition, Revised</p>
</editionStmt>   
<extent>pp. 198-200, 339-401, 354-55</extent>   
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>G. P. Putnam's Sons</publisher>   
<pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>   
<date value="1875">1875</date>   
<idno type="callNo">Print copy consulted: UVA library call number PS 2980 v. 16 1875</idno>
</publicationStmt>   
</biblFull>
</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc>   
<encodingDesc>
<projectDesc>
<p>Prepared for the University of Virginia Library Electronic Text Center.</p>
</projectDesc>   
<editorialDecl>
<p>All quotation marks retained as data.</p>   
<p>All unambiguous end-of-line hyphens have been removed, and the trailing part of a word has been joined to the preceding line.</p>   
<p>The images exist as archived TIFF images, one or more JPEG versions for general use, and thumbnail GIFs.</p>   
<p>Keywords in the header are a local Electronic Text Center scheme to aid in establishing analytical groupings.</p>
</editorialDecl>   
</encodingDesc>   
<profileDesc>
<creation>
<date value="1846">1846</date>
</creation>   
<langUsage>
<language id="eng" usage="main">English</language>
</langUsage>   
<textClass>
<keywords>
<term>prose; non-fiction</term>
</keywords>   
</textClass>
</profileDesc>   
<revisionDesc>
<change>
<date value="1997-05">May 1997</date>   
<respStmt>
<resp>corrector</resp>   
<name>Carol Osborne</name>
</respStmt>   
<item>added TEI header and tags; corrected the following error, page 354: Italy remains] Italy still remains.</item>
</change>   
<change>
<date value="2005-07">July 2005</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>Corrector</resp>
<name>Margaret Konkol</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Converted SGML to XML and fixed tagging.</item>
</change>
<change>
<date value="2007-09">September 2007</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>Migration</resp>
<name>Ethan Gruber, University of Virginia Library</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Converted XML markup from TEI Lite to uva-dl-tei (TEI P4 with local customizations).</item>
</change>
<change>
<date value="2008-01">January 2008</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>Migration</resp>
<name>Greg Murray, University of Virginia Library</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Programmatically updated TEI header markup (but not header content) for minimal compliance with current QA requirements.</item>
</change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>   
  
<text id="d1">  
<body id="d2"> 

  
<div1 type="article" id="d3"> <pb n="198"/><head>Views A-Foot; or Europe Seen with Knapsack  
and Staff, (Household Edition)<lb/>  
By Bayard Taylor (New York: Putnam's, 1875)</head>  
  
  
<p>[<hi rend="italic">from Chapter XIX, "Leipsic and Dresden"</hi>] The railroad 
brought us in three hours from Leipsic, over the eighty miles of plain 
that intervene.  We came from the station through the <hi rend="italic">Neustadt</hi>, 
passing the Japanese Palace and the equestrian statue of Augustus the 
Strong.  The magnificent bridge over the Elbe was so much injured by the 
late inundation as to be impassable, and we were obliged to go some 
distance up the river bank and cross on a bridge of boats.  Next morning 
my first search was for the Picture Gallery.  We set off at random, and 
after passing the Church of Our Lady, with its lofty dome of solid 
stone, which withstood the heaviest bombs during the war with Frederick 
the Great, came to an open square, one side of which was occupied by an 
old, brown, red-roofed building,  
 
 <pb n="199"/>   
which I at once recognized as the 
object of our search.</p> 
  
<p>I have just taken a last look at the gallery this morning, and left 
it with real regret; for during the two visits, Raphael's heavenly 
picture of the Madonna and Child had so grown into my love and 
admiration, that it was painful to think I should never see it again. 
There are many more which clung so strongly to my imagination, 
gratifying in the highest degree the love for the Beautiful, that I left 
them with sadness, and the thought that I would now only have the 
memory.  I can see the inspired eye and god-like brow of the 
Jesus-child, as if I were still standing before the picture, and the 
sweet, holy countenance of the Madonna still looks upon me.  Yet, though 
this picture is a miracle of art, the first glance filled me with 
disappointment.  It has somewhat faded, during the three hundred years 
that have rolled away since the hand of Raphael worked the canvas and 
the glass with which it is covered for better preservation, injures the 
effect.  After I had gazed on it a while every thought of this vanished. 
The figure of the Virgin seemed to soar in the air, and it was difficult 
to think the clouds were not in motion.  Two divine cherubs look up from 
below, and in her arms sits the sacred child.  Those two faces beam from 
the picture like those of angels.  The dark, prophetic eye and pure brow 
of the young Jesus chain one like a spell.  There is something more than 
mortal in its expression &mdash; something in that infant face which 
indicates a power mightier than the proudest manhood.  There is no glory 
around the head; but the spirit which shines from those features, marks 
his divinity.  In the  
  
 <pb n="200"/>   
sweet face of the mother a sorrowful forboding 
mingles with its tenderness, as if she knew the world into which the 
Saviour was born and foresaw the path in which he was to tread.  It is a 
picture which one can scarce look upon without tears.</p> 
  
 
 <pb n="339"/>  
  
<p>[<hi rend="italic">from Chapter XXXII, "Scenes in Genoa, Leghorn, and Pisa"</hi>] 
Has the reader ever seen some grand painting of a city, rising with its 
domes and towers and palaces from the edge of a glorious bay, shut in by 
mountains &mdash; the whole scene clad in those deep, delicious, sunny hues, 
which we admire so much in the picture although they appear unrealized 
in Nature?  If so, he can figure to himself Genoa, as she appeared to us 
at sunset, from the battlements west of the city.  When we had passed 
through the gloomy gate of the fortress that guards the western 
promontory, the whole scene opened on us at once in all its majesty. 
The battlements where we were standing, and the blue mirror of the 
Mediterranean just below, with a few vessels moored near the shore, made 
up the foreground; just in front lay the queenly  
 
 <pb n="340"/> 
city, stretching out to 
the eastern point of the bay, like a great meteor &mdash; this point, crowned 
with the towers and dome of a cathedral, representing the nucleus, while 
the tail gradually widened out and was lost among the numberless villas 
that reached to the top of the mountains behind.  As we gazed, a purple 
glow lay on the bosom of the sea, while far beyond the city, the eastern 
half of the mountain crescent around the gulf was tinted with the 
loveliest hue of orange.  The impressions which one derives from looking 
on remarkable scenery depend, for much of their effect, on the time and 
weather.  I have been very fortunate in this respect in two instances, 
and shall carry with me through life, two glorious pictures of a very 
different character &mdash; the wild sublimity of the Brocken in cloud and 
storm, and the splendor of Genoa in an Italian sunset. </p> 
  
 
 <pb n="354"/>  
  
<p>[<hi rend="italic">from Chapter XXXIII, "Residence in Florence"</hi>] Italy still remains 
the home of Art, and it is but just she should keep these treasures, 
though the age that brought them forth has passed away.  They are her 
only support now; her people are dependent for their subsistence on the 
glory of the Past.  The spirits of the old painters, living  
 
 <pb n="355"/> 
still on 
their canvas, earn from year to year the bread of an indigent and 
oppressed people.  This ought to silence those utilitarians at home, who 
oppose the cultivation of the fine arts, on the ground of their being 
useless luxuries.  Let them look to Italy, where a picture by Raphael or 
Correggio is a rich legacy for a whole city.  Nothing is useless that 
gratifies the perception of Beauty, which is at once the most delicate 
and the most intense of our mental sensations, binding us by an 
unconscious link nearer to nature and to Him, whose every thought is 
born of Beauty, Truth and Love.  I envy not the man who looks with a 
cold and indifferent spirit on these immortal creations of the old 
masters &mdash; these poems written in marble and on the canvas.  They who 
oppose every thing which can refine and spiritualize the nature of man, 
by binding him down to the cares of the work-day world alone, cheat life 
of half its glory.</p> 
  
</div1>  
 
</body>  
</text>  
</TEI.2>  
  
 
