<?xml version="1.0"?>

<?dlps id="ThoWilk"?>
<?dlps page-images="none" figure-images="no"?>
<?dlps transcription="other"?>

<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/tei-p4/tei2.dtd" [
<!ENTITY % POSTKB "INCLUDE">
<!ENTITY % TEI.extensions.ent SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.ent">
<!ENTITY % TEI.extensions.dtd SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.dtd">
<!ENTITY % ISOnum SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/charent/iso-num.ent"> %ISOnum;
<!ENTITY % ISOpub SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/charent/iso-pub.ent"> %ISOpub;

]>

 
<TEI.2 id="ThoWilk"> 
<teiHeader type="migrated" creator="Etext">
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title type="main">Miss Wilkins: An Idealist in Masquerade</title>
<title type="sort">miss wilkins an idealist in masquerade</title>
<author>Thompson, Charles Miner</author>
<respStmt>
<resp>Creation of machine-readable version:</resp> 
<name>Judy Boss</name> 
<resp>Conversion to TEI.2-conformant markup:</resp>  
<name>University of Virginia Library Electronic Text Center</name>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt> 
<extent>ca. <num type="kilobytes">46</num> kilobytes</extent> 
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>University of Virginia Library</publisher>
<pubPlace>Charlottesville, Virginia</pubPlace> 
<idno type="ETC">ThoWilk</idno> 
<date value="1995">1995</date>
<availability status="public">
<p n="copyright">Copyright &copy; 1995 by the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia</p>
<p n="access">Publicly accessible</p>
</availability>
<idno type="uva-pid">uva-lib:476391</idno>
</publicationStmt>
<seriesStmt>
<title>University of Virginia Library, Text collection</title>
<idno type="uva-set">UVA-LIB-Text</idno>
</seriesStmt> 
<sourceDesc>
<biblFull>
<titleStmt>
<title type="main">Miss Wilkins: An Idealist in Masquerade</title>
<title type="sort">miss wilkins an idealist in masquerade</title>
<author>Charles Miner Thompson</author>
</titleStmt> 
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>Atlantic Monthly (Houghton, Mifflin &amp; Co.)</publisher> 
<pubPlace>Cambridge, Mass</pubPlace> 
<date value="1899-05">May 1899</date>
</publicationStmt> 
<seriesStmt>
<p>83</p>
</seriesStmt> 
<notesStmt>
<note>
<p>
<hi rend="italic">Atlantic Monthly</hi> 83 (May 1899): 665-675.</p>
</note>
</notesStmt>
</biblFull>
</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc> 
<encodingDesc>
<projectDesc>
<p>Prepared for the University of Virginia Library Electronic Text Center</p>
</projectDesc> 
<editorialDecl>
<p>All quotation marks retained as data</p> 
<p>All unambiguous end-of-line hyphens have been removed, and the 
trailing part of a word has been joined to the preceding line.</p> 
<p id="ETC">Keywords in the header are a local Electronic Text Center scheme  
to aid in establishing analytical groupings</p>
</editorialDecl> 
<refsDecl>
<p>ID elements are given for each page element and are composed of the text's 
unique cryptogram and the given page number, as in AusEmma1 for page one of  
Jane Austen's Emma.</p>
</refsDecl>
</encodingDesc> 
<profileDesc>
<creation>
<date value="1899">1899</date>
</creation> 
<langUsage>
<language id="eng" usage="main">English</language>
</langUsage> 
<textClass>
<keywords>
<term>fiction ; prose</term>
</keywords>
</textClass>
</profileDesc> 
<revisionDesc>
<change>
<date value="1995-07">July 1995</date> 
<respStmt>
<resp>corrector</resp> 
<name>Jamie L Spriggs, Electronic Text Center, University of Virginia</name>
</respStmt> 
<item>Added header; Tagged with TEI2-compatible SGML markup; parsed against  
"teilite" dtd; Checked against Alderman Library's copy AP2 / A8.</item>
</change> 
<change>
<date value="2005-07">July 2005</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>Corrector</resp>
<name>Margaret Konkol</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Converted SGML to XML and fixed tagging.</item>
</change>
<change>
<date value="2007-09">September 2007</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>Migration</resp>
<name>Ethan Gruber, University of Virginia Library</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Converted XML markup from TEI Lite to uva-dl-tei (TEI P4 with local customizations).</item>
</change>
<change>
<date value="2008-01">January 2008</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>Migration</resp>
<name>Greg Murray, University of Virginia Library</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Programmatically updated TEI header markup (but not header content) for minimal compliance with current QA requirements.</item>
</change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader> 
 
<text id="d1">  
<body id="d2"> 

<div1 type="story" id="d3">
<pb n="665"/>  
<head> MISS WILKINS: AN IDEALIST IN MASQUERADE</head> 
 
<p>ON any walk or drive in rural New England, in the springtime, 
one is sure to find on some abandoned farm an unkempt old apple 
orchard.  The gnarled and twisted trees uphold on their rotting 
trunks more dead than living branches, and bear, if at all, only a 
few scattered and ghostly blossoms.  And in that group of pitiable 
trees, dying there in the warm sunshine, there will be nothing to 
suggest life and joyousness except the golden woodpeckers with 
their flickering flight, and the bluebirds with their musical, low 
warble.  If, indeed, the orchard stands upon a sloping hillside, 
one can glance away and see in the valley prosperous villages, 
smiling, fertile farms, and other orchards, well kept, healthy, and 
looking from their wealth of blossoms like white clouds stranded.  
But if one be of a pessimistic complexion, he can shut his eyes to 
that pleasanter prospect, gaze only at the old orchard, and think 
of it as typical of New England.  So, in fact, in its limited 
degree, it is; but almost to the ultimate degree of exactness is it 
typical of the New England village which Miss Wilkins delights to 
draw.  In place of the worn-out trees there are gnarled and twisted 
men and women.  There are, of course, the young people, with their 
brief, happy time of courtship, to take the place in it of the 
birds; but her village, like the orchard, is a desolate and 
saddening spectacle.  In that community of Pembroke which she has 
celebrated, what twisted characters!  Barney Thayer refuses to 
marry Charlotte Barnard because, as the result of a quarrel with 
her father, Cephas, he hastily vows never to enter the house again.  
Not the anger of his mother, not the suffering of his sweetheart, 
not even jealousy of handsome Thomas Paine,&mdash;who, seeing her 
forsaken, makes bold to woo,&mdash;has power to move him from his 
stubborn stand.  The selfish pride of Cephas is so great that he 
lets his daughter's happiness be destroyed rather than admit 
himself wrong, or take the smallest step to reconcile him with her 
lover.  Barney Thayer inherits his self-will from his mother, a 
woman of indomitable will, who rules her family with an iron hand.  
When she hears that Barney has refused to marry Charlotte, she 
forbids him ever to step within her door again; when her youngest 
son, Ephraim, who has a weak heart and whom the doctor has 
forbidden her to whip, disobeys her, she whips him, and he dies; 
when her daughter Rebecca falls in love with William Berry, she 
forbids the marriage for a trivial cause, and when Rebecca, denied 
the legitimate path of love, steps aside into the other way, she 
disowns and casts her out.  She loses all her children rather than 
yield to them the least shadow of her authority.  Charlotte 
Barnard's cousin, Sylvia Crane, leaving her own house on the Sunday 
night of Charlotte's quarrel with Barney to comfort her, misses the 
weekly call of Richard Alger, her lover.  His nature, compounded of 
habit and pride and stubbornness, does not let him come again, once 
his pride has been offended, once his habit has been broken.  Silas 
Berry&mdash;William Berry's father&mdash;is determined to sell his cherries 
for an exorbitant price.  When the young people refuse to buy, he 
tells William and Rose, his children, to invite them to a picnic 
and cherry-picking.  When the guests are departing, he waylays them 
to demand payment for his cherries.  He outrages common decency 
with his mean trickery, but he has his way.  Nearly every character 
in the book is a monstrous example of stubbornness,&mdash;of that will 
which enforces its ends, however trivial, even to self-destruction. 
<pb n="666"/>   
The people are not normal; they are hardly sane.  Such is 
Miss Wilkins's village, and it is a true picture; but it wholly 
represents New England life no more than the dying apple orchard 
wholly represents New England scenery. 
</p><p>But the purpose of this comparison is to set forth a truth 
comforting to those who wish to believe that a race full of good 
qualities has not yet run its full course, and not to pick a 
quarrel with the author.  The realist makes it his boast that he 
tells the truth, but he exercises as rigid a selection in incidents 
and characters as the most arrant romancer, and, as this novel of 
Pembroke aptly illustrates, tells a story often as far away from 
average truth.  As a matter of fact, there is small meaning in the 
terms "realism" and "romanticism."  The logical application of the 
principles of either would lead to the production of the 
unreadable.  That wise Frenchman who said that style is the man 
said everything.  Art is the expression of personality.  A certain 
definite character, with a gift for expression, more or less great, 
is acted upon by a certain environment and reacts upon it, with 
certain literary results.  A striking novel like Pembroke is a 
miracle no more than a thunderstorm, but is the result of natural 
causes working in accordance with natural laws.  If Pembroke gives 
a picture of New England life which is more fairly to be called 
incomplete than inaccurate, the reason lies in the personality of 
the writer and the nature of her environment, the two factors of 
her limitations.  And so the real task is, not to find fault with 
her for not going outside the circle of her talent, but to measure 
the length of its radius, and to guess, if possible, what 
determined it. 
</p><p>May it be many years before that intimate biography appears 
from which alone can be gathered the knowledge necessary to 
understand fully the causes of Miss Wilkins's qualities and 
limitations; but from the known circumstances of her life a few 
inferences may be drawn which will in a measure account for them.  
The known facts are meagre enough, and do not include the date of 
her birth in Randolph, Massachusetts.  Her father, an architect and 
builder, a graduate of the building trades, and not of the 
technical schools, was a native of cosmopolitan Salem, and a 
descendant from Bray Wilkins, a prominent Puritan who played his 
part as judge in that New England inquisition before which the 
witches stood their lamentable trial.  Her mother was of the 
Holbrooks of Holbrook,&mdash;"fine, 'genteel' people of the old sort."  
Her formative years were passed in Brattleboro, Vermont, where her 
father kept a store, and her schooling was not in the contemporary 
sense extensive.  Her most valuable education in all likelihood was 
derived in part from her own observation of life, and in part from 
her own independent reading, to the excellence of which as 
literature occasional references in her writings to such authors as 
Marvel and Herrick bear significant witness.  On leaving 
Brattleboro she returned to Randolph, where she has lived ever 
since.  The events of her quiet life have been the publication of 
her books.  These appeared in the following order: A Humble 
Romance, stories, 1887; A New England Nun, stories, 1891; Jane 
Field, a novel, 1892; Young Lucretia, stories for children, 1892; 
Giles Corey, Yeoman, a play, 1893; Pembroke, a novel, 1891; 
Madelon, a novel, 1896; Jerome, a novel, 1897; and Silence, 
stories, 1898. 
</p><p>This biographical sketch, brief and imperfect as it is, will, 
if examined attentively, be found to contain much which explains 
the nature and the direction of the author's talent.  It appears, 
for example, that her opportunities for the observation of life 
have been only those afforded by two country towns,&mdash;in the 
impressionable days of her girlhood, by one.  Of Brattleboro, I 
know only that it is a prosperous village in  
<pb n="667"/>  the lovely 
Connecticut Valley, with the Green Mountains behind it, and the 
hills of New Hampshire before it.  But many another Vermont town I 
know well, and I suppose myself safe in assuming that the current 
of life and progress has followed substantially the same course 
there as elsewhere in the state. 
</p><p>In general, the development of the Vermont village has been 
marked by three periods.  The first is that of the founders.  The 
pioneers came and builded it in the wilderness.  Energy and hope 
were high, and faith in the ultimate good fortunes of the new 
community was complete.  Of course no village in that stage of 
development now exists. 
</p><p>The second period begins when the faith and energy of the 
founders are passed away, and the village lives an isolated, 
humdrum life, unbroken by any incident more exciting than the 
arrival of the daily stage.  If the village is built high and far 
away upon a hill, it probably survives in this second stage of 
development to this day.  It has its general store, serving as a 
club for the men; its little square schoolhouse, where elementary 
instruction is given to the children; its church, to which a 
minister from some more prosperous community drives on an 
occasional Sunday and charitably holds services.  It is inhabited 
mainly by old men and old women; for the young people have gone out 
into the world to seek their fortunes.  In such a village as this 
will be found those rare beings, Yankees who talk the full Yankee 
dialect.  They are, for the most part, simple and sane folk with a 
large fund of humor and shrewdness, who lead happy and healthful 
lives.  They are drawn with a comprehension and sympathy the most 
complete, and with a touch infinitely loving, in the sweet and 
wholesome works of Mr. Rowland E. Robinson.  Yet these people, who 
in Mr. Robinson's books live in a Yankee Arcadia upon which the 
sophisticated have every reason to turn envious glances, are the 
same as those who, interpreted by a different temperament, make 
Pembroke seem a town of battling lunatics.  Both writers tell the 
truth.  There is another side to the shield which shows so far in 
Mr. Robinson's exhibiting hands.  In these little remote 
communities can be found personalities which, if weak, have 
narrowed and deadened, or which, unchecked by any effective public 
opinion, have assumed forms of willful distortion.  In them live 
people who, having no large matters upon which to exercise 
naturally active minds, give importance to trifles; who, lacking 
social life, grow morbid and wrong-headed.  And among them it is 
easy to find such perverted strength of will as that shown by 
Barney Thayer, or such contemptible meanness as that of old Silas 
Berry.  From such a village, and from the lonely farms about it, 
come the saddening inmates of the two insane asylums of Vermont,&mdash; 
Vermont, which has a smaller population than the city of Boston! 
</p><p>The third period is that of most of the larger valley towns.  
To them, about 1850, came the railway and the telegraph, and by 
bringing them into touch with the great world gave them a 
renaissance into life and activity.  Brattleboro is in that third 
stage.  It should have been well begun, but still far from 
completely attained when Miss Wilkins lived there as a child.  The 
older people then alive should have been relics of the narrower 
day.  They should have been sprinkled through the population of the 
revived community like old wooden buildings in the midst of smart 
brick blocks in a growing town,&mdash;the subjects of many a story, 
their eccentricities the material of many a joke.  Any one who has 
lived in such a village at a time not too far removed from its 
period of transition knows that the local store of anecdote&mdash; 
sometimes, in truth, a precious one&mdash;has been furnished by the 
queer doings of just such people.  Generally these stories are told 
as humorous, but if one has  
<pb n="668"/>  the bent he may take them as 
pathetic; and there are other stories, too, which he may hear, if 
he have ears, that are grim and tragic enough. 
</p><p>What influence the accident of this environment had upon Miss 
Wilkins becomes plain when we consider that the best part of any 
story-teller's equipment lies in his store of vivid childhood 
memories.  There is evidence that Miss Wilkins remembers the time 
when the electric cars did not slide, with griding trolley, through 
the streets of modern, prosperous Randolph.  In no book of hers are 
there mountains such as those which stand behind and in front of 
Brattleboro, nor is there any broad and beautiful river 
perpetuating her memories of the Connecticut.  The scenery&mdash;never 
in any case much dwelt upon&mdash;is that of a flat country, of eastern 
Massachusetts, of Randolph.  And from Randolph, too, she got her 
knowledge of the trade of shoe-making as it was before the days of 
the factory.  But the circumstance that her formative period was 
spent in Brattleboro, and the internal evidence of her work, 
otherwise than in the exceptions named, suggest, if they do not 
command, the conclusion that the larger part of her material was 
obtained there.  The narrow field for the observation of life thus 
afforded her was still further restricted, of course, by the fact 
of her sex.  Had she been a boy, she would have roamed the fields, 
gone fishing and hunting, had the privilege of sitting in the 
country store and listening to the talk of the men of evenings; she 
would have taken an interest in the local politics, and have 
learned to look at life as the men look at it, with the larger and 
more catholic view which is theirs not by virtue of greater 
insight, but by virtue of the undeniably larger, freer lives they 
are permitted to live.  As she was a girl, her outlook was confined 
to the household; her sources of information were the tales of 
gossiping women, which would naturally relate mostly to the family 
quarrels and dissensions that are the great tragedies of their 
lives. 
</p><p>To the restriction of environment and of sex must also be 
added the restriction of temperament.  Miss Wilkins has a keen and 
deep sense of humor, but it is never so keen and deep as her sense 
of the pathetic, and when a scene or a situation is in quarrel 
between them, her sense of humor is sure to come lamely off.  The 
most distinctly humorous of her stories, and also one of her best 
and best known, is The Revolt of Mother.  In this, a situation 
which in the hands of a writer more exclusively humorous would be 
laughable becomes in hers one over which it seems heartless to 
smile, so clearly is its underlying pathos revealed.  Without 
burdening too much the weary back of heredity we may recall her 
witch-persecuting Puritan ancestors in Salem, and, remembering 
Hawthorne's similar ancestry, say to ourselves that she was 
probably a serious, imaginative child, with a faculty for brooding 
over questions of conduct, who could be expected to feel the pathos 
in the humorous stories, and deeply to relish the grim and tragic 
ones.  She should have had a memory for detail even greater than 
that which children commonly possess, and because, as her biography 
shows, she was of the strain of New England gentlefolk and of a 
sensitive, imaginative disposition, the hardness and the narrowness 
of the lives which interested her must have seemed more painful 
than they ever did to those who lived them.  For this is the 
fallacy of the sensitive: to attribute their own sensitiveness to 
those grown callous to hardship, and to pity them accordingly. 
</p><p>Here, then, was a powerful mind, fond of the dramatic, 
interested in the problem of the will,&mdash;as any child whose 
ancestors have debated predestination and freedom of the will time 
out of mind has a perfect right to be,&mdash;thrown into a community in 
which persons of broad culture and knowledge of the world are  
<pb n="669"/>   
rare, and in which the more striking deviations from the 
commonplace are provided by personalities deformed by ungenerous 
circumstances.  To her sensitiveness, the narrowness and poverty of 
many of the lives would seem notably pitiful; to her dramatic 
imagination and inborn taste for metaphysics, the strange tragedies 
of morbid conscientiousness and perverted will would appeal as 
problems of absorbing interest.  With an outlook upon life 
restricted at best, and still further limited by the peculiarly 
serious quality of her mind, with few or no distractions, how could 
she do otherwise than observe and brood and wonder, until the 
special portion of the life about her which she saw clearly and 
which interested her most should be known to her in every detail of 
its physical accompaniments, in every one of its psychological 
nooks and crannies?  However painfully and slowly she may have 
spelled out the A B C's of its lives and characters, she came at 
last to know the whole alphabet, to be its absolute and tyrannous 
mistress, able to write with it whatever story she might wish.  Is 
it any wonder that such a mind, working on such material, should 
have produced as its first work such stories as compose the volume 
entitled A Humble Romance? 
</p><p>This book, which appeared in 1887, came with the force of a 
new revelation of New England to itself.  The literary merit of the 
stories was remarkable.  The short, terse sentences, written in the 
simplest, homeliest words, had a biting force.  Its skillfully 
lavish use of homely detail, always accurate, always significant, 
gave it an astonishing reality.  The paragraphs were as simple and 
direct as the sentences, and each advanced the story swiftly and 
easily upon its predestined course.  There was no wavering from the 
direct line, there were no stumbling-blocks of impertinent 
description or incident, no superfluities even.  There was no 
annoying striving after elegance of diction, no self-conscious 
attempt at cleverness of phrase or an artistic manner.  Everywhere 
was the sharp definiteness of the writer who sees clearly.  
Everywhere was the unconsciousness of an absorbed artist, not 
preoccupied with theories of art, with personal vanities, with fear 
of the critics or anxiety to please the public, but dominated by 
the one idea of setting down accurately the definite vision which 
her imagination had conceived and matured, and which now of 
necessity must be born.  The stories had, furthermore, a certain 
rare quality which always gives strength to fiction.  It is the air 
on the part of the author of being exterior to his story and 
irresponsible for it, of seeming to say, "I do not explain, I do 
not justify, I find no fault, I neither laugh over them nor grieve; 
these events are not of my invention,&mdash;they happened.  I report 
them, and allege nothing about them except that they are true."  It 
is this quality, as much as any, which gives a peculiar 
impressiveness to the tales of Guy de Maupassant.  So far as method 
is concerned, his story called in its English version A Bit of 
String might have been written by Miss Wilkins. 
</p><p>A good literary style is always more or less of a miracle.  It 
cannot be acquired by industry, it cannot be taught in the schools.  
Like any other aptitude of the mind it may be trained and 
perfected, but it is essentially a gift of nature.  A gift of 
nature, then, we must call Miss Wilkins's style; but the especial 
form of its development may be accounted for in part by the fact 
that she served her apprenticeship as a writer of stories for 
children and young people,&mdash;a capital school in which to practice 
clearness and simplicity of phrase and directness of narrative.  
And as young people are avid of detail and great lovers of the 
realistic method,&mdash;for example may be cited their love of Robinson 
Crusoe, and Gulliver's Travels, and Pilgrim's Progress,&mdash;writing 
for children could but strengthen any natural inclination to  
<pb n="670"/>   
these qualities of style.  But excellent as in many respects 
the style of this first book was, it yet had numerous and serious 
blemishes.  Although direct references to bygone writers and now 
and then the use of a word in an obsolete sense showed Miss Wilkins 
to be acquainted with literature of a good sort, her style was 
deficient in grace, in music, as if written by one whose ear is 
untrained by any attentive listening to the rich harmonies of old 
prose.  And it was deficient also in correctness and in elegance: 
it was to some degree an uneducated and uncultured style.  She 
could be so tasteless as to speak of cottages as being "natty," and 
of an attractive woman as being the "merry feature of the place;" 
she could stoop to use such a newspaperish phrase as "sacred 
edifice" instead of "church;" she did not avoid such colloquialisms 
as "the girl colored <hi rend="italic">up</hi>," "the air <hi rend="italic">felt like</hi> snow," 
as the use of "directly" in the sense of "at once," of "quite" in 
the sense of "very," of "smart" in the sense of "efficient;" she 
was ignorant enough to speak of "calm equanimity," and to say that 
a girl looked into another person's eyes "directly with no 
circumlocution;" she was frequently ungrammatical, as when she said 
of one of her characters that he "chose the site of his buildings 
because <hi rend="italic">they</hi> would be easily accessible to the railway;" she 
invariably split her infinitives; occasionally she even failed to 
be clear.  This sentence is certainly puzzling: "Some might have 
questioned if her subtle fineness of strength was on a plane equal 
enough to admit of any struggle."  This criticism of detail only 
serves to make plain that, as the biographical sketch implies, Miss 
Wilkins, as a writer, belongs to the noble army of the self-made.  
These defects of form show how much, in the beginning, she was 
hampered by the lack of a liberal education in literature, just as 
the limitations of substance show how much she is hampered by the 
lack of a liberal education in life.  Imagination is a quality the 
manifestations of which are various.  There have been persons of 
restricted lives who have written, and written well, of kinds of 
life which they had never seen; but I think they have not done so 
whose dependence lay upon the mastery of homely detail.  For such, 
the immediate vision of their eyes, or, better yet, the vivid 
memories of the life which lay about them in childhood, are the 
only sources of effective writing.  The romancer, the poet, the 
philosopher, may live and die in his own library and yet write 
well, but the novelist who reports men in their habit as they lived 
must write of the life he knows.  And as Miss Wilkins is such a 
writer, the limitations of her environment determine the scope of 
her work, and they are unfortunately great.  If we keep them in 
mind, the fact is not surprising that of the twenty-eight stories 
in A Humble Romance every one is told from the point of view of 
some woman,&mdash;and that there are very few which do not deal with one 
of those family or neighborhood quarrels which have been referred 
to as the staple of the women's gossip in small country towns.  The 
book is, in fact, a collection of twenty-eight special cases of 
unhappiness among a peculiarly isolated and small-minded class of 
countrywomen.  Their mental attitude is caught with astonishing 
precision, but by this very success the stories gain an atmosphere 
at once narrow and mean.  They are saved from being unpleasant by 
their undeniable pathos, and by being so thoroughly human, if 
petty, as readily to excite sympathy.  As the author may not be 
asked to spoil her effect by labeling her incidents special cases, 
it becomes easy to see how distorted and untruthful an impression 
of New England life&mdash;an impression all the more untruthful in the 
general because so accurate in the particular&mdash;she would succeed 
unconsciously in conveying.  By the path of this analysis we come 
in sight once more of the dying apple orchard of the opening 
simile.  
<pb n="671"/>  Continuing along this path a little farther, we 
find ourselves standing fairly in the midst of the gnarled and 
twisted trunks; for observe, at least seventeen of the stories are 
tales of happiness postponed, or misery caused by an unbending 
will, which, abnormally developed, has become the master of its 
possessor instead of the servant of his intellect.  They are 
stories of people who won't simply and solely because they won't. 
</p><p>I confess that in considering Miss Wilkins's work I ask myself 
again and again, with a never failing and perhaps impertinent 
curiosity, what circumstances in her life could so have revealed to 
her and impressed upon her imagination the awful power for evil of 
a perverted will.  But her favorable environment and Puritan 
ancestry make it easy to understand how the problem of the will, 
once it had attracted her attention, should appeal with 
extraordinary force to one of her analytic, brooding, somewhat 
sombre temperament, and how it should seem to be laid upon her, as 
with a heavy hand, to embody her impressions in dramatic form.  The 
dramatic value of unreasonable stubbornness is her own personal 
discovery, the particular thing which gives her work psychological 
interest and distinction.  I know of no writer who has treated it 
so persistently, so variously, who has seemed so infatuated with 
it.  In no study of New England character&mdash;in the form either of 
history or of fiction&mdash;has the native strength of will been made so 
prominent.  Consciously or unconsciously, she has seized upon it 
and set it forth as the keystone of New England character.  It is 
not the exclusive possession of New England people, of course; but 
that it is in a marked degree characteristic no one can doubt.  The 
stubborn Puritan came to no relaxing land, but to one from which 
only dogged perseverance could wring a living, and so it is not 
strange if his descendants have acquired a character which may be 
described as granitic.  Psychologists and pathologists have found 
a study of abnormal conditions to be most profitable; Miss Wilkins 
has followed in their footsteps, and has studied the will in its 
perversities.  But as from disease we may learn what health is, so 
from her abnormal people we may learn what is the normal New 
England character.  Notable for its significance in the case of 
such poverty-stricken people as those whom Miss Wilkins describes 
is the fact that their contests of will, their long-drawn battles 
of stubbornness, are seldom fought for sordid ends.  I spoke just 
now of the atmosphere of A Humble Romance as being "mean:" it is so 
on account of the family bickerings of which it is full; but these 
bickerings have their fine aspect in that they are almost always 
upon some question of personal dignity, or freedom, or point of 
ethical opinion.  These people are nonconformists to their 
backbones.  They are fanatics or martyrs according to the point of 
view.  Were the theatre upon which they moved larger, or their own 
natures more generously cultivated, so that their rebellions should 
be upon really vital points, their tragedy would have beauty, and 
perhaps grandeur.  The old Puritans exercised their stubbornness 
upon a great issue; these country descendants, living in narrow 
ways and thinking narrow thoughts, exercise their stubbornness upon 
petty issues.  That is the only difference.  And these perverted 
and abnormal wills&mdash;baleful forces in characters diseased&mdash;attest 
the real strength of New England character.  It is easy to 
understand the success of a book which reproduces with a great 
wealth of accurate and homely detail a life which is still close to 
the richest and most cultivated of us, and which is of the very 
fibre of our thought and character,&mdash;a book which, in a land where 
women are the larger portion of the reading public, is written 
exclusively from the feminine point of view; but I choose to think 
that it was mainly the insistence upon a fine basic quality of  
<pb n="672"/>   
New England character which made A Humble Romance come with 
all the force of a new revelation of New England to itself. 
</p><p>This long examination of A Humble Romance would be 
disproportionate were not this first book, and its succeeding 
sister volume, A New England Nun, in a way a brief memorandum of 
Miss Wilkins's entire message to the world, which her later work, 
for the most part, only serves to amplify and make clear.  When one 
begins to read the novels, the short stories assume almost the 
aspect of preliminary sketches of their scenes and episodes, for 
they are similar not only in substance, but in method.  Those 
cogent reasons which publishers urge, reinforced by the ambition 
which every writer of fiction feels to try his hand in the most 
important form of his art, made it inevitable that, sooner or 
later, Miss Wilkins should write novels.  But, natural as it was, 
it is none the less regrettable.  For years she studied the shorter 
form and wrote in it,&mdash;years which necessarily left their indelible 
impress upon her talent.  Some acute person once said that every 
author learns to think in the length in which he is accustomed to 
write,&mdash;the paragrapher in the length of paragraphs, the editorial 
writer in the length of editorial articles, the historian in the 
length of the monograph or full-bodied history.  Miss Wilkins, 
whose earliest and longest training has been in the short story, 
thinks in the length of the short story.  Her novels, with the 
apparent exception of Jane Field, which is simply a short story of 
unusual extent, have the air of a chronological series of short 
stories about the same people.  She has never been able to see the 
larger proportions of the novel in their proper perspective.  
Moreover, in writing short stories she taught herself, with a 
thoroughness the results of which she will never be able wholly to 
overcome, a genuine mastery of the short, terse sentence.  To its 
telling force as used by her in A Humble Romance tribute has been 
paid.  The value of that tribute is not diminished by the suspicion 
that the sentences were short so invariably because the author at 
that time lacked the ability to combine clauses and sub-clauses 
into a compact, forcible whole, or by the admission that, effective 
as they are in the short stories, they grow monotonous when page of 
them follows page throughout a long book.  Their lack of variety 
can be seen, their monotony can be guessed, from these typical 
quotations from A Conquest of Humility, in A Humble Romance:&mdash; 
</p><p>"The young girl trembled and caught hold of her mother's 
dress; her eyes grew big and wild.  Hiram Caldwell drove up the 
road.  He met the gaze of the people with solemn embarrassment.  
But he was not so important as he had been.  There was a large, 
white-headed old man who drew the larger share of attention.  He 
got lumberingly out of the buggy when Hiram drew rein at the gate.  
Then he proceeded up the gravel walk to the house.  The people 
stood back and stared.  No one dared speak to him except Mrs. 
Erastus Thayer.  She darted before him in the path; her brown silk 
skirts swished." 
</p><p>"Her features were strong and fine.  She would have been 
handsome if her complexion had been better.  Her skin was thick and 
dull." 
</p><p>Mastery in the methods of the short story, and a fixed habit 
of writing in short sentences, are not the most useful 
qualifications to bring to the task of writing novels.  Many 
lessons of technique have to be laboriously unlearned by the writer 
thus trained when he attempts the new and ampler form.  That Miss 
Wilkins has succeeded in overcoming the results of her earliest 
training in any measure is due, no doubt, to the artistic 
restlessness which is one of her most marked characteristics.  She 
has written for children; she has written society verses; she wrote 
little prose  
<pb n="673"/>  poems in the day, fortunately brief, when they 
were popular under the absurd name of "etchings" or "pastels in 
prose;" she has tried her hand more than once at the drama, as 
Giles Corey, Yeoman, remains to witness; she has written a 
detective story; she has tried historical fiction; and she has 
composed romances not only of the kind in which passionate love is 
the theme, but also of the kind in which, as in Hawthorne, 
idealistic beauty is the end.  Some of these experiments have been 
so obviously outside the range of her abilities that those who have 
watched her progress with a loving solicitude&mdash;and these are not a 
few&mdash;have trembled for her future.  But whether partial failures or 
full successes, they showed artistic health, a talent curious about 
itself and ambitious to miss no possible development, a commendable 
desire to find out for itself its own strength and its own 
limitations.  And these experiments have served their useful 
purpose in developing both her talent and her style. 
</p><p>As a result of her practice in so many varieties of 
composition, she has advanced much in her understanding of the form 
of the novel; but it has had its chief effect, naturally enough, 
upon her style.  In the art of constructing sentences she has made 
really remarkable gain.  Those who are interested in style simply 
as style will find much to reward their curiosity in tracing her 
progress from the direct bald statements of her earliest manner 
through the florid sentences of Madelon and the long loose ones of 
Jerome to the really excellent prose style which she at last 
attains in Evelina's Garden, a story in her latest work, Silence.  
But the point here is that the practice which gave her talent its 
direction was not of the kind to fit her for the writing of novels.  
She made herself a specialist in the beginning, and, like all 
specialists, made her irretrievable sacrifices of possibilities of 
development. 
</p><p>In the novels, as in the short stories, the will is still the 
theme.  Willfulness, of a good or bad kind, is still the 
predominating characteristic of the people, from stern Jane Field, 
whose sense of justice and whose self-confident determination to 
judge moral questions for herself lead her stubbornly to pursue the 
path of crime, to haughty Jerome, ready to sacrifice everything 
good and sweet in life upon the altar of his own inordinate, 
willful pride.  But Pembroke&mdash;her first real novel, and to my mind 
unquestionably the best&mdash;contains the most complete summary of her 
observations upon the stubbornness of the New England character.  
Its plot, which has already been roughly outlined, shows clearly 
enough why it should be, in an artistic sense, her most successful 
novel.  The scene and the characters are those which she knows in 
every detail of their interior and exterior life; its psychological 
problems are those which have most interested her, and upon which 
she has thought most deeply and persistently.  The novel is great 
by its fidelity to life, by its dignity of theme, and by its social 
significance.  On the other hand, it has the expected and 
unavoidable defects.  The first impulse of the reader is to dispute 
the assumption that such a community as Pembroke ever existed; but 
on reflection he will admit that although it may not actually 
exist, it could be easily assembled, and that the exaggeration of 
which it is indubitably guilty is due to a legitimate selection, 
for the purpose of artistic emphasis, of circumstances unusual in 
combination, but in themselves and separately usual enough.  Then, 
being the study of an entire community, it lacks any broad central 
current of interest.  The reader is lost in a multitude of details, 
episodes, and characters, out of which he emerges rather with a 
sense of the undesirableness of an uncontrollable will than with 
any definite idea of one or two supremely interesting characters or 
of a connected chain of events.  The sense of confusion inevitable 
<pb n="674"/>  in a study of a community is increased by the writer's 
inability, already noted, not to deal with separate episodes as if 
they were short stories.  It is owing to this lack of homogeneity, 
partly necessary, partly due to want of skill, that what one 
remembers about the novel are particular pages and passages of 
great beauty and strength.  Many people would refer to Pembroke, I 
think, as the novel which contained&mdash;let us say for example&mdash;that 
capital description of the boy Ephraim's solitary, joyous coasting, 
pages remarkable for their rich blending of humor and pathos. 
</p><p>In two important technical respects Jerome is a better novel 
than Pembroke; for it has a strong central interest in the 
personality of its hero which binds its many short-story-like 
episodes together, and its style, in Miss Wilkins's later acquired 
manner of flowing sentences pleasantly varied in cadence and in 
length, makes it much more easily readable.  Jerome himself, 
however, is a most unsympathetic person.  The reader cannot help 
feeling a growing impatience with this wrong-headed young man, who, 
in a way repugnant to all common sense, insists upon taking the 
very roughest and hardest road to the success for which his 
strength of character plainly destines him.  Besides, the plot, 
slight and weak at best, shocks one's sense of average 
probabilities.  But worse than all, Miss Wilkins departs from that 
fine impartiality of the disinterested observer, which gives such 
force to her short stories and to Pembroke, and becomes a preacher 
and a sentimentalist.  The book is written to insinuate an 
accusation against the present social system.  Now, a story must by 
its nature be an appeal to the emotions, and to a logical person 
any attempt to influence him upon matters of fact and reason by a 
story touched with emotion, and made up of selected, even if true 
incidents, must and always will be annoying.  It is fighting in 
ambush, and no novel with a purpose should ever be written which 
does not proclaim itself such on its title-page.  Those who wish to 
hear a song will not turn out to hear a sermon.  This particular 
offender is redeemed, however, by many excellent pages of 
narrative, description, and character drawing, in which Miss 
Wilkins reaches as high levels of artistic achievement as she has 
ever attained.  Although not the strongest of her novels, it is 
easily the most readable. 
</p><p>In all its pages, there are none which are more pleasant than 
those which deal with Squire Merritt's family, and with his three 
friends, Eliphalet Means, John Jennings, and Colonel Lanson.  In 
all that has been said heretofore about Miss Wilkins's work, the 
idea has been conveyed that she knows no other side of New England 
life than that typified by the dying apple orchard.  As a matter of 
fact, not only the Merritts and their friends, but handsome Thomas 
Paine in Pembroke, and the Gordons and Parson Fair in Madelon, are 
witnesses to her understanding of the old-time New England 
gentry,&mdash;charming people, charmingly drawn, whom it is a great 
pleasure to meet in her generally graceless world, and her success 
with whom leads to the hope that there may yet come from her some 
more comprehensive and generally truthful picture of New England 
life.  Perhaps it is because she knows how gracious and beautiful 
New England life can be at its best that Miss Wilkins has cried out 
so sharply over its deformities, as is the wont of sensitive 
natures knowing the good and seeing the evil.  A plausible argument 
could indeed be made to show that the best realists are idealists 
at heart, whose very sensitiveness has made them more ready than 
the average person to perceive ugly realities, and who have 
consciously or unconsciously tried to rouse sluggish humanity to 
endeavor by unsparing pictures of the petty and the mean and the 
ignoble in human life.  Were such an argument to be made Miss 
Wilkins would furnish a telling example; for back of all her work 
is the idea, the sense of the mystery of human life, the question, 
"Why is this?" and she gently pushes selected incidents and 
characters before you, as if filled with the desire to learn, from 
any one who knows, the meaning of these problems,&mdash;clues doubtless, 
each one in its degree, to the answer to the Great Problem.  Her 
preoccupation with the mystery of life shows itself in little 
ways,&mdash;in the sense which some persons have of the unreality of her 
people; in her indifference to scenery, which she may well consider 
as of small moment in comparison with human beings; in her 
indifference to accuracy in antiquarian detail as compared with 
artistic truth.  Behind all her work one feels that he encounters 
the questioning eyes of an idealist.  Although she is ranked in the 
popular judgment as a realist, there is in her work the purest vein 
of romance and ideality, and even a certain touch of mysticism and 
allegory, which allies her, however distantly, to the literary 
family of Hawthorne.  These qualities may be noticed even in her 
early short stories, and in Pembroke their presence, in spite of 
their bungling and mechanical expression here, is to be perceived 
in the physical deformity which seems to accompany Barney Thayer's 
deformity of character.  They show themselves most conspicuously, 
if not most agreeably, however, in Madelon.  Like her other volumes 
in describing the fortunes of people of various kinds and degrees 
of stubbornness, it is unlike them in having romantic love for its 
theme, and in presenting as one of its principal characters, Lot 
Gordon, a man in whom mysticism and ideality are unexpectedly the 
most notable qualities.  They show themselves most charmingly in 
Evelina's Garden, a little tale which is a gem of its kind, and 
which shows that Miss Wilkins can command at least a hesitating 
comparison to the author of the most beautiful American romances.  
It is to be hoped that she will cast aside in favor of this kind of 
work the tales of antiquarian interest, such as Silence itself, 
which ought to be moving but is not, and The Little Maid at the 
Door.  She does not breathe freely in the musty atmosphere of 
colonial history.  Her Puritans, with their stilted speech, are 
uncommonly tiresome. 
</p><p>How is such a writer to be classified?  I think she cannot be 
classified at all.  A modest and conscientious artist, 
unfortunately limited by an imperfect education in books, and by an 
equally imperfect experience of life; who has cultivated her great 
natural gift for expression to the best of her opportunities and 
ability, and used it to set forth as vividly as possible such few 
of the multitudinous aspects of life as her temperament and 
environment have permitted her to see,&mdash;that is Miss Wilkins.  Only 
writers of mediocre ability&mdash;natural imitators&mdash;can be put in a 
class and accurately labeled.  A really original writer, like Miss 
Wilkins, no matter how limited, is <hi rend="italic">sui generis</hi>.  She can be 
described, she cannot be classified.  But if she must have her tag, 
the most nearly satisfactory will be that which declares her an 
idealist masquerading in the soiled and ragged cloak of realism. 
</p><signed>                    <hi rend="italic">Charles Miner Thompson</hi></signed> 
 
 
</div1> 
</body> 
</text> 
</TEI.2> 
