<?xml version="1.0"?>

<?dlps id="TruWhar"?>
<?dlps page-images="none" figure-images="no"?>
<?dlps transcription="other"?>

<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/tei-p4/tei2.dtd" [
<!ENTITY % POSTKB "INCLUDE">
<!ENTITY % TEI.extensions.ent SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.ent">
<!ENTITY % TEI.extensions.dtd SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.dtd">
<!ENTITY % ISOnum SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/charent/iso-num.ent"> %ISOnum;
<!ENTITY % ISOlat1 SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/charent/iso-lat1.ent"> %ISOlat1;
<!ENTITY % ISOpub SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/charent/iso-pub.ent"> %ISOpub;
]> 
 
<TEI.2 id="TruWhar"> 
<teiHeader type="migrated" creator="Etext">
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title type="main">Edith Wharton</title>
<title type="sort">edith wharton</title>
<author>Wharton review: Trueblood, Charles K.</author>
<respStmt>
<resp>Creation of machine-readable version:</resp> 
<name>Judy Boss</name> 
<resp>Conversion to TEI.2-conformant markup:</resp>  
<name>University of Virginia Library Electronic Text Center</name>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt> 
<extent>ca. <num type="kilobytes">34</num> kilobytes</extent> 
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>University of Virginia Library</publisher>
<pubPlace>Charlottesville, Virginia</pubPlace> 
<idno type="ETC">TruWhar</idno> 
<date value="1996">1996</date>
<availability status="public">
<p n="copyright">Copyright &copy; 1996 by the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia</p>
<p n="access">Publicly accessible</p>
</availability>
<idno type="uva-pid">uva-lib:476402</idno>
</publicationStmt>
<seriesStmt>
<title>University of Virginia Library, Text collection</title>
<idno type="uva-set">UVA-LIB-Text</idno>
</seriesStmt> 
<sourceDesc>
<biblFull>
<titleStmt>
<title type="main">Edith Wharton</title>
<title level="j">Dial</title>
<title type="sort">edith wharton</title>
<author>Wharton review: Charles K. Trueblood</author>
</titleStmt> 
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>Jansen, McClurg</publisher> 
<pubPlace>Chicago</pubPlace> 
<date value="1920-01">January 1920</date>
</publicationStmt> 
<seriesStmt>
<p>68</p>
</seriesStmt> 
<notesStmt>
<note>
<p>Trueblood, Charles K.  "Edith Wharton."  <hi rend="italic">The Dial</hi> 68  
(Jan. 1920): 80-91.</p>
</note>
</notesStmt>
</biblFull>
</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc> 
<encodingDesc>
<projectDesc>
<p>Prepared for the University of Virginia Library Electronic Text Center</p>
</projectDesc> 
<editorialDecl>
<p>All quotation marks retained as data</p> 
<p>All unambiguous end-of-line hyphens have been removed, and the 
trailing part of a word has been joined to the preceding line.</p> 
<p id="ETC">Keywords in the header are a local Electronic Text Center scheme  
to aid in establishing analytical groupings</p>
</editorialDecl> 
<refsDecl>
<p>ID elements are given for each page element and are composed of the text's 
unique cryptogram and the given page number, as in AusEmma1 for page one of  
Jane Austen's Emma.</p>
</refsDecl> 
</encodingDesc> 
<profileDesc>
<creation>
<date value="1920-01">January 1920</date>
</creation> 
<langUsage>
<language id="eng" usage="main">English</language>
</langUsage> 
<textClass>
<keywords>
<term>non-fiction; prose</term> 
<term>Women Writers</term>
</keywords> 
</textClass>
</profileDesc> 
<revisionDesc>
<change>
<date value="1996-04">April 1996</date> 
<respStmt>
<resp>corrector</resp> 
<name>Judy Boss</name>
</respStmt> 
<item>Note:  I have omitted the umlaut on "preeminently" on page 80, paragraph  
2, line 2; I have omitted the circumflex accent on "roles" on page 81, line 2.</item>
</change> 
<change>
<date value="1996-04">April 1996</date> 
<respStmt>
<resp>corrector</resp> 
<name>Jamie L Spriggs, Electronic Text Center, University of Virginia</name>
</respStmt> 
<item>Added header; Tagged with TEI.2-compatible SGML; Checked against  
Alderman's AP2/D48 (Re-introduced missing accents as in print text); Parsed  
against local "teilite" dtd.</item>
</change>
<change>
<date value="2007-09">September 2007</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>Migration</resp>
<name>Ethan Gruber, University of Virginia Library</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Converted XML markup from TEI Lite to uva-dl-tei (TEI P4 with local customizations).</item>
</change>
<change>
<date value="2008-01">January 2008</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>Migration</resp>
<name>Greg Murray, University of Virginia Library</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Programmatically updated TEI header markup (but not header content) for minimal compliance with current QA requirements.</item>
</change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader> 
 
<text id="d1"> 
 

<body id="d2"> 
<div1 type="essay" id="d3"> <pb n="80" id="TruWhar80"/> 
<head> 
<bibl>EDITH WHARTON 
BY CHARLES K. TRUEBLOOD 
</bibl>
</head>
 
<p>MADAME de Treymes' way of expressing her predilection for Durham 
was to say that he was extremely clever; and casting about to find 
terms of appreciation for the distinguished persons the reader 
discovers in Mrs. Wharton's pages, one can probably find none more 
fit than the dictum that whatever else they may be they are 
extremely clever.  Unqualified, such a remark is slight enough.  
The characters of any novelist who tends to psychology are likely 
to be clever, for considerable cleverness in the subject is 
necessary to psychological interest and some cleverness necessary 
to any interest.  And cleverness must be an elastic term to cover 
such diverse qualities as the clairvoyance of Mrs. Ansell, or the 
fastidiousness of Justine Brent, or the polished and brittle 
worldliness of Mr. Langhope.  Again, not all of these persons are 
extremely clever: Gerty Farish was not clever at all, and Undine 
Spragg was only clever enough to be extremely fashionable; though 
here it should be remembered that Gerty Farish was rather 
patronized by the narrator of her history, and Undine Spragg flayed 
with satire.  Moreover, one cannot take the measure of an author's 
qualities, say the last word about his work, in a word; even if it 
were possible, cleverness would probably not be the only 
discoverable last word about the qualities of Mrs. Wharton.  But it 
is at least an allusion, and as a first word cannot be 
unserviceable. 
</p><p>One should, therefore, hasten to add that the cleverness of 
Mrs. Wharton's characters is pre&euml;minently a social quality; it is 
the cleverness of intercourse, which has been its school and is the 
means of its expression.  It would as little prosper in isolation 
and repay study so as would the originality of Meredith's 
characters in such case.  Mrs. Wharton's characters hardly belong 
to a novelist of solitude; they are rarely and not long out of 
sound of each other; almost any two of the leading performers at 
least would be enough in themselves for a civilization.  Their 
minds are formed to the maze of sophistication, and it is a mark of 
their complexity that they are <pb n="81" id="TruWhar81"/> inseparable.  They are like 
actors who have many times rehearsed a piece together and know each 
other's r&ocirc;les; as in fact they have repeated together and know the 
code of amenity until it has become a fine instrument to the hand 
of their cleverness.  They might well be thought of as playing a 
game, so much are they dependent on their opponents for their 
effect, so often does the reader desire to applaud their strokes; 
but it is evidently a serious game they are playing.  Their 
cleverness, thus seen, is considerably fraught with gravity, and as 
the characters of a novelist whose every word is significant, for 
whom fantasy and gratuity would be ineptitude, they seem 
responsible even for their particles of speech.  One is tempted to 
say they feel it; certainly they do not forget the rules of their 
game: they take many things very gravely, but they would never do 
or say anything either irrelevant or "heavy." 
</p><p>Great and responsible as their cleverness is, however, the 
originality which enters into it is dilute.  Such a fact is 
intelligible, for the more concentrated forms of originality are 
equivalent to genius or eccentricity, neither of which phenomena 
appears among Mrs. Wharton's characters.  These persons, in fact, 
illustrate the possibilities, remarkably fulfilled really, of 
responsible cleverness to an artist whose aim is, as one takes Mrs. 
Wharton's to be, fineness and significance of effect.  Their 
cleverness is vigorous and varied yet controllable and never 
ineffective.  It offsets the gravity of a tragic theme but does not 
vitiate the representative and typical qualities of those whose 
chief characteristic it is; such persons may not be the most 
salient figures possible to fiction, but that they may, and do in 
these novels, combine importance with sophistication, is not to be 
denied.  And although the art which depicts such characters is 
likely to be individualistic, it is yet more amenable than hostile 
to classic principles, for its subject matter is inherently alien 
to disproportion and deformity: symmetry and absence of angularity 
are among the most obvious characteristics of clever people.  
Indeed the cleverness of Mrs. Wharton's characters is not 
infrequently to be found manifested as sober taste, as excellent 
sense, of which the conditioning personal quality is less an 
abundance of originality, a peculiarly mental quality, than the 
soundness of temperament. 
</p><p>Temperament is the soul of cleverness; for while the latter 
may not in the least, even in its most responsible form, imply 
intellectual profundity or great force, it does imply a 
consciousness heightened <pb n="82" id="TruWhar82"/> and quickened by an abundance of 
such contacts as are provided only by alert and delicate 
sensibility, that faculty so impossible to the temperamentally 
inert.  How much the reader discovers in the psychology of Mrs. 
Wharton's characters of the instantaneous, the non-logical; one 
finds them intuitive minded, whether he consider the native 
readiness of Mattie Silver or Ethan Frome, or the infallible 
trained insight of Mrs. Ansell: they see the matter at a glance or 
they do not see it ever!  The social talent of the great Miss Bart 
is here worth remembering for the sake of the prominence which a 
delicate sensibility played in her tactical triumphs; her 
perceptions were "fine threadlike feelers" that went out to her 
opponents in the great game she was playing and made her knowledge 
of their minds and characters almost divination.  Indeed by her 
eminence and excellence&mdash;she is the foremost and most typically 
clever of Mrs. Wharton's characters&mdash;she demonstrates the fact that 
her creator's best insight is her insight into the feminine 
character, and the feminine side of the masculine character, that 
her best art appears in the portrayal of the eternal feminine, the 
most eternal part of which is temperament. 
</p><p>Mrs. Wharton's characters, however, are superior not so much 
by abundance as by differentiation of temperament; for where the 
consideration is of such cleverness as they possess, it is evident 
that mere native sensibility is not a sufficient explanation: there 
must be a large element of discrimination present.  The zenith of 
cleverness, in fact, is to be reached&mdash;and they do reach that 
rather than any other zenith&mdash;only through the intellectualizing of 
temperament; in which process the intellect has the visible 
primacy, though feeling is the really urgent power.  Two stages in 
this progress of cleverness can be seen in the artless fervor of 
Mattie Silver and the fastidiousness of Justine Brent.  The 
difference between these two was really of degree alone: they were 
alike in that they both felt abundantly; different, in that 
Justine, as her author said, "felt with her mind."  Feeling with 
their minds is indeed the culmination of their cleverness, the best 
thing Mrs. Wharton's characters do; it is a more delicate spectacle 
than simple thinking and a far finer material to the hand of the 
artist.  And thus seen, the sober cleverness of these emancipated 
young women and poised young men is really their most human 
quality; it is a real refinement of the most fundamental thing 
about humanity, namely, its emotions. <pb n="83" id="TruWhar83"/> 
</p><p>Refinement of feeling, with them, has grown up into a fusion 
with ethical principle and has given them an aesthetic morality, 
the effectiveness of which in general is witnessed by the current 
saying that gentility&mdash;which is the code of such morality&mdash;is not 
a thing to be assumed, that it must be a part of character.  But 
this may mean merely that gentility, being a code devised by 
persons of accomplished feeling for themselves and their coequals, 
cannot readily be assumed by those who are not also of 
temperamental quality.  Moreover the aspect of gentility as a code 
is readily seen when the life declines that vitalized it: it then 
becomes mere ceremony.  At its best, however, and we see it so in 
Mrs. Wharton's best characters, it is an indisseverable ornament of 
its possessor, like well modulated speech, and is so mistaken for 
its animating temperament, for the voice that utters it.  The 
refinement of Mrs. Wharton's characters, how from another side it 
is to be seen as integrity of feeling, could be shown again by 
reference to Lily Bart.  She had no lack of opportunities to secure 
a field for the fitting exercise of her cleverness; how many times 
she was on the point of so doing by an alliance with wealthy 
stupidity, but how many times recoiled because "at heart she 
despised" a chance of such a sort!  She could never quite, even on 
the edge of ruin, bring herself to sacrifice her integrity of 
feeling permanently; and although her recoil was as much a matter 
of fastidiousness as of principle, it was no less energetic for 
that.  Historically, no doubt, this integrity of temperament has 
its root principles among the old and tried rules of conduct, the 
fundamental social conventions; but with these individuals such 
rules are so interfused with the medium feeling in which they are 
held as no longer to be recognizable as anything so abstract as 
principles.  How much a matter of feeling they are to become is 
reserved for Ralph Marvell and his family circle of Dagonets and 
Fairfords to show.  This group of people is typical of Mrs. 
Wharton's favourite finely temperamental sort of person, and they 
behaved typically toward Undine Spragg's suit for divorce: it was 
an ugly fact in their lives, but they preserved their integrity of 
feeling by ignoring it; they turned their backs upon it; they 
avoided talking and thinking about it; they even made a fatal 
mistake in dealing with it&mdash;all to spare their feelings. 
</p><p>As a matter of fact, among the Dagonets, the Fairfords, the 
Marvells, the Seldens, the de Chelles, the reader finds himself in 
an aristocracy 
<pb n="84" id="TruWhar84"/>of temperament.  And when such an aristocracy 
is not the direct subject of Mrs. Wharton's art, it is her tacit 
standard, the instrument of her criticism, the secret of her 
detachment, her weapon of satire.  It is not the upper classes 
merely that she has in mind, but the upper and inner classes; and 
in her judgments she is identified with them.  Her standard is 
never absent from her work, and is usually held up by a definite 
bearer, such as Lawrence Selden in The House of Mirth; and how many 
and how determinedly held aloft are the banners of refinement in 
The Custom of the Country!  Nearly every active character has one 
except the imperious and inept heroine, about whom we are kept 
clear as to the fact that however high she gets in the upper 
classes she is never of the inner.  The advantages which such a 
preoccupation confers upon Mrs. Wharton's art are obvious and not 
slight: so, it conforms to the standards of the best taste, for 
truly there could be no better taste than old Mr. Dagonet's or 
Charles Bowen's.  And hers being a society in which the principles 
of dignity exclude vagary and extravagance, she is placed well 
along, by her choice of matter, toward what is every artist's 
dream: the maximum of effect with the minimum of means.  Like her 
own heroine, Mrs. Leath, she does not often "misplace her strokes." 
</p><p>But while Mrs. Wharton is occupied with an aristocracy 
chiefly, the reader is obliged to turn to her earliest novel, The 
Valley of Decision, to see her as anything like a historian of 
manners.  And this, while not the least charming of her works, is, 
on the whole, the least characteristic.  Those leisurely Italian 
journeys, the rich panoramas, the, for her, singularly abundant 
spectacle of human affairs, the very populousness of the novel in 
accessory figures&mdash;these manifold external impressions are noticed 
less for their ulterior than their intrinsic value.  And there is 
thus a certain plenitude of graceful exteriorization in the novel, 
but along with greater charm, less of the acute significance of her 
best work, less of her very distinct truth of the human heart&mdash;and 
that truth less particularized than one finds it in her later work.  
It is only when one comes to The House of Mirth, The Fruit of the 
Tree, Sanctuary, and Madame de Treymes, or The Reef, that he finds 
minute interior searching balanced with exteriorization to produce 
her characteristic art: an economy of strokes done with edged 
tools, such as fine perceptions and that rather cold but bracing 
thing, an acute mind, further sensitized by <pb n="85" id="TruWhar85"/> trained feeling 
("trained down" perhaps), and critical to the point of satire. 
</p><p>If its evidences in her work are justly indicative of its 
importance, her critical proclivity must be considered as taking 
nearly as eminent a place among her powers as her creative faculty 
itself.  Although quite as much temperamental as intellectual in 
the matter it deals with, a preoccupation with the touchstones of 
educated feeling, a business chiefly of gauging the qualities, the 
cleverness of persons, it is yet very cool judgement and 
accompanies her creative power to the end of the chapter.  Her 
characters, the stars at least, share greatly in this power of 
criticism; it is merely in another capacity of their cleverness 
that they estimate themselves and their companions with precision.  
And the accuracy of their judgements is equalled by their finality; 
they "judge with their characters," which are notable for their 
stability of principle, for their chief principle, namely, cool and 
intelligent fineness of feeling, is a remarkable self-preservative.  
Their very stability is one of the factors entering into their ease 
of estimation; they are indeed stable&mdash;so stable that as they were 
in the beginning, so they are in the end.  Dr. Wyant was an 
exception, but one suspects in his degeneration an ulterior 
architectural purpose.  Certainly with all their mobility they 
advance in the same plane; and apparently their movements must 
remain horizontal, since neither growth nor decay but rather 
maturity is the condition of their temperamental acumen. 
</p><p>The rather cold fineness of Mrs. Leath is an example of this 
stability of temperament; her sensitiveness of principle added much 
to the poignancy of her situation in that it augmented her torture 
and remained to the end a hopelessly irreconcilable element in her 
compromise; she was perpetually crucified by the criticism her 
instinct passed upon the anomalous position which her passion for 
Darrow compelled her into.  Even more notable is the firmness to 
its principles of Justine Brent's warmer but more highly 
intellectualized temperament before the heavy shock of old Mr. 
Langhope's outraged feelings and her husband's involuntary recoil.  
Justine Brent is in this respect her creator's most distinct 
figure; no other of Mrs. Wharton's women is so certain of herself; 
in none is the native power of criticism sounder; in none is the 
integrity of feeling more absolute; in none is the tragedy much 
greater.  Miss Bart, to whom the reader naturally turns as the most 
distinguished of Mrs. Wharton's 
<pb n="86" id="TruWhar86"/>characters, shows ultimately 
the same infallibility of feeling, as her friend the rapid Mrs. 
Fisher so convincingly testified.  "I don't know what to make of 
her," that lady said; "she works like a slave preparing the ground 
and sowing the seed, and then when it comes time to harvest she 
either oversleeps herself or goes on a picnic. . . .  Sometimes I 
think it is because she at heart despises the things she is working 
for."  Miss Bart's power of criticism was indeed very coolly 
impartial and played over her wealthy acquaintances and herself 
alike; she knew them and knew herself, and saw their errors and her 
own with desperate clarity.  But however she might menace one 
aspect of herself with another, her fineness with her cleverness, 
she did, in spite of herself, "save herself whole from the wreck of 
her life." 
</p><p>Mrs. Wharton's characters are nearly all preoccupied with that 
great feat; and some of them, indeed, do so save themselves.  Sophy 
Viner was "ardently honest" with herself and made it the great 
point of her life to be true to her memory of Darrow.  Darrow did 
not fail to attempt the repair of that breach in his integrity 
which the indulgence of the gentleman's code had permitted; and it 
was due to the fineness of their textures and finish if the 
fragments of his identity repelled further decay when their 
principle of cohesion was so largely destroyed.  John Amherst and 
Lawrence Selden, Ralph Marvell and Raymond de Chelles are so 
evidently saved whole that they are saved from the dulness of cold 
overstability only by their distinction and serious cleverness.  
The subtly acute drama of Sanctuary lies in the saving whole of the 
fine feeling which Mrs. Peyton had instilled into her son Richard, 
whose lack of natural fineness had been inherited from his father.  
Indeed, the likelihood is that they will all be saved whole, for 
they are protected from excess by the power of their self-criticism; they know themselves; they think with ability and toward 
the end of preserving their integrity of feeling.  Perhaps they 
have learned their high lessons too well; their fineness is 
sometimes accompanied by coolness and they are not infrequently 
critical to the point of satire. 
</p><p>When the question is less of their self-critical quality than 
of general social judgment, the reader readily remembers the 
accomplished detachment of Mrs. Ansell.  The individual distinction 
that she achieves through her lens-like social insight&mdash;she is not 
surpassed in this point even by the great Miss Bart&mdash;is sufficient 
nearly to lay 
<pb n="87" id="TruWhar87"/> 
the suspicion that she is a <hi rend="italic">dea ex machina</hi>.  Her practice of tact on 
every occasion, as the most artificial thing about her, is the mark for 
ironical animadversions on the part of her author; but her delicate 
impartiality and the imaginative quality of her judgment command respect.  She 
is unique among even the more eminent of Mrs. Wharton's social critics in 
combining so exact a capacity for estimation and characterization 
with apparently so little temptation to use it ironically.  By 
heredity, by environment, by the force of her own temperament she 
was with the enemies of John Amherst; yet she understood him as 
none of them did, certainly as the delicately sarcastic old Mr. 
Langhope did not.  Mr. Langhope was, in fact, even in his silences 
and omissions, critical to the point of satire; he is not the 
cleverest of Mrs. Wharton's characters, but he is nearly as typical 
as any, for he has the generally cool and ironically detached 
attitude, such as Miss Bart had for the wealthy and stupid Percy 
Gryce, or as Justine Brent had for Westy Gaines.  The security of 
such an attitude lies in the knowing that one's own sense of 
fitness is adequate; and of this they are, properly no doubt, sure.  
These superior persons are distinguished in their field of social 
criticism, which, if it is transient, is yet an art. 
</p><p>The element of critical detachment contributes traceably to 
produce the acute definition characteristic of Mrs. Wharton's art.  
The fiction of few contemporary writers has so much distinctness; 
it is like that produced by many touches of a fine abrasive or a 
dilute acid.  The edges may sometimes come out too sharp, as in The 
Custom of the Country and the most sardonic of her short stories; 
but if she does not stop this side satire, if she does not always 
avoid angularity, she does achieve distinctness.  Indeed Summer, 
her latest novel, but one, gives countenance to the idea that the 
direction of her art is permanently toward impersonal distinctness 
as the one merit.  Apparently her former virtues of fineness, which 
so well offset the marble-like qualities of her art, are sacrificed 
to bringing out the edges, which are as clear and hard as those of 
Kipling at his hardest; it is a not too pleasing change from 
carving in social ivory to graving in sociological steel.  The 
reader will regret to find that this is the end apparently toward 
which the acuity of her stories points, though his regret will not 
be that steel engraving is without worth but that it is worth 
considerably less than carving.  The subject of her fiction has 
never before been so utterly harsh, or the distinctness 
<pb n="88" id="TruWhar88"/>with 
which it is depicted so boldly detached, so painful to the reader.  
Distinctness, though, is perhaps the only artistic refuge, except 
style, from the harsh subject, or that one with which the artist's 
sympathies are imperfect.  One suspects that distinctness has 
sometimes been her refuge in drawing the masculine character.  
Aside from the cool, grave cleverness of temperament which is the 
<hi rend="italic">primum mobile</hi> of their virtues, her men have distinctness as 
their chief merit.  They are rather more distinct than masculine. 
</p><p>If Mrs. Wharton is anywhere to be found dealing with qualities 
decidedly masculine, it would be in the case of Ethan Frome.  His 
jealousy was a very little modified and very masculine thing, 
compared to which the complicated emotion of Owen Leath seems 
somewhat trifling and the violence of George Dorset somewhat 
hectic.  His rather aboriginal "big talk" is something to smile at, 
but a manly failing.  His confused stammer when his wife caught him 
in his one fabrication, showed a masculine lack of "suppleness in 
deceiving," much inferior to George Darrow's capacity for quiet 
half-truths.  His whole simplicity in the hands of his wife sets 
him apart from the average of Mrs. Wharton's heroes: Mr. Langhope, 
for instance, was managed by his old friend Mrs. Ansell, but only 
with difficulty; George Darrow was a subtler person than either 
Sophy Viner or Mrs. Leath; even the fascinating Miss Bart was not 
superior to Lawrence Selden; and Justine Brent's benevolent 
imposition on her husband was possibly less because he was not 
clever than because she was extremely clever.  Ethan's pleasure in 
his masculine accomplishments, his inarticulateness in the presence 
of Mattie, his clumsy wit, his gropings after the proper word&mdash;such 
things bespeak a masculine ingenuousness often submerged and 
sometimes subverted in the calm drawing-rooms that figure in Mrs. 
Wharton's pages. 
</p><p>On another side, however, he shows the qualities that run 
counter and ally him with the Dagonets and Fairfords and Madame de 
Treymes: he has the undeveloped elements of their cool and sober 
cleverness, their intelligence, their fineness of feeling, their 
soundness of temperament, and, despite his clumsiness, their 
delicacy.  He tortured himself as to the fancied vulgarity or 
inappropriateness of the things he said to Mattie Silver; he was at 
a disadvantage in his quarrel with his wife because of his disgust 
at its sordidness and venom.  At the end he was held back from 
seeking his freedom by his moral integrity. <pb n="89" id="TruWhar89"/> 
 
</p><p>"With the sudden perception of the point to which his madness 
had carried him, the madness fell and he saw his life before him as 
it was.  He was a poor man, the husband of a sickly woman, whom his 
desertion would leave alone and destitute; and even if he had had 
the heart to desert her, he could have done so only by deceiving 
two kindly people who had pitied him. 
</p><p>"He turned and walked slowly back to the farm." 
 
</p><p>Mrs. Wharton has more distinguished characters than Ethan 
Frome, more involved and perhaps more spectacularly executed scenes 
than those grim ones which take place in the cold farmhouse of 
Starkfield; yet the best of her other work achieves no more tragic 
proportions, nor more surely brings the reader back to the 
permanent possibilities of human nature. 
</p><p>Ethan Frome, compared to Mrs. Wharton's other works, although 
it presents as most obvious the spectacle of a religiously 
transferred technic, still does not convince the reader of the 
vital importance of technic.  That social criticism which acted as 
a resolvent of drawing-room involutions and so well expounded the 
subtleties of the ultra-civilized consciousness, has diminished 
here, and unobtrusively readapted itself when set to work on the 
relatively simple souls of Ethan Frome and Mattie Silver.  The 
rich, involved matter which, in Pater's opinion, is the challenge 
and promise of a fine effect, is no longer here; yet the effect is, 
and would point the reader to the obvious conclusion that an 
artist's technic matters less than the quality and quantity of his 
imagination.  And in this all-decisive power Mrs. Wharton has a 
large share; but it is of the sort better described as having the 
characteristic of light than of heat.  Its images and their 
relationships seem rather the result of deliberate pause and focus 
than the blowing up of such a great conflagration as makes the 
pages of Frank Norris's Octopus lurid.  Light is a better word than 
heat to associate with the impersonality and severe detachment of 
Mrs. Wharton's imagination, with its very rational coolness, with 
the meagreness of its humour, with its very restrained passion, 
with its selective tendency to linger upon beauty, with the clarity 
of its satiric glance. 
</p><p>It seems, indeed, an eminently interior imagination, of which 
Ethan Frome, as the chief digression from its chosen field, but 
distinguishes that field more definitely.  Topographically, it is 
not <pb n="90" id="TruWhar90"/> extensive, for though it ranges through two continents, 
it moves by an itinerary of drawing-rooms, and the unvarying 
<hi rend="italic">terminus ad quem</hi> of its travels is a drawing-room.  Its 
embodied images are indigenous to the drawing-room atmosphere, 
which, should they walk abroad, remains a fine aura about them, an 
<hi rend="italic">air</hi>.  The reader could hardly imagine the great Miss Bart 
"camping out," and would likely suspect that Undine Spragg's scorn 
of Apex City is the fruit of her first lessons in drawing-room 
perspective.  The distinguished gentlemen and ladies in The Valley 
of Decision are at their best chiefly in noble drawing rooms; the 
soft panorama of northern Italy described in this novel is viewed 
evidently with an indoor eye.  But this is only to say that Mrs. 
Wharton's imagination is subjugated by the definite taste of those 
"old families" whose traditional gentility is still fertilized by 
hereditary cleverness.  The inveteracy of such taste is shown but 
too well in the mordant irony to which she subjects the merely 
fashionable section of her world of drawing-rooms.  It is too 
sharp, not as satire, but as art, for its obvious extremity, to 
which she sometimes pushes it, is caricature.  The reader who 
remembers the first abode of Undine Spragg in New York as the Hotel 
Stentorian may reasonably reflect that while two such names are 
well aimed darts at the socially ambitious of America, to spend 
much of one's skill in such marksmanship, is to deviate from the 
art of fiction. 
</p><p>And one is not long in concluding that these novels are too 
specialized to be the epic of America.  They are not spacious 
enough, or populous, or noisy, or grandiloquent, or full enough of 
"energy divine," although they are powerful in their chosen 
direction.  One is surprised to find in any of them the figure of 
a captain of finance, but not surprised that when he appears he is 
on a vacation and that the financial part of his life is lived 
elsewhere than in the story.  Mrs. Wharton's treatment of what to 
Americans is the greatest of the passions is a shade too mature to 
fit the American temper well.  She is too acute for sentiment, 
commercialism, and aboriginality, some notes of which apparently 
must be sounded in the future epic, if we may prognosticate from 
the vast public appeal of Mrs. Gene Stratton-Porter, the popular 
magazines, and Jack London.  Mrs. Wharton's novels are like the 
well-geared social establishments of her own inner circle.  Their 
tone is that of rather cool good sense, fine shades, delicate 
discrimination, things said without words, of everything that 
Undine Spragg would take for plain or monotonous <pb n="91" id="TruWhar91"/> &mdash;in short, 
of modulated cleverness.  Speed, vulgarity, vastness, 
unconventionality even, if it be excessive, find no place except 
the ironic in her pages. 
</p><p>The art of fiction would seem by now almost a traditional 
field for the assertion of feminine emancipation; but if Mrs. 
Wharton can be said to assert any emancipation at all, it is only 
that of the individual woman who frees herself by the force of her 
own character and talent.  The emancipation of her sex is a note 
she does not sound, doubtless because she believes in equality.  
For evidence of her belief that civilized women are on a practical 
equality with civilized men is to be found in the irony with which 
she handles the heroines of the divorce court.  That she regards 
them as both shirkers and imperialists might reasonably be inferred 
from the fact that she makes Charles Bowen describe Undine Spragg 
as the product of the "custom of the country,"&mdash;the custom, that 
is, of allowing wives to shirk the responsibility of an intelligent 
share in their husbands' interests, and further, of allowing them 
to lay violent hands on fundamental social conventions for the sake 
of their own convenience, to make their first appeal to what should 
be the court of last resort.  The sharpness of her satire of the 
vulgar and insensible, the fashionable, the divorced, is 
significant of the essential conservatism of her regard for the 
civilized <hi rend="italic">status quo</hi> and the conventions of educated 
sensibility.  Perhaps her eminence as an artist, joined to the fact 
that she is a woman, will lead to her being called a New Woman&mdash;we 
are vague about such words.  But if she is to be called a New Woman 
truly, it will be because she is doing a relatively new thing for 
a New Woman to do: namely, defending some of the oldest things in 
our civilization. 
</p> 
 
</div1> 
</body> 
</text> 
</TEI.2> 
