<?xml version="1.0"?>

<?dlps id="TurDesp"?>
<?dlps page-images="none" figure-images="no"?>
<?dlps transcription="other"?>

<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/tei-p4/tei2.dtd" [
<!ENTITY % POSTKB "INCLUDE">
<!ENTITY % TEI.extensions.ent SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.ent">
<!ENTITY % TEI.extensions.dtd SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.dtd">
<!ENTITY % ISOnum SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/charent/iso-num.ent"> %ISOnum;
<!ENTITY % ISOlat1 SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/charent/iso-lat1.ent"> %ISOlat1;
<!ENTITY % ISOpub SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/charent/iso-pub.ent"> %ISOpub;
 
]> 
<TEI.2 id="TurDesp"> 
<teiHeader type="migrated" creator="Etext">
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title type="main">Desperate</title>
<title type="sort">desperate</title>
<author>Turgenev, Ivan</author>
<respStmt>
<resp>Creation of machine-readable version:</resp>  
<name>Judy Boss</name>  
<resp>Creation of digital images:</resp>  
<name/>  
<resp>Conversion to TEI.2-conformant markup:</resp>  
<name>University of Virginia Library Electronic Text Center.</name>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt>  
<extent>ca. <num type="kilobytes">48</num> kilobytes</extent>  
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>University of Virginia Library</publisher>
<pubPlace>Charlottesville, Virginia</pubPlace>  
<idno type="ETC">TurDesp</idno>  
<date value="1996">1996</date>
<availability status="public">
<p n="copyright">Copyright &copy; 1996 by the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia</p>
<p n="access">Publicly accessible</p>
</availability>
<idno type="uva-pid">uva-lib:476403</idno>
</publicationStmt>
<seriesStmt>
<title>University of Virginia Library, Text collection</title>
<idno type="uva-set">UVA-LIB-Text</idno>
</seriesStmt>  
<notesStmt>
<note>
<p>Emendation page 338, section 4, para. 8: to gives a crack ] to give a crack</p>
</note>  
<note>
<p>Electronic version has not been checked against print source by Electronic Text Center.</p>
</note>
</notesStmt>  
<sourceDesc>
<biblFull>
<titleStmt>
<title type="main">Desperate</title>
<title level="j">Cosmopolitan</title>
<title type="sort">desperate</title>
<author>Ivan Turgenev</author>
<respStmt>
<resp>Translator</resp>  
<name>Charlotte Adams</name>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt>  
<extent>pp 335-344</extent>  
<publicationStmt>  
<date value="1888-08">August 1888</date>  
<idno type="callNo">Print source not available.</idno>
</publicationStmt>  
<notesStmt>
<note>
<p>Cosmopolitan, Vol. 5, Aug. 1888.</p>
</note>  
<note>
<p>Bibliographic information for print source not checked against original.</p>
</note>
</notesStmt>
</biblFull>
</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc>  
<encodingDesc>
<projectDesc>
<p>Prepared for the University of Virginia Library Electronic Text Center.</p>
</projectDesc>  
<editorialDecl>
<p>All quotation marks retained as data.</p>  
<p>All unambiguous end-of-line hyphens have been removed, and the trailing part of a word has been joined to the preceding line.</p>  
<p>Keywords in the header are a local Electronic Text Center scheme to aid in establishing analytical groupings.</p>
</editorialDecl>  
</encodingDesc>  
<profileDesc>
<creation>
<date value="1888">1888</date>
</creation>  
<langUsage>
<language id="eng" usage="main">English</language>
</langUsage>  
<textClass>
<keywords>
<term>fiction; prose</term>  
<term>Literature in Translation</term>
</keywords>  
</textClass>
</profileDesc>  
<revisionDesc>
<change>
<date value="1996-10">October 1996</date>  
<respStmt>
<resp>corrector</resp>  
<name>Stephen Ramsay, Electronic Text Center</name>
</respStmt>  
<item>Added TEI header and tags.</item>
</change>
<change>
<date value="2007-09">September 2007</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>Migration</resp>
<name>Ethan Gruber, University of Virginia Library</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Converted XML markup from TEI Lite to uva-dl-tei (TEI P4 with local customizations).</item>
</change>
<change>
<date value="2008-01">January 2008</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>Migration</resp>
<name>Greg Murray, University of Virginia Library</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Programmatically updated TEI header markup (but not header content) for minimal compliance with current QA requirements.</item>
</change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>  
<text id="d1">  
 
<body id="d2"> 
 

 
<div1 type="story" id="d3"> <pb n="335"/>  
<head>DESPERATE.<lb/> 
 BY IVAN TOURGUENEFF.<lb/> 
(Translated Directly from the Russian by Charlotte Adams.) 
</head> 
 
<div2 type="section" n="1" id="d4"><head>I.</head><lb/> 
 
<p>THERE were eight men of us in the room, and we were 
discoursing of contemporary events and people. 
</p><p>"I do not understand these gentlemen," remarked A.  "They are, 
as it were, desperate&mdash;truly desperate.  There was never yet 
anything like it!" 
</p><p>"No&mdash;there was," interposed P., an already old, gray-haired 
man; "desperate people have been plentiful before; only they did 
not resemble the desperate people of to-day.  Some one said of the 
poet Yasicoff that in him was ecstasy, not directed toward 
anything&mdash;objectless ecstasy.  So it was with those people&mdash;their 
despair was objectless.  Let me relate to you the history of my 
cousin's son, Misha Polteff.  It may serve as an example of the 
desperation of those days.  He appeared in God's world in the year 
1828, on the ancestral estate of his father, in one of the most 
obscure corners of an obscure province of the steppes.  Misha's 
father, Andre&iuml; Nikolaevitch Polteff, I still remember well.  
He was a true landowner of the old school, a pious, serious man, 
sufficiently well educated for that time.  To tell the truth, he 
was a little crazy and suffering from epilepsy.  But these are old-school and aristocratic maladies.  With andre&iuml; Nikolaevitch, 
the paroxysms were mild, and they generally resolved themselves 
into sleep and melancholy.  He was good-hearted, affable, and not 
without a certain haughtiness.  The whole life of Andre&iuml; 
Nikolaevitch was passed in the prompt performance of all the 
ceremonies established from remote times, in strict conformity with 
all the customs of the ancient, orthodox, holy Russian existence.  
He rose and went to bed, ate and drank and bathed, was merry or 
angry (though the second, in truth, rarely happened), even smoked 
his pipe and played cards (two great innovations!), not as it 
occurred to him to do after his own fashion, but after the law and 
ordinance of his fathers&mdash;exactly and formally.  He was of high 
stature, well-formed and fleshy; he had a soft and somewhat hoarse 
voice, as is often the case with worthy Russians; he observed 
neatness in his linen and dress, wore white cravats and tobacco-colored, long-skirted surtouts&mdash;but his noble blood always showed 
itself; no one would have taken him for a priest's son or a 
shopkeeper.  Always, upon all possible occasions and meetings, 
Andre&iuml; Nikolaevitch invariably knew how to act, what to say, 
and precisely what expressions to use; he knew when he ought to 
doctor himself, and exactly with what&mdash;in which omens he ought to 
believe, and which might be left unnoticed; in a word, he knew 
everything that it was proper to do.  For to old men everything is 
foreseen and ordained.  One does not merely imagine it for one's 
self.  And the essential thing <hi rend="italic">is</hi>, 
'Without God, not over the threshold.'<ref target="n355">*</ref>  

It must be confessed a mortal dullness reigned in 
his house, in those low, warm and dark rooms, so often resounding 
with vesper hymns and Te Deums, and pervaded with the almost 
irremovable odor of incense and lenten food. 
</p><p>"Andre&iuml; Nikolaevitch, when no longer in his first youth, 
married a poor gentlewoman, a neighbor of his, a very nervous and 
sickly person, educated at a boarding-school.  She played on the 
piano not badly, she spoke French after the boarding-school manner.  
She willingly abandoned herself to ecstasy, and still more 
willingly did she give herself up to melancholy and even to tears.  
In a word, her character was the reverse of tranquil.  Accounting 
her life unhappy, she could not love her husband, who 'assuredly' 
did not understand her; but she respected and tolerated him, and 
being a perfectly honorable and passionless creature, she never 
once even thought of another 'object.'  Besides, she was constantly 
absorbed by cares firstly, for her own really feeble health; 
secondly, for the health of her husband, whose paroxysms always 
inspired her with a superstitious terror, and lastly, for 
<pb n="336"/>  
her only son, Misha, whom she educated herself with great zeal.  
Andre&iuml; Nikolaevitch did not interfere with his wife's training 
of Misha, upon the condition that under no pretext whatever should 
a departure be made from the order, once for all determined, in 
which all should proceed in his house. 
 
 
</p>
</div2>
<div2 type="section" n="2" id="d5"><head>II.</head><lb/>  
 
<p>"I REMEMBER this Misha at thirteen years of age.  He was a 
very pretty boy, with rosy cheeks and soft lips (indeed, he was 
quite soft and plump all over), with somewhat prominent, humid 
eyes; he was carefully combed and brushed, caressing and modest&mdash;a 
perfect little girl.  Only one thing in him did not please me; he 
laughed rarely, but when he did laugh, his teeth, large, white, and 
pointed, like those of a wild beast, were unpleasantly displayed, 
and in the laugh itself sounded something sharp and even fierce, 
almost like a wild beast, and through his eyes ran evil sparks.  
His mother praised him because he was so obedient and polite, and 
did not love to associate with wanton boys, but attached himself 
more and more to the society of women.  'A milksop!' his father, 
Andre&iuml; Nikolaevitch, said of him.  'A mamma's baby, but he 
goes willingly to the Lord's temple, and this rejoices me.'  One 
old man, a neighbor, a former police commissioner, said once before 
me of Misha, 'By your leave, he will be a rebel,' and this speech, 
I remember, then very much astonished me.  The former police 
commissioner truly saw the rebel everywhere. 
</p><p>"Precisely such an exemplary youth did Misha remain until the 
eighteenth year of his age, up to the very death of his parents, 
whom he lost almost on one and the same day.  Living constantly at 
Moscow, I heard nothing of my young relative.  It is true, a person 
who came from his province assured me that Misha had sold his 
paternal estate for a song, but this news appeared to me 
incredible. 
</p><p>"Suddenly, one autumn morning, a barouche entered the 
courtyard of my house, drawn by an excellent pair of trotters, with 
a monstrous coachman on the box; and in the barouche, wrapped in a 
cloak of military cut, with two 
arsheen <ref target="n336">*</ref> of otter fur collar, with 
his traveling-cap worn on one side in a devil-may-care fashion, sat 
Misha!  Seeing me (I stood at the window of the drawing-room, and 
gazed with astonishment at the entering equipage), he began to 
laugh his sharp laugh, and lightly throwing aside the ends of the 
cloak, jumped from the barouche and ran into the house. 
</p><p>"'Misha!  Mikha&iuml;l Andre&euml;vitch!' I began.  'Is this 
you?' 
</p><p>"'Call me "thou" and "Misha,"' he interrupted me.  'Yes, this 
is I&mdash;in my own person.  I have appeared in Moscow, to look at the 
people, and to show myself! and so I drove to you.  What trotters, 
eh!' he again began to laugh. 
</p><p>"Although seven years had passed since I had last seen Misha, 
I recognized him immediately.  His face had remained quite 
youthful, and was, as before, charming; even the mustache had not 
yet pierced through, only there was a puffiness in his cheeks, 
under his eyes, and from his mouth came the odor of wine. 
</p><p>"'And have you been long in Moscow?' I asked.  'I supposed 
that you were managing your estate.' 
</p><p>"'Ah! the estate I immediately put one side.  As soon as my 
parents (may the kingdom of heaven be theirs!) died (Misha crossed 
himself, simply, without the slightest mockery), I immediately, 
without the least delay&mdash;one&mdash;two&mdash;three&mdash;ha! ha!  It slipped off 
cheaply&mdash;trickery!  The rascal so insinuated himself!  O well, it 
is all the same.  At least, I live to my satisfaction, and I amuse 
others.  But why do you stare at me so?  Was it possible for me to 
drag the thing along any further?  Little dove of a cousin, can not 
one have a glass?' 
</p><p>"Misha spoke with extreme rapidity, and at the same time as if 
half asleep. 
</p><p>"'Misha!  For Heaven's sake!  Fear God!  Whom do you 
resemble&mdash;with such a look?  And asking for a glass!  And to sell 
so fine an estate for nothing!' 
</p><p>"'I always fear and remember God,' he replied.  'And really he 
is good&mdash;God&mdash;to pardon.  And I also am good.  I never yet in my 
life harmed any one.  And a little glass is also good.  It harms no 
one.  Little uncle, do you wish me to spin round the table with a 
cord, whip out the ace with my last?  Or shall I dance a little?' 
<pb n="337"/>  
</p><p>"'Pray spare me!  What, dance here!  You would better sit 
down.' 
</p><p>"'I will sit down.  But why do you say nothing to me about my 
grays?  Look, they are really lions.  Until now I have hired them, 
but I shall undoubtedly buy them, together with the coachman.  And 
I really had the money; yes, I let it slip yesterday at the 
gambling-table.  It is nothing!  We shall revenge ourselves tomorrow.  Uncle, how about the little glass!' 
</p><p>"'By your leave, I could no longer contain myself.  Misha, how 
old are you?  Not with horses, not with card-playing, should you 
busy yourself, but should enter either the university or the army.' 
</p><p>"Misha at first again began to laugh, then whistled 
protractedly.  'Well, uncle, I see you are now in a melancholy 
frame of mind.  I will drop in another time.  Here is something for 
you.  Drive out in the evening to the "Falconer."  There is a tent 
erected for me.  The gipsies sing.  Will you?  Only observe, and on 
the tent is a pennon, and on the pennon in magical gold letters is 
written "Chorus of Polteff Gipsies!"  The pennon curves itself like 
a snake&mdash;the letters are golden&mdash;it is enticing to every one to 
read.  Refreshments for whoever wishes it; I refuse nothing.  The 
dust has gone all over Moscow.  My respects!  Will you come?  And&mdash; 
there is with me there such an&mdash;aspic!  Black as a boot&mdash;wicked as 
a dog&mdash;and eyes&mdash;coals!  It is impossible to tell whether she will 
kiss or bite.  Will you come, uncle?  Well, until we meet!' 
</p><p>"And suddenly embracing me and slapping me on the shoulder, 
Misha hurried into the court and into the barouche, waved his 
traveling-cap above his head, gave a yell, and the monstrous 
coachman squinted at him across his beard, the trotters tore off, 
and all disappeared. 
</p><p>"On the following day I, sinful man, drove out to the 
'Falconer,' and actually saw the tent with the pennon and 
inscription. 
</p><p>"The skirts of the tent were raised; noise, tumult, yells 
proceeded thence.  The people crowded around; on the ground, on a 
spread carpet sat gipsy men and women, who sang and beat 
kettledrums; and in the midst of them, with guitar in his hands, in 
a red silk shirt and wide velvet trousers, whirled Misha, turning 
a pirouette.  'Gentlemen!  Your reverences!  We ask your mercy!  
The performance will begin immediately.  Gratis,' cried he, in a 
cracked voice.  'Hollo!  Champagne!  Clap!  On the forehead!  On 
the floor!' 
</p><p>"Luckily he did not see me, and I hastened to withdraw. 
</p><p>"I will not, gentlemen, enlarge my astonishment at the sight 
of such an alteration.  And indeed, how could this gentle and 
modest boy have changed suddenly into a drunken wag?  Is it 
possible that all this lurked in him in childhood, and showed 
itself as soon as the pressure of parental authority was removed 
from him?  And that 'dust went from him over Moscow,' as he 
expressed himself, there was certainly no longer any kind of doubt.  
I led a wild life at his age, but here appeared something frenzied, 
a certain madness of self-destruction, a desperation. 
 
 
</p>
</div2>
<div2 type="section" n="3" id="d6"><head>III.</head><lb/>  
 
<p>"THIS amusement lasted two months.  I stood again at the 
window of the drawing-room and looked out on the court.  A novice-monk entered the gate with a slow step.  A conical cap was drawn 
down on his forehead, his hair fell scattered right and left under 
it&mdash;he wore a long cassock with a leathern girdle.  Could it be 
Misha?  It was he. 
</p><p>"I went to the stairway to meet him.  'What is this 
masquerade?' I asked. 
</p><p>"'It is not a masquerade, uncle,' Misha answered me, with a 
deep sigh; 'but as I have spent my fortune to the last copeck, and 
as powerful repentance has taken possession of me, I have decided 
to set off for the Sergius monastery of the Holy Trinity to pray 
for my sins.  For what asylum now remains to me?  And I have come 
to take leave of you, uncle, as a prodigal son.' 
</p><p>"I looked steadfastly at Misha.  His face was as rosy and 
fresh as ever (for that matter, it did not change to the last), his 
eyes were humid and kind, somewhat languid, his small hands were 
white&mdash;but, he smelt of wine. 
</p><p>"'Well?' I said at length; 'the affair is good if there be no 
other way out!  But why do you smell of wine?' 
</p><p>"'Old leaven,' answered Misha, and suddenly began to laugh, 
but immediately recollecting himself, he bent low and straight in 
a monastic salute and added, 'If you please 
<pb n="338"/>  
something&mdash;a 
little luck-greeting for the journey.  I am really going on foot to 
the monastery.' 
</p><p>"'When?' 
</p><p>"'To-day&mdash;directly.' 
</p><p>"'Why, then, are you in such a hurry?' 
</p><p>"'Uncle!  My motto has always been&mdash;"Faster!  Faster!"' 
</p><p>"'And what is your motto now?' 
</p><p>"'It is the same also now&mdash;only faster to the&mdash;good!' 
</p><p>"So Misha went away, leaving me to meditate over the 
vicissitudes of human destinies.  But he soon reminded me of his 
existence.  Two months after his visit, I received from him a 
letter, the first of those letters with which he subsequently 
favored me.  And mark the singularity!  I have rarely seen a neater 
and more legible handwriting than this scatterbrained fellow 
possessed.  And the style of his letter was very correct, slightly 
oratorical.  Invariable demands for assistance alternated with 
promises of reform, with honorable speeches and vows.  All this 
seemed, and possibly was, sincere.  Misha's scrawl under the 
letter, was continually accompanied by peculiar flourishes, dashes, 
periods, and a great many exclamation-marks.  In this first letter, 
Misha informed me of the new 'turn of his fortunes.'  Subsequently 
he called these turns 'plunges,' and he 'plunged' often.  He was 
going out to the Caucasus to serve 'with his breast,' his tsar and 
country in the capacity of a cavalry subaltern.  And although a 
certain benevolent aunt came to the relief of his distressed 
condition and sent him a small sum, he asked my assistance in 
equipping himself.  I acceded to his demand, and heard nothing of 
him again for the space of two years.  I confess, I strongly 
doubted whether he had gone to the Caucasus.  But it appeared that 
he had gone thither, that through patronage he had entered the 
T&mdash; regiment as an under-officer, and served in it these two 
years.  The wildest stories were afloat concerning him.  They were 
related to me by an officer of his regiment. 
 
 
</p>
</div2>
<div2 type="section" n="4" id="d7"><head>IV.</head>
 
<p>"I LEARNED much of a kind that I had not expected from him.  
It did not astonish me, assuredly, that as a military man, as an 
ardent soldier, he should show himself inferior, even, frankly, 
worthless; but what I did not expect was this: that personal 
bravery was not remarked in him, that in battle he wore a 
melancholy and drooping look, now bored, now alarmed.  All 
discipline oppressed him, inspired him with sadness; he was bold to 
madness when the matter concerned only himself personally; there 
was no wager so foolish that he would refuse to accept it; but to 
injure another&mdash;to kill&mdash;to fight&mdash;this he could not do; it might 
have been because his heart was good, and it might have been 
because his 'cotton-wool education,' as he expressed it, had made 
him effeminate.  He was always and forever ready to destroy 
himself, but others&mdash;no.  'The devil will take him away,' his 
companions remarked of him.  'He is withered up!  A clout!  And a 
desperate one!  Truly, a confirmation-child!' 
</p><p>"Subsequently I asked Misha how this evil report got about&mdash; 
what obliged him to drink deep, to risk his life, and so forth?  He 
had always the same answer&mdash;'grief.' 
</p><p>"'How, if you please, grief?' 
</p><p>"'One comes thus to one's self&mdash;one regains one's senses&mdash;one 
falls to meditating over poverty&mdash;over injustice&mdash;over Russia!  
Well&mdash;it is done!  Immediately&mdash;grief&mdash;as if there were a bullet in 
one's forehead.  One begins to debauch, in spite of one's self.' 
</p><p>"'What made you drag yourself back hither to Russia?' 
</p><p>"'Only this!  I am afraid to think of it.' 
</p><p>"'All this grief of yours comes from inactivity.' 
</p><p>"'But I do not know how to do anything, uncle&mdash;cousin.  To 
wager even my life at cards, to play parole, to give a crack on 
the collar&mdash;this I know how to do.  You, here, tell me how I can 
risk my life for something.' 
</p><p>"'But why not live a simple life?  Why risk it?' 
</p><p>"'I can not&mdash;you say I act without reflection.  One begins to 
reflect&mdash;and at once riot ferments in one's head.  Only these 
Germans reflect.' 
</p><p>"How could one manage to talk with him?  Desperate&mdash; 
completely! 
</p><p>"Among the number of Caucasian stories which I mentioned I 
shall relate to you two or three.  Once, in a company of officers, 
Misha began to boast of a bartered saber&mdash;a genuine Persian blade.  
The officers expressed a doubt as to its genuineness. 
<pb n="339"/>  
Misha 
began to argue.  'Well,' exclaimed he, at length, 'they say in the 
matter of blades the first connoisseur is Abdulka the Crooked.  I 
will go to him and inquire.' 
</p><p>"The officers were astonished.  'Who is this Abdulka?  The one 
who lives in the hills&mdash;not the tributary, Abdul Khan?' 
</p><p>"'He himself!' 
</p><p>"'He will arrest you as a spy and put you in prison, provided 
he does not cut off your head with this very sword.  And how shall 
you reach him?  They will kill you immediately.' 
</p><p>"'All the same I will go to him.' 
</p><p>"'A wager that you do not go.  A wager!' 
</p><p>"And Misha immediately saddled his horse and rode off to 
Abdulka.  Three days passed.  All were convinced that he had come 
to the end predicted.  Behold, he returned&mdash;somewhat intoxicated, 
and with a saber&mdash;only not that which he had taken away.  They 
began to question him.  'It is nothing,' he said.  'Abdulka is a 
good man.  At first, truly, he ordered my feet to be fettered and 
prepared to impale me.  I explained to him why I had come, and 
showed him the saber.  "Do not detain me," and "do not expect a 
ransom for me.  I have not a copeck to my name, and I have no 
relations."  Abdulka was astonished; he gazed at me with his 
solitary eye.  "Now," he says, "you rogue, you!  Ought I to believe 
you?"  "Believe me," I said: "I never lie" (and really Misha never 
lied).  Again Abdulka gazed at me.  "Do you know how to drink 
wine?"  "I know how," I said.  "I will drink as much as you will 
give me."  Again Abdulka was astonished, called upon Allah.  And 
hereupon he bade his little daughter (very pretty, only with a look 
like a jackal) to drag in the wineskin.  And I fell to work.  "But 
your saber," said he, "is counterfeit&mdash;here, take a genuine one.  
Now we are friends."  And you have lost your wager, gentlemen.  
Pay!' 
</p><p>"The second legend of Misha is of like nature.  He loved cards 
passionately, but as money was not abundant with him, and he did 
not pay card-debts (although a cheater he never was), no one would 
play with him.  He once began to urge one of his fellow-officers&mdash; 
he really must play with him. 
</p><p>"'And if you lose, you will not pay.' 
</p><p>"'I will not pay with money, but I will shoot myself through 
the left hand with this very pistol.' 
</p><p>"'And what advantage will there be to me in this?' 
</p><p>"'No advantage, but all the same it will be interesting.' 
</p><p>"This conversation took place after a drinking-bout, before 
witnesses.  Misha's proposition did appear interesting to the 
officer.  The cards were brought, the game began.  Misha was in 
luck&mdash;he won a hundred roubles. 
</p><p>"Hereupon his adversary struck himself on the forehead.  'What 
a booby I am!' he exclaimed.  'What a snare I have fallen into!  If 
you had lost, you would have shot yourself through the hand&mdash;but 
now you hold your pistol-pocket fast.' 
</p><p>"'You have lied,' replied Misha.  'I have won, and I will 
shoot myself through the hand.'  He seized the pistol.  Pop!  The 
ball passed through, and a week later the wound was completely 
healed. 
</p><p>"Still another time Misha was riding along a road at night 
with his companions.  And they saw by the side of the road yawn a 
narrow ravine, yawning&mdash;dark, very dark&mdash;the bottom not visible. 
</p><p>"'Here,' said one of his comrades, 'desperate as Misha is, he 
will not jump into this ravine.' 
</p><p>"'No, I will jump.' 
</p><p>"'No, you will not jump, because it is ten sajens 
<ref target="n337">*</ref> deep, and 
it is certain to break one's neck.' 
</p><p>"'But all the same I shall jump.  Do you want a bet?' 
</p><p>"'Ten roubles.' 
</p><p>"'Good!' 
</p><p>"And his comrade had not finished uttering this word when 
Misha was off his horse, at the ravine, and had begun to rattle 
down among the stones.  All were benumbed.  A full minute passed 
and they heard, borne up as it were from the bowels of the earth, 
the sound of Misha's voice. 
</p><p>"'I have fallen on sand.  But I flew a long time!  Ten roubles 
from you.' 
</p><p>"'Climb out!' his companions began to cry. 
</p><p>"'Yes&mdash;climb out,' retorted Misha.  'I should say so!  You 
must go for ropes and lanterns, and meanwhile, so that I do not get 
tired waiting, throw me down the flask.' 
 

<pb n="340"/>  
</p><p>"Misha sat five hours in the bottom of the ravine, and when 
they dragged him out his shoulder was dislocated&mdash;but this did not 
disturb him in the least.  On the following day, the bonesetter 
from the blacksmith's set his shoulder, and he handled him as if 
nothing were the matter. 
 
 
</p>
</div2>
<div2 type="section" n="5" id="d8"><head>V.</head><lb/>  
 
<p>"FROM the Caucasus he again appeared in Moscow, in Circassian 
costume, with cartridge-boxes on his breast, a dagger in his 
girdle, a high fur cap on his head.  He did not part with this 
costume until the end, although he was no longer in the military 
service, being expelled on account of his non-appearance at drill.  
He made a short call on me, borrowed a little money, and began 
another course of 'plunges' by begging.  Beautifully written 
letters were scattered abroad, addressed to all possible persons, 
beginning with the metropolite and ending with the riding-masters 
and professional nurses.  Visits were made to acquaintances and 
strangers.  But in making his visits he was neither servile nor 
importunate.  On the contrary, he bore himself decorously and even 
with a cheerful mien, although a chronic odor of wine accompanied 
him everywhere, and his Oriental costume by degrees became 
transformed into tatters.  'If you give, God will reward you, 
although I do not deserve it.  If you do not give, you will be 
quite right and I will not be at all angry.  I feed myself, thanks 
to God!  For there are people poorer than I and much more worthy of 
assistance&mdash;much, very much.' 
</p><p>"During his impecunious travels he reached his paternal nest, 
sold by him for a trifle to a well-known speculator and usurer.  
The speculator was at home, and hearing of the arrival of the 
former possessor, transformed into a vagrant, he gave orders that 
he should not be admitted into the house, and in case of need 
should even be thrust out by the neck.  Misha declared that he 
would not go into the house contaminated by the presence of the 
rogue, and he set off for the graveyard to pray over the dust of 
his parents.  In the graveyard he was joined by an old man, a 
house-servant, who had once been his nurse.  The speculator had 
deprived the old man of his monthly allowance and driven him away 
from the manor-house.  The latter had found a refuge in the corner 
of a peasant's hut.  Misha had not left behind him an especially 
good memory; but when the old servant learned of the arrival of his 
young lord, he immediately ran to the graveyard, found Misha 
sitting on the ground between the tombstones, asked of him for old 
memories' sake his little hand, and shed tears upon the tatters 
with which were clothed the once daintily attired limbs of his 
nursling.  Misha gazed long and silently at the old man. 
</p><p>"'Timothe&iuml;,' said he, at length. 
</p><p>"Timothe&iuml; shuddered.  'What is your pleasure?' 
</p><p>"'Have you a shovel?' 
</p><p>"'It is possible to procure one.  But what do you want a 
shovel for, Mr. Mikha&iuml;l Andre&iuml;tch?' 
</p><p>"'I wish to dig a little grave for myself here, 
Timothe&iuml;&mdash;yes, and to lie here forever and ever between my 
parents.  Truly, only one little place is left to me in the world.  
Bring the shovel.' 
</p><p>"'I obey,' said Timothe&iuml;.  He went and brought it.  And 
Misha immediately began to dig the earth and Timothe&iuml; stood 
near, supporting his chin on his hand, and repeating, 'Only you and 
I are left, lord.'  And Misha dug and dug, from time to time 
inquiring, 'It is really not worth while to live, is it, 
Timothe&iuml;?'  'It is not worth while, little father.'  The grave 
had already become tolerably deep.  The people saw Misha's work, 
and ran to report upon it to the new possessor.  The speculator was 
at first angry and wished to send for the police&mdash;this, then, is 
sacrilege!  But afterward, probably considering that to have an 
affair with this madman would be inexpedient and might result in 
scandal, he went to the graveyard and, approaching Misha, who was 
working for dear life, politely saluted him.  The latter continued 
to dig, as if not remarking his successor. 
</p><p>"'Mikha&iuml;l Andre&iuml;tch,' began the speculator, 'permit 
me to learn what you are doing here.' 
</p><p>"'Don't you see&mdash;I am digging a grave for myself.' 
</p><p>"'Why is this?' 
</p><p>"'Because I do not wish to live any longer.' 
</p><p>"The speculator raised his hands.  'You do not wish to live?' 
</p><p>"Misha looked menacingly at the speculator.  
<pb n="341"/>  
'Does 
this astonish you?  Are you not the cause of all&mdash;are you not?  Did 
you not, Judas, rob me, taking advantage of my youth?  Did you not 
tear the skin from the peasants?  Did you not deprive this decrepit 
man here of his bread?  Did you not?  O Lord!  Everywhere only 
injustice, and oppression, and wickedness.  Perish&mdash;it means&mdash;all.  
I do not wish to live&mdash;I do not&mdash;to live any longer in Russia!'  
And the shovel began to move still more rapidly in Misha's hands. 
</p><p>"'The devil knows what this all is,' thought the speculator; 
'really, in truth, he will bury himself.  Mikha&iuml;l 
Andre&iuml;tch,' he began again, 'listen; I am indeed guilty before 
you.  They did not so speak of you to me.'  Misha dug.  'But why 
this desperation?'  Misha went on digging, and threw the earth on 
the feet of the speculator.  'Will it not please you to come to my 
house to eat a bite and rest a little?' 
</p><p>"Misha slightly raised his head.  'And will there be some 
drinking?' 
</p><p>"'If you like.  Why should there not?' 
</p><p>"'And you invite Timothe&iuml;?' 
</p><p>"'Why not?  Him, too.' 
</p><p>"Misha began to reflect.  'Only, look you, you thrust me out 
into the world.  Do not think to escape with one little bottle.' 
</p><p>"'Do not be uneasy.  There shall be as much as you like of 
everything.' 
</p><p>"Misha rose and threw down the shovel.  'Well, Timothe&iuml;,' 
he turned to the old man-nurse, 'let us respect the master.  Let us 
go.' 
</p><p>"'I obey,' answered the old man.  And all three repaired to 
the house. 
</p><p>"The speculator knew with whom he had to deal.  Misha, it is 
true, at first made him promise that he would bestow upon the 
peasants immunity from all imposts; but an hour later that same 
Misha, together with Timothe&iuml;, both drunk, danced a gallopade 
in those very rooms in which still lodged the God-fearing phantom 
of Andre&iuml; Nikolaevitch, and an hour later, the heavily-sleeping Misha, lying in the telega together with his high fur cap 
and his dagger, set off for the city, twenty-five versts distant, 
and was lodged there under a shed.  As for Timothe&iuml;, who still 
stood on his feet and only hiccoughed, he was put out.  One does 
not get rid of a gentleman in the same way as of a servant. 
 
 
</p>
</div2>
<div2 type="section" n="6" id="d9"><head>VI.</head><lb/>  
 
<p>"AGAIN some time passed and I heard nothing of Misha.  God 
knows whither he had disappeared.  Here, once, sitting by the 
samovar in the station of the T&mdash; highway waiting for horses, I 
suddenly heard, under the open window of the waiting-room, a hoarse 
voice, saying in French, 'Sir! sir! take pity on a poor ruined 
gentleman.'  I raised my head and looked.  A mangy fur cap, broken 
cartridge-boxes on the torn Circassian coat, a dagger in a cracked 
sheath, a swollen but yet rosy face, disheveled but still thick 
hair&mdash;my God!  Misha!  He had begun to ask alms on the highway.  I 
involuntarily cried out.  He recognized me, shuddered, turned away.  
I detained him, but what was to be said to him&mdash;read him a moral 
lecture?  In silence I held out to him a five-rouble bank-note; he 
as silently took it, with his still white and plump, though 
trembling and dirty little hand, and disappeared round the corner 
of the house.  They were slow in bringing up the horses, and it 
troubled me that I had so coldly allowed him to go away.  I drove 
on farther, and at half a verst from the station I found before me 
on the road a crowd of people advancing with an odd, as it were, 
measured step.  I overtook this crowd, and what did I see?  Twelve 
beggar-men, with their bags across their shoulders, were walking, 
two and two, singing and leaping, and in front of them danced 
Misha, stamping his feet in time, and repeating "Ready and lively! 
step&mdash;step&mdash;step!'  As soon as my barouche stopped near him and he 
saw me, he immediately began to cry 'Halt!  Right about!  Front!  
Guard the highway!'  The beggars caught up his cry and stopped, and 
he with his customary laugh leaped onto the carriage step, and 
again cried 'Hurrah!' 
</p><p>"'What is all this?' I asked, in involuntary amazement. 
</p><p>"'This?  This is my corps, my army, all little beggars&mdash;God's 
people&mdash;comrades, friends.  Every one of them, through your 
kindness, has drunk a little glass; and hereupon we all rejoice and 
make merry.  Uncle, really only with beggars&mdash;with God's people&mdash;is 
it possible to live in the world.' 
</p><p>"I answered him nothing, but he seemed to me at this time such 
a good fellow, his 
<pb n="342"/>   
face expressed such childish 
ingenuousness, that something, as it were, suddenly flashed upon 
me, something pricked me in the heart. 
</p><p>"'Sit down by me in the carriage,' I said to him.  He was 
astonished. 
</p><p>"'What!  In the carriage?' 
</p><p>"'Sit down!  Sit down!' I repeated, 'I wish to make a 
proposition to you.  Sit down!  Let us go to my house!' 
</p><p>"'Well, as you command.'  He sat down. 
</p><p>"'Now, you dear friends, worthy comrades,' he said, turning to 
the beggars.  'Good-by, until we meet!'  Misha took off his fur cap 
and bowed low.  The beggars were all literally disconcerted.  I 
ordered the coachman to whip up the horses, and the carriage rolled 
on.  The thought had suddenly come to me to take him home to my 
country-house, at a distance of thirty versts from that station&mdash;to 
save him, or at least to attempt to. 
</p><p>"'Listen, Misha,' I said, 'do you wish to settle down with me?  
You shall live comfortably, you will be provided with clothes and 
linen, you shall be suitably equipped, and money will be given you 
for tobacco, and the like, on one condition&mdash;not to drink wine.  
Are you agreed?' 
</p><p>"Misha was even frightened with joy; he opened his eyes wide, 
grew purple, and suddenly falling on my shoulder, began to kiss me, 
and to repeat in a broken voice, 'Uncle&mdash;benefactor!  God reward 
you.'  He fell into a fit of weeping, and taking off his fur cap, 
occupied himself with wiping his eyes, nose and lips. 
</p><p>"'Remember the promise&mdash;not to drink wine.' 
</p><p>"'And may it be cursed,' he exclaimed, flourishing both arms, 
still more strongly enveloping me in that spirituous odor with 
which he was saturated. 
</p><p>"'Really, uncle, if you knew my life&mdash;really, if not grief&mdash; 
harsh fate!  For that reason, I swear, I swear, I will reform&mdash;I 
will prove.  Uncle, I never lied&mdash;ask any one.  I am an honorable 
but an unhappy man, uncle.  I have received no kindness from any 
one.'  Here he finally broke off.  I endeavored to calm him, and 
succeeded in so far that when we drew up before my house Misha was 
already sleeping heavily, resting his head on my lap. 
 
 
</p>
</div2>
<div2 type="section" n="7" id="d10"><head>VII.</head><lb/>  
 
<p>"HE was immediately given a room to himself, and was put into 
a bath.  All his apparel, his dagger and fur cap and boots full of 
holes, were carefully laid away in a pantry; clean linen was put on 
him, slippers, and some of my clothing, which exactly suited his 
build and height.  When he came to table, washed, neat, fresh, he 
seemed so contrite and happy, he beamed all over with such joyous 
gratitude, that I was delighted.  His face was quite transformed.  
Boys of twelve years wear such a face on Easter Sunday, when, after 
communion, heavily oiled, in new jackets and starched collars, they 
go to keep the festival with their parents.  Misha continually felt 
of himself, cautiously and distrustfully, and repeated all the 
time, 'What is this?  Am I not in heaven?'  And on the following 
day he declared that he could not sleep all night from ecstasy.  In 
my house lived then an old aunt with her niece; they were both 
extremely disturbed when they learned of the presence of Misha; 
they did not understand how I could invite him to my house.  A very 
evil report of him was abroad.  But I knew that he was always very 
polite with ladies, and I built hopes on his promise to reform.  
For the first two days under my roof Misha not only answered my 
expectations, but surpassed them, and he simply enchanted my 
ladies.  With the old lady he played piquet, he assisted her to 
unwind her yarn, he showed her two new games of patience; the 
niece, who had something of a voice, he accompanied on the piano, 
read to her Russian and French verses; he related to both ladies 
merry but decorous anecdotes; in a word he rendered them divers 
services, so that they more than once expressed to me their 
astonishment, and the old lady even remarked that here could be 
seen how unjust people sometimes are.  There was nothing they did 
not say&mdash;he was so gentle and well-bred&mdash;poor Misha!  It is true at 
the table his mouth visibly watered every time he only so much as 
looked at a bottle.  But I had only to threaten him a little with 
my finger, and he raised his eyes to heaven, and pressed his hand 
to his heart.  'I have sworn!  I am now regenerated,' he assured 
me. 
</p><p>"'God grant it!' thought I.  But this regeneration did not 
last long. 
</p><p>"Beginning with the third day, he grew 
<pb n="343"/>  
silent; 
although, as before, he remained near the ladies and entertained 
them.  Now a melancholy, now a thoughtful expression began to flit 
across his face, and his face itself became pale and apparently 
thin.  'Are you indisposed?' I asked him.  'Yes,' he replied, 'my 
head aches a little.' 
</p><p>"On the fourth day he was entirely silent; he sat in the 
corner, bowing his head, like an orphan, and with his despondent 
look awakening a feeling of compassion in both ladies, who now, in 
their turn, endeavored to entertain him.  At table he ate nothing, 
looked at his plate, and rolled bread-balls.  On the fifth day, the 
feeling of pity in the ladies changed to distrust and even fear.  
Misha grew wild, held aloof from people, and crept along the wall 
as if thieving, looking suddenly around, exactly as if some one 
called him.  And what had become of the rosy color of his face? 
</p><p>"'Are you not well?' I asked him. 
</p><p>"'No&mdash;I am well,' he answered, abruptly. 
</p><p>"'Are you bored?' 
</p><p>"'Bored&mdash;with what?'  But he turned away and did not look me 
in the eye.  On the following day, my aunt came to me in my study 
in great agitation, and declared that she would leave my house with 
her niece, if Misha was to remain in it.  'He is not a man&mdash;he is 
a wolf.  He walks&mdash;walks&mdash;so silent, and so wild.  He almost 
gnashes his teeth.  Katia and I are so nervous.  At first we were 
very much interested in him, but now we are afraid of his 
craziness.'  I did not know what answer to make.  I could not drive 
Misha away, for I had invited him to my house.  He soon relieved me 
from the embarrassing position. 
</p><p>"On that same day I suddenly heard a hollow and angry voice, 
'Nikola&iuml; Nikola&iuml;tch!  Nikola&iuml; Nikola&iuml;tch!'  I 
looked around.  Misha stood at the door with a frightful, 
darkening, distorted countenance. 
</p><p>"'Nikola&iuml; Nikola&iuml;tch,' he repeated (no longer 
'Uncle'). 
</p><p>"'What is the matter with you?' 
</p><p>"'Let me go, directly.  Let me go or I shall do some mischief!  
I shall set fire to the house or murder some one.'  Misha suddenly 
began to shudder.  'Order my clothing to be returned to me, let 
them take me in a telega as far as the high-road, and give me a 
trifle of money.' 
</p><p>"'Are you then dissatisfied?' I began.  He began to cry at the 
top of his voice, 'I can not live in your accursed gentleman's 
house.  It oppresses me to live so tranquilly.  I wonder how you 
bear it!'  'That is,' I interrupted him, 'you mean you can not live 
without wine.'  'Well, yes; well, yes,' he began to cry again; 
'only let me go to my brothers, to my friends, to the beggars&mdash;away 
from your decorous and contrary nobleman's breed.'  I wished to 
remind him of his sworn promises, but the excited expression of 
Misha's face, his broken voice, the convulsive trembling of all his 
limbs, all this was so dreadful that I hastened to escape from him.  
I declared to him that his clothes would be given to him 
immediately, that a telega should be harnessed for him, and taking 
from my drawer a twenty-rouble bank-note, I laid it on table.  
Misha had already begun to approach me with threats, but here he 
suddenly controlled himself, his face became contracted, he struck 
himself on the breast, the tears started from his eyes, and 
murmuring, 'Uncle!  Angel!  Really I am a lost man,' he seized the 
bank-note and ran out. 
</p><p>"An hour later he was already seated in the telega, again 
dressed in his Circassian coat, again rosy and joyous, and when the 
horses moved from the place, he chirruped, pulled off his fur cap 
and waving it above his head, made bow after bow.  Just before his 
departure, he long and closely embraced me and stammered, 
'Benefactor!  Benefactor!  It is impossible to save me.'  He even 
ran to the ladies and kissed their hands over and over again, 
placed himself on his knees, called upon God and asked forgiveness.  
Katia I afterward found in tears. 
</p><p>"But the coachman with whom Misha had taken his departure, on 
his return, reported to me that he had driven him to the first 
dramshop on the highway, and that there they stopped and began to 
treat everybody without distinction, and soon was unconsciousness.  
>From this time on I no longer met Misha, but I learned his final 
fate in the following manner. 
 
 
</p>
</div2>
<div2 type="section" n="8" id="d11"><head>VIII.</head><lb/>  
 
<p>"THREE years later I again found myself on my estate.  
Suddenly the domestic entered my apartment, and announced that Mrs. 
Polteva was asking for me.  I knew no 
<pb n="344"/>  
Mrs. Polteva, and the 
servant making the announcement smiled with inquiring sarcasm.  To 
my interrogative glance, he answered that a lady was asking for 
me&mdash;young, poorly-dressed&mdash;and that she had come in a peasant's 
telega with one horse, and had driven herself.  I ordered him to 
ask Mrs. Polteva to come to me in my study. 
</p><p>"I saw a woman of twenty-five years of age, in the dress of 
the middle class, with a large handkerchief on her head.  Her face 
was open, round, and not without attractiveness.  Her expression 
was gloomy and somewhat mournful, her movements shy. 
</p><p>"'You are Mrs. Polteva?' I asked. 
</p><p>"'Exactly so,' she answered in a soft voice, refusing to sit 
down.  'I am the widow of your nephew, Mikha&iuml;l 
Andre&euml;vitch Polteff.' 
</p><p>"Mikha&iuml;l Andre&euml;vitch is dead?  How long?  But sit 
down, I beg of you.' 
</p><p>"She let herself down on a chair. 
</p><p>"'The second month has passed.' 
</p><p>"'And had you been long married?' 
</p><p>"'I had lived with him a whole year.' 
</p><p>"'Where have you come from now?' 
</p><p>"'I am from below Toula.  There is a village there&mdash;Zuamenskoe 
Gloushkovo&mdash;it may be you would like to know I am the daughter of 
a sacristan there.  We lived there with Mikha&iuml;l 
Andre&euml;vitch.  He settled down with my father.  A whole year we 
lived together there.' 
</p><p>"The young woman's lips began to quiver, and she raised her 
hand to them.  It seemed as though she were about to cry, but she 
recovered herself, coughing. 
</p><p>"'The late Mikha&iuml;l Andre&euml;vitch,' she continued, 
'before his death, instructed me to come to you.  "Without fail," 
he said, "go."  And he said to me that I should thank you for all 
your kindness, and that I should give you&mdash;here&mdash;this&mdash;very&mdash;little 
thing'&mdash;she took from her pocket a small packet&mdash;'which he always 
carried about him, and Mikha&iuml;l Andre&euml;vitch said&mdash;if it 
will please you to accept this in memory of him&mdash;if you do not 
disdain it&mdash;"nothing else have I to give," said he&mdash;that is&mdash;you&mdash;  
I can not, I can not&mdash;' 
</p><p>"In the little packet was a small silver cup bearing the 
cipher of Misha's mother.  This cup I had often seen in Misha's 
hands, and once he said to me, speaking of a certain poor fellow, 
that he was indeed destitute, since he had neither a little cup nor 
a little lamp, 'and I have this!' 
</p><p>"I thanked her, took the little cup, and asked her of what 
disease Misha died.  'Probably&mdash;'  Here, I bit my tongue, but the 
young woman understood my intimation.  She quickly looked at me, 
then cast down her eyes and mournfully repeated, 'Ah, no; this he 
forsook from the time that we became acquainted with him.  Only 
what health was his!  Quite ruined!  As soon as he stopped 
drinking, directly his sickness came to light.  So he became 
steady, wished to help father in everything&mdash;at farming, or in the 
garden, or whatever came to hand&mdash;in vain&mdash;for he was of noble 
race.  Only where to get strength?  Also, he wished to occupy 
himself with writing; this, as you know, he could do beautifully, 
but his hands shook and he could not hold the pen properly.  He 
always reproached himself: "I&mdash;a fine gentleman&mdash;did no good to any 
one&mdash;I did not help&mdash;I did not work."  He was very much cast down 
about this, and he said that our people worked, but we&mdash;what&mdash; 
Nikola&iuml; Nikola&iuml;tch, he was a good man, and he loved me&mdash; 
and I, ah&mdash;pardon&mdash;' 
</p><p>"Here the young woman fell to weeping outright.  I would have 
liked to comfort her, but I did not know how. 
</p><p>"Is there a baby left you?' I asked. 
</p><p>"She sighed.  'No, there is none&mdash;and if there had been&mdash;'  
And the tears flowed still more freely. 
</p><p>         &mdash; 
 
</p><p>"This is the end to which Misha was brought," concluded the 
old man.  "You gentlemen, assuredly, are agreed with me that I was 
right in calling him desperate; but probably you are also agreed 
upon this, that he did not resemble the desperate people of to-day, 
although it may be supposed that a philosopher would discover 
analogous features between him and them.  Here there was a thirst 
for self-destruction&mdash;grief&mdash;dissatisfaction, and what all this 
signifies I leave to the philosopher to judge." 
 
</p> 
</div2> 

<closer> 
<dateline>BOUGIVAL, <date value="1881-11"><hi rend="italic">November</hi>, 1881.</date></dateline> 
</closer> 

</div1> 

<div1 type="notes" id="d12"> 

<note id="n355"><seg type="note-symbol">[note]</seg> <p>A Russian proverb.</p></note> 
 
<note id="n336"><seg type="note-symbol">[note]</seg> <p>Russian ell</p></note> 

<note id="n337"><seg type="note-symbol">[note]</seg> <p>Seventy English feet. </p></note>

</div1> 
 
</body> 
</text> 
</TEI.2> 
 
