<?xml version="1.0"?>

<?dlps id="Twa2Sav"?>
<?dlps page-images="none" figure-images="no"?>
<?dlps transcription="other"?>

<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/tei-p4/tei2.dtd" [
<!ENTITY % POSTKB "INCLUDE">
<!ENTITY % TEI.extensions.ent SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.ent">
<!ENTITY % TEI.extensions.dtd SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.dtd">
<!ENTITY % ISOnum SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/charent/iso-num.ent"> %ISOnum;
<!ENTITY % ISOpub SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/charent/iso-pub.ent"> %ISOpub;

]>
<TEI.2 id="Twa2Sav">
	<teiHeader type="migrated" creator="Etext">
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title type="main">Our Fellow Savages of the Sandwich Islands</title>
<title type="sort">our fellow savages of the sandwich islands</title>
<author>Twain, Mark, 1835-1910</author>
<respStmt>
					<resp>Creation of machine-readable version:</resp>
					<name>Steve Railton</name>
					<resp>Conversion to TEI.2-conformant markup:</resp>
					<name>J. Nathaniel Goldsmith, University of Virginia Library Electronic Text
						Center.</name>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt>
			<extent>ca. <num type="kilobytes">24</num> kilobytes</extent>
			<publicationStmt>
<publisher>University of Virginia Library</publisher>
<pubPlace>Charlottesville, Virginia</pubPlace>
				<idno type="ETC">Twa2Sav</idno>
				<date value="2001">2001</date>
<availability status="public">
<p n="copyright">Copyright &copy; 2001 by the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia</p>
<p n="access">Publicly accessible</p>
</availability>
<idno type="uva-pid">uva-lib:476406</idno>
</publicationStmt>
<seriesStmt>
<title>University of Virginia Library, Text collection</title>
<idno type="uva-set">UVA-LIB-Text</idno>
</seriesStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
<biblFull>
<titleStmt>
<title type="main">Our Fellow Savages of the Sandwich Islands</title>
<title type="sort">our fellow savages of the sandwich islands</title>
<author>Mark Twain, pseud. Samuel Langhorne Clemens</author>
</titleStmt>
					<publicationStmt>
						<idno type="callNo">Source copy consulted:</idno>
</publicationStmt>
					</biblFull>
</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc>
		<encodingDesc>
<projectDesc>
<p>Prepared for the University of Virginia Library Electronic Text Center.</p>
</projectDesc>
			<editorialDecl>
<p>All unambiguous end-of-line hyphens have been removed, and the trailing part of a
					word has been joined to the preceding line.</p>
				<p id="ETC">Some keywords in the header are a local Electronic Text Center scheme to
					aid in establishing analytical groupings.</p>
</editorialDecl>
			</encodingDesc>
		<profileDesc>
			<langUsage>
<language id="eng" usage="main">English</language>
</langUsage>
			<textClass>
<keywords>
<term>non-fiction</term>
					<term>prose</term>
					<term>masculine</term>
					<term>Mark Twain</term>
</keywords>
				</textClass>
</profileDesc>
		<revisionDesc>
<change>
<date value="2001-07">July, 2001</date>
				<respStmt>
<resp>corrector</resp>
					<name/>
</respStmt>
				<item/>
</change>
<change>
<date value="2007-09">September 2007</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>Migration</resp>
<name>Ethan Gruber, University of Virginia Library</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Converted XML markup from TEI Lite to uva-dl-tei (TEI P4 with local customizations).</item>
</change>
<change>
<date value="2008-01">January 2008</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>Migration</resp>
<name>Greg Murray, University of Virginia Library</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Programmatically updated TEI header markup (but not header content) for minimal compliance with current QA requirements.</item>
</change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

	<text id="d1">


		<body id="d2">
			<div1 type="speech" id="d3">

				<div2 type="note" id="d4">
					<p>[<hi rend="italic">The text below is Fred W. Lorch's composite, from</hi> The
						Trouble Begins at Eight<hi rend="italic">. Assembled mainly from newspaper
							accounts, it represents the lecture as MT gave it during his 1869-1870
							tour of the northeast.</hi>]</p>
				</div2>

				<div2 type="introduction" id="d5">
					
					<p>I have the pleasure of introducing to you Mr. Samuel Clemens, otherwise Mark
						Twain, a gentleman whose high character and unimpeachable veracity are only
						surpassed by his personal comeliness and native modesty. I am the gentleman
						referred to. I suppose I ought to ask pardon for breaking the usual custom
						on such occasions and introducing myself, but it could not be avoided, as
						the gentleman who was to introduce me did not know my real name, hence I
						relieved him of his duties.</p>
				</div2>

				<div2 type="section" n="1" id="d6">
					<head>UNPLEASANT OBJECTS </head>
					<p>The first object I saw in the Sandwich Islands was an unpleasant one, and
						hence it suggested the beginning of my lecture. We cannot forget unpleasant
						things. In an old cathedral in Milan they showed me relics and other
						unpleasant objects, but one above all I remember simply because it was a
						very unpleasant thing. It was a curious, ancient statue, ascribed to
						Phidias, because it was imagined that no other artist could have ever copied
						nature so delicately and accurately. It was a figure carved in stone of a
						man without skin. It was a thoroughly skinned man, and every vein, artery,
						fiber, tendon, and even the tissue of the human frame, were marvelously and
						faithfully portrayed even to the minutest detail. It was not a pleasant
						thing to look at, but, somehow, there was a fascination about it because it
						looked so natural. It did. It looked as if it was in pain, and you felt that
						a thoroughly skinned man could only look like that. I have tried to get rid
						of such an unpleasant association, and dreamed and dreamed&mdash;that he
						had come to stay a week with me. I remember once when a mere
						girl&mdash;a child, so to speak&mdash;I ran away from school. I was
						afraid to go home at night&mdash;not that I cared anything about it
						myself, but my parents were prejudiced against that sort of thing, and
						although my judgment was quite as good as theirs, still as they had the
						majority they generally settled everything their own way, and so I was
						afraid to go home. I went to my father's office and laid myself on the
						lounge. It was late at night. The moon was beginning to creep up and to cast
						a few beams of light upon the floor. Looking upon the floor I discovered a
						long and mysterious looking shape. I turned my back upon it. It annoyed me;
						not that I was frightened, oh no, but just when I knew the moon's rays must
						have lighted up the spot I turned and looked, and lo! it was a dead man, his
						white face turned up to the moonlight, and he was cold and stiff and stark.
						I never before felt so sick in my life. I never before wanted to take a walk
						so badly as I did then. I did not go away in a hurry. I simply went through
						the window and took the sash with me. I did not need the sash, but it was
						handier to take than it was to leave it. I was not scared but a good deal
						agitated. I have never got rid of that man yet. He had&mdash;it
						appeared&mdash;fallen lifeless in the street, and they had brought him
						in to hold an inquest upon him, or to try him, and of course they found him
						guilty. It is not advisable to go to one's subject in a direct line and that
						accounts for the foregoing remarks. If a man is going to pop the question he
						begins a long way from his subject and talks of the weather. So it is with
						me; great subjects should be approached cautiously. I shall tell the truth
						as nearly as I can and quite as nearly as <hi rend="italic">any</hi>
						newspaperman can. The nonsense with which I shall embellish it will not
						detract from its truthfulness; that will be but as the barnacle to the
						oyster. I don't know&mdash;<hi rend="italic">sotto
						voce</hi>&mdash;whether the barnacle does stick to the oyster or the
						oyster to the barnacle&mdash;that figure is of my own invention. I was
						born and reared a long way from tidewater and I don't know whether the
						barnacle does stick to the oyster, but if it don't I do.</p>
				</div2>

				<div2 type="section" n="2" id="d7">
					<head>THE SANDWICH ISLANDS </head>
					<p>These islands are situated some twenty-one hundred miles southwest from San
						Francisco. The prevailing opinion&mdash;that they are in South
						America&mdash;is a mistake. They are situated in the Pacific Ocean, and
						their entire area is not greater, I suppose, than that of Rhode Island and
						Connecticut combined. They are of volcanic origin; of volcanic construction
						I should say. They are composed of lava harder than any statement I have
						made for three months. There is not a spoonful of legitimate dirt in the
						whole group, unless it has been lately imported. These islands were
						discovered some eighty or ninety years ago by Captain Cook, though another
						man came very near discovering them before, and he was diverted from his
						course by a manuscript found in a bottle. He wasn't the first man who has
						been diverted by suggestions got out of a bottle. Eight of these islands are
						inhabited, four of the eight are entirely girdled with a belt of mountains
						comprising the most productive sugar lands in the world. The sugar lands in
						Louisiana are considered rich, and yield from 500 to 1,700 pounds per acre,
						but those of the Sandwich Islands yield from 2,500 to 13,000 pounds per
						acre. A 200-acre crop of wheat in the states is worth $20,000 or $30,000; a
						200-acre crop of sugar in these islands is worth $200,000. You could not do
						that in this country, unless you planted it with stamps and reaped it in
						bonds. When these islands were discovered the population was about 400,000,
						but the white man came and brought various complicated diseases, and
						education, and civilization, and all sorts of calamities, and consequently
						the population began to drop off with commendable activity. Forty years ago
						they were reduced to 60,000, and the educational and civilizing facilities
						being increased they dwindled down to 55,000, and it is proposed to send a
						few more missionaries and finish them. It isn't the education or
						civilization that has settled them; it is the imported diseases, and they
						have all got the consumption and other reliable distempers, and to speak
						figuratively, they are retiring from business pretty fast.</p>
				</div2>

				<div2 type="section" n="3" id="d8">
					<head>MANNERS OF THE PEOPLE </head>
					<p>There are about three thousand white people in the islands; they are mostly
						Americans. In fact they are the kings of the Sandwich Islands; the monarchy
						is not much more than a mere name. These people stand as high in the scale
						of character as any people in the world, and some of them who were born and
						educated in those islands don't even know what vice is. The natives of the
						Sandwich Islands of color are a rich, dark brown, a kind of black and tan.
						The tropical sun and the easygoing ways inherited from their ancestors have
						made them rather idle, but they are not vicious at all; they are good
						people. The native women in the rural districts wear a loose, magnificent,
						curtain calico garment, but the men don't. Upon great occasions the men wear
						an umbrella, or some little fancy article like that&mdash;further than
						this they have no inclination towards gorgeousness of costume. In ancient
						times the king was the ruler of all the land, and supreme head of the church
						and state; his voice was superior to all law; he was absolute; his power was
						sacred. After the king in authority came the high priests of the ancient
						superstition, and after them the great chiefs, little better than slaves to
						the king. Next came the common plebians, and they were slaves to the whole
						party, <hi rend="italic">were</hi> abused and killed at the slightest
						pretext. And below them, away down at the bottom of this pile of tyranny and
						superstition, came the women, and they were the abject slaves of all; they
						were degraded to the level of the beasts, and thought to be no better. They
						were cruelly maltreated. By the law of the land it was death for a woman to
						eat at the same table with her husband, or to eat out of the same dish with
						him. Even those darkened people seemed to have a glimmering idea of the
						danger of the women eating forbidden fruit, and they didn't want to take the
						risk. Now the Sandwich Islanders are the best educated of any people on the
						earth, and I don't suppose there is a single <hi rend="italic"
						>Kannacker</hi> of 18 years and upward, but what can read and write. And all
						this wonderful work was accomplished by our American missionaries. And what
						is curious further, this great work was paid for in great part by the
						American Sunday school children with their pennies. Though it is beyond all
						comprehension that many a bad little boy has reaped a lucrative income, by
						confiscating the pennies given him for missionary contributions, dropping
						into the box such brass buttons as he could spare from his garments. It is
						the proudest reflection of my life that I never did that&mdash;never did
						it but once or twice, anyhow. These natives are an exceeding hospitable
						people. If you want to stay two or three days and nights in a native cabin
						you will be welcome. They will feast you on raw fish, with the scales on,
						cocoanuts, plantains, baked dogs and fricasseed cats, all the luxuries of
						the season. But if you want to trade with one of them, that's business. He
						will tell one falsehood after another right straight along, and not ordinary
						lies either, but monstrous incredible ones, and when a native is caught in a
						lie it doesn't incommode him at all. All these natives have a dozen mothers
						at least, not natural mothers, but adopted ones. A California man went down
						there and opened a sugar plantation. One of his hands came and said he
						wanted to bury his mother. He gave him permission. In a few days the man
						wanted to go and bury another mother. He gave him permission. In a few days
						the man wanted to go and bury another mother. The Californian thought it
						strange, but said "Well, go and plant her." Within a month the man wanted to
						bury some more mothers. "Look ye here," said the planter, "I don't want to
						be hard upon you in your affliction, but it appears to me your stock of
						mothers holds out pretty well. It interferes with business, so clear out and
						never come back till you have buried every mother you have in the
					world."</p>
				</div2>

				<div2 type="section" n="4" id="d9">
					<head>DOGS </head>
					<p>They are very fond of dogs, these people; not the great Newfoundland or the
						stately mastiff, but a species of little mean, contemptible cur, that a
						white man would condemn to death on general principles. There is nothing
						attractive about these dogs&mdash;there is not a handsome feature about
						them, unless it is their bushy tails. A friend of mine said if he had one of
						these dogs he would cut off his tail and throw the rest of the dog away.
						They feed this dog, pet him, take ever so much care of him, and then cook
						and eat him. I couldn't do that. I would rather go hungry for two days than
						devour an old personal friend in that way; but many a white citizen of those
						islands throws aside his prejudices and takes his dinner off one of those
						puppies&mdash;and after all it is only our cherished American sausage
						with the mystery removed.</p>
				</div2>

				<div2 type="section" n="5" id="d10">
					<head>CANNIBALISM </head>
					<p>It used to be popular to call these Sandwichers cannibals. They are not
						cannibals. There was one, however, who opened an office in a back settlement
						and did a good business, eating up a good many <hi rend="italic"
						>Kannackers</hi> in his time. In other cities I usually illustrate
						cannibalism on the stage, but being a stranger here I don't feel at liberty
						to ask favors, but still, if anyone in the audience would lend me an infant,
						I will go on with the show. However, it is of no consequence. I know that
						children have grown scarce lately on account of the neglect with which they
						are treated since the woman's movement began. That cannibal I was speaking
						about reduced the Democratic vote a good deal, but getting tired of <hi
							rend="italic">Kannackers</hi>&mdash;they are not good for a steady
						diet&mdash;he thought he would see how a white man would go with onions.
						So he kidnapped an old whaler who had been in the service sixty-five years,
						but either the crime or his conscience, or the weight of the whaler on his
						stomach, or both together, killed him. I was told this. I don't believe it
						quite myself, and only told it on account of the moral it conveys. There
						must be a moral in it somewhere, because I have told the story thirty or
						forty times, and never got it out yet. They have some curious customs there;
						among others, if a man makes a bad joke they kill him. I can't speak from
						experience on that point, because I never lectured there. I suppose if I had
						I should not be lecturing here.</p>
				</div2>

				<div2 type="section" n="6" id="d11">
					<head>CLIMATE AND CUSTOMS </head>
					<p>The climate of these islands is delightful, it is beautiful. In Honolulu the
						thermometer stands at about 80 or 82 degrees pretty much all the year
						round&mdash;don't change more than 12 degrees in twelve months. In the
						sugar districts the thermometer stands at 70 and does not change at all. Any
						kind of a thermometer will do&mdash;one without any quicksilver is just
						as good. That climate is very healthy&mdash;as healthy as ours; indeed,
						a man told me it was so hot in Wall Street the other day that gold went up
						to 160 in the shade.</p>

					<p>If you would see magnificent scenery&mdash;scenery on a mighty
						scale&mdash;and get scenery which charms with its softness and delights
						you with its unspeakable beauty, at the same moment that it deeply impresses
						you with its grandeur and its sublimity, you should go to the islands.</p>

					<p>Each island is a mountain or two or three mountains. They begin at the
						seashore&mdash;in a torrid climate where the cocoa palm grows and the
						coffee tree, the mango, orange, banana, and the delicious cherimoya; they
						begin down there in a sweltering atmosphere, rise with a grand and gradual
						sweep till they hide their beautiful regalia of living green in the folds of
						the drooping clouds, and higher and higher yet they rise among the mists
						till their emerald forests change to dull and stunted shrubbery, then to
						scattering constellations of the brilliant silver sword, then higher yet to
						dreary, barren desolation&mdash;no tree, no shrubs, nothing but torn and
						scorched and blackened piles of lava; higher yet, and then, towering toward
						heaven, above the dim and distant land, above the waveless sea, and high
						above the rolling plains of clouds themselves, stands the awful summit,
						wrapped in a mantle of everlasting ice and snow and burnished with a
						tropical sunshine that fires it with a dazzling splendor! Here one may stand
						and shiver in the midst of eternal winter and look down upon a land reposing
						in the loveliest hue of summer that hath no end.</p>

					<p>The volcano of Kee-law-ay-oh is 17,000 feet in diameter and from 700 to 800
						feet deep. Vesuvius is nowhere. It is the largest live volcano in the world;
						shoots up flames tremendously high. You witness a scene of unrivaled
						sublimity; and witness the most astonishing sights. When the volcano of
						Kee-law-ay-oh broke through a few years ago, lava flowed out of it for
						twenty days and twenty nights, and made a stream forty miles in length, till
						it reached the sea, tearing up forests in its awful fiery path, swallowing
						up huts, destroying all vegetation, rioting through shady dells and sinuous
						canyons. Amidst this carnival of destruction, majestic columns of smoke
						ascended and formed a cloudy, murky pall overhead. Sheets of green, blue,
						lambent flame were shot upwards and pierced this vast gloom, making all
						sublimely grand.</p>

					<p>With all their kindly ways these people practice some cruelties. They will
						put a live chicken into the hot ashes simply to see it hop about. They would
						burn the flesh before the missionaries came, and would put out an eye, or a
						tooth, when a chief died. And if their grief was deep, and they could get
						relief in no other way, they would go out and scalp a neighbor. In the
						season of mourning for a great person they permit any crime that will best
						express sorrow.</p>

					<p>They do everything differently from other people. They mount a horse from the
						off side. They turn to the left instead of the right. They say the same
						words for "good bye" and "how do you do." They always, in beckoning for you
						to come, motion in the opposite direction. Even the birds partake of this
						peculiarity. The native duck lives four thousand feet above the level of the
						sea, and never sees water except when it rains. They (the islanders) groan
						in a heartbroken way when they are particularly happy. They have some
						customs we might import with advantage. I don't call any to mind just now.</p>

					<p>In Honolulu they are the most easygoing people in the world. Some of our
						people are not acquainted with their customs. They started a gas company
						once, and put the gas at $13 a thousand feet. They only took in $16 the
						first month. They all went to bed at dark. They are an excellent people. I
						speak earnestly. They do not know even the name of some of the vices in this
						country. A lady called on a doctor. She wanted something for general
						debility. He ordered her to drink porter. She called him again. The porter
						had done her no good. He asked her how much porter she had taken. She said a
						tablespoonful in a tumbler of water. I wish we could import such a blessed
						ignorance into this country. They don't do much drinking there; it is too
						expensive. When they have paid the tax for importing the liquor they have
						got nothing left to purchase the liquor with. They are very innocent and
						drink anything that is limpid&mdash;kerosene, turpentine, hair oil. In
						our town on a Fourth of July an entire community got drunk on a barrel of
						Mrs. Winslow's soothing syrup.</p>
				</div2>

				<div2 type="section" n="7" id="d12">
					<head> LIARS </head>
					<p>These Sandwichers believe in a superstition that the biggest liars in the
						world have got to visit the Islands some time before they die. They believe
						that because it is a fact&mdash;you misunderstand&mdash;I mean that
						when liars get there they stay there. They have had several specimens they
						boast of. They treasure up their little perfections, and they allude to them
						as if the man was inspired&mdash;from below. They had a man among them
						named Morgan. He never allowed anyone to tell a bigger lie than himself, and
						he always told the last one too. When someone was telling about the natural
						bridge in Virginia, he said he knew all about it, as his father helped to
						build it. Someone was bragging of a wonderful horse he had. Morgan told them
						of one he had once. While out riding one day a thunder shower came on and
						chased him for eighteen miles, and never caught him. Not a single drop of
						rain dropped onto his nose, but his dog was swimming behind the wagon the
						whole of the way. Once, when the subject of mean men was being discussed,
						Morgan told them of an incorporated company of mean men. They hired a poor
						fellow to blast rock for them. He drilled a hole four feet deep, put in the
						powder, and began to tamp it down around the fuse. I know all about tamping,
						as I have worked in a mine myself. The crowbar struck a spark and caused a
						premature explosion, and that man and his crowbar shot up into the air, and
						he went higher and higher and higher till he didn't look bigger than a bee,
						and then he went out of sight; and presently he came in sight again, looking
						no bigger than a bee; and he came further and further and further till he
						was as big as a dog, and further and further and further till he was as big
						as a boy, and he came further and further till he assumed the full size and
						shape of a man, and he came down and fell right into the same old spot and
						went to tamping again. And would you believe it&mdash;concluded
						Morgan&mdash;although that poor fellow was not gone more than fifteen
						minutes, yet that mean company docked him for the loss of time.</p>
				</div2>
			</div1>
		</body>
	</text>
</TEI.2>
