<?xml version="1.0"?>

<?dlps id="Twa7Aro"?>
<?dlps page-images="none" figure-images="no"?>
<?dlps transcription="other"?>

<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/tei-p4/tei2.dtd" [
<!ENTITY % POSTKB "INCLUDE">
<!ENTITY % TEI.extensions.ent SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.ent">
<!ENTITY % TEI.extensions.dtd SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.dtd">
<!ENTITY % ISOnum SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/charent/iso-num.ent"> %ISOnum;
<!ENTITY % ISOpub SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/charent/iso-pub.ent"> %ISOpub;

]>
<TEI.2 id="Twa7Aro">
<teiHeader type="migrated" creator="Etext">
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title type="main">Around the World Letter, No. 7</title>
<title type="sort">around the world letter, no 7</title>
<author>Twain, Mark, 1835-1910</author>
<respStmt>
<resp>Creation of machine-readable version:</resp>
<name>Steve Railton</name>
<resp>Conversion to TEI.2-conformant markup:</resp>
<name>M. Eleanor Culley, University of Virginia Library Electronic Text Center.</name>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt>
<extent>ca. <num type="kilobytes">13</num> kilobytes</extent>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>University of Virginia Library</publisher>
<pubPlace>Charlottesville, Virginia</pubPlace>
<idno type="ETC">Twa7Aro</idno>
<date value="2001">2001</date>
<availability status="public">
<p n="copyright">Copyright &copy; 2001 by the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia</p>
<p n="access">Publicly accessible</p>
</availability>
<idno type="uva-pid">uva-lib:476411</idno>
</publicationStmt>
<seriesStmt>
<title>University of Virginia Library, Text collection</title>
<idno type="uva-set">UVA-LIB-Text</idno>
</seriesStmt>
<sourceDesc>
<biblFull>
<titleStmt>
<title type="main">Around the World Letter, No. 7</title>
<title type="sort">around the world letter, no 7</title>
<author>Mark Twain, pseud. Samuel Langhorne Clemens</author>
</titleStmt>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>Buffalo Express</publisher>
<date value="1870-01-22">January 22, 1870</date>
<idno type="callNo">Source copy consulted:</idno>
</publicationStmt>
</biblFull>
</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc>
<encodingDesc>
<projectDesc>
<p>Prepared for the University of Virginia Library Electronic Text Center.</p>
</projectDesc>
<editorialDecl>
<p>All unambiguous end-of-line hyphens have been removed, and the  trailing part of a word has been joined to the preceding line.</p>
<p id="ETC">Some keywords in the header are a local Electronic Text Center scheme  to aid in establishing analytical groupings.</p>
</editorialDecl>
</encodingDesc>
<profileDesc>
<langUsage>
<language id="eng" usage="main">English</language>
</langUsage>
<textClass>
<keywords>
<term>non-fiction</term>
<term>prose</term>
<term>masculine</term>
<term>Mark Twain</term>
</keywords>
</textClass>
</profileDesc>
<revisionDesc>
<change>
<date value="2001-07">July, 2001</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>corrector</resp>
<name/>
</respStmt>
<item/>
</change>
<change>
<date value="2007-09">September 2007</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>Migration</resp>
<name>Ethan Gruber, University of Virginia Library</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Converted XML markup from TEI Lite to uva-dl-tei (TEI P4 with local customizations).</item>
</change>
<change>
<date value="2008-01">January 2008</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>Migration</resp>
<name>Greg Murray, University of Virginia Library</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Programmatically updated TEI header markup (but not header content) for minimal compliance with current QA requirements.</item>
</change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>



<text id="d1">
<body id="d2">

<div1 type="letter" id="d3">
<head>
Buffalo <hi rend="italic">Express</hi>22 January 1870<lb/>
Around the World: Letter No. 7: Pacific Coast &mdash; Concluded</head>



<div2 type="section" n="1" id="d4">
<head>CHINAMEN</head>
<p>
One of California's curiosities the people in the States will some day become familiar with
through the Pacific Railroad. I mean the Chinamen. California contains 70,000 of them, and
every ship brings more. There is a Chinese quarter in every city and village in California and
Nevada, for Boards of Aldermen will not allow them to live all around town just wherever they
choose to locate. This is not a hardship, for they prefer to herd together.</p>
<p/>

<div3 type="subsection" n="1" id="d5">
<head>Peculiarities and Superstitions</head>
<p>
They are a people who fondly stick to their ancient customs. They dress in the quaint costumes
their ancestors wore 500 years ago. They build temples, gaudy with gilding and hideous with
staring idols, and there they worship after the fashion of their fathers. A strict record is kept by
their chiefs of the name and residence of every Chinaman, and when he dies his body is sent back
to China for burial &mdash; for they can never get to their Heaven unless they start from China. And
besides, Chinamen worship their ancestors, and they all want their share of worship after they are
done with this world. Even when the Chinese government sells a shipload of degraded and
criminal coolies to a Cuban or Sandwich Island planter, it is strictly stipulated that the body of
every one of them must be sent back to China after death.</p>

<p>
The Chinamen being smart, shrewd people, take to some few of our commercial customs and
virtues, but somehow we can't make great headway in the matter of civilizing them. We can teach
them to gamble a little, but somehow we can't make them get drunk. It is discouraging &mdash; because
you can't regenerate a being that won't get drunk.</p>

<p>
The Chinaman is the most frugal, industrious and thrifty of all creatures. No matter how slender
are the wages you pay him he will manage to lay up money. And Chinamen are the most gifted
gardeners in the world. Give one of them a sandbank that would not support a lizard, and he will
make it yield generous crops of vegetables. The Chinaman wastes <hi rend="italic">nothing</hi>. Every thing
has a value in his eyes. He gathers up all the cast-away rags and bones and bits of glass, and
makes marketable articles of them. And he picks up all the old fruit cans you throw away and
melts them up to get the tin and solder. When a white man discards a gold placer as no longer
worth anything, the patient Chinaman, always satisfied with small profits, and never in a hurry to
get rich, takes possession and works it contentedly for years.</p>

<p>
The Chinaman makes a good cook, a good washerwoman, a good chambermaid, a good
gardener, a good banker's clerk, a good miner, a good railroad laborer, a good <hi rend="italic">anything</hi>
you choose to put him at &mdash; for these people are all educated, they are all good accountants, they
are very quiet and peaceable, they never disturb themselves about politics; they are so tractable,
quick, smart, and naturally handy and ingenious, that you can teach them anything; they have no
jealousies; they never lose a moment, never require watching to keep them at work; they are
gifted with a world of patience, endurance and contentment. They are the best laboring class
America has ever seen &mdash; and they do not care a cent who is President. They are miserably abused
by the laws of California, but that sort of thing will cease, some day. It was found just about
impossible to build the California end of the Pacific Railroad with white men at $3 per day and
take care of all the broils and fights and strikes; but they put on Chinamen at a dollar a day and
"find" themselves, and <hi rend="italic">they</hi> built it without fights or strikes or anything, and saved the
bulk of their wages, too. You will have these long-tailed toilers among you in "the States" some
day, but you will find them right easy to get along with &mdash; and you will like them, too, because
they will stand a heap of abuse. You will find them ever so convenient, because when you get
mad you can snatch a club and go out and take satisfaction out of a Chinaman. The native
American Negro is getting so insolent, now, that the patriot from Ireland cannot take a little
recreation out of him without getting into trouble. So the Chinaman will afford a needed
relief.</p>
</div3>
<div3 type="subsection" n="2" id="d6">
<head>Modest Villainy</head>
<p>
As evidence that Chinamen are satisfied with small gains, I will remark that they drill five holes
into the edge of gold coins &mdash; drill clear through from edge to edge &mdash; and save the gold thus bored
out and fill up the hole with some sort of metallic composition that does not spoil the ring of the
coin. Their counterfeiters put nine parts good metal and only one part base metal in their bogus
coins &mdash; and so it is very lucrative in the long run and the next thing to impossible to detect the
cheat. It is only greedy bungling <hi rend="italic">Christian</hi> counterfeiters that blunder into trouble, by
trying to swindle their fellow creatures too heavily.</p>
</div3>
</div2>

<div2 type="section" n="2" id="d7">
<head>DESPERADOES</head>
<p>
Another curious feature about California life was the breed of desperadoes she reared and
fostered on her soil and afterward distributed over adjacent Territories through her Vigilance
Committees when she had had enough of their exploits. These men went armed to the teeth with
monstrous revolvers, and preyed upon each other. Their slightest misunderstandings were settled
on the spot by the bullet; but they very rarely molested peaceable citizens. They robbed and
gambled and killed people for three or four years, and then "died with their boots on," as they
phrased it; that is, they were killed themselves &mdash; almost invariably &mdash; and they never expected
any other fate, and were very seldom disappointed.</p>

<div3 type="subsection" n="1" id="d8">
<head>Sam Brown</head>
<p>
Sam Brown, of Nevada, killed sixteen men in his time, and was journeying toward Esmeralda to
kill a seventeenth, who had stopped the breath of a friend of his, when a party of law-abiding
citizens waylaid him and slaughtered him with shot guns. Mourners were exceeding scarce at his
funeral. It is said that Sam Brown called for a drink at the bar of the Slaughter House in Carson
City one morning (a saloon so nicknamed because so many men had been killed in it) and invited
a stranger up to drink with him. The stranger said he never drank and wished to be excused. By
the custom of the country, that was a deadly insult, and so Brown very properly shot him down.
He left him lying there and went away, warning everybody to let the body alone, because it was
<hi rend="italic">his</hi> meat, he said. And it is said, also, that he came back after awhile and made a coffin
and buried the man himself &mdash; though I never could quite believe that without
assistance.</p>

<p>
Virginia City was full of desperadoes, and some of the pleasantest newspaper reporting I ever did
was in those days, because I reported the inquests on the entire lot of them, nearly. We had a
fresh one pretty much every morning. Toward the last it was melancholy to see how the material
was running short. Those were halcyon days! I don't know what halcyon days are, but that is the
proper expression to use in this connection, I believe.</p>
</div3>

<div3 type="subsection" n="2" id="d9">
<head>Jack Williams</head>
<p>
Jack Williams was one of the luckiest of the Virginia City desperadoes. He killed a good many
men. He was a kind-hearted man, and gave all his custom to a poor undertaker who was trying to
get along. But by and bye some body poked a double barrelled shot gun through a crack while
Williams was sitting at breakfast, and riddled him at such a rate that there was hardly enough of
him left to hold an inquest on &mdash; and then the poor unfortunate undertaker's best friend was gone,
and he had to take in his sign. Thus he was stricken in the midst of his prosperity and his
happiness &mdash; for he was just on the point of getting married when Jack Williams was taken away
from him, and of course he had to give it up then.</p>

</div3>

<div3 type="subsection" n="3" id="d10">
<head>Cemeterial Curiosities</head>

<p>
It is said that the first twenty-six graves in the cemetery at Virginia City were those of men who
all died by the bullet.  And the first six in another of those towns contained the bodies of a
desperado and five of his victims &mdash; and there in the bosom of his family, made dear to him by
ties of blood, he calmly sleeps unto this day.</p>
</div3>
<div3 type="subsection" n="4" id="d11">
<head>Mr. Slade</head>

<p>
At the Rocky Ridge station in the Rocky Mountains, in the old days of overland stages and pony
expresses, I had the gorgeous honor of breakfasting with Mr. Slade, the Prince of all the
desperadoes; who killed twenty-six men in his time; who used to cut off his victims' ears and
send them as keepsakes to their relatives; and who bound one of his victims hand and foot and
practiced on him with his revolver for hours together &mdash; a proceeding which seems almost
inexcusable until we reflect that Rocky Ridge is away off in the dull solitudes of the mountains,
and the poor desperadoes have hardly any amusements. Mr. Slade afterward went to Montana
and began to thin out the population as usual &mdash; for he took a great interest in trimming the census
and regulating the vote &mdash; but finally the Vigilance Committee captured him and hanged him,
giving him just fifteen minutes to prepare himself in. The papers said he cried on the
scaffold.</p>

<p>
The Vigilance Committee is a wholesome regulator in the new countries, and bad characters have
a lively dread of it. In Montana one of these gentlemen was placed on his mule and informed that
he had precisely fifteen minutes to leave the country in. He said, "Gents, if this mule don't balk,
five'll answer."</p>
<p>
But that is sufficient about the desperadoes. I merely wished to make passing mention of them as
a Californian production.</p>
</div3>
</div2>
<byline>Mark Twain</byline>

</div1>
</body>
</text>
</TEI.2>