<?xml version="1.0"?>

<?dlps id="TwaAmer"?>
<?dlps page-images="none" figure-images="no"?>
<?dlps transcription="other"?>

<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/tei-p4/tei2.dtd" [
<!ENTITY % POSTKB "INCLUDE">
<!ENTITY % TEI.extensions.ent SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.ent">
<!ENTITY % TEI.extensions.dtd SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.dtd">
<!ENTITY % ISOnum SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/charent/iso-num.ent"> %ISOnum;
<!ENTITY % ISOpub SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/charent/iso-pub.ent"> %ISOpub;
]>  
<TEI.2 id="TwaAmer">  
<teiHeader type="migrated" creator="Etext">
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title type="main">The American Vandal Abroad</title>
<title type="sort">american vandal abroad</title>
<author>Twain, Mark, 1835-1910</author>
<respStmt>
<resp>Creation of machine-readable version:</resp>   
<name>Stephen Railton</name>   
<resp>Creation of digital images:</resp>   
<name>Tom Palombi, Electronic Text Center</name>   
<resp>Conversion to TEI.2-conformant markup:</resp>   
<name>University of Virginia Library Electronic Text Center.</name>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt>   
<extent>ca. <num type="kilobytes">20</num> kilobytes</extent>   
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>University of Virginia Library</publisher>
<pubPlace>Charlottesville, Virginia</pubPlace>   
<idno type="ETC">TwaAmer</idno>   
<date value="1997-09">September 1997</date>
<availability status="public">
<p n="copyright">Copyright &copy; 1997 by the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia</p>
<p n="access">Publicly accessible</p>
</availability>
<idno type="uva-pid">uva-lib:476412</idno>
</publicationStmt>
<seriesStmt>
<title>University of Virginia Library, Text collection</title>
<idno type="uva-set">UVA-LIB-Text</idno>
</seriesStmt>   
<sourceDesc>
<biblFull>
<titleStmt>
<title type="main">The American Vandal Abroad</title>
<title level="m">Mark Twain's Speeches</title>
<title type="sort">american vandal abroad</title>
<author>Mark Twain</author>
<respStmt>
<resp>Editor</resp>   
<name>Albert Bigelow Paine</name>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt>   
<editionStmt>
<p>This edition publishes Twain's "American Vandal Abroad Speech," which was delivered on his 1868-69 tour.</p>
</editionStmt>   
<extent>pp. 21-30</extent>   
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>Harper &amp; Brothers</publisher>   
<pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>   
<date value="1923">1923</date>   
<idno type="callNo">Print copy consulted:</idno>
</publicationStmt>   
</biblFull>
</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc>   
<encodingDesc>
<projectDesc>
<p>Prepared for the University of Virginia Library Electronic Text Center.</p>
</projectDesc>   
<editorialDecl>
<p>All unambiguous end-of-line hyphens have been removed, and the trailing part of a word has been joined to the preceding line.</p>   
<p>The images exist as archived TIFF images, one or more JPEG versions for general use, and thumbnail GIFs.</p>   
<p>Some keywords in the header are a local Electronic Text Center scheme to aid in establishing analytical groupings.</p>
</editorialDecl>   
</encodingDesc>   
<profileDesc>
<langUsage>
<language id="eng" usage="main">English</language>
</langUsage>   
<textClass>
<keywords>
<term>prose; fiction</term>
</keywords>   
</textClass>
</profileDesc>   
<revisionDesc>
<change>
<date value="1997-09">September 1997</date>   
<respStmt>
<resp>corrector</resp>   
<name>Tom Palombi, Electronic Text Center</name>
</respStmt>   
<item>Added TEI header and tags.</item>
</change>
<change>
<date value="2007-09">September 2007</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>Migration</resp>
<name>Ethan Gruber, University of Virginia Library</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Converted XML markup from TEI Lite to uva-dl-tei (TEI P4 with local customizations).</item>
</change>
<change>
<date value="2008-01">January 2008</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>Migration</resp>
<name>Greg Murray, University of Virginia Library</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Programmatically updated TEI header markup (but not header content) for minimal compliance with current QA requirements.</item>
</change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>   
  
<text id="d1">  
 
<front id="d2">  
<pb/> 
<div1 type="introduction" id="d3">  
<head>The American Vandal Abroad</head>  
  
<p>There is no definitive text of a MT lecture.  For the "American  
Vandal" he followed his usual practice of writing it out and committing  
it to memory, but in performance it was a living thing.  In essence it  
remained the same throughout the 1868-1869 tour, but on any given night  
he could make it longer or shorter, try out new ideas, and so on.  The  
version below is Albert Bigelow Paine's, from <hi rend="italic">Mark Twain's  
Speeches</hi>; other versions can be found in Fred W. Lorch's <hi rend="italic"> Trouble Begins  
At Eight</hi> and Paul Fatout's <hi rend="italic">Mark Twain Speaking</hi>.  Paine's is  
the shortest, probably about half as long as any talk MT delivered, and  
the least humorous.  Like Mrs. Fairbanks, Paine obviously preferred what  
MT called "the serious passages."  These moments were important to  
contemporary audiences, who wanted to feel "improved" or "instructed" or  
"uplifted" in the lyceum, but MT's great popularity as a speaker came  
from his humor.  To see examples of the kinds of passages audiences  
laughed at, but Paine minimized, the text below has links to a couple  
additional passages &mdash; the first from Fatout's, the second from Lorch's  
versions of the lecture. 
  
</p>  
</div1>  
 
</front>  
  
<body id="d4">  

<div1 type="section" id="d5">  <pb/> 
  
<p>I am to speak of the American Vandal this evening, but I wish to say  
in advance that I do not use this term in derision or apply it as a  
reproach, but I use it because it is convenient; and duly and properly  
modified, it best describes the roving, independent, free-and-easy  
character of that class of traveling Americans who are <hi rend="italic">not</hi>  
elaborately educated, cultivated, and refined, and gilded and filigreed  
with the ineffable graces of the first society.  The best class of our  
countrymen who go abroad keep us well posted about their doings in  
foreign lands, but their brethren vandals cannot sing their own praises  
or publish their adventures.  
  
</p><p>The American Vandal gallops over England, Scotland, Spain, and  
Switzerland, and finally brings up in Italy.  He thinks it is the proper  
thing to visit Genoa, the stately old City of Palaces, whose vast marble  
edifices almost meet together over streets so narrow that three men can  
hardly walk abreast in them, and so crooked that a man generally comes  
out of them about the same place he went in.  He only stays in Genoa  
long enough to see a few celebrated things and get some fragments of  
stone from the house Columbus was born in &mdash; for your genuine Vandal is  
an intolerable and incorrigible relic gatherer.  It is estimated that if  
all the fragments of stone brought from Columbus's house by travelers  
were collected together they would suffice to build a house fourteen  
thousand feet high &mdash; and I suppose they would.  
  
</p><p>Next he hurries to Milan and takes notes of the Grand Cathedral (for  
he is always taking notes).  Oh, I remember Milan and the noble  
cathedral well enough &mdash; that marble miracle of enchanting architecture.  
I remember how we entered and walked about its vast spaces and among its  
huge columns, gazing aloft at the monster windows all aglow with  
brilliantly colored scenes in the life of the Savior and his followers.  
And I remember the side-shows and curiosities there, too.  The guide  
showed us a coffee-colored piece of sculpture which he said was supposed  
to have come from the hand of Phidias, since it was not possible that  
any other man, of any epoch, could have copied nature with such  
faultless accuracy.  The figure was that of a man without a skin; with  
every vein, artery, muscle, every fiber and tendon and tissue of the  
human frame, represented in minute detail.  It looked natural, because  
it looked somehow <hi rend="italic">as if it were in pain</hi>.  A skinned man <hi rend="italic">would  
be likely to look that way</hi> &mdash; unless his attention were occupied by  
some other matter.  
  
</p><p>The Vandal goes to see the ancient and most celebrated painting in  
the world, "The Last Supper."  We all know it in engravings: the  
disciples all sitting on one side of a long, plain table and Christ with  
bowed head in the center &mdash; all the last suppers in the world are copied  
from this painting.  It is so damaged now, by the wear and tear of three  
hundred years, that the figures can hardly be distinguished.  The Vandal  
goes to see this picture &mdash; which all the world praises &mdash; looks at it  
with a critical eye, and says it's a perfect old nightmare of a picture  
and he wouldn't give forty dollars for a million like it (and I indorse  
his opinion), and then he is done with Milan.  
  
</p><p>He paddles around the Lake of Como for a few days, and then takes the  
cars.  He is bound for Venice, the oldest and the proudest and the  
princeliest republic that ever graced the earth.  We put on a good many  
airs with our little infant of a Republic of a century's growth, but we  
grow modest when we stand before this gray, old imperial city that used  
to laugh the armies and navies of half the world to scorn, and was a  
haughty, invincible, magnificent Republic for fourteen hundred years!  
The Vandal is bound for Venice!  He has a long, long, weary ride of it;  
but just as the day is closing he hears some one shout, "Venice!" and  
puts his head out of a window, and sure enough, afloat on the placid  
sea, a league away, lies the great city with its towers and domes and  
steeples drowsing in a golden mist of sunset!  
  
</p><p>Have you been to Venice, and seen the winding canals, and the stately  
edifices that border them all along, ornamented with the quaint devices  
and sculptures of a former age?  And have you seen the great Cathedral  
of St. Mark's &mdash; and the Giant's Staircase &mdash; and the famous Bridge of  
Sighs &mdash; and the great Square of St. Mark's &mdash; and the ancient pillar  
with the winged lion of St. Mark that stands on it, whose story and  
whose origin are a mystery &mdash; and the Rialto, where Shylock used to loan  
money on human flesh and other collateral?</p>
	
	<p>I had begun to feel that the old Venice of song and story had  
departed forever.  But I was too hasty.  When we swept gracefully out  
into the Grand Canal and under the mellow moonlight the Venice of poetry  
and romance stood revealed.  Right from the water's edge rose palaces of  
marble; gondolas were gliding swiftly hither and thither and  
disappearing suddenly through unsuspected gates and alleys; ponderous  
stone bridges threw their shadows athwart the glittering waves.  There  
were life and motion everywhere, and yet everywhere there was a hush, a  
stealthy sort of stillness, that was suggestive of secret enterprises of  
bravos and of lovers; and clad half in moonbeams and half in mysterious  
shadows, the grim old mansions of the republic seemed to have an  
expression about them of having an eye out for just such enterprises as  
these.  At that same moment music came stealing over the waters &mdash;  
Venice was complete.</p>
	
	<p><hi rend="italic">Our</hi> Vandals hurried away from Venice and scattered abroad  
everywhere.  You could find them breaking specimens from the dilapidated  
tomb of Romeo and Juliet at Padua &mdash; and infesting the picture galleries  
of Florence &mdash; and risking their necks on the Leaning Tower of Pisa &mdash;  
and snuffing sulphur fumes on the summit of Vesuvius &mdash; and burrowing  
among the exhumed wonders of Herculaneum and Pompeii &mdash; and you might  
see them with spectacles on, and blue cotton umbrellas under their arms,  
benignantly contemplating Rome from the venerable arches of the  
Coliseum.  
  
</p><p>And finally we sailed from Naples, and in due time anchored before  
the Piraeus, the seaport of Athens in Greece.  But the quarantine was in  
force, and so they set a guard of soldiers to watch us and would not let  
us go ashore.  However, I and three other Vandals took a boat, and  
muffled the oars, and slipped ashore at 11.30 at night, and dodged the  
guard successfully.  Then we made a wide circuit around the slumbering  
town, avoiding all roads and houses &mdash; for they'd about as soon hang a  
body as not for violating the quarantine laws in those countries.  We  
got around the town without any accident, and then struck out across the  
Attic Plain, steering straight for Athens &mdash; over rocks and hills and  
brambles and everything &mdash; with Mt. Helicon for a landmark.  And so we  
tramped for five or six miles.  The Attic Plain is a mighty  
uncomfortable plain to travel in, even if it <hi rend="italic">is</hi> so historical.  
The armed guards got after us three times and flourished their gleaming  
gun barrels in the moonlight, because they thought we were stealing  
grapes occasionally &mdash; and the fact is we <hi rend="italic">were</hi> &mdash; for we found by  
and by that the brambles that tripped us up so often were grape-vines &mdash;  
but these people in the country didn't know that we were  
quarantine-blockade runners, and so they only scared us and jawed Greek  
at us, and let us go, instead of arresting us.  
  
</p><p>We didn't care about Athens particularly, but we wanted to see the  
famous Acropolis and its ruined temples, and we did.  We climbed the  
steep hill of the Acropolis about one in the morning and tried to storm  
that grand old fortress that had scorned the battles and sieges of three  
thousand years.  We had the garrison out mighty quick &mdash; four Greeks &mdash;  
and we bribed them to betray the citadel and unlock the gates.  In a  
moment we stood in the presence of the noblest ruins we had ever seen &mdash;  
the most elegant, the most graceful, the most imposing.  The renowned  
Parthenon towered above us, and about us were the wreck of what were  
once the snowy marble Temples of Hercules and Minerva, and another whose  
name I have forgotten.  Most of the Parthenon's grand columns are still  
standing, but the roof is gone.  
  
</p><p>As we wandered down the marble-paved length of this mighty temple,  
the scene was strangely impressive.  Here and there in lavish profusion  
were gleaming white statues of men and women, propped against blocks of  
marble, some of them armless, some without legs, others headless, but  
all looking mournful and sentient and startlingly human!  They rose up  
and confronted the midnight intruder on every side; they stared at him  
with stony eyes from unlooked-for nooks and recesses; they peered at him  
over fragmentary heaps far down the desolate corridors; they barred his  
way in the midst of the broad forum, and solemnly pointed with handless  
arms the way from the sacred fane; and through the roofless temple the  
moon looked down and banded the floor and darkened the scattered  
fragments and broken statues with the slanting shadows of the  
columns!  
  
</p><p>What a world of ruined sculpture was about us!  Stood up in rows,  
stacked up in piles, scattered broadcast over the wide area of the  
Acropolis, were hundreds of crippled statues of all sizes and of the  
most exquisite worksmanship; and vast fragments of marble that once  
belonged to the entablatures, covered with bas-reliefs representing  
battles and sieges, ships of war with three and four tiers of oars,  
pageants and processions &mdash; everything one could think of.  
  
</p><p>We walked out into the grass-grown, fragment-strewn court beyond the  
Parthenon.  It startled us every now and then, to see a stony white face  
stare suddenly up at us out of the grass, with its dead eyes.  The place  
seemed alive with ghosts.  We half expected to see the Athenian heroes  
of twenty centuries ago glide out of the shadows and steal into the old  
temple they knew so well and regarded with such boundless pride.  
  
</p><p>The full moon was riding high in the cloudless heavens now.  We  
sauntered carelessly and unthinkingly to the edge of the lofty  
battlements of the citadel, and looked down, and, lo!  a vision!  And  
such a vision!  Athens by moonlight!  All the beauty in all the world  
could not rival it!  The prophet that thought the splendors of the New  
Jerusalem were revealed to him, surely saw this instead.  It lay in the  
level plain right under our feet &mdash; all spread abroad like a picture &mdash;  
and we looked down upon it as we might have looked from a balloon.  We  
saw no semblance of a street, but every house, every window, every  
clinging vine, every projection, was as distinct and sharply marked as  
if the time were noonday; and yet there was no glare, no glitter,  
nothing harsh or repulsive &mdash; the silent city was flooded with the  
mellowest light that ever streamed from the moon, and seemed like some  
living creature wrapped in peaceful slumber.  On its father side was a  
little temple whose delicate pillars and ornate front glowed with a rich  
luster that chained the eye like a spell; and, nearer by, the palace of  
the king reared its creamy walls out of the midst of a great garden of  
shrubbery that was flecked all over with a random shower of amber lights  
&mdash; a spray of golden sparks that lost their brightness in the glory of  
the moon and glinted softly upon the sea of dark foliage like the pallid  
stars of the Milky Way!  Overhead, the stately columns, majestic still  
in their ruin; underfoot, the dreaming city; in the distance the silver  
sea &mdash; not on the broad earth is there another picture half so  
beautiful!  
  
</p><p>We got back to the ship safely, just as the day was dawning.  We had  
walked upon pavements that had been pressed by Plato, Aristotle,  
Demosthenes, Socrates, Phocion, Euclid, Xenophon, Herodotus, Diogenes,  
and a hundred others of deathless fame, and were satisfied.  We got to  
stealing grapes again on the way back, and half a dozen rascally guards  
with muskets and pistols captured us and marched us in the center of a  
hollow square nearly to the sea &mdash; till we were beyond all the  
graperies.  Military escort &mdash; ah, I never travelled in so much state in  
all my life.  
  
</p><p>I leave the Vandal here.  I have not time to follow him farther &mdash;  
not <hi rend="italic">our</hi> Vandals to Constantinople and Smyrna and the Holy Land,  
Egypt, the islands of the sea, and to Russia and his visit to the  
emperor.  But I wish I <hi rend="italic">could</hi> tell of that visit of our gang of  
Quaker City Vandals to the grandest monarch of the age, American's  
stanch, old steadfast friend, Alexander II, Autocrat of  
Russia!</p> 
 
<p>In closing these remarks I will observe that I could have said more  
about the American Vandal abroad, and less about other things, but I  
found that he had too many disagreeable points about him, and so I  
thought I would touch him lightly and let him go.  
  
</p><p>If there is a moral to this lecture it is an injunction to all  
Vandals to <hi rend="italic">travel</hi>.  I am glad the American Vandal <hi rend="italic">goes</hi>  
abroad.  It does him good.  It makes a better man of him.  It rubs out a  
multitude of his old unworthy biases and prejudices.  It aids his  
religion, for it enlarges his charity and his benevolence, it broadens  
his views of men and things; it deepens his generosity and his  
compassion for the failings and shortcomings of his fellow creatures.  
Contact with men of various nations and many creeds teaches him that  
there are <hi rend="italic">other</hi> people in the world besides his own little  
clique, and other opinions as worthy of attention and respect as his  
own.  He finds that he and <hi rend="italic">his</hi> are not the most momentous matters  
in the universe.  Cast into trouble and misfortune in strange lands and  
being mercifully cared for by those he never saw before, he begins to  
learn that best lesson of all &mdash; that one which culminates in the  
conviction that God puts <hi rend="italic">something</hi> good and something lovable in  
every man his hands create &mdash; that the world is <hi rend="italic">not</hi> a cold,  
harsh, cruel, prison-house, stocked with all manner of selfishness and  
hate and wickedness.  It <hi rend="italic">liberalizes</hi> the Vandal to travel.  You  
never saw a bigoted, opionated, stubborn, narrow-minded, self-conceited,  
<hi rend="italic">almighty mean man</hi> in your life but he had stuck in one place ever  
since he was born and thought God made the world and dyspepsia and bile  
for <hi rend="italic">his</hi> especial comfort and satisfaction.  So I say, <hi rend="italic">by all  
means</hi> let the American Vandal go on traveling, and let no man  
discourage him.  
  
</p><p>[From <hi rend="italic">Mark Twain's Speeches</hi>, ed. Albert Bigelow Paine (New York:  Harper &amp; Brothers, 1923), pages 21-30.]  
</p>  
</div1>  
  
</body>  
</text>  
</TEI.2>  
