<?xml version="1.0"?>

<?dlps id="TwaEnco"?>
<?dlps page-images="none" figure-images="no"?>
<?dlps transcription="other"?>

<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/tei-p4/tei2.dtd" [
<!ENTITY % POSTKB "INCLUDE">
<!ENTITY % TEI.extensions.ent SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.ent">
<!ENTITY % TEI.extensions.dtd SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.dtd">
<!ENTITY % ISOnum SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/charent/iso-num.ent"> %ISOnum;
<!ENTITY % ISOpub SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/charent/iso-pub.ent"> %ISOpub;
 
]> 
<TEI.2 id="TwaEnco"> 
<teiHeader type="migrated" creator="Etext">
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title type="main">Encounter with an Interviewer</title>
<title type="sort">encounter with an interviewer</title>
<author>Twain, Mark, 1835-1910</author>
<respStmt>
<resp>Creation of machine-readable version:</resp>  
<name>Stephen Railton</name>  
<resp>Creation of digital images:</resp>  
<name>Tom Palombi, Electronic Text Center</name>  
<resp>Conversion to TEI.2-conformant markup:</resp>  
<name>University of Virginia Library Electronic Text Center.</name>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt>  
<extent>ca. <num type="kilobytes">14</num> kilobytes</extent>  
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>University of Virginia Library</publisher>
<pubPlace>Charlottesville, Virginia</pubPlace>  
<idno type="ETC">TwaEnco</idno>  
<date value="1997-09">September 1997</date>
<availability status="public">
<p n="copyright">Copyright &copy; 1997 by the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia</p>
<p n="access">Publicly accessible</p>
</availability>
<idno type="uva-pid">uva-lib:476416</idno>
</publicationStmt>
<seriesStmt>
<title>University of Virginia Library, Text collection</title>
<idno type="uva-set">UVA-LIB-Text</idno>
</seriesStmt>  
<sourceDesc>
<biblFull>
<titleStmt>
<title type="main">Encounter with an Interviewer</title>
<title level="m">Lotos Leaves</title>
<title type="sort">encounter with an interviewer</title>
<author>Mark Twain</author>
<respStmt>
<resp>Editors</resp>  
<name>John Brougham and John Elderkin</name>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt>  
<publicationStmt>  
<date value="1874-11">November 1874</date>  
<idno type="callNo">Print copy consulted:</idno>
</publicationStmt>  
</biblFull>
</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc>  
<encodingDesc>
<projectDesc>
<p>Prepared for the University of Virginia Library Electronic Text Center.</p>
</projectDesc>  
<editorialDecl>
<p>All unambiguous end-of-line hyphens have been removed, and the trailing part of a word has been joined to the preceding line.</p>  
<p>The images exist as archived TIFF images, one or more JPEG versions for general use, and thumbnail GIFs.</p>  
<p>Some keywords in the header are a local Electronic Text Center scheme to aid in establishing analytical groupings.</p>
</editorialDecl>  
</encodingDesc>  
<profileDesc>
<langUsage>
<language id="eng" usage="main">English</language>
</langUsage>  
<textClass>
<keywords>
<term>prose; fiction</term>
</keywords>  
</textClass>
</profileDesc>  
<revisionDesc>
<change>
<date value="1997-09">September 1997</date>  
<respStmt>
<resp>corrector</resp>  
<name>Tom Palombi, Electronic Text Center</name>
</respStmt>  
<item>Added TEI header and tags.</item>
</change>
<change>
<date value="2007-09">September 2007</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>Migration</resp>
<name>Ethan Gruber, University of Virginia Library</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Converted XML markup from TEI Lite to uva-dl-tei (TEI P4 with local customizations).</item>
</change>
<change>
<date value="2008-01">January 2008</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>Migration</resp>
<name>Greg Murray, University of Virginia Library</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Programmatically updated TEI header markup (but not header content) for minimal compliance with current QA requirements.</item>
</change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>  
 
<text id="d1"> 
<front id="d2">
<pb/> 
<div1 type="introduction" id="d3"> 
 
 
<p>"Sam Clemens interviews Mark Twain" was an idea for a sketch that MT 
proposed in his journal near the end of his career.  He never wrote 
that.  But for a volume titled <hi rend="italic">Lotos Leaves</hi>, edited by John 
Brougham and John Elderkin and issued in November, 1874, he did write 
this somewhat surreal sketch, about his own (non-existent) twin brother. 
This is his earliest rehearsal of the trope of changelings that he 
employs in both <hi rend="italic">The Prince and the Pauper</hi> and <hi rend="italic">Pudd'nhead 
Wilson</hi>.  Later MT used versions of this "encounter" as part of his 
live performances. 
</p> 
 
</div1> 

</front> 
 
<body id="d4"> 

<div1 type="story" id="d5"> <pb/>
<head>An Encounter with an Interviewer</head> 
 
 
<p>The nervous, dapper, "peart" young man took the chair I offered him, and 
said he was connected with the <hi rend="italic">Daily Thunderstorm</hi>, and 
added,&mdash; 
 
</p><p>"Hoping it's no harm, I've come to interview you." 
 
</p><p>"Come to what?" 
 
</p><p><hi rend="italic">"Interview</hi> you." 
 
</p><p>"Ah! I see. Yes,&mdash;yes. Um! Yes,&mdash;yes." 
 
</p><p>I was not feeling bright that morning. Indeed, my powers seemed a bit 
under a cloud. However, I went to the bookcase, and when I had been 
looking six or seven minutes, I found I was obliged to refer to the 
young man. I said,&mdash; 
 
</p><p>"How do you spell it?" 
 
</p><p>"Spell what?" 
 
</p><p>"Interview." 
 
</p><p>"O my goodness! What do you want to spell it for?" 
 
</p><p>"I don't want to spell it; I want to see what it means." 
 
</p><p>"Well, this is astonishing, I must say. <hi rend="italic">I</hi> can tell you what it 
means, if you&mdash;if you&mdash;" 
 
</p><p>"O, all right! That will answer, and much obliged to you, too." 
 
</p><p>"I n, <hi rend="italic">in</hi>, t e r, <hi rend="italic">ter</hi>, <hi rend="italic">in</hi>ter&mdash;" 
 
</p><p>"Then you spell it with an <hi rend="italic">I</hi>?" 
 
</p><p>"Why, certainly!" 
 
</p><p>"O, that is what took me so long." 
 
</p><p>"Why, my <hi rend="italic">dear</hi> sir, what did <hi rend="italic">you</hi> propose to spell it 
with?" 
 
</p><p>"Well, I&mdash;I&mdash;I hardly know. I had the Unabridged, and I was ciphering 
around in the back end, hoping I might tree her among the pictures. But 
it's a very old edition." 
 
</p><p>"Why, my friend, they wouldn't have a <hi rend="italic">picture</hi> of it in even the 
latest e&mdash; My dear sir, I beg your pardon, I mean no harm in the world, 
but you do not look as&mdash;as&mdash;intelligent as I had expected you would. No 
harm,&mdash;I mean no harm at all." 
 
</p><p>"O, don't mention it! It has often been said, and by people who would 
not flatter and who could have no inducement to flatter, that I am quite 
remarkable in that way. Yes,&mdash;yes; they always speak of it with 
rapture." 
 
</p><p>"I can easily imagine it. But about this interview. You know it is the 
custom, now, to interview any man who has become notorious." 
 
</p><p>"Indeed! I had not heard of it before. It must be very interesting. What 
do you do it with?" 
 
</p><p>"Ah, well,&mdash;well,&mdash;well,&mdash;this is disheartening. It <hi rend="italic">ought</hi> to be 
done with a club in some cases; but customarily it consists in the 
interviewer asking questions and the interviewed answering them. It is 
all the rage now. Will you let me ask you certain questions calculated 
to bring out the salient points of your public and private history?" 
 
</p><p>"O, with pleasure,&mdash;with pleasure. I have a very bad memory, but I hope 
you will not mind that.  That is to say, it is an irregular 
memory,&mdash;singularly irregular. Sometimes it goes in a gallop, and then 
again it will be as much as a fortnight passing a given point. This is a 
great grief to me." 
 
</p><p>"O, it is no matter, so you will try to do the best you can." 
 
</p><p>"I will. I will put my whole mind on it." 
 
</p><p>"Thanks. Are you ready to begin?" 
 
</p><p>"Ready." 
 
</p><p><hi rend="bold">Q.</hi> How old are you? 
 
</p><p><hi rend="bold">A.</hi> Nineteen, in June. 
 
</p><p><hi rend="bold">Q.</hi> Indeed! I would have taken you to be thirty-five or 
six. Where were you born? 
 
</p><p><hi rend="bold">A.</hi> In Missouri. 
 
</p><p><hi rend="bold">Q.</hi> When did you begin to write? 
 
</p><p><hi rend="bold">A.</hi> In 1836. 
 
</p><p><hi rend="bold">Q.</hi> Why, how could that be, if you are only nineteen now? 
 
</p><p><hi rend="bold">A.</hi> I don't know. It does seem curious somehow. 
 
</p><p><hi rend="bold">Q.</hi> It does, indeed. Who do you consider the most remarkable man 
you ever met? 
 
</p><p><hi rend="bold">A.</hi> Aaron Burr. 
 
</p><p><hi rend="bold">Q.</hi> But you never could have met Aaron Burr, if you are only 
nineteen years&mdash; 
 
</p><p><hi rend="bold">A.</hi> Now, if you know more about me than I do, what do you ask me 
for? 
 
</p><p><hi rend="bold">Q.</hi> Well, it was only a suggestion; nothing more. How did you 
happen to meet Burr? 
 
</p><p><hi rend="bold">A.</hi> Well, I happened to be at his funeral one day, and he asked me 
to make less noise, and&mdash; 
 
</p><p><hi rend="bold">Q.</hi> But, good heavens! If you were at his funeral, he must have 
been dead; and if he was dead, how could he care whether you made a 
noise or not? 
 
</p><p><hi rend="bold">A.</hi> I don't know. He was always a particular kind of a man that 
way. 
 
</p><p><hi rend="bold">Q.</hi> Still, I don't understand it at all. You say he spoke to you 
and that he was dead. 
 
</p><p><hi rend="bold">A.</hi> I didn't say he was dead. 
 
</p><p><hi rend="bold">Q.</hi> But wasn't he dead? 
 
</p><p><hi rend="bold">A.</hi> Well, some said he was, some said he wasn't. 
 
</p><p><hi rend="bold">Q.</hi> What do you think? 
 
</p><p><hi rend="bold">A.</hi> O, it was none of my business! It wasn't any of my 
funeral. 
 
</p><p><hi rend="bold">Q.</hi> Did you&mdash; However, we can never get this matter 
straight. Let me ask about something else. What was the date of your 
birth? 
 
</p><p><hi rend="bold">A.</hi> Monday, October 31, 1693. 
 
</p><p><hi rend="bold">Q.</hi> What! Impossible! That would make you a hundred and eighty 
years old. How do you account for that? 
 
</p><p><hi rend="bold">A.</hi> I don't account for it at all. 
 
</p><p><hi rend="bold">Q.</hi> But you said at first you were only nineteen, and now 
you make yourself out to be one hundred and eighty. It is an awful 
discrepancy. 
 
</p><p><hi rend="bold">A.</hi> Why, have you noticed that? (<hi rend="italic">Shaking hands</hi>.) Many a 
time it has seemed to me like a discrepancy, but somehow I couldn't make 
up my mind. How quick you notice a thing! 
 
</p><p><hi rend="bold">Q.</hi> Thank you for the compliment, as far as it goes. Had you, or 
have you, any brothers or sisters? 
 
</p><p><hi rend="bold">A.</hi> Eh! I&mdash;I&mdash;I think so,&mdash;yes,&mdash;but I don't remember. 
 
</p><p><hi rend="bold">Q.</hi> Well, that is the most extraordinary statement I ever 
heard! 
 
</p><p><hi rend="bold">A.</hi> Why, what makes you think that? 
 
</p><p><hi rend="bold">Q.</hi> How could I think otherwise? Why, look here! who is this a 
picture of on the wall?  Isn't that a brother of yours? 
 
</p><p><hi rend="bold">A.</hi> Oh! yes, yes, yes! Now you remind me of it, that <hi rend="italic">was</hi> a 
brother of mine. That's William,&mdash;<hi rend="italic">Bill</hi> we called him. Poor old 
Bill! 
 
</p><p><hi rend="bold">Q.</hi> Why? Is he dead, then? 
 
</p><p><hi rend="bold">A.</hi> Ah, well, I suppose so. We never could tell. There was a great 
mystery about it. 
 
</p><p><hi rend="bold">Q.</hi> That is sad, very sad. He disappeared, then? 
 
</p><p><hi rend="bold">A.</hi> Well, yes, in a sort of general way. We buried him. 
 
</p><p><hi rend="bold">Q.</hi> <hi rend="italic">Buried</hi> him! <hi rend="italic">Buried</hi> him without knowing whether 
he was dead or not? 
 
</p><p><hi rend="bold">A.</hi> O no! Not that. He was dead enough. 
 
</p><p><hi rend="bold">Q.</hi> Well, I confess that I can't understand this. If you buried 
him and you knew he was dead&mdash; 
 
</p><p><hi rend="bold">A.</hi> No! no! we only thought he was. 
 
</p><p><hi rend="bold">Q.</hi> O, I see! He came to life again? 
 
</p><p><hi rend="bold">A.</hi> I bet he didn't. 
 
</p><p><hi rend="bold">Q.</hi> Well, I never heard anything like this. <hi rend="italic">Somebody</hi> was 
dead. <hi rend="italic">Somebody</hi> was buried. Now, where was the mystery? 
 
</p><p><hi rend="bold">A.</hi> Ah, that's just it! That's it exactly. You see we were 
twins,&mdash;defunct and I,&mdash;and we got mixed in the bath-tub when we were 
only two weeks old, and one of us was drowned. But we didn't know which. 
Some think it was Bill, some think it was me. 
 
</p><p><hi rend="bold">Q.</hi> Well, that <hi rend="italic">is</hi> remarkable. What do <hi rend="italic">you</hi> 
think? 
 
</p><p><hi rend="bold">A.</hi> Goodness knows! I would give whole worlds to know. This 
solemn, this awful mystery has cast a gloom over my whole life. But I 
will tell you a secret now, which I never have revealed to any creature 
before. One of us had a peculiar mark, a large mole on the back of the 
left hand,&mdash;that was <hi rend="italic">me. That child was the one that was 
drowned.</hi> 
 
</p><p><hi rend="bold">Q.</hi> Very well, then, I don't see that there is any mystery about 
it, after all. 
 
</p><p><hi rend="bold">A.</hi> You don't? Well, <hi rend="italic">I</hi> do. Anyway I don't see how they 
could ever have been such a blundering lot as to go and bury the wrong 
child. But, 'sh!&mdash;don't mention it where the family can hear of it. 
Heaven knows they have heart-breaking troubles enough without adding 
this. 
 
</p><p><hi rend="bold">Q.</hi> Well, I believe I have got material enough for the present, 
and I am very much obliged to you for the pains you have taken. But I 
was a good deal interested in that account of Aaron Burr's funeral. 
Would you mind telling me what particular circumstance it was that made 
you think Burr was such a remarkable man? 
 
</p><p><hi rend="bold">A.</hi> O, it was a mere trifle! Not one man in fifty would have 
noticed it at all. When the sermon was over, and the procession all 
ready to start for the cemetery, and the body all arranged nice in the 
hearse, he said he wanted to take a last look at the scenery, and so he 
<hi rend="italic">got up and rode with the driver</hi>. 
 
</p><p>Then the young man reverently withdrew. He was very pleasant company, 
and I was sorry to see him go.<lb/> 
 
&mdash;<hi rend="italic">1874</hi> 
</p> 
 
</div1> 

</body> 
 
</text> 
</TEI.2> 
