<?xml version="1.0"?>

<?dlps id="TwaHon4"?>
<?dlps page-images="none" figure-images="no"?>
<?dlps transcription="other"?>

<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/tei-p4/tei2.dtd" [
<!ENTITY % POSTKB "INCLUDE">
<!ENTITY % TEI.extensions.ent SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.ent">
<!ENTITY % TEI.extensions.dtd SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.dtd">
<!ENTITY % ISOnum SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/charent/iso-num.ent"> %ISOnum;
<!ENTITY % ISOpub SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/charent/iso-pub.ent"> %ISOpub;

]>
<TEI.2 id="TwaHon4">
<teiHeader type="migrated" creator="Etext">
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title type="main">Scenes in Honolulu &mdash; No. 4</title>
<title type="sort">scenes in honolulu &mdash; no 4</title>
<author>Twain, Mark, 1835-1910</author>
<respStmt>
<resp>Creation of machine-readable version:</resp>
<name>Steve Railton</name>
<resp>Conversion to TEI.2-conformant markup:</resp>
<name>J. Nathaniel Goldsmith, University of Virginia Library Electronic Text Center.</name>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt>
<extent>ca. <num type="kilobytes">19</num> kilobytes</extent>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>University of Virginia Library</publisher>
<pubPlace>Charlottesville, Virginia</pubPlace>
<idno type="ETC">TwaHon4</idno>
<date value="2001">2001</date>
<availability status="public">
<p n="copyright">Copyright &copy; 2001 by the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia</p>
<p n="access">Publicly accessible</p>
</availability>
<idno type="uva-pid">uva-lib:476420</idno>
</publicationStmt>
<seriesStmt>
<title>University of Virginia Library, Text collection</title>
<idno type="uva-set">UVA-LIB-Text</idno>
</seriesStmt>
<sourceDesc>
<biblFull>
<titleStmt>
<title type="main">Scenes in Honolulu &mdash; No. 4</title>
<title type="sort">scenes in honolulu &mdash; no 4</title>
<author>Mark Twain, pseud. Samuel Langhorne Clemens</author>
</titleStmt>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>Sacramento Union</publisher>
<pubPlace>Sacramento</pubPlace>
<date value="1866-04-19">19 April 1866</date>
<idno type="callNo">Source copy consulted:</idno>
</publicationStmt>
</biblFull>
</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc>
<encodingDesc>
<projectDesc>
<p>Prepared for the University of Virginia Library Electronic Text Center.</p>
</projectDesc>
<editorialDecl>
<p>All unambiguous end-of-line hyphens have been removed, and the  trailing part of a word has been joined to the preceding line.</p>
<p id="ETC">Some keywords in the header are a local Electronic Text Center scheme  to aid in establishing analytical groupings.</p>
</editorialDecl>
</encodingDesc>
<profileDesc>
<langUsage>
<language id="eng" usage="main">English</language>
</langUsage>
<textClass>
<keywords>
<term>non-fiction</term>
<term>prose</term>
<term>masculine</term>
<term>Mark Twain</term>
</keywords>
</textClass>
</profileDesc>
<revisionDesc>
<change>
<date value="2001-07">July, 2001</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>corrector</resp>
<name/>
</respStmt>
<item/>
</change>
<change>
<date value="2007-09">September 2007</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>Migration</resp>
<name>Ethan Gruber, University of Virginia Library</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Converted XML markup from TEI Lite to uva-dl-tei (TEI P4 with local customizations).</item>
</change>
<change>
<date value="2008-01">January 2008</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>Migration</resp>
<name>Greg Murray, University of Virginia Library</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Programmatically updated TEI header markup (but not header content) for minimal compliance with current QA requirements.</item>
</change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text id="d1">
<body id="d2">
<div1 type="letter" id="d3">
<head>19 April 1866<lb/>
HONOLULU, MARCH, 1866.
</head>

<div2 type="section" n="1" id="d4">
<head>OUR ARRIVAL ELABORATED A LITTLE MORE</head>

<p>We came in sight of two of this group of islands, Oahu and Molokai (pronounced 
O-waw-hoo and Mollo-<hi rend="italic">ki</hi>), on the morning of the 18th, and soon exchanged the 
dark blue waters of the deep sea for the brilliant light blue of "sounding." The fat, ugly 
birds (said to be a species of albatross) which had skimmed after us on tireless wings 
clear across the ocean, left us, and an occasional flying fish went skimming over the 
water in their stead. Oahu loomed high, rugged, treeless, barren, black and dreary, out of 
the sea, and in the distance Molokai lay like a homely swaybacked whale on the water.</p>
</div2>

<div2 type="section" n="2" id="d5">
<head>THE HAWAIIAN FLAG</head>
<p>	As we rounded the promontory of Diamond Head (bringing into view a grove of 
coconut trees, first ocular proof that we were in the tropics), we ran up the Stars and 
Stripes at the main spencer gaff, and the Hawaiian flag at the fore. The latter is suggestive 
of the prominent political elements of the Islands. It is part French, part English, part 
American, and is Hawaiian in general. The union is the English cross; the remainder of 
the flag (horizontal stripes) looks American, but has a blue French stripe in addition to 
our red and white ones. The flag was gotten up by foreign legations in council with the 
Hawaiian Government. The eight stripes refer to the eight islands which are inhabited; 
the other four are barren rocks incapable of supporting a population.</p>
</div2>

<div2 type="section" n="3" id="d6">
<head>REFLECTIONS</head>
<p>	As we came in sight we fired a gun, and a good part of Honolulu turned out to 
welcome the steamer. It was Sunday morning, and about church time, and we steamed 
through the narrow channel to the music of six different church bells, which sent their 
mellow tones far and wide, over hills and valleys, which were peopled by naked, savage, 
thundering barbarians only fifty years ago! Six Christian churches within five miles of 
the ruins of a pagan temple, where human sacrifices were daily offered up to hideous 
idols in the last century! We were within pistol shot of one of a group of islands whose 
ferocious inhabitants closed in upon the doomed and helpless Captain Cook and 
murdered him, eighty-seven years ago; and lo! their descendants were at church! Behold 
what the missionaries have wrought!</p>
</div2>

<div2 type="section" n="4" id="d7">
<head>THE CROWD ON THE PIER</head>

<p>	By the time we had worked our slow way up to the wharf, under the guidance of 
McIntyre, the pilot, a mixed crowd of four or five hundred people had assembled: 
Chinamen, in the costume of their country; foreigners and the better class of natives, and 
"half whites" in carriages and dressed in Sacramento summer fashion; other native men 
on foot, some in the cast-off clothing of white folks, and a few wearing a battered hat, an 
old ragged vest, and nothing else&mdash;at least nothing but an unnecessarily slender rag passed 
between the legs; native women clad in a single garment&mdash;a bright colored robe or 
wrapper as voluminous as a balloon, with full sleeves. This robe is "gathered" from 
shoulder to shoulder, before and behind, and then descends in ample folds to the feet&mdash;seldom a chemise or any other undergarment&mdash;fits like a circus tent fits the tent pole, and 
no hoops. These robes were bright yellow, or bright crimson, or pure black occasionally, 
or gleaming white; but "solid colors" and "stunning" ones were the rule. They wore little 
hats such as the sex wear in your cities, and some of the younger women had very pretty 
faces and splendid black eyes and heavy masses of long black hair, occasionally put up in 
a "net"; some of these dark, gingerbread colored beauties were on foot&mdash;generally on bare 
foot, I may add&mdash;and others were on horseback&mdash;astraddle; they never ride any other way, 
and they ought to know which way is best, for there are no more accomplished 
horsewomen in the world, it is said. The balance of the crowd consisted chiefly of little 
half-naked native boys and girls. All were chattering in the catchy, chopped-up Kanaka 
language; but what they were chattering about will always remain a mystery to me.</p>
</div2>

<div2 type="section" n="5" id="d8">
<head>THE KING</head>
<p>	Captain Fitch said, "There's the King! that's him in the buggy! I know him far as I 
can see him."</p>

<p>	I had never seen a king in my life, and I naturally took out my notebook and put 
him down: "Tall, slender, dark; full-bearded; green frock coat, with lapels and collar 
bordered with gold band an inch wide; plug hat&mdash;broad gold band around it; royal 
costume looks too much like a livery; this man isn't as fleshy as I thought he was."</p>

<p>	I had just got these notes entered when Captain Fitch discovered that he had got 
hold of the wrong King&mdash;or, rather, that he had got hold of the King's driver or a carriage&mdash;driver of one of the nobility. The King was not present at all. It was a great 
disappointment to me. I heard afterward that the comfortable, easy-going King 
Kamehameha (pronounced Ka-may-ah-may-ah) V had been seen sitting on a barrel on 
the wharf, the day before, fishing; but there was no consolation in that; that did not 
restore to me my lost King. </p>
</div2>

<div2 type="section" n="6" id="d9">
<head>HONOLULU</head>
<p>The town of Honolulu (said to contain between twelve thousand and fifteen 
thousand inhabitants) is spread over a dead level; has streets from twenty to thirty feet 
wide, solid and level as a floor, most of them straight as a line and a few as crooked as a 
corkscrew; houses one and two stories high, built of wood, straw, 'dobes, and dull cream-colored 
pebble-and-shell-conglomerated coral cut into oblong square blocks and laid in 
cement, but no brick houses; there are great yards, more like plazas, about a large number 
of the dwelling houses, and these are carpeted with bright green grass, into which your 
foot sinks out of sight; and they are ornamented by a hundred species of beautiful flowers 
and blossoming shrubs, and shaded by noble tamarind trees and the "Pride of India," with 
its fragrant flower, and by the "Umbrella Tree," and I do not know how many more. I had 
rather smell Honolulu at sunset than the old police courtroom in San Francisco. </p>
</div2>

<div2 type="section" n="7" id="d10">
<head>ALMOST A KING</head>
<p>	I had not shaved since I left San Francisco&mdash;ten days. As soon as I got ashore, I 
hunted for a striped pole, and shortly found one. I always had a yearning to be a king. 
This may never be, I suppose. But at any rate it will always be a satisfaction to me to 
know that if I am not a king, I am the next thing to it&mdash;I have been shaved by the King's 
barber. </p>
</div2>

<div2 type="section" n="8" id="d11">
<head>LANDSMEN ON "SEA LEGS"</head>

<p>	Walking about on shore was very uncomfortable at first; there was no spring to 
the solid ground, and I missed the heaving and rolling of the ship's deck; it was 
unpleasant to lean unconsciously to an anticipated lurch of the world and find that the 
world did not lurch, as it should have done. And there was something else missed&mdash;something gone something wanting, I could not tell what&mdash;a dismal vacuum of some kind 
or other&mdash;a sense of emptiness. But I found out what it was presently. It was the absence 
of the ceaseless dull hum of beating waves and whipping sails and fluttering of the 
propeller, and creaking of the ship&mdash;sounds I had become so accustomed to that I had 
ceased to notice them and had become unaware of their existence until the deep Sunday 
stillness on shore made me vaguely conscious that a familiar spirit of some kind or other 
was gone from me. Walking on the solid earth with legs used to the "giving" of the decks 
under his tread made Brown sick, and he went off to bed and left me to wander alone 
about this odd-looking city of the tropics.</p>
</div2>

<div2 type="section" n="9" id="d12">
<head>NEW SCENES AND STRONG CONTRASTS</head>
<p>The further I traveled through the town the better I liked it. Every step revealed a 
new contrast&mdash;disclosed something I was unaccustomed to. In place of the grand mud-colored brown stone fronts of San Francisco, I saw neat white cottages, with green 
window shutters; in place of front yards like billiard tables with iron fences around them, 
I saw those cottages surrounded by ample yards, about like Portsmouth Square (as to 
size), thickly clad with green grass, and shaded by tall trees, through whose dense foliage 
the sun could scarcely penetrate; in place of the customary infernal geranium languishing 
in dust and general debility on tin-roofed rear additions or in bedroom windows, I saw 
luxurious banks and thickets of flowers, fresh as a meadow after a rain, and glowing with 
the richest dyes; in place of the dingy horrors of the "Willows," and the painful sharp-pointed shrubbery of that funny caricature of nature which they call "South Park," I saw 
huge-bodied, wide-spreading forest trees, with strange names and stranger appearance&mdash;trees that cast a shadow like a thundercloud, and were able to stand alone without being 
tied to green poles; in place of those vile, tiresome, stupid, everlasting goldfish, wiggling 
around in glass globes and assuming all shades and degrees of distortion through the 
magnifying and diminishing qualities of their transparent prison houses, I saw cats&mdash;Tom 
cats, Mary Ann cats, long-tailed cats, bobtail cats, blind cats, one-eyed cats, walleyed 
cats, cross-eyed cats, gray cats, black cats, white cats, yellow cats, striped cats, spotted 
cats, tame cats, wild cats, singed cats, individual cats, groups of cats, platoons of cats, 
companies of cats, regiments of cats, armies of cats, multitudes of cats, millions of cats, 
and all of them sleek, fat, lazy, and sound asleep; in place of roughs and rowdies staring 
and blackguarding on the corners, I saw long-haired, saddle-colored Sandwich Island 
maidens sitting on the ground in the shade of corner houses, gazing indolently at 
whatever or whoever happened along; instead of that wretched cobblestone pavement 
nuisance, I walked on a firm foundation of coral, built up from the bottom of the sea by 
the absurd but persevering insect of that name, with a light layer of lava and cinders 
overlying the coral, belched up out of fathomless hell long ago through the seared and 
blackened crater that stands dead and cold and harmless yonder in the distance now; 
instead of cramped and crowded streetcars, I met dusky native women sweeping by, free 
as the wind, on fleet horses and astraddle, with gaudy riding sashes streaming like 
banners behind them; instead of the combined stenches of Sacramento Street, Chinadom, 
and Brannan Street slaughterhouses, I breathed the balmy fragrance of jessamine, 
oleander, and the Pride of India; in place of the hurry and bustle and noisy confusion of 
San Francisco, I moved in the midst of a summer calm as tranquil as dawn in the Garden 
of Eden; in place of our familiar skirting sand hills and the placid bay, I saw on the one 
side a framework of tall, precipitous mountains close at hand, clad in refreshing green, 
and cleft by deep, cool, chasmlike valleys&mdash;and in front the grand sweep of the ocean; a 
brilliant, transparent green near the shore, bound and bordered by a long white line of 
foamy spray dashing against the reef, and further out the dead blue water of the deep sea, 
flecked with "white caps," and in the far horizon a single, lonely sail&mdash;</p>

<p>	At this moment, this man Brown, who has no better manners than to read over 
one's shoulder, observes: </p>

<p>	"Yes, and hot. Oh, I reckon not (only 82 in the shade)! Go on, now, and put it all 
down, now that you've begun; just say, 'And more "santipedes," and cockroaches, and 
fleas, and lizards, and red ants, and scorpions, and spiders, and mosquitoes and 
missionaries'&mdash;oh, blame my cats if I'd live here two months, not if I was High-You-Muck-a-Muck and King of Wawhoo, and had a harem full of hyenas!" (Wahine, most 
generally pronounced Wyheeny, seems to answer for wife, woman, and female of 
questionable character, indifferently. I never can get this man Brown to understand that 
"hyena" is not the proper pronunciation. He says "It ain't any odds; it describes some of 
 'em, anyway.") </p>

<p>	I remarked: "But, Mr. Brown, these are trifles."</p>

<p>"Trifles be&mdash;blowed! You get nipped by one of them scorpions once, and see how 
you like it! There was Mrs. Jones, swabbing her face with a sponge; she felt something 
grab her cheek; she dropped the sponge and out popped a scorpion an inch and a half 
long! Well, she just got up and danced the Highland fling for two hours and a half&mdash;and 
yell!&mdash;why, you could have heard her from Lu-wow to Hoolahoola, with the wind fair! 
and for three days she soaked her cheek in brandy and salt, and it swelled up as big as 
your two fists. And you want to know what made me light out of bed so sudden last 
night? Only a 'santipede'&mdash;nothing, only a 'santipede,' with forty-two legs on a side, and 
every foot hot enough to burn a hole through a rawhide. Don't you know one of them 
things grabbed Miss Boone's foot when she was riding one day? He was hid in the 
stirrup, and just clamped himself around her foot and sunk his fangs plum through her 
shoe; and she just throwed her whole soul into one war whoop and then fainted. And she 
didn't get out of bed nor set that foot on the floor again for three weeks. And how did 
Captain Godfrey always get off so easy? Why, because he always carried a bottle full of 
scorpions and santipedes soaked in alcohol, and whenever he got bit he bathed the place 
with that devilish mixture or took a drink out of it, I don't recollect which. And how did 
he have to do once, when he hadn't his bottle along? He had to cut out the bite with his 
knife and fill up the hole with arnica, and then prop his mouth open with the bootjack to 
keep from getting the lockjaw. Oh, fill me up about this lovely country! You can go on 
writing that slop about balmy breezes and fragrant flowers, and all that sort of truck, but 
you're not going to leave out them santipedes and things for want of being reminded of it, 
you know." </p>

<p> I said mildly: "But, Mr. Brown, these are the mere&mdash;" </p>

<p>	"Mere&mdash;your grandmother! they ain't the mere anything! What's the use of you 
telling me they're the mere&mdash;mere&mdash;whatever it was you was going to call it? You look at 
them raw splotches all over my face&mdash;all over my arms&mdash;all over my body! Mosquito 
bites! Don't tell me about mere&mdash;mere things! You can't get around them mosquito bites. I 
took and brushed out my bar [mosquito net] good night before last, and tucked it in all 
around, and before morning I was eternally thawed up, anyhow. And the night before I 
fastened her up all right, and got in bed and smoked that old strong pipe until I got 
strangled and smothered and couldn't get out, and then they swarmed in there and 
jammed their bills through my shirt and sucked me as dry as a life preserver before I got 
my breath again. And how did that deadfall work? I was two days making it, and sweated 
two buckets full of brine, and blame the mosquito even went under it; and sloshing 
around in my sleep I ketched my foot in it and got it	flattened out so that it wouldn't go 
into a green turtle shell forty-four inches across the back. Jim Ayers grinding out seven 
double verses of poetry about Waw-<hi rend="italic">hoo</hi>! and crying about leaving the blasted 
place in the two last verses; and you slobbering here about&mdash;there you are!  Now&mdash;<hi rend="italic">now</hi>, what do you say? That yellow spider could straddle over a saucer just like 
nothing&mdash;and if I hadn't been here to set that spittoon on him, he would have been between 
your sheets in a minute&mdash;he was traveling straight for your bed&mdash;he had his eye on it. Just 
pull at that web that he's been stringing after him&mdash;pretty near as hard to break as sewing 
silk; and look at his feet sticking out all round the spittoon. Oh, confound Waw-<hi rend="italic">hoo</hi>!" </p>

<p>  I am glad Brown has got disgusted at that murdered spider and gone; I don't like to be 
interrupted when I am writing&mdash;especially by Brown, who is one of those men who 
always looks at the unpleasant side of every thing, and I seldom do. </p>
</div2>

<closer>
<signed>MARK TWAIN</signed>
</closer>

</div1>
</body>
</text>
</TEI.2>
