<?xml version="1.0"?>

<?dlps id="TwaHowt"?>
<?dlps page-images="none" figure-images="no"?>
<?dlps transcription="other"?>

<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/tei-p4/tei2.dtd" [
<!ENTITY % POSTKB "INCLUDE">
<!ENTITY % TEI.extensions.ent SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.ent">
<!ENTITY % TEI.extensions.dtd SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.dtd">
<!ENTITY % ISOnum SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/charent/iso-num.ent"> %ISOnum;
<!ENTITY % ISOpub SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/charent/iso-pub.ent"> %ISOpub;
 
]> 
<TEI.2 id="TwaHowt"> 
<teiHeader type="migrated" creator="Etext">
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title type="main">How to Tell a Story</title>
<title type="sort">how to tell a story</title>
<author>Twain, Mark, 1835-1910</author>
<respStmt>
<resp>Creation of machine-readable version:</resp>  
<name>Stephen Railton</name>  
<resp>Conversion to TEI.2-conformant markup:</resp>  
<name>Text prepared by the 1997-98 J. Wallace Sieg Graduate Fellow Jennifer 
Easley for the University of Virginia Library Electronic Text Center.</name>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt>  
<extent>ca. <num type="kilobytes">15</num> kilobytes</extent>  
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>University of Virginia Library</publisher>
<pubPlace>Charlottesville, Virginia</pubPlace>  
<idno type="ETC">TwaHowt</idno>  
<date value="1997">1997</date>
<availability status="public">
<p n="copyright">Copyright &copy; 1997 by the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia</p>
<p n="access">Publicly accessible</p>
</availability>
<idno type="uva-pid">uva-lib:476423</idno>
</publicationStmt>
<seriesStmt>
<title>University of Virginia Library, Text collection</title>
<idno type="uva-set">UVA-LIB-Text</idno>
</seriesStmt>  
<sourceDesc>
<biblFull>
<titleStmt>
<title type="main">How to Tell a Story</title>
<title type="sort">how to tell a story</title>
<author>Mark Twain, pseud. Samuel Langhorne Clemens</author>
</titleStmt>  
<publicationStmt>  
<idno type="callNo">Print copy consulted:</idno>
</publicationStmt>  
</biblFull>
</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc>  
<encodingDesc>
<projectDesc>
<p>Prepared for the University of Virginia Library Electronic Text Center.</p>
</projectDesc>  
<editorialDecl>
<p>All unambiguous end-of-line hyphens have been removed, and the trailing part of a word has been joined to the preceding line.</p>  
<p>The images exist as archived TIFF images, one or more JPEG versions for general use, and thumbnail GIFs.</p>  
<p>Some keywords in the header are a local Electronic Text Center scheme to aid in establishing analytical groupings.</p>
</editorialDecl>  
</encodingDesc>  
<profileDesc>
<creation>
<date value="1895">1895</date>
</creation>  
<langUsage>
<language id="eng" usage="main">English</language>
</langUsage>  
<textClass>
<keywords>
<term>prose; non-fiction</term>
</keywords>  
</textClass>
</profileDesc>  
<revisionDesc>
<change>
<date value="1997-09">September, 1997</date>  
<respStmt>
<resp>corrector</resp>  
<name>Jennifer Easley, Electronic Text Center</name>
</respStmt>  
<item>Added TEI header and tags.</item>
</change>
<change>
<date value="2007-09">September 2007</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>Migration</resp>
<name>Ethan Gruber, University of Virginia Library</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Converted XML markup from TEI Lite to uva-dl-tei (TEI P4 with local customizations).</item>
</change>
<change>
<date value="2008-01">January 2008</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>Migration</resp>
<name>Greg Murray, University of Virginia Library</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Programmatically updated TEI header markup (but not header content) for minimal compliance with current QA requirements.</item>
</change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>  
 
<text id="d1"> 
 
<body id="d2"> 
 
<div1 type="essay" id="d3"> 
<head> 
How to Tell a Story<lb/> 
THE HUMOROUS STORY AN AMERICAN<lb/> 
DEVELOPMENT.&mdash;IT'S DIFFERENCE<lb/> 
FROM COMIC AND WITTY STORIES. 
</head> 
 
<div2 type="section" id="d4"> 
<p> 
I do not claim that I can tell a story as it ought to be told. I only 
claim to know how a story ought to be told, for I have been almost daily 
in the company of the most expert storytellers for many years. 
</p><p> 
There are several kinds of stories, but only one difficult kind&mdash;the 
humorous. I will talk mainly about that one. The humorous story is 
American, the comic story is English, the witty story is French. The 
humorous story depends for its effect upon the <hi rend="italic">manner</hi> of the 
telling; the comic story and the witty story upon the <hi rend="italic">matter</hi>. 
</p><p> 
The humorous story may be spun out to great length, and may 
wander around as much as it pleases, and arrive nowhere in 
particular; but the comic and witty stories must be brief and end with 
a point. The humorous story bubbles gently along, the others burst. 
</p><p> 
The humorous story is strictly a work of art,&mdash;high and delicate 
art,&mdash;and only an artist can tell it; but no art is necessary in telling 
the comic and the witty story; anybody can do it. The art of telling a 
humorous story&mdash;understand, I mean by word of mouth, not print&mdash;was 
created in America, and has remained at home. 
</p><p> 
The humorous story is told gravely; the teller does his best to 
conceal the fact that he even dimly suspects that there is anything 
funny about it; but the teller of the comic story tells you beforehand 
that it is one of the funniest things he has ever heard, then tells it 
with eager delight, and is the first person to laugh when he gets 
through. And sometimes, if he has had good success, he is so glad and 
happy that he will repeat the "nub" of it and glance around from face to 
face, collecting applause, and then repeat it again. It is a pathetic 
thing to see. 
</p><p> 
Very often, of course, the rambling and disjointed humorous story 
finishes with a nub, point, snapper, or whatever you like to call it. 
Then the listener must be alert, for in many cases the teller will 
divert attention from that nub by dropping it in a carefully casual and 
indifferent way, with the pretense that he does not know it is a nub. 
</p><p> 
Artemus Ward used that trick a good deal; then when the belated 
audience presently caught the joke he would look up with innocent 
surprise, as if wondering what they had found to laugh at.  Dan Setchell 
used it before him, Nye and Riley and others use it to-day. 
</p><p> 
But the teller of the comic story does not slur the nub; he shouts at 
you&mdash;every time. And when he prints it, in England, France, Germany and 
Italy, he italicises it, puts some whooping exclamation-points after it, 
and sometimes explains it in a parenthesis. All of which is very 
depressing, and makes one want to renounce joking and lead a better 
life. 
</p><p> 
Let me set down an instance of the comic method, using an anecdote 
which has been popular all over the world for twelve or fifteen hundred 
years. The teller tells it in this way:  
</p> 
</div2> 
 
<div2 type="story" id="d5"> 
<head>THE WOUNDED SOLDIER</head> 
<p> 
In the course of a certain battle a soldier whose leg had been shot 
off appealed to another soldier who was hurrying by to carry him to the 
rear, informing him at the same time of the loss which he had sustained; 
whereupon the generous son of Mars, shouldering the unfortunate, 
proceeded to carry out his desire. The bullets and cannon-balls were 
flying in all directions, and presently one of the latter took the 
wounded man's head off&mdash;without, however, his deliverer being aware of 
it. In no long time he was hailed by an officer, who said: 
</p><p> 
"Where are you going with that carcass?" 
</p><p> 
"To the rear, sir&mdash;he's lost his leg!" 
</p><p> 
"His leg, forsooth?" responded the astonished officer; "you mean his 
head, you booby." 
</p><p> 
Whereupon the soldier dispossessed himself of his burden, and stood 
looking down upon it in great perplexity. At length he said: 
</p><p> 
"It is true, sir, just as you have said." Then after a pause he 
added, <hi rend="italic">"But he</hi> TOLD <hi rend="italic">me</hi> IT WAS HIS LEG!!!!!" 
</p> 
</div2> 
 
<div2 type="section" id="d6"> 
<p> 
Here the narrator bursts into explosion after explosion of thunderous 
horse-laughter, repeating that nub from time to time through his 
gaspings and shriekings and suffocatings. 
</p><p> 
It takes only a minute and a half to tell that in its comic-story 
form; and isn't worth the telling, after all. Put into the 
humorous-story form it takes ten minutes, and is about the funniest 
thing I have ever listened to&mdash;as James Whitcomb Riley tells it. 
</p><p> 
He tells it in the character of a dull-witted old farmer who has just 
heard it for the first time, thinks it unspeakably funny, and is trying 
to repeat it to a neighbor. But he can't remember it; so he gets it all 
mixed up and wanders helplessly round and round, putting in tedious 
details that don't belong in the tale and only retard it; taking them 
out conscientiously and putting in others that are just as useless; 
making minor mistakes now and then and stopping to correct them and 
explain how he came to make them; remembering things which he forgot to 
put in in their proper place and going back to put them in there; 
stopping his narrative a good while in order to try to recall the name 
of the soldier that was hurt, and finally remembering that the soldier's 
name was not mentioned, and remarking placidly that the name is of no 
real importance, after all,&mdash;and so on, and so on, and so on. 
</p><p> 
The teller is innocent and happy and pleased with himself, and has to 
stop every little while to hold himself in and keep from laughing 
outright; and does hold in, but his body quakes in a jelly-like way with 
interior chuckles; and at the end of the ten minutes the audience have 
laughed until they are exhausted, and the tears are running down their 
faces. 
</p><p> 
The simplicity and innocence and sincerity and unconsciousness of the 
old farmer are perfectly simulated, and the result is a performance 
which is thoroughly charming and delicious. This is art&mdash;and fine and 
beautiful, and only a master can compass it; but a machine could tell 
the other story. 
</p><p> 
To string incongruities and absurdities together in a wandering and 
sometimes purposeless way, and seem innocently unaware that they are 
absurdities, is the basis of the American art, if my position is 
correct. Another feature is the slurring of the point. A third is the 
dropping of a studied remark apparently without knowing it, as if one 
were thinking aloud. The fourth and last is the pause. 
</p><p> 
Artemus Ward dealt in numbers three and four a good deal. He would 
begin to tell with great animation something which he seemed to think 
was wonderful; then lose confidence, and after an apparently 
absent-minded pause add an incongruous remark in a soliloquizing way; 
and that was the remark intended to explode the mine&mdash;and it did. 
</p><p> 
For instance, he would say eagerly, excitedly, "I once knew a man in 
New Zealand who hadn't a tooth in his head"&mdash;here his animation would 
die out; a silent, reflective pause would follow, then he would say 
dreamily, and as if to himself, "and yet that man could beat a drum 
better than any man I ever saw." 
</p><p> 
The pause is an exceedingly important feature in any kind of story, 
and a frequently recurring feature, too. It is a dainty thing, and 
delicate, and also uncertain and treacherous; for it must be exactly the 
right length&mdash;no more and no less&mdash;or it fails of its purpose and makes 
trouble. If the pause is too short the impressive point is passed, and 
the audience have had time to divine that a surprise is intended&mdash;and 
then you can't surprise them, of course. 
</p><p> 
On the platform I used to tell a negro ghost story that had a pause 
in front of the snapper on the end, and that pause was the most 
important thing in the whole story. If I got it the right length 
precisely, I could spring the finishing ejaculation with effect enough 
to make some impressionable girl deliver a startled little yelp and jump 
out of her seat&mdash;and that was what I was after. This story was called 
"The Golden Arm," and was told in this fashion. You can practise with it 
yourself&mdash;and mind you look out for the pause and get it right. 
</p> 
</div2> 
 
<div2 type="story" id="d7"> 
<head>THE GOLDEN ARM</head> 
<p> 
Once 'pon a time dey wuz a monsus mean man, en he live 'way out in de 
prairie all 'lone by hisself, 'cep'n he had a wife. En bimeby she died, 
en he tuck en toted her way out dah in de prairie en buried her. Well, 
she had a golden arm&mdash;all solid gold, fum de shoulder down. He wuz 
pow'ful mean&mdash;pow'ful; en dat night he couldn't sleep, caze he want dat 
golden arm so bad. 
</p><p> 
When it come midnight he couldn't stan' it no mo'; so he git up, he 
did, en tuck his lantern en shoved out thoo de storm en dug her up en 
got de golden arm; en he bent his head down 'gin de win', en plowed en 
plowed en plowed thoo de snow. Den all on a sudden he stop (make a 
considerable pause here, and look startled, and take a listening 
attitude) en say: "My <hi rend="italic">lan'</hi>, what's dat!" 
</p><p> 
En he listen&mdash;en listen&mdash;en de win' say (set your teeth together and 
imitate the wailing and wheezing singsong of the wind), "Bzzz-z-zzz"&mdash;en 
den, way back yonder what de grave is, he hear a <hi rend="italic">voice!</hi>&mdash;he hear 
a voice all mix' up in de win'&mdash;can't hardly tell 'em 
'part&mdash;"Bzzz-zzz&mdash;W-h-o&mdash;g-o-t&mdash;m-y&mdash;g-o-l-d-e-n&mdash;<hi rend="italic">arm?</hi>&mdash;zzz&mdash;zzz&mdash;W-h-o 
g-o-t m-y g-o-l-d-e-n <hi rend="italic">arm?"</hi> (You must begin to shiver violently 
now.) 
</p><p> 
En he begin to shiver en shake, en say, "Oh, my! <hi rend="italic">Oh</hi>, my lan'!" 
en de win' blow de lantern out, en de snow en sleet blow in his face en 
mos' choke him, en he start a-plowin' knee-deep toward home mos' dead, 
he so sk'yerd&mdash;en pooty soon he hear de voice agin, en (pause) it 'us 
comin' <hi rend="italic">after</hi> him! "Bzzz&mdash;zzz&mdash;zzz&mdash;W-h-o&mdash;g-o-t&mdash;m-y 
g-o-l-d-e-n&mdash;<hi rend="italic">arm?"</hi> 
</p><p> 
When he git to de pasture he hear it agin&mdash;closter now, en 
a-<hi rend="italic">comin'!</hi>&mdash;a-comin' back dah in de dark en de storm&mdash;(repeat the 
wind and the voice). When he git to de house he rush up-stairs en jump 
in de bed en kiver up, head and years, en lay dah shiverin' en 
shakin'&mdash;en den way out dah he hear it <hi rend="italic">again!</hi>&mdash;en 
a-<hi rend="italic">comin'!</hi> En bimeby he hear (pause&mdash;awed, listening 
attitude)&mdash;pat&mdash;pat&mdash;pat&mdash;<hi rend="italic">hit's a-comin' up-stairs!</hi> Den he hear 
de latch, en he <hi rend="italic">know</hi> it's in de room! 
</p><p> 
Den pooty soon he know it's a-<hi rend="italic">stannin' by de bed!</hi> (Pause.) 
Den&mdash;he know it's a&mdash;<hi rend="italic">bendin' down over him</hi>&mdash;en he cain't skasely 
git his breath! Den&mdash;den&mdash;he seem to feel someth'n <hi rend="italic">c-o-l-d</hi>, right 
down 'most agin his head! (Pause.) 
</p><p> 
Den de voice say, <hi rend="italic">right at his 
year</hi>&mdash;"W-h-o&mdash;g-o-t&mdash;m-y&mdash;g-o-l-d-e-n <hi rend="italic">arm?"</hi> (You must wail it 
out very plaintively and accusingly; then you stare steadily and 
impressively into the face of the farthest-gone auditor,&mdash;a girl, 
preferably,&mdash;and let that awe-inspiring pause begin to build itself in 
the deep hush. When it has reached exactly the right length, jump 
suddenly at that girl and yell, <hi rend="italic">"You've</hi> got it!" 
</p><p> 
If you've got the <hi rend="italic">pause</hi> right, she'll fetch a dear little yelp 
and spring right out of her shoes.  But you <hi rend="italic">must</hi> get the pause 
right; and you will find it the most troublesome and aggravating and 
uncertain thing you ever undertook.) 
</p> 
</div2> 
</div1> 
</body> 
</text> 
</TEI.2> 
 
