<?xml version="1.0"?>

<?dlps id="TwaSoci"?>
<?dlps page-images="none" figure-images="no"?>
<?dlps transcription="other"?>

<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/tei-p4/tei2.dtd" [
<!ENTITY % POSTKB "INCLUDE">
<!ENTITY % TEI.extensions.ent SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.ent">
<!ENTITY % TEI.extensions.dtd SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.dtd">
<!ENTITY % ISOnum SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/charent/iso-num.ent"> %ISOnum;
<!ENTITY % ISOpub SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/charent/iso-pub.ent"> %ISOpub;
 
]> 
<TEI.2 id="TwaSoci"> 
<teiHeader type="migrated" creator="Etext">
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title type="main">Sociable Jimmy</title>
<title type="sort">sociable jimmy</title>
<author>Twain, Mark, 1835-1910</author>
<respStmt>
<resp>Creation of machine-readable version:</resp>  
<name>Stephen Railton</name>  
<resp>Conversion to TEI.2-conformant markup:</resp>  
<name>University of Virginia Library Electronic Text Center.</name>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt>  
<extent>ca. <num type="kilobytes">13</num> kilobytes</extent>  
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>University of Virginia Library</publisher>
<pubPlace>Charlottesville, Virginia</pubPlace>  
<idno type="ETC">TwaSoci</idno>  
<date value="1997">1997</date>
<availability status="public">
<p n="copyright">Copyright &copy; 1997 by the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia</p>
<p n="access">Publicly accessible</p>
</availability>
<idno type="uva-pid">uva-lib:476431</idno>
</publicationStmt>
<seriesStmt>
<title>University of Virginia Library, Text collection</title>
<idno type="uva-set">UVA-LIB-Text</idno>
</seriesStmt>  
<sourceDesc>
<biblFull>
<titleStmt>
<title type="main">Sociable Jimmy</title>
<title level="j">The New York Times</title>
<title type="sort">sociable jimmy</title>
<author>Mark Twain, pseud. Samuel Langhorne Clemens</author>
</titleStmt>  
<extent>p. 7</extent>  
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>H.J. Raymond &amp; Co.</publisher>  
<pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>  
<date value="1874-11-29">November 29, 1874</date>  
<idno type="callNo">Print copy consulted: UVa Library MicFilm N-US NY-2</idno>
</publicationStmt>  
</biblFull>
</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc>  
<encodingDesc>
<projectDesc>
<p>Prepared for the University of Virginia Library Electronic Text Center.</p>
</projectDesc>  
<editorialDecl>
<p>All quotation marks retained as data.</p>  
<p>All unambiguous end-of-line hyphens have been removed, and the trailing part of a word has been joined to the preceding line.</p>  
<p>Keywords in the header are a local Electronic Text Center scheme to aid in establishing analytical groupings.</p>
</editorialDecl>  
</encodingDesc>  
<profileDesc>
<creation>
<date value="1874">1874</date>
</creation>  
<langUsage>
<language id="eng" usage="main">English</language>
</langUsage>  
<textClass>
<keywords>
<term>prose; fiction</term>
</keywords>  
</textClass>
</profileDesc>  
<revisionDesc>
<change>
<date value="1997-06">June 1997</date>  
<respStmt>
<resp>corrector</resp>  
<name>Christine Ruotolo</name>
</respStmt>  
<item>Added TEI header and tags.</item>
</change>
<change>
<date value="2007-09">September 2007</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>Migration</resp>
<name>Ethan Gruber, University of Virginia Library</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Converted XML markup from TEI Lite to uva-dl-tei (TEI P4 with local customizations).</item>
</change>
<change>
<date value="2008-01">January 2008</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>Migration</resp>
<name>Greg Murray, University of Virginia Library</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Programmatically updated TEI header markup (but not header content) for minimal compliance with current QA requirements.</item>
</change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>  
 
<text id="d1"> 
<body id="d2"> 
 

 
<div1 type="story" id="d3">  <pb n="7"/>  
<head> 
Sociable Jimmy.<lb/> 
BY MARK TWAIN. 
</head> 
 
<p>[I sent the following home in a private letter some  
time ago from a certain little village. It was in 
the days when I was a public lecturer. I did it because  
I wished to preserve the memory of the 
most artless, sociable, and exhaustless talker I ever  
came across. He did not tell me a single 
remarkable thing, or one that was worth remembering;  
and yet he was himself so interested in his 
small marvels, and they flowed so naturally and comfortably  
from his lips that his talk got the 
upper hand of my interest, too, and I listened as one who  
receives a revelation. I took down what 
he had to say, just as he said it&mdash;without  
altering a word or adding one.] 
 
</p><p>I had my supper in my room this evening (as usual),  
and they sent up a bright, simple, guileless 
little darky boy to wait on me&mdash;ten years old&mdash;a wide-eyed,  
observant little chap. I said: 
 
</p><p>"What is your name, my boy?"  
 
</p><p>"Dey calls me Jimmy, sah, but my right name's James, sah." 
 
</p><p>I said, "Sit down there, Jimmy &mdash; I'll not want you just yet." 
 
</p><p>He sat down in a big arm chair, hung both his legs over one  
of the arms, and looked 
comfortable and conversational. I said: 
 
</p><p>"Did you have a pleasant Christmas, Jimmy?" 
 
</p><p>"No, sah &mdash; not zackly. I was kind o' sick den.  
But de res' o' de people <hi rend="italic">dey</hi> had a good 
time &mdash; mos' all uv 'em had a good time. Dey all  
got drunk. Dey all gits drunk heah, every 
Christmas, and carries on and has awful good times." 
 
</p><p>"So you were sick and lost it all. But unless  
you were very sick I should think that if 
you had asked the doctor he might have let you get&mdash;get&mdash;a  
<hi rend="italic">little</hi> drunk&mdash;and&mdash;" 
 
</p><p>"Oh, no, sah&mdash;I don' never git drunk&mdash;it's de  
white folks&mdash;dem's de ones I mean. Pa 
used to git drunk, but dat was befo' I was big&mdash;but  
he's done quit. He don' git drunk no mo' now. 
Jis' takes one sip in de mawnin', now, cuz his stomach  
riles up, he sleeps so soun'. Jis' one sip&mdash;over to  
de s'loon&mdash;every mawnin'. He's powerful sickly&mdash;powerful&mdash;sometimes  
he can't hardly git aroun', he can't. He goes to de doctor  
every week&mdash;over to Ragtown. An' one time he tuck 
some stuff, you know, an' it mighty near <hi rend="italic">fetched</hi> him.  
Ain't it dish yer blue vittles dat's pison?&mdash;ain't dat  
it?&mdash;truck what you pisons cats wid?" 
 
</p><p>"Yes, blue vittles [vitriol] is a very  
convincing article with a cat." 
 
</p><p>"Well, den, dat was it. De ole man, he tuck de  
bottle and shuck it, and shuck it&mdash;he seed it was blue,  
and he didn't know but it was blue mass, which he tuck  
mos always&mdash;blue mass pills&mdash;but den he 'spected maybe  
dish yer truck might be some other kin' o' blue stuff; and so he 
sot de bottle down, and drat it if it wa'n't blue vittles, sho'  
nuf when de doctor come. An' de doctor he say if he'd a  
tuck dat blue vittles it would a highsted him, sho. People can't be too 
particlar 'bout sich things. Yes, in<hi rend="italic">deedy!</hi> 
 
</p><p>"We ain't got no cats heah, 'bout dis hotel. Bill he  
don't like 'em. He can't stan' a cat no 
way. Ef he was to ketch one he'd slam it outen de winder  
in a minute. Yes he would. Bill's down 
on cats. So is de gals &mdash; waiter gals. When dey ketches a 
cat bummin' aroun' heah, dey jis' <hi rend="italic">scoops</hi> 
him&mdash;'deed dey do. Dey snake him into de cistern&mdash;dey's  
been cats drownded in dat water dat's in yo' pitcher. I seed a cat  
in dere yistiddy&mdash;all swelled up like a pudd'n. I bet you dem gals done 
dat. Ma says if dey was to drownd a cat for <hi rend="italic">her</hi>, de fust one of 'em  
she ketched she'd jam her into de cistern 'long wid de cat. Ma  
wouldn't <hi rend="italic">do</hi> dat, I don't reckon, but 'deed an' double, she <hi rend="italic">said</hi> she  
would. I can't kill a chicken &mdash; well, I kin wring its neck off, cuz  
dat don't make 'em no sufferin' scacely; but I can't take and chop  
dey heads off, like some people kin. It makes me feel so&mdash;so&mdash;well,  
I kin see dat chicken nights so's I can't sleep. Mr. Dunlap, he's de  
richest man in dis town. Some people says dey's fo' thousan' people  
in dis town &mdash; dis city. But Bill says dey ain't but 'bout thirty-three  
hund'd. And Bill he knows, cuz he's lived heah all his life, do' dey <hi rend="italic">do</hi> say he won't 
never set de river on fire. I don't know how dey fin' out&mdash;<hi rend="italic">I</hi> wouldn't like  
to count all dem people. Some folks says dis town would be considerable  
bigger if it wa'n't on accounts of so much lan' all roun' it dat ain't got  
no houses on it." [This in perfect seriousness&mdash;dense simplicity&mdash;no 
idea of a joke.] "I reckon you seed dat church as you come along up  
street. Dat's an awful big church&mdash;awful high steeple. An' it's all  
solid stone, excep' jes de top part&mdash;de steeple, I means&mdash;dat's wood.  
It falls off when de win' blows pooty hard, an' one time it stuck in a cow's 
back and busted de cow all to de mischief. It's gwine to kill somebody yit,  
dat steeple is. A man&mdash;big man, he was&mdash;bigger'n what Bill is&mdash;he tuck it  
up dere and fixed it again&mdash;an' he didn't look no bigger'n a boy, he was  
so high up. Dat steeple's awful high. If you look out de winder you  
kin see it." [I looked out, and was speechless with awe and admiration&mdash;which  
gratified Jimmy beyond expression. The wonderful steeple was some sixty  
or seventy feet high, and had a clock-face on it.] "You see dat arrer on top  
o' dat steeple? Well, sah, dat arrer is pooty nigh as big as dis do' [door].  
I seed it when dey pulled it outen de cow. It mus' be awful to stan' in dat steeple when 
de clock is strikin' &mdash; dey say it is. Booms and jars so's you think the world's a  
comin' to an end. <hi rend="italic">I</hi> wouldn't like to be up dere when de clock's a strikin'. Dat  
clock ain't just a <hi rend="italic">striker</hi>, like dese common clocks. It's a <hi rend="italic">bell</hi>&mdash;jist a  
reglar <hi rend="italic">bell</hi>&mdash;and it's a buster. You can hear dat bell all over dis 
city. You ought to hear it boom, boom, boom, when dey's a fire. My  
sakes! Dey ain't got no bell like dat in Ragtown. <hi rend="italic">I</hi> ben to Ragtown, and I  
ben mos' halfway to Dockery [thirty miles]. De bell in Ragtown's got  
so old now she don't make no soun' scacely." 
 
</p><p>[Enter the landlord&mdash;a kindly man, verging toward fifty. My small friend, 
without changing position, says]: 
 
</p><p>"Bill, didn't you say dat dey was only thirty-three hund'd people in dis 
city?" 
 
</p><p>"Yes, about thirty-three hundred is the population now." 
 
</p><p>"Well, some folks says dey's fo' thousan'." 
 
</p><p>"Yes, I know they do; but it isn't correct." 
 
</p><p>"Bill, I don't think this gen'lman kin eat a whole prairie  
chicken, but de <hi rend="italic">tole</hi> me to fetch it all up." 
 
</p><p>"Yes, that's all right&mdash;he ordered it." 
 
</p><p>[Exit "Bill," leaving me comfortable; for I had been perishing to know who 
"Bill" was.] 
 
</p><p>"Bill, he's de oldest. And he's de bes', too. Dey's fo'teen  
in dis fam'ly&mdash;all boys an' gals. Bill he suppo'ts 'em  
all&mdash;an' he don' never complain&mdash;he's <hi rend="italic">real</hi> good, Bill is.  
All dem brothers an' sisters o' his'n ain't no 'count&mdash;all  
ceptin' dat little teeny one dat fetched in dat milk. 
Dat's Kit, sah. She ain't only nine year ole. But she's  
de mos' lady-like one in de whole bilin'. You don't never  
see Kit a-rairin' an' a chargin' aroun' an' kickin' up her  
heels like de res' o' de gals in dis fam'ly does gen'ally.  
Dat was Nan dat you hearn a cuttin' dem shines on de pi-anah while 
ago. An' sometimes ef she don't rastle dat pi-anah when she gits  
started! <hi rend="italic">Tab</hi> can't hole a candle to <hi rend="italic">her</hi>, but Tab kin <hi rend="italic">sing</hi>  
like de very nation. She's de only one in dis fam'ly dat can sing. You 
don't never hear a yelp outen Nan. Nan can't sing for shucks. I'd  
jes lieves hear a tom-cat dat's got scalded. Dey's fo'teen in  
dis fam'ly 'sides de ole man and de ole 'ooman&mdash;all brothers an'  
sisters. But some of 'em don't live heah&mdash;do' Bill he suppo'ts  
'em&mdash;lends 'em money, an' pays dey debts an' he'ps 'em along.  
I tell you Bill he's <hi rend="italic">real</hi> good. Dey all gits drunk&mdash;all 'cep  
Bill. De ole man he gits drunk, too, same as de res' uv 'em.  
Bob, he don't git drunk much&mdash;jes' sloshes roun' de 
s'loons some, an' takes a dram sometimes. Bob he's  
next to Bill&mdash;bout forty year old. Dey's all married&mdash;all  
de fam'ly's married&mdash;cep' some of de gals. Dere's fo'teen.  
It's de biggest fam'ly in dese parts, dey say. Dere's  
Bill&mdash;Bill Nubbles&mdash;Nubbles is de name; Bill, an' Grig,  
an' Duke, an' Bob, an' Nan, an' Tab, an' Kit, an' Sol,  
an' Si, an' Phil, an' Puss, an'Jake, an' Sal&mdash;Sal she's 
married an' got chil'en as big as I is&mdash;an' Hoss Nubbles,  
he's de las'. Hoss is what dey mos' always calls him, but  
he's got another name dat I somehow disremember, it's so  
kind o' hard to git de hang of it." [Then, observing that  
I had been taking down the extraordinary list of 
nicknames for adults, he said]: "But in de mawnin'  
I can ask Bill what's Hoss's other name, an' den I'll  
come up an' tell you when I fetches yo' breakfast. An'  
maybe I done got some o' dem names mixed up, but Bill,  
he kin tell me. Dey's fo'teen." 
 
</p><p>By this time he was starting off with the waiter  
(and a pecuniary consideration for his sociability), and,  
as he went out, he paused a moment and said: 
 
</p><p>"Dad fetch it, somehow dat other name don't come.  
But, anyways, you jes read dem names over and see if dey's  
fo'teen." [I read the list from the flyleaf of Longfellow's <hi rend="italic">New 
England Tragedies</hi>.] "Dat's right, sah. Dey's all down. I'll  
fetch up Hoss's other name in the mawnin', sah. Don't you  
be oneasy." 
 
</p><p>[Exit whistling "Listen to the Mocking Bird."]</p> 
 
   
 
</div1> 
</body> 
</text> 
</TEI.2> 
 
