<?xml version="1.0"?>

<?dlps id="TylHago"?>
<?dlps page-images="none" figure-images="no"?>
<?dlps transcription="other"?>

<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/tei-p4/tei2.dtd" [
<!ENTITY % POSTKB "INCLUDE">
<!ENTITY % TEI.extensions.ent SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.ent">
<!ENTITY % TEI.extensions.dtd SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.dtd">
<!ENTITY % ISOnum SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/charent/iso-num.ent"> %ISOnum;
<!ENTITY % ISOlat2 SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/charent/iso-lat2.ent"> %ISOlat2;
<!ENTITY % ISOpub SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/charent/iso-pub.ent"> %ISOpub;
  
]>  
<TEI.2 id="TylHago">  
<teiHeader type="migrated" creator="Etext">
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title type="main">Hagoromo</title>
<title type="sort">hagoromo</title>
<author>Tyler, Royall</author>
<respStmt>
<resp>Creation of machine-readable version:</resp>   
<name>Winnie Chan</name>   
<resp>Creation of digital images:</resp>   
<name/>   
<resp>Conversion to TEI.2-conformant markup:</resp>   
<name>University of Virginia Library Electronic Text Center.</name>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt>   
<extent>ca. <num type="kilobytes">26</num> kilobytes</extent>   
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>University of Virginia Library</publisher>
<pubPlace>Charlottesville, Virginia</pubPlace>   
<idno type="ETC">TylHago</idno>   
<date value="1997">1997</date>
<availability status="public">
<p n="copyright">Copyright &copy; 1997 by the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia</p>
<p n="access">Publicly accessible</p>
</availability>
<idno type="uva-pid">uva-lib:476436</idno>
</publicationStmt>
<seriesStmt>
<title>University of Virginia Library, Text collection</title>
<idno type="uva-set">UVA-LIB-Text</idno>
</seriesStmt>   
<seriesStmt>
<p>Japanese Text Initiative</p>
</seriesStmt>   
<notesStmt>
<note>
<p>Copyright 1978 Royall Tyler. Except for brief quotations in a review, no
part of this text may be reproduced or utilized in any form or by any
means, electronic or mechanical, including photocopying and recording,
or by any information storage or retrieval system, without permission in
writing from the author. Please address inquiries to Royall Tyler in
care of East Asia Program, Cornell University, 140 Uris Hall, Ithaca, NY
14853-7601.</p>
</note>
</notesStmt>   
<sourceDesc>
<biblFull>
<titleStmt>
<title type="main">The Feather Mantle (Hagoromo: a woman play)</title>
<title level="m">Pining Wind: a Cycle of N&omacr; Plays</title>
<title type="sort">feather mantle hagoromo a woman play</title>
<author>Royall Tyler</author>
</titleStmt>   
<editionStmt>
<p>1st Edition</p>
</editionStmt>   
<extent>pp. 17-26</extent>   
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>Cornell China-Japan Program</publisher>   
<pubPlace>Ithaca, New York</pubPlace>   
<date value="1978">1978</date>   
<idno type="callNo">Print copy consulted: UVa Library call number PL 782 .E5 P55 v.1</idno>
</publicationStmt>   
<seriesStmt>
<p>Cornell University East Asia Papers, number 17</p>
</seriesStmt>   
<notesStmt>
<note>
<p>Copyright 1978 Royall Tyler. From <hi rend="italic">Pining Wind: A Cycle of Noh 
Plays</hi> (English translation). Cornell East Asia Series no. 
17, 204 pp., 0-939657-17-1, $12 paper.  East Asia Program, Cornell 
University, 140 Uris Hall, Ithaca, NY 14853-7601 (ph.  607-255-6222; 
fax: 607-255-1388, kks3@cornell.edu).</p>
</note> 
<note>
<p>CAUTION: Except for brief quotations in a review, no part of this 
text may be reproduced or utilized in any form or by any means, 
electronic or mechanical, including photocopying and recording, or by 
any information storage or retrieval system, without permission in 
writing from the author. Please address inquiries to Royall Tyler in 
care of East Asia Program, Cornell University, 140 Uris Hall, Ithaca, NY 
14853-7601.</p>
</note>
</notesStmt>
</biblFull>
</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc>   
<encodingDesc>
<projectDesc>
<p>Prepared for the University of Virginia Library Electronic Text Center.</p>
</projectDesc>   
<editorialDecl>
<p>All quotation marks retained as data.</p>   
<p>All unambiguous end-of-line hyphens have been removed, and the trailing part of a word has been joined to the preceding line.</p>   
<p>Spacing in print text has been preserved. Natural line breaks have been removed, and the trailing part of a line has been joined to the preceding line.</p>   
<p>Keywords in the header are a local Electronic Text Center scheme to aid in establishing analytical groupings.</p>   
<p>Underlining for emphasis has been rendered as italics.</p>
</editorialDecl>   
</encodingDesc>   
<profileDesc>
<creation>
<date value="1978">1978</date>
</creation>   
<langUsage>
<language id="eng" usage="main">English</language>   
<language id="rj">Romaji</language>
</langUsage>   
<textClass>
<keywords>
<term>drama; poetry; prose</term>   
<term>Literature in Translation</term>
</keywords>   
</textClass>
</profileDesc>   
<revisionDesc>
<change>
<date value="1997-02">February 1997</date>   
<respStmt>
<resp>corrector</resp>   
<name>Winnie Chan</name>
</respStmt>   
<item>Added TEI header and tags.</item>
</change>
<change>
<date value="2007-09">September 2007</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>Migration</resp>
<name>Ethan Gruber, University of Virginia Library</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Converted XML markup from TEI Lite to uva-dl-tei (TEI P4 with local customizations).</item>
</change>
<change>
<date value="2008-01">January 2008</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>Migration</resp>
<name>Greg Murray, University of Virginia Library</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Programmatically updated TEI header markup (but not header content) for minimal compliance with current QA requirements.</item>
</change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>   
  
<text id="d1">    
<front id="d2">  
<div1 type="introduction" id="d3">
<pb n="17" id="TylHago17"/>   
  
<head>  
THE FEATHER MANTLE<lb/>  
(<hi rend="italic">Hagoromo</hi>: a woman play)  
</head>  
  
<p>  
This play begins on a perfect spring day: sweeping blue sky, mild air,  
pines along the beach, and sunlit sea. The world we know appeared, they  
say, when sky and earth split apart; now, though, heaven and earth seem  
still conjoined at ease, one lightly-breathing vastness. As on such a day  
the earthbound heart rises of itself into free space, so an angel, too,  
may, as in <hi rend="italic">The Feather Mantle</hi>, descend.  
</p>  
  
<p>  
No one knows for certain who wrote <hi rend="italic">The Feather Mantle</hi>, or  
when, but it makes a fine introduction to the whole n&omacr; repertoire.  
Many of the marks of a god play can be found in it, and one of these is  
thanks given for our Sovereign's reign. This thanks is rendered for all  
harmony and delight, to the Lord who shall reign for ever and ever; whose  
reign endures, indeed, even through the trials enacted in the plays that  
follow. (If his reign did not so endure, then return to communion and  
illumination would hardly be possible.) This Sovereign is not only secular  
and historical; he is also the focal point and power center of the world.  
</p>  
  
<p>  
It is the angel's warm, feminine charm that puts <hi rend="italic">The Feather  
Mantle</hi> in the class of woman plays, for true god plays avoid such  
coloring. This very charm, though, makes <hi rend="italic">The Feather Mantle</hi>  
more perfectly representative, for love is the heart of Japanese  
poetry&mdash;especially if to love between man and woman, one joins love  
for the fleeting graces of nature herself.  
</p>  
  
<p>  
And who indeed is this charming celestial maiden? She proves to be the  
laurel tree that grows in the moon, and the very moon itself,   
    
  
 <pb n="18" id="TylHago18"/>   
giver of every gift. Her garment is less a human mantle than sky, mist,  
and cloud. The flowers in her hair are doubtless actually growing in the  
green spring hills. She really does have all of nature's fleeting graces,  
of which the moon is the sign, and might well move one to love.  
</p>  
  
<p> In n&omacr;, mention of the full moon is likely to be coupled, as  
here, with the Buddhist term True Semblance   
(<hi rend="italic">shinnyo</hi>). True Semblance can loosely be said to mean  
Reality, but this reality is no absolute to be grasped at and held. True  
Semblance can be owned or defined no more than the angel's loveliness.  
</p>  
  
<p>  
As the moon, the angel invokes her own 'true ground,' the Bodhisattva  
Seishi. This is because Shinto deities, the natural powers of the world,  
were widely held to be local manifestations of the universal Buddhas and  
Bodhisattvas. Such a local manifestation is the projected image, and the  
name of this mode of understanding is <hi rend="italic">honji  
suijaku</hi>, true ground and projected image. Seishi stands to the  
right of the Buddha Amida, Lord of Infinite Light, and is Amida's  
all-illuminating wisdom. Thus the angel, with all her graces, is actually  
wisdom manifest.  
</p>  
  
<p>  
Versions of the story of <hi rend="italic">The Feather Mantle</hi> are to be found  
all over the world. The pattern is that a band of celestial maidens (in  
ancient Japanese accounts the number is eight) come down to earth to enjoy  
some particularly wholesome pleasure, such as bathing in a spring or  
drinking fresh milk. There, a man surprises them. All escape back to  
heaven but the last one, who is detained by the man and often has to marry  
him. Much later, though, she does fly home again, and the man, who by some  
failing has let her escape, can never follow.  
</p>  
    
  
 <pb n="19" id="TylHago19"/>   
<p>  
What the angel does during her visit to earth is to transmit certain music  
called the Suruga Dance from East Country Pleasures. East Country  
Pleasures is <hi rend="italic">Azuma-asobi</hi>, a body of songs and dances from  
the region far to the east of Miyako, the capital. There is a tradition  
that an angel did indeed give the Suruga Dance to mankind on a beach in  
the province of Suruga. From the standpoint of n&omacr;, however, one  
might imagine that it is music itself that she teaches, and that the whole  
repertoire is an unfolding of this music.  
</p>  
</div1>  
</front>  
    
  

<body id="d4">  
<div1 type="play" id="d5"><head><hi rend="italic">ISSEI</hi></head>  
   <pb n="20" id="TylHago20"/>   
  

<stage>  
A small pine stands down front. Caught in its branches is a length of  
cloth that represents the mantle. Sideman and two Sideman's Seconds enter,  
carrying fishing poles; they stand down front, to one side of the pine.  
When all three sing together, they are face to face; when Sideman speaks  
alone, he faces front.  
</stage>  

  
  
<p>ISSEI</p>

<milestone unit="speech" n="Hago1"/>
<sp>  
<speaker>Sideman and Side Second</speaker>  
  
<lg>
<l> Swift winds blow </l>
<l>by Mio</l>
<l>down the curving shore</l>
<l>small craft row</l>
<l>and fishermen</l>
<l>call o'er the sea lanes!</l>
</lg>
  
</sp>  

  
  
<p>NANORI</p>
<milestone unit="speech" n="Hago2"/>
<sp>  
<speaker>Sideman</speaker>  
<p>  
I'm a fisherman known on the pine barrens of Mio as Hakury&omacr;.  
</p>  
</sp>  

  
  
<p>SASHI</p> 
<milestone unit="speech" n="Hago3"/>
<sp>  
<speaker>Sideman and Side Second</speaker>  
<lg>  
<l>Boundless leagues of lovely hills, and clouds suddenly rise; one lone  
tower's bright moon marks first the rain's clearing.' Yes, a time it  
is </l>   
<l>of mild calm!</l>    
<l>Spring again has touched</l>    
<l>pine barrens</l>    
<l>wave on lingering wave </l>   
<l>the morning mists, </l>   
<l>moon loitering in sky meadows </l>   
<l>endless</l>    
<l>the gaze roves on: </l>   
<l>a scene to quiet, </l>   
<l>to absorb the heart! </l> 
</lg>  
</sp>  

  
  
<p>SAGEUTA</p> 
<milestone unit="speech" n="Hago4"/>
<sp>  
<lg>  
<l>I'll not forget</l>    
<l>how mountain trails</l>    
<l>we took to Clearview Cove, </l>   
<l>and spied afar </l>   
<l>Mio's pine barrens:</l>    
<l>come now, friends,</l>    
<l>there's where we'll go </l>   
<l>come now, friends,</l>    
<l>there's where we'll go!</l>  
</lg>  
</sp>  

  
  
<p>AGEUTA</p>
<milestone unit="speech" n="Hago5"/>
<sp>  
<lg>  
<l>Wind-billowed, </l>   
<l>the clouds float high</l>    
<l>waves then to you </l>
<l>the clouds float high</l>    
<l>waves then to you </l>   
<l>are they, men, </l>   
<l>no fishing done, </l>   
<l>will you hurry home? </l>   
<l>Wait! It's spring a while, </l>   
<l>and mild blows the morning breeze, </l>   
<l>yes, the pines' song everlasting, </l>   
<l>waves are silent </l>   
<l>in the morning calm </l>   
<l>and fishermen crowd forth </l>   
<l>in teeming craft </l>   
<l>fishermen crowd forth </l>   
<l>in teeming craft!  </l>
</lg>  
</sp>  
    
  
 <pb n="21" id="TylHago21"/>   
<stage>  
Sideman's Seconds sit slightly upstage of Sideman's spot. Sideman lays  
down his pole at stagehand stop, takes fan in hand, and comes out to main  
spot.  
</stage>  

  
  
<p>*</p>  
<milestone unit="speech" n="Hago6"/>  
<sp>  
<speaker>Sideman</speaker>  
<p>  
I've just come up to the pine barrens of Mio, and I'm gazing at the view  
of the shore, when from the void blossoms fall, music resounds, and  
wondrous fragrances pervade all space. This can hardly be common. And in  
fact I see here, hung on this pine tree, a beautiful mantle. A closer look  
now: color and scent are marvelous indeed. This is no ordinary mantle.  
I'll take it home with me to show my friends, and to keep as an heirloom  
in my house.  
</p>  
</sp>  
  
<stage>  
Carrying the mantle in both hands, he starts toward Sideman's spot. But  
Doer calls to him as she comes through curtain, and starts down bridgeway.  
She wears the <hi rend="italic">z&omacr;-onna</hi> mask and an  
angel's glittering crown.  
</stage>  

  
  
<p>MONDO</p>  
<milestone unit="speech" n="Hago7"/>
<sp>  
<speaker>Doer</speaker>  
<p>  
I'm sorry, but that mantle's mine! Why have you taken it?  
</p>  
</sp>  
  
<stage>  
Sideman is now at Sideman's spot.)  
</stage>  
<milestone unit="speech" n="Hago8"/>  
<sp>  
<speaker>Sideman</speaker>  
<p>  
I just happen to have run across it, so I'm taking it home with me.  
</p>  
</sp>  

<milestone unit="speech" n="Hago9"/>  
<sp>  
<speaker>Doer</speaker>  
<p>  
But it's an angel's feather mantle! It isn't supposed to be given to a  
human being! Do please leave it where it was!  
</p>  
</sp>  
  
<milestone unit="speech" n="Hago10"/>
<sp>  
<speaker>Sideman</speaker>  
<p>  
As I understand it, then, this is an angel's mantle. Why, in that case,  
it's obviously a wonder in these latter days, and I ought to have it as a  
treasure for the whole land! I'm not going to give it back.  
</p>  
</sp>  

<milestone unit="speech" n="Hago11"/>  
<sp>  
<speaker>Doer</speaker>  
<p>  
Oh no! Without the feather mantle, flying is over for me; I'll never be  
able to return to Heaven! Please, please give it back!  
</p>  
</sp>  
    
  
 <pb n="22" id="TylHago22"/>   
<milestone unit="speech" n="Hago12"/>
<sp>  
<speaker>Sideman</speaker>  
<lg>  
<l>Hakury&omacr; </l>   
<l>will not heed </l>   
<l>this gracious plea,</l>    
<l>but grows stubborn: </l>   
<l>heartless I've always been, </l>   
<l>I, a fisherman.</l>    
<l>The celestial </l>   
<l>feather mantle </l>   
<l>he hides from her.  </l>
</lg>  
  
<stage>  
He turns front, away from Doer, who is by now at main spot.  
</stage>  
  
<lg>  
<l>No indeed, says he, </l>   
<l>and turns to go.  </l>
</lg>  
</sp>  
  
<milestone unit="speech" n="Hago13"/>
<sp>  
<speaker>Doer</speaker>  
<lg>  
<l>In her plight now</l>    
<l>the angel, </l>   
<l>like a wingless bird, </l> 
</lg>  
</sp>  
  
<sp>  
<speaker>Sideman</speaker>  
<lg>  
<l>moving to rise,</l>  
<l>has no mantle; </l> 
</lg>  
</sp>  
  
<milestone unit="speech" n="Hago14"/>
<sp>  
<speaker>Doer</speaker>  
<lg>  
<l>on earth, is caught </l>  
<l>in the nether world. </l> 
</lg>  
</sp>  
  
<milestone unit="speech" n="Hago15"/>
<sp>  
<speaker>Sideman</speaker>  
<lg>  
<l>Either way, alas! . . .</l>
<l>she laments,  </l>
</lg>  
</sp>  
  
<milestone unit="speech" n="Hago16"/>
<sp>  
<speaker>Doer</speaker>  
<lg>  
<l>but as Hakury&omacr; </l>   
<l>will keep the mantle,  </l>
</lg>  
</sp>  
  
<milestone unit="speech" n="Hago17"/>
<sp>  
<speaker>Sideman</speaker>  
<p>  
helpless,  
</p>  
</sp>  

<milestone unit="speech" n="Hago18"/>  
<sp>  
<speaker>Doer</speaker>  
<p>  
hopeless  
</p>  
</sp>  

  
  
<p>AGEUTA</p>  

<milestone unit="speech" n="Hago19"/>  
<sp>  
<speaker>Chorus</speaker>  
<lg>  
<l>tears run, </l>   
<l>shining jewel headdress, </l>   
<l>flowers in her hair</l>    
<l>droop and wilt: </l>   
<l>the five signs </l>   
<l>of an angel's fall </l>   
<l>are here</l>    
<l>before my very eyes&mdash; </l>   
<l>oh pitiful!  </l>
</lg>  
</sp>  
  
<stage>  
She gazes up to her right into the sky.  
</stage>  

  
  
<p>SHIMO-NO-EI</p>  

<milestone unit="speech" n="Hago20"/>  
<sp>  
<speaker>Doer</speaker>  
<lg>  
<l>To the fields of Heaven </l>   
<l>backward I gaze, </l>   
<l>but mists rise, </l>   
<l>cloudways blur, </l>   
<l>the path is lost!' </l> 
</lg>  
</sp>  

  
  
<p>SAGEUTA</p>  

<milestone unit="speech" n="Hago21"/>  
<sp>  
<speaker>Chorus</speaker>  
<lg>  
<l>My home so dear, </l>   
<l>the sky, oh when</l>    
<l>shall I pass yonder move </l>   
<l>the clouds</l>    
<l>and enviously </l>   
<l>I look on! </l> 
</lg>  
</sp>  

  
  
<p>AGEUTA</p>  

<milestone unit="speech" n="Hago22"/>  
<sp>  
<lg>  
<l>The kalavinka's</l>    
<l>voice I loved</l>    
<l>the kalavinka's </l>
<l>voice I loved</l>    
<l>to hear, now fades</l>    
<l>and wild geese cry </l>   
<l>down the skyways,</l>    
<l>going home&mdash;</l>  
<l>and oh, this   </l>
    
  
 <pb n="23" id="TylHago23"/>   
<l>longing!</l>    
<l>Plovers, gulls, </l>   
<l>with waves offshore come and go</l>    
<l>breezes of spring</l>    
<l>blowing through the sky, they too</l>    
<l>quicken yearning </l>   
<l>blowing through the sky, they too</l>    
<l>quicken yearning! </l> 
</lg>  
</sp>  
  
<stage>  
She gazes up at sky, and weeps.  
</stage>  

  
  
<p>MONDO</p>  

<milestone unit="speech" n="Hago23"/>  
<sp>  
<speaker>Sideman</speaker>  
<p>  
I can see now you're suffering terribly. I'll give you back your mantle.  
</p>  
</sp>  

<milestone unit="speech" n="Hago24"/>  
<sp>  
<speaker>Doer</speaker>  
<p>  
Oh, I'm so happy! Then do bring it to me!  
</p>  
</sp>  
  
<stage>  
She presses toward Sideman.  
</stage>  
  
<milestone unit="speech" n="Hago25"/>
<sp>  
<speaker>Sideman</speaker>  
<p>  
A moment, though.  
</p>  
  
<stage>  
He retreats an equal distance.  
</stage>  
  
<p>  
I'll return your mantle if you'll be kind enough to do right here and now  
the angel dance I've heard tell of.  
</p>  
</sp>  

<milestone unit="speech" n="Hago26"/>  
<sp>  
<speaker>Doer</speaker>  
<p>  
I'm so happy! Yes, I <hi rend="italic">will</hi> get home to Heaven!  
And for joy I'll indeed dance, right here and now. You shall pass my dance  
on to the downcast folk of your world. But I can't do anything without my  
mantle. Please give it back to me first.  
</p>  
</sp>  

<milestone unit="speech" n="Hago27"/>  
<sp>  
<speaker>Sideman</speaker>  
<p>  
Oh no, if I return your mantle you won't dance, you'll head straight up to  
Heaven.  
</p>  
</sp>  

<milestone unit="speech" n="Hago28"/>  
<sp>  
<speaker>Doer</speaker>  
<p>  
No, suspicion's for the human realm; in Heaven there's no falsehood.  
</p>  
</sp>  

<milestone unit="speech" n="Hago29"/>  
<sp>  
<speaker>Sideman</speaker>  
<p>  
I'm so ashamed! Why then, says he, by all means; and gives her back the  
mantle.  
</p>  
</sp>  
  
<stage>  
Side gives mantle to Doer, then goes to sit at Sideman's spot.  
</stage>  

  
  
<p>MONO-GI-ASHIRAI</p>  
  
<stage>  
Doer withdraws to stagehand spot, where she puts on the mantle. She then  
comes out to main spot.  
</stage>  

  
  
<p>KAKEAI</p>  
    
  
 <pb n="24" id="TylHago24"/>   
<milestone unit="speech" n="Hago30"/>
<sp>  
<speaker>Doer</speaker>  
<lg>  
<l>The maiden,</l>    
<l>in mantle clothed, </l>   
<l>does Rainbow Skirts and Cloak of Wings;  </l>
</lg>  
</sp>  

<milestone unit="speech" n="Hago31"/>  
<sp>  
<speaker>Sideman</speaker>  
<lg>  
<l>the celestial </l>   
<l>feather mantle </l>   
<l>moves to the winds, </l> 
</lg>  
</sp>  

<milestone unit="speech" n="Hago32"/>  
<sp>  
<speaker>Doer</speaker>  
<lg>  
<l>moist with rain </l>   
<l>the blossom sleeves, </l> 
</lg>  
</sp>  

<milestone unit="speech" n="Hago33"/>  
<sp>  
<speaker>Sideman</speaker>  
<p>  
as music plays  
</p>  
</sp>  

<milestone unit="speech" n="Hago33"/>  
<sp>  
<speaker>Doer</speaker>  
<p>  
and she dances on!  
</p>  
</sp>  

  
  
<p>SHIDAI</p>  

<milestone unit="speech" n="Hago35"/>  
<sp>  
<speaker>Chorus</speaker>  
<lg>  
<l>The Suruga Dance </l>   
<l>from East Country Pleasures </l>   
<l>the Suruga Dance</l>    
<l>from East Country Pleasures: </l>   
<l>Sparely, this </l>   
<l>is how it began! </l> 
</lg>  
</sp>  

  
  
<p>KURI</p>  

<milestone unit="speech" n="Hago36"/>  
<sp>  
<lg>  
<l>Now, to speak of </l>   
<l>the long-faring sky:</l>    
<l>ages past, in the Twin Gods' time, </l>   
<l>when they laid out the world </l>   
<l>in each one </l>   
<l>of its ten directions, </l>   
<l>the sky had no end, </l>   
<l>and that it why </l>   
<l>they dubbed it </l>   
<l>long-faring. </l> 
</lg>  
</sp>  

  
  
<p>SASHI</p>  

<milestone unit="speech" n="Hago37"/>  
<sp>  
<speaker>Doer</speaker>  
<lg>  
<l>As for the Palace </l>   
<l>of the Moon,</l>    
<l>with glittering ax </l>   
<l>hewn for all eternity:  </l>
</lg>  
</sp>  

<milestone unit="speech" n="Hago38"/>  
<sp>  
<speaker>Chorus</speaker>  
<lg>  
<l>robed in white or black </l>   
<l>the angel throng </l>   
<l>made two bands, </l>   
<l>each of thrice five, </l>   
<l>and all moon long, </l>   
<l>night by night,</l>    
<l>a celestial maid</l>    
<l>with task assigned</l>    
<l>carries out her role.  </l>
</lg>  
</sp>  

<milestone unit="speech" n="Hago39"/>  
<sp>  
<speaker>Doer</speaker>  
<lg>  
<l>Of these I am one: </l>   
<l>celestial maiden  </l>
</lg>  
</sp>  

<milestone unit="speech" n="Hago40"/>  
<sp>  
<speaker>Chorus</speaker>  
<lg>  
<l>of the moon</l>    
<l>laurel tree, </l>   
<l>I've split in two, </l>   
<l>to visit </l>   
<l>and myself pass on </l>   
<l>to your world here </l>   
<l>the Suruga Dance </l>   
<l>of the East Country! </l> 
</lg>  
</sp>  

  
  
<p>KUSE</p>  

<milestone unit="speech" n="Hago41"/>  
<sp>  
<lg>  
<l>Mists of spring</l>    
<l>trail on long-faring </l>   
<l>moon laurel flowers bloom! </l>   
<l>Yes, crown of blossoms</l>    
<l>in full hue </l>   
<l>surely means spring! </l>   
<l>Oh lovely! </l>   
<l>Though no Heaven, </l>   
<l>here too we've sweet grace.</l>    
<l>Winds of the skies,</l>    
    
  
 <pb n="25" id="TylHago25"/>   
<l>blow shut the clouds'</l>    
<l>passageways! </l>   
<l>The maiden lingers, </l>   
<l>pine barrens'</l>    
<l>spring hues to see </l>   
<l>on Mio Cape,</l>    
<l>and the moon so </l>   
<l>Clearview Cove, </l>
<l>snows of Fuji&mdash; </l>   
<l>which excels? </l>   
<l>Peerless this spring dawn,  </l>  
<l>the waves,</l>    
<l>the pining wind </l>   
<l>so mild, </l>   
<l>the tranquil shore! </l>   
<l>Sky and earth, why, what parts them? </l>   
<l>Zoned with light</l>    
<l>are Inner Shrine and Outer, </l>   
<l>whose gods' offspring </l>   
<l>rule here still; </l>   
<l>the very moon's</l>    
<l>spotlessly clear </l>   
<l>our sunrise land, Japan!  </l>
</lg>  
</sp>  

<milestone unit="speech" n="Hago42"/>  
<sp>  
<speaker>Doer</speaker>  
<lg>  
<l>In this our Sovereign's reign </l>   
<l>celestial </l>   
<l>feather mantles</l>    
<l>seldom descend: </l> 
</lg>  
</sp>  

<milestone unit="speech" n="Hago43"/>  
<sp>  
<speaker>Chorus</speaker>  
<lg>  
<l>caressed, the rock</l>    
<l>yet wears not away, </l>   
<l>oh happy news! </l>   
<l>Songs of the East:</l>    
<l>with voices join </l>   
<l>in sweet concert </l>   
<l>drone-pipes, flutes,</l>    
<l>harps and zitherns </l>   
<l>swelling out past the Lone Cloud; </l>   
<l>red sinks the sun, </l>   
<l>so mirroring Mount Sumeru; </l>   
<l>green in the waves </l>   
<l>Float Isle Moor</l>    
<l>gale-swept, </l>   
<l>where blossoms fall, </l>   
<l>yes, whirling snow </l>   
<l>the white cloud sleeves </l>   
<l>are lovely indeed! </l> 
</lg>  
</sp>  
  
<stage>  
Pausing in her dance movements, Doer sits at main spot and joins palms in  
reverence.  
</stage>  

  
  
<p>EI</p>  
<milestone unit="speech" n="Hago44"/>  
<sp>  
<speaker>Doer</speaker>  
<p>  
Hail to thee, Seishi, oh thou True Ground of the Moon, daughter of Heaven!  
</p>  
</sp>  

<milestone unit="speech" n="Hago45"/>  
<sp>  
<speaker>Chorus</speaker>  
<lg>  
<l>A dance, then, </l>  
<l>from the East Country Pleasures.  </l>
</lg>  
</sp>  

  
  
<p>JO-NO-MAI</p>  
  
<stage>  
Doer rises and, between these two passages of text, dances a 
<hi rend="italic">jo-no-mai</hi> dance. She goes on dancing, however, as text  
resumes.  
</stage>  

  
  
<p>NORIJI</p>  
<milestone unit="speech" n="Hago46"/>  
<sp>  
<speaker>Doer</speaker>  
<lg>  
<l>Now, the mantle blue </l> 
<l>that's Heaven's lofty sky,  </l>
</lg>  
</sp>  

<milestone unit="speech" n="Hago47"/>  
<sp>  
<speaker>Chorus</speaker>  
<lg>  
<l>now, the mantling mist </l> 
<l>that rises in spring,  </l>
</lg>  
</sp>  

<milestone unit="speech" n="Hago48"/>  
<sp>  
<speaker>Doer</speaker>  
<lg>  
<l>hue and fragrance</l>    
<l>both delight! </l>   
<l>The maiden's train  </l>
</lg>  
</sp>  
    
  
 <pb n="26" id="TylHago26"/>   
<sp>  
<speaker>Chorus</speaker>  
<lg>  
<l>sweeps and sways, </l>   
<l>all rustling, </l>   
<l>flowers nod in her hair; </l>   
<l>celestial </l>   
<l>feather sleeves </l>   
<l>billow, coil and turn, </l>   
<l>the dancing sleeves!  </l>
</lg>  
</sp>  

  
  
<p>HA-NO-MAI</p>  
  
<stage>  
Between these two passages, she dances a 
<hi rend="italic">ha-no-mai</hi> dance. Again, she continues dancing as text  
resumes.  
</stage>  

  
  
<p>NORIJI</p>  
<milestone unit="speech" n="Hago49"/>  
<sp>  
<lg>  
<l>As on and on</l>    
<l>the dances go</l>    
<l>as on and on </l>   
<l>the dances go,</l>    
<l>she who's named moon</l>    
<l>palace lady </l>   
<l>high in the dark sky</l>    
<l>this thrice fifth night</l>    
<l>becomes again</l>    
<l>face of True Semblance, </l>   
<l>the full moon, and rains riches: </l>   
<l>prayers fulfilled, </l>   
<l>the realm replete, </l>   
<l>the seven treasures </l>   
<l>overflowing,</l>    
<l>these on our land bestows;</l>    
<l>and so time runs, </l>   
<l>the celestial</l>    
<l>feather mantle</l>    
<l>wind-borne billows </l>   
<l>down the shore; </l>   
<l>pine barrens of Mio,</l>    
<l>Float Isle's clouds, </l>   
<l>Mount Ashitaka, yes,</l>    
<l>and Fuji's </l>   
<l>towering peak</l>    
<l>fade out, </l>   
<l>mist-veiled </l>   
<l>into high Heaven</l>    
<l>she is lost from view.</l>  
</lg>  
</sp>  
    

</div1>  
</body>  
</text>  
</TEI.2>  
  
 
