<?xml version="1.0"?>

<?dlps id="VerBloc"?>
<?dlps page-images="none" figure-images="no"?>
<?dlps transcription="other"?>

<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/tei-p4/tei2.dtd" [
<!ENTITY % POSTKB "INCLUDE">
<!ENTITY % TEI.extensions.ent SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.ent">
<!ENTITY % TEI.extensions.dtd SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.dtd">
<!ENTITY % ISOnum SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/charent/iso-num.ent"> %ISOnum;
<!ENTITY % ISOpub SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/charent/iso-pub.ent"> %ISOpub;
 
]> 
<TEI.2 id="VerBloc"> 
<teiHeader type="migrated" creator="Etext">
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title type="main">The Blockade Runners</title>
<title type="sort">blockade runners</title>
<author>Verne, Jules, 1828-1905</author>
<respStmt>
<resp>Creation of machine-readable version</resp>
<name>Judy Boss</name>
</respStmt>
<respStmt>
<resp>Conversion to TEI-conformant markup</resp>
<name>University of Virginia Library Electronic Text Center</name>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt> 
<extent>ca. <num type="kilobytes">113</num> kilobytes</extent> 
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>University of Virginia Library</publisher>
<pubPlace>Charlottesville, Virginia</pubPlace>
<idno type="ETC">VerBloc</idno> 
<date value="1995">1995</date>
<availability status="public">
<p n="copyright">Copyright &copy; 1995 by the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia</p>
<p n="access">Publicly accessible</p>
</availability>
<idno type="uva-pid">uva-lib:476446</idno>
</publicationStmt>
<seriesStmt>
<title>University of Virginia Library, Text collection</title>
<idno type="uva-set">UVA-LIB-Text</idno>
</seriesStmt> 
<sourceDesc>
<biblFull>
<titleStmt>
<title type="main">The Omnibus</title>
<title type="sort">omnibus</title>
<author>Verne, Jules</author>
</titleStmt> 
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>J. B. Lippincott Company</publisher>
<pubPlace>Garden City, NY</pubPlace>
</publicationStmt> 
</biblFull>
</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc> 
<encodingDesc>
<projectDesc>
<p>Prepared for the University of Virginia Library Electronic Text Center</p>
</projectDesc> 
<editorialDecl>
<p>All quotation marks retained as data</p> 
<p>All unambiguous end-of-line hyphens have been removed, and the 
trailing part of a word has been joined to the preceding line.</p> 
<p id="ETC">Keywords in the header are a local Electronic Text Center scheme 
to aid in establishing analytical groupings</p>
</editorialDecl> 
<refsDecl>
<p>ID elements are given for each page element and are composed of the text's 
unique cryptogram and the given page number, as in SpeFQue1 for page one of 
Spenser's Faerie Queene.</p>
</refsDecl>
</encodingDesc> 
<profileDesc>
<creation>
<date value="1876">1876</date>
</creation> 
<langUsage>
<language id="eng" usage="main">English</language>
</langUsage> 
<textClass>
<keywords>
<term>fiction; prose</term>
</keywords>
</textClass>
</profileDesc> 
<revisionDesc>
<change>
<date value="1995-02">February 1995</date> 
<respStmt>
<resp>corrector</resp>
<name>Kelly Tetterton</name>
</respStmt>
<item>updated header and tags</item>
</change> 
<change>
<date value="1993-10">October 1993</date> 
<respStmt>
<resp>corrector</resp>
<name>Kelly Tetterton</name>
</respStmt>
<item>minimal TEI tagging; italics included; entity references 
included; unambiguous line-end hyphenation removed</item>
</change> 
<change>
<date value="1993-10">October 1993</date> 
<respStmt>
<resp>corrector</resp>
<name>Judy Boss</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Text scanned in, proofed, and the following changes made: 
p. 491: desination] destination;
p. 493: pentrate] penetrate; 
p. 508: thiry] thirty</item>
</change> 
<change>
<date value="2005-07">July 2005</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>Corrector</resp>
<name>Margaret Konkol</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Converted SGML to XML and fixed tagging.</item>
</change>
<change>
<date value="2007-09">September 2007</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>Migration</resp>
<name>Ethan Gruber, University of Virginia Library</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Converted XML markup from TEI Lite to uva-dl-tei (TEI P4 with local customizations).</item>
</change>
<change>
<date value="2008-01">January 2008</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>Migration</resp>
<name>Greg Murray, University of Virginia Library</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Programmatically updated TEI header markup (but not header content) for minimal compliance with current QA requirements.</item>
</change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader> 
<text id="d1">  
 
<front id="d2"> 
<pb n="487"/>  
<titlePage id="d3"> 
	<pb/>
<titlePart type="main"> 
THE BLOCKADE RUNNERS 
</titlePart> 
</titlePage> 
</front> 
<body id="d4"> 


<div1 type="chapter" n="1" id="d5"> <pb n="489"/>  
<head>THE <hi rend="italic">"Dolphin"</hi></head> 
<p>THE Clyde was the first river whose waters were lashed 
into foam by a steam-boat.  It was in 1812 when the steamer 
called the <hi rend="italic">Comet</hi> ran between Glasgow and Greenock, at 
the speed of six miles an hour.  Since that time more than 
a million of steamers or packet-boats have plied this Scotch 
river, and the inhabitants of Glasgow must be as familiar 
as any people with the wonders of steam navigation. 
</p><p>However, on the 3rd of December, 1862, an immense 
crowd, composed of shipowners, merchants, manufacturers, 
workmen, sailors, women, and children, thronged the muddy 
streets of Glasgow, all going in the direction of Kelvin 
Dock, the large shipbuilding premises belonging to Messrs. 
Tod &amp; MacGregor.  This last name especially proves that 
the descendants of the famous Highlanders have become 
manufacturers, and that they have made workmen of all the 
vassals of the old clan chieftains. 
</p><p>Kelvin Dock is situated a few minutes' walk from the 
town, on the right bank of the Clyde.  Soon the immense 
timber-yards were thronged with spectators; not a part of 
the quay, not a wall of the wharf, not a factory roof showed 
an unoccupied place; the river itself was covered with craft 
of all descriptions, and the heights of Govan, on the left 
bank, swarmed with spectators. 
</p><p>There was, however, nothing extraordinary in the event 
about to take place; it was nothing but the launching of a 
ship, and this was an everyday affair with the people of 
Glasgow.  Had the <hi rend="italic">Dolphin</hi>, then &mdash; for that was the name of 
the ship built by Messrs.  Tod &amp; MacGregor &mdash; some special 
peculiarity? To tell the truth, it had none. 
</p><p>It was a large ship, about 1,500 tons, in which everything 
combined to obtain superior speed.  Her engines, of 500 
horse-power, were from the workshops of Lancefield Forge; 
<pb n="490"/>  
they worked two screws, one on either side the stern-post, 
completely independent of each other.  As for the depth of 
water the <hi rend="italic">Dolphin</hi> would draw, it must be very inconsiderable; 
connoisseurs were not deceived, and they concluded 
rightly that this ship was destined for shallow straits.  But 
all these particulars could not in any way justify the eagerness 
of the people: taken altogether, the <hi rend="italic">Dolphin</hi> was nothing 
more or less than an ordinary ship.  Would her launching 
present some mechanical difficulty to be overcome? Not any 
more than usual.  The Clyde had received many a ship of 
heavier tonnage, and the launching of the <hi rend="italic">Dolphin</hi> would 
take place in the usual manner. 
</p><p>In fact, when the water was calm, the moment the ebb-tide set in, the workmen began to operate.  Their mallets 
kept perfect time falling on the wedges meant to raise the 
ship's keel: soon a shudder ran through the whole of her 
massive structure; although she had only been slightly 
raised, one could see that she shook, and then gradually 
began to glide down the well greased wedges, and in a few 
moments she plunged into the Clyde.  Her stern struck the 
muddy bed of the river, then she raised herself on the top 
of a gigantic wave, and, carried forward by her start, would 
have been dashed against the quay of the Govan timber-yards, if her anchors had not restrained her. 
</p><p>The launch had been perfectly successful, the <hi rend="italic">Dolphin</hi> 
swayed quietly on the waters of the Clyde, all the spectators 
clapped their hands when she took possession of her 
natural element, and loud hurrahs arose from either bank. 
</p><p>But wherefore these cries and this applause? Undoubtedly 
the most eager of the spectators would have been 
at a loss to explain the reason of his enthusiasm.  What was 
the cause, then, of the lively interest excited by this ship? 
Simply the mystery which shrouded her destination; it 
was not known to what kind of commerce she was to be 
appropriated, and in questioning different groups the 
diversity of opinion on this important subject was indeed 
astonishing. 
</p><p>However, the best informed, at least those who pretended 
to be so, agreed in saying that the steamer was going to take 
<pb n="491"/>  
part in the terrible war which was then ravaging the United 
States of America, but more than this they did not know, 
and whether the <hi rend="italic">Dolphin</hi> was a privateer, a transport ship, 
or an addition to the Federal marine was what no one could 
tell. 
</p><p>"Hurrah!" cried one, affirming that the <hi rend="italic">Dolphin</hi> had been 
built for the Southern States. 
</p><p>"Hip! hip! hip!" cried another, swearing that never had 
a faster boat crossed to the American coasts. 
</p><p>Thus its destination was unknown, and in order to obtain 
any reliable information one must be an intimate friend, or, 
at any rate, an acquaintance of Vincent Playfair &amp; Co., of 
Glasgow. 
</p><p>A rich, powerful, intelligent house of business was that 
of Vincent Playfair &amp; Co., in a social sense, an old and 
honourable family, descended from those tobacco lords who 
built the finest quarters of the town.  These clever merchants, 
by an act of the Union, had founded the first Glasgow warehouse 
for dealing in tobacco from Virginia and Maryland. 
Immense fortunes were realised; mills and foundries sprang 
up in all parts, and in a few years the prosperity of the city 
attained its height. 
</p><p>The house of Playfair remained faithful to the enterprising 
spirit of its ancestors, it entered into the most daring 
schemes, and maintained the honour of English 
commerce.  The principal, Vincent Playfair, a man of fifty, 
with a temperament essentially practical and decided, although 
somewhat daring, was a genuine shipowner.  Nothing 
affected him beyond commercial questions, not even the 
political side of the transactions, otherwise he was a perfectly 
loyal and honest man. 
</p><p>However, he could not lay claim to the idea of building 
and fitting up the <hi rend="italic">Dolphin</hi>; she belonged to his nephew, 
James Playfair, a fine young man of thirty, the boldest 
skipper of the British merchant marine. 
</p><p>It was one day at the Tontine coffee-room under the 
arcades of the town hall, that James Playfair, after having 
impatiently scanned the American journal, disclosed to his 
uncle an adventurous scheme. 
<pb n="492"/>  
</p><p>"Uncle Vincent," said he, coming to the point at once, 
"there are two millions of pounds to be gained in less than 
a month." 
</p><p>"And what to risk?" asked Uncle Vincent. 
</p><p>"A ship and a cargo." 
</p><p>"Nothing else?" 
</p><p>"Nothing, except the crew and the captain, and that 
does not reckon for much." 
</p><p>"Let us see," said Uncle Vincent. 
</p><p>"It is all seen," replied James Playfair.  "You have read 
the <hi rend="italic">Tribune</hi>, the <hi rend="italic">New York Herald, The Times</hi>, the <hi rend="italic">Richmond 
Inquirer</hi>, the <hi rend="italic">American Review</hi>?" 
</p><p>"Scores of times, nephew." 
</p><p>"You believe, like me, that the war of the United States 
will last a long time still?" 
</p><p>"A very long time." 
</p><p>"You know how much this struggle will affect the interests 
of England, and especially those of Glasgow?" 
</p><p>"And more especially still the house of Playfair &amp; Co.," 
replied Uncle Vincent. 
</p><p>"Theirs especially," added the young Captain. 
</p><p>"I worry myself about it every day, James, and I cannot 
think without terror of the commercial disasters which this 
war may produce; not but that the house of Playfair is 
firmly established, nephew; at the same time it has correspondents 
which may fail.  Ah! those Americans, slave-holders or Abolitionists, I have no faith in them!" 
</p><p>If Vincent Playfair was wrong in thus speaking with 
respect to the great principles of humanity, always and 
everywhere superior to personal interests, he was, nevertheless, 
right from a commercial point of view.  The most 
important material was failing at Glasgow, the cotton 
famine became every day more threatening, thousands of 
workmen were reduced to living upon public charity. 
Glasgow possessed 25,000 looms, by which 625,000 yards 
of cotton were spun daily; that is to say, fifty millions of 
pounds yearly.  From these numbers it may be guessed what 
disturbances were caused in the commercial part of the town 
when the raw material failed altogether.  Failures were 
<pb n="493"/>  
hourly taking place, the manufactories were closed, and the 
workmen were dying of starvation. 
</p><p>It was the sight of this great misery which had put the 
idea of his bold enterprise into James Playfair's head. 
</p><p>"I will go for cotton, and will get it, cost what it may." 
</p><p>But, as he also was a merchant as well as his uncle 
Vincent, he resolved to carry out his plan by way of exchange, 
and to make his proposition under the guise of a 
commercial enterprise. 
</p><p>"Uncle Vincent," said he, "this is my idea." 
</p><p>"Well, James?" 
</p><p>"It is simply this: we will have a ship built of superior 
sailing qualities and great bulk." 
</p><p>"That is quite possible." 
</p><p>"We will load her with ammunition of war, provisions, 
and clothes." 
</p><p>"Just so." 
</p><p>"I will take the command of this steamer, I will defy 
all the ships of the Federal marine for speed, and I will 
run the blockade of one of the southern ports." 
</p><p>"You must make a good bargain for your cargo with 
the Confederates, who will be in need of it," said his uncle. 
</p><p>"And I shall return laden with cotton." 
</p><p>"Which they will give you for nothing." 
</p><p>"As you say, Uncle.  Will it answer?" 
</p><p>"It will; but shall you be able to get there?" 
</p><p>"I shall, if I have a good ship." 
</p><p>"One can be made on purpose.  But the crew?" 
</p><p>"Oh, I will find them.  I do not want many men; enough 
to work with, that is all.  It is not a question of fighting with 
the Federals, but distancing them." 
</p><p>"They shall be distanced," said Uncle Vincent, in a 
peremptory tone; "but now, tell me, James, to what port 
of the American coast do you think of going?" 
</p><p>"Up to now, Uncle, ships have run the blockade of New 
Orleans, Wilmington, and Savannah, but I think of going 
straight to Charleston; no English boat has yet been able to 
penetrate into the harbour, except the <hi rend="italic">Bermuda</hi>.  I will do 
like her, and, if my ship draws but very little water, I shall 
<pb n="494"/>  
be able to go where the Federalists will not be able to 
follow." 
</p><p>"The fact is," said Uncle Vincent, "Charleston is overwhelmed 
with cotton; they are even burning it to get rid 
of it." 
</p><p>"Yes," replied James; "besides, the town is almost invested; 
Beauregard is running short of provisions, and he 
will pay me a golden price for my cargo!" 
</p><p>"Well, nephew, and when will you start?" 
</p><p>"In six months; I must have the long winter nights to 
aid me." 
</p><p>"It shall be as you wish, nephew." 
</p><p>"It is settled, then, Uncle?" 
</p><p>"Settled!" 
</p><p>"Shall it be kept quiet?" 
</p><p>"Yes; better so." 
</p><p>And this is how it was that five months later the steamer 
<hi rend="italic">Dolphin</hi> was launched from the Kelvin Dock timber-yards, 
and no one knew her real destination. 
</p></div1><div1 type="chapter" n="2" id="d6"> 
<head>GETTING UNDER SAIL</head> 
<p>THE <hi rend="italic">Dolphin</hi> was rapidly equipped, her rigging was 
ready, and there was nothing to do but fit her up.  She carried 
three schooner-masts, an almost useless luxury; in fact, 
the <hi rend="italic">Dolphin</hi> did not rely on the wind to escape the Federalists, 
but rather on her powerful engines. 
</p><p>Towards the end of December a trial of the steamer was 
made in the gulf of the Clyde.  Which was the more satisfied, 
builder or captain, it is impossible to say.  The new steamer 
shot along wonderfully, and the patent log showed a speed 
of seventeen miles an hour, a speed which as yet no English, 
French, or American boat had ever obtained.  The <hi rend="italic">Dolphin</hi> 
would certainly have gained by several lengths in a sailing 
match with the fastest opponent. 
</p><p>The loading was begun on the 25th of December, the 
<pb n="495"/>  
steamer having ranged along the steamboat-quay a little 
below Glasgow Bridge, the last which stretches across the 
Clyde before its mouth.  Here the wharfs were heaped with 
a heavy cargo of clothes, ammunition, and provisions which 
were rapidly carried to the hold of the <hi rend="italic">Dolphin</hi>.  The nature 
of this cargo betrayed the mysterious destination of the 
ship, and the house of Playfair could no longer keep it 
secret; besides, the <hi rend="italic">Dolphin</hi> must not be long before she 
started.  No American cruiser had been signalled in English 
waters; and, then, when the question of getting the crew 
came, how was it possible to keep silent any longer? They 
could not embark them, even, without informing the men 
whither they were bound, for, after all, it was a matter of 
life and death, and when one risks one's life, at least it is 
satisfactory to know how and wherefore. 
</p><p>However, this prospect hindered no one; the pay was 
good, and everyone had a share in the speculation, so that 
a great number of the finest sailors soon presented themselves. 
James Playfair was only embarrassed which to choose, 
but he chose well, and in twenty-four hours his muster-roll 
bore the names of thirty sailors who would have done honour 
to her Majesty's yacht. 
</p><p>The departure was settled for the 3rd of January; on 
the 31st of December the <hi rend="italic">Dolphin</hi> was ready, her hold full 
of ammunition and provisions, and nothing was keeping 
her now. 
</p><p>The skipper went on board on the 2nd of January, and 
was giving a last look round his ship with a captain's eye, 
when a man presented himself at the fore part of the <hi rend="italic">Dolphin</hi>, 
and asked to speak with the Captain.  One of the sailors 
led him on to the poop. 
</p><p>He was a strong, hearty-looking fellow, with broad 
shoulders and ruddy face, the simple expression of which 
ill-concealed a depth of wit and mirth.  He did not seem 
to be accustomed to a seafaring life, and looked about him 
with the air of a man little used to being on board a ship; 
however, he assumed the manner of a Jack-tar, looking up 
at the rigging of the <hi rend="italic">Dolphin</hi>, and waddling in true sailor 
fashion. 
<pb n="496"/>  
</p><p>When he had reached the Captain, he looked fixedly at 
him, and said, "Captain James Playfair?" 
</p><p>"The same," replied the skipper.  "What do you want 
with me?" 
</p><p>"To join your ship." 
</p><p>"There is no room; the crew is already complete." 
</p><p>"Oh, one man, more or less, will not be in the way; quite 
the contrary." 
</p><p>"You think so?" said James Playfair, giving a sidelong 
glance at his questioner. 
</p><p>"I am sure of it," replied the sailor. 
</p><p>"But who are you?" asked the Captain. 
</p><p>"A rough sailor, with two strong arms, which, I can tell 
you, are not to be despised on board a ship, and which 
I now have the honour of putting at your service." 
</p><p>"But there are other ships besides the <hi rend="italic">Dolphin</hi>, and other 
captains besides James Playfair.  Why do you come here?" 
</p><p>"Because it is on board the <hi rend="italic">Dolphin</hi> that I wish to serve, 
and under the orders of Captain James Playfair." 
</p><p>"I do not want you." 
</p><p>"There is always need of a strong man, and if to prove 
my strength you will try me with three or four of the 
strongest fellows of your crew, I am ready." 
</p><p>"That will do," replied James Playfair.  "And what is 
your name?" 
</p><p>"Crockston, at your service." 
</p><p>The Captain made a few steps backwards in order to get 
a better view of the giant who presented himself in this odd 
fashion.  The height, the build, and the look of the sailor 
did not deny his pretensions to strength. 
</p><p>"Where have you sailed?" asked Playfair of him. 
</p><p>"A little everywhere." 
</p><p>"And do you know where the <hi rend="italic">Dolphin</hi> is bound for?" 
</p><p>"Yes; and that is what tempts me." 
</p><p>"Ah, well! I have no mind to let a fellow of your stamp 
escape me.  Go and find the first mate, and get him to enrol 
you." 
</p><p>Having said this, the Captain expected to see the man 
<pb n="497"/>  
turn on his heels and run to the bows, but he was mistaken. 
Crockston did not stir. 
</p><p>"Well! did you hear me?" asked the Captain. 
</p><p>"Yes, but it is not all," replied the sailor.  "I have something 
else to ask you." 
</p><p>"Ah! You are wasting my time," replied James, sharply; 
"I have not a moment to lose in talking." 
</p><p>"I shall not keep you long," replied Crockston; "two 
words more and that is all; I was going to tell you that I 
have a nephew." 
</p><p>"He has a fine uncle, then," interrupted James Playfair. 
</p><p>"Hah! Hah!" laughed Crockston. 
</p><p>"Have you finished?" asked the Captain, very impatiently. 
</p><p>"Well, this is what I have to say, when one takes the 
uncle, the nephew comes into the bargain." 
</p><p>"Ah! indeed!" 
</p><p>"Yes, that is the custom, the one does not go without 
the other." 
</p><p>"And what is this nephew of yours?" 
</p><p>"A lad of fifteen whom I am going to train to the sea; 
he is willing to learn, and will make a fine sailor some day." 
</p><p>"How now, Master Crockston," cried James Playfair; 
"do you think the <hi rend="italic">Dolphin</hi> is a training-school for cabin-boys?" 
</p><p>"Don't let us speak ill of cabin-boys: there was one of 
them who became Admiral Nelson, and another Admiral 
Franklin." 
</p><p>"Upon my honour, friend," replied James Playfair, "you 
have a way of speaking which I like; bring your nephew, 
but if I don't find the uncle the hearty fellow he pretends to 
be, he will have some business with me.  Go, and be back in 
an hour." 
</p><p>Crockston did not want to be told twice; be bowed awkwardly 
to the Captain of the <hi rend="italic">Dolphin</hi>, and went on to the 
quay.  An hour afterwards he came on board with his 
nephew, a boy of fourteen or fifteen, rather delicate and 
weakly looking, with a timid and astonished air, which 
showed that he did not possess his uncle's self-possession and 
<pb n="498"/>  
vigorous corporeal qualities.  Crockston was even obliged to 
encourage him by such words as these: 
</p><p>"Come," said he, "don't be frightened, they are not going 
to eat us, besides, there is yet time to return." 
</p><p>"No, no," replied the young man, "and may God protect 
us!" 
</p><p>The same day the sailor Crockston and his nephew were 
inscribed in the muster-roll of the <hi rend="italic">Dolphin</hi>. 
</p><p>The next morning, at five o'clock, the fires of the steamer 
were well fed, the deck trembled under the vibrations of 
the boiler, and the steam rushed hissing through the escape-pipes.  The hour of departure had arrived. 
</p><p>A considerable crowd, in spite of the early hour, flocked 
on the quays and on Glasgow Bridge; they had come to 
salute the bold steamer for the last time.  Vincent Playfair 
was there to say good-bye to Captain James, but he conducted 
himself on this occasion like a Roman of the good old 
times.  His was a heroic countenance, and the two loud kisses 
with which he gratified his nephew were the indication of a 
strong mind. 
</p><p>"Go, James," said he to the young Captain, "go quickly, 
and come back quicker still; above all, don't abuse your 
position.  Sell at a good price, make a good bargain, and you 
will have your uncle's esteem." 
</p><p>On this recommendation, borrowed from the manual of 
the perfect merchant, the uncle and nephew separated, and 
all the visitors left the boat. 
</p><p>At this moment Crockston and John Stiggs stood together 
on the forecastle, while the former remarked to his 
nephew, "This is well, this is well; before two o'clock we shall 
be at sea, and I have a good opinion of a voyage which 
begins like this." 
</p><p>For reply the novice pressed Crockston's hand. 
</p><p>James Playfair then gave the orders for departure. 
</p><p>"Have we pressure on?" he asked of his mate. 
</p><p>"Yes, Captain," replied Mr. Mathew. 
</p><p>"Well, then, weigh anchor." 
</p><p>This was immediately done, and the screws began to 
<pb n="499"/>  
move.  The <hi rend="italic">Dolphin</hi> trembled, passed between the ships in 
the port, and soon disappeared from the sight of the people, 
who shouted their last hurrahs. 
</p><p>The descent of the Clyde was easily accomplished, one 
might almost say that this river had been made by the hand 
of man, and even by the hand of a master.  For sixty years, 
thanks to the dredges and constant dragging, it has gained 
fifteen feet in depth, and its breadth has been tripled between 
the quays and the town.  Soon the forests of masts and 
chimneys were lost in the smoke and fog; the noise of the 
foundry hammers and the hatchets of the timber-yards 
grew fainter in the distance.  After the village of Partick 
had been passed the factories gave way to country houses 
and villas.  The <hi rend="italic">Dolphin</hi>, slackening her speed, sailed between 
the dykes which carry the river above the shores, and 
often through a very narrow channel, which, however, is 
only a small inconvenience for a navigable river, for, after 
all, depth is of more importance than width.  The steamer, 
guided by one of those excellent pilots from the Irish sea, 
passed without hesitation between floating buoys, stone 
columns, and biggings, surmounted with lighthouses, which 
mark the entrance to the channel.  Beyond the town of Renfrew, 
at the foot of Kilpatrick hills, the Clyde grew wider. 
Then came Bouling Bay, at the end of which opens the 
mouth of the canal which joints Edinburgh to Glasgow. 
Lastly, at the height of four hundred feet from the ground, 
was seen the outline of Dumbarton Castle, almost indiscernible 
through the mists, and soon the harbour-boats of 
Glasgow were rocked on the waves which the <hi rend="italic">Dolphin</hi> caused. 
Some miles farther on Greenock, the birthplace of James 
Watt, was passed: the <hi rend="italic">Dolphin</hi> now found herself at the 
mouth of the Clyde, and at the entrance of the gulf by which 
it empties its waters into the Northern Ocean.  Here the first 
undulations of the sea were felt, and the steamer ranged 
along the picturesque coast of the Isle of Arran.  At last the 
promontory of Cantyre, which runs out into the channel, 
was doubled; the Isle of Rattelin was hailed, the pilot returned 
by a shore-boat to his cutter, which was cruising in 
<pb n="500"/>  
the open sea; the <hi rend="italic">Dolphin</hi>, returning to her Captain's authority, 
took a less frequented route round the north of 
Ireland, and soon, having lost sight of the last European 
land, found herself in the open ocean. 
</p></div1><div1 type="chapter" n="3" id="d7"> 
<head>THINGS ARE NOT WHAT THEY SEEM</head> 
<p>THE <hi rend="italic">Dolphin</hi> had a good crew, not fighting men, or boarding 
sailors, but good working men, and that was all she 
wanted.  These brave, determined fellows were all, more or 
less, merchants; they sought a fortune rather than glory; 
they had no flag to display, no colours to defend with cannon; 
in fact, all the artillery on board consisted of two small 
swivel signal-guns. 
</p><p>The <hi rend="italic">Dolphin</hi> shot bravely across the water, and fulfilled 
the utmost expectations of both builder and captain.  Soon 
she passed the limit of British seas; there was not a ship 
in sight; the great ocean route was free; besides, no ship of 
the Federal marine would have a right to attack her beneath 
the English flag.  Followed she might be, and prevented 
from forcing the blockade, and precisely for this 
reason had James Playfair sacrificed everything to the speed 
of his ship, in order not to be pursued. 
</p><p>Howbeit a careful watch was kept on board, and, in spite 
of the extreme cold, a man was always in the rigging ready 
to signal the smallest sail that appeared on the horizon. 
When evening came, Captain James gave the most precise 
orders to Mr. Mathew. 
</p><p>"Don't leave the man on watch too long in the rigging; 
the cold may seize him, and in that case it is impossible to 
keep a good look-out; change your men often." 
</p><p>"I understand, Captain," replied Mr. Mathew. 
</p><p>"Try Crockston for that work; the fellow pretends to 
have excellent sight; it must be put to trial; put him on the 
morning watch, he will have the morning mists to see 
through.  If anything particular happens call me." 
<pb n="501"/>  
</p><p>This said, James Playfair went to his cabin.  Mr. Mathew 
called Crockston, and told him the Captain's orders. 
</p><p>"To-morrow, at six o'clock," said he, "you are to relieve 
watch of the main masthead." 
</p><p>For reply, Crockston gave a decided grunt, but Mr. 
Mathew had hardly turned his back when the sailor muttered 
some incomprehensible words, and then cried: 
</p><p>"What on earth did he say about the mainmast?" 
</p><p>At this moment his nephew, John Stiggs, joined him 
on the forecastle. 
</p><p>"Well, my good Crockston," said he. 
</p><p>"It's all right, all right," said the seaman, with a forced 
smile; "there is only one thing, this wretched boat shakes 
herself like a dog coming out of the water, and it makes my 
head confused." 
</p><p>"Dear Crockston, and it is for my sake." 
</p><p>"For you and him," replied Crockston, "but not a word 
about that, John.  Trust in God, and He will not forsake 
you." 
</p><p>So saying, John Stiggs and Crockston went to the sailor's 
berth, but the sailor did not lie down before he had seen the 
young novice comfortably settled in the narrow cabin which 
he had got for him. 
</p><p>The next day, at six o'clock in the morning, Crockston 
got up to go to his place; he went on deck, where the first 
officer ordered him to go up into the rigging, and keep good 
watch. 
</p><p>At these words the sailor seemed undecided what to do; 
then, making up his mind, he went towards the bows of the 
<hi rend="italic">Dolphin</hi>. 
</p><p>"Well, where are you off to now?" cried Mr. Mathew. 
</p><p>"Where you sent me," answered Crockston. 
</p><p>"I told you to go to the mainmast." 
</p><p>"And I am going there," replied the sailor, in an ununconcerned 
tone, continuing his way to the poop. 
</p><p>"Are you a fool?" cried Mr. Mathew, impatiently; "you 
are looking for the bars of the main on the foremast.  You 
are like a cockney, who doesn't know how to twist a cat-o'-<pb n="502"/>  
nine-tails, or make a splice.  On board what ship can you 
have been, man? The mainmast, stupid, the mainmast!" 
</p><p>The sailors who had run up to hear what was going on 
burst out laughing when they saw Crockston's disconcerted 
look, as he went back to the forecastle. 
</p><p>"So," said he, looking up the mast, the top of which was 
quite invisible through the morning mists; "so, am I to climb 
up here?" 
</p><p>"Yes," replied Mr. Mathew, "and hurry yourself! By 
St. Patrick, a Federal ship would have time to get her bowsprit 
fast in our rigging before that lazy fellow could get to 
his post.  Will you go up?" 
</p><p>Without a word, Crockston got on the bulwarks with 
some difficulty; then he began to climb the rigging with 
most visible awkwardness, like a man who did not know how 
to make use of his hands or feet.  When he had reached the 
topgallant, instead of springing lightly on to it, he remained 
motionless, clinging to the ropes, as if he had been seized 
with giddiness.  Mr. Mathew, irritated by his stupidity, 
ordered him to come down immediately. 
</p><p>"That fellow there," said he to the boatswain, "has never 
been a sailor in his life.  Johnston, just go and see what he 
has in his bundle." 
</p><p>The boatswain made haste to the sailor's berth. 
</p><p>In the meantime Crockston was with difficulty coming 
down again, but, his foot having slipped, he slid down the 
rope he had hold of, and fell heavily on the deck. 
</p><p>"Clumsy blockhead! land-lubber!" cried Mr. Mathew, by 
way of consolation.  "What did you come to do on board the 
<hi rend="italic">Dolphin</hi>! Ah! you entered as an able seaman, and you cannot 
even distinguish the main from the foremast! I shall 
have a little talk with you." 
</p><p>Crockston made no attempt to speak; he bent his back 
like a man resigned to anything he might have to bear; 
just then the boatswain returned. 
</p><p>"This," said he to the first officer, "is all that I have 
found; a suspicious portfolio with letters." 
</p><p>"Give them here," said Mr. Mathew.  "Letters with Federal 
stamps! Mr. Halliburtt, of Boston! An Abolitionist! 
<pb n="503"/>  
a Federalist! Wretch! you are nothing but a traitor, and 
have sneaked on board to betray us! Never mind, you will 
be paid for your trouble with the cat-o'-nine-tails! Boatswain, 
call the Captain, and you others just keep an eye 
on that rogue there." 
</p><p>Crockston received these compliments with a hideous 
grimace, but he did not open his lips.  They had fastened 
him to the capstan, and he could move neither hand nor foot. 
</p><p>A few minutes later James Playfair came out of his cabin 
and went to the forecastle, where Mr. Mathew immediately 
acquainted him with the details of the case. 
</p><p> "What have you to say?" asked James Playfair, scarcely 
able to restrain his anger. 
</p><p>"Nothing," replied Crockston. 
</p><p>"And what did you come on board my ship for?" 
</p><p>"Nothing." 
</p><p>"And what do you expect from me now?" 
</p><p>"Nothing." 
</p><p>"Who are you? An American, as letters seem to prove?" 
Crockston did not answer. 
</p><p>"Boatswain," said James Playfair, "fifty lashes with the 
cat-o'-nine-tails to loosen his tongue.  Will that be enough, 
Crockston?" 
</p><p>"It will remain to be seen," replied John Stiggs' uncle 
without moving a muscle. 
</p><p>"Now then, come along, men," said the boatswain. 
</p><p>At this order, two strong sailors stripped Crockston of 
his woollen jersey; they had already seized the formidable 
weapon, and laid it across the prisoner's shoulders, 
when the novice, John Stiggs, pale and agitated, hurried 
on deck. 
</p><p>"Captain!" exclaimed he. 
</p><p>"Ah! the nephew!" remarked James Playfair. 
</p><p>"Captain," repeated the novice, with a violent effort to 
steady his voice, "I will tell you what Crockston does not 
want to say.  I will hide it no longer; yes, he is American, 
and so am I; we are both enemies of the slave-holders, but 
not traitors come on board to betray the <hi rend="italic">Dolphin</hi> into the 
hands of the Federalists." 
<pb n="504"/>  
</p><p>"What did you come to do, then?" asked the Captain, 
in a severe tone, examining the novice attentively.  The 
latter hesitated a few seconds before replying, then he said, 
"Captain, I should like to speak to you in private." 
</p><p>Whilst John Stiggs made this request, James Playfair 
did not cease to look carefully at him; the sweet young face 
of the novice, his peculiarly gentle voice, the delicacy and 
whiteness of his hands, hardly disguised by paint, the large 
eyes, the animation of which could not bide their tenderness 
 &mdash; all this together gave rise to a certain suspicion in the 
Captain's mind.  When John Stiggs had made his request, 
Playfair glanced fixedly at Crockston, who shrugged his 
shoulders; then he fastened a questioning look on the novice, 
which the latter could not withstand, and said simply to him, 
"Come." 
</p><p>John Stiggs followed the Captain on to the poop, and 
then James Playfair, opening the door of his cabin, said 
to the novice, whose cheeks were pale with emotion, "Be so 
kind as to walk in, miss." 
</p><p>John, thus addressed, blushed violently, and two tears 
rolled involuntarily down his cheeks. 
</p><p>"Don't be alarmed, miss," said James Playfair, in a gentle 
voice, "but be so good as to tell me how I come to have the 
honour of having you on board?" 
</p><p>The young girl hesitated a moment, then, reassured by 
the Captain's look, she made up her mind to speak. 
</p><p>"Sir," said she, "I wanted to join my father at Charleston; 
the town is besieged by land and blockaded by sea.  I 
knew not how to get there, when I heard that the <hi rend="italic">Dolphin</hi> 
meant to force the blockade.  I came on board your ship, 
and I beg you to forgive me if I acted without your consent, 
which you would have refused me." 
</p><p>"Certainly," said James Playfair. 
</p><p>"I did well, then, not to ask you," resumed the young 
girl, with a firmer voice. 
</p><p>The Captain crossed his arms, walked round his cabin, 
and then came back. 
</p><p>"What is your name?" said he. 
</p><p>"Jenny Halliburtt." 
<pb n="505"/>  
</p><p>"Your father, if I remember rightly the address on the 
letters, is he not from Boston?" 
</p><p>"Yes, sir." 
</p><p>"And a Northerner is thus in a southern town in the 
thickest of the war?" 
</p><p>"My father is a prisoner; he was at Charleston when the 
first shot of the Civil War was fired, and the troops of the 
Union driven from Fort Sumter by the Confederates.  My 
father's opinions exposed him to the hatred of the slavist 
part, and by the order of General Beauregard he was imprisoned. 
I was then in England, living with a relation who 
has just died, and left alone, with no help but that of 
Crockston, our faithful servant, I wished to go to my father 
and share his prison with him." 
</p><p>"What was Mr. Halliburtt, then?" asked James Playfair. 
</p><p>"A loyal and brave journalist," replied Jenny proudly, 
one of the noblest editors of the <hi rend="italic">Tribune</hi>, and the one who 
was the boldest in defending the cause of the negroes." 
</p><p>"An Abolitionist," cried the Captain angrily; "one of 
those men who, under the vain pretence of abolishing slavery, 
have deluged their country with blood and ruin." 
</p><p>"Sir!" replied Jenny Halliburtt, growing pale, "you are 
insulting my father; you must not forget that I stand alone 
to defend him." 
</p><p>The young Captain blushed scarlet; anger mingled with 
shame struggled in his breast; perhaps he would have answered 
the young girl, but he succeeded in restraining 
himself, and, opening the door of the cabin, he called 
"Boatswain!" 
</p><p>The boatswain came to him directly. 
</p><p>"This cabin will henceforward belong to Miss Jenny 
Halliburtt.  Have a cot made ready for me at the end of 
the poop; that's all I want." 
</p><p>The boatswain looked with a stupefied stare at the young 
novice addressed in a feminine name, but on a sign from 
James Playfair he went out. 
</p><p>"And now, miss, you are at home," said the young Captain 
of the <hi rend="italic">Dolphin</hi>.  Then he retired. 
<pb n="506"/>  
</p></div1><div1 type="chapter" n="4" id="d8"> 
<head>CROCKSTON'S TRICK</head> 
<p>IT WAS not long before the whole crew knew Miss Halliburtt's 
story, which Crockston was no longer hindered from 
telling.  By the Captain's orders he was released from the 
capstan, and the cat-o'-nine-tails returned to its Place. 
</p><p>"A pretty animal," said Crockston, "especially when it 
shows its velvety paws." 
</p><p>As soon as he was free, he went down to the sailors' 
berths, found a small portmanteau, and carried it to Miss 
Jenny; the young girl was now able to resume her feminine 
attire, but she remained in her cabin, and did not again 
appear on deck. 
</p><p>As for Crockston, it was well and duly agreed that, as 
he was no more a sailor than a horse-guard, he should be 
exempt from all duty on board. 
</p><p>In the meanwhile the <hi rend="italic">Dolphin</hi>, with her twin screws cutting 
the waves, sped rapidly across the Atlantic, and there 
was nothing now to do but keep a strict look-out.  The day 
following the discovery of Miss Jenny's identity, James 
Playfair paced the deck at the poop with a rapid step; he 
had made no attempt to see the young girl and resume the 
conversation of the day before. 
</p><p>Whilst he was walking to and fro, Crockston passed him 
several times, looking at him askant with a satisfied grin. 
He evidently wanted to speak to the Captain, and at last 
his persistent manner attracted the attention of the latter, 
who said to him, somewhat impatiently: 
</p><p>"How now, what do you want? You are turning round 
me like a swimmer round a buoy: when are you going to 
leave off?" 
</p><p>"Excuse me, Captain," answered Crockston, winking, 
"I wanted to speak to you." 
</p><p>"Speak, then." 
</p><p>"Oh, it is nothing very much.  I only wanted to tell you 
frankly that you are a good fellow at bottom." 
</p><p>"Why at bottom?" 
<pb n="507"/>  
</p><p>"At bottom and surface also." 
</p><p>"I don't want your compliments." 
</p><p>"I am not complimenting you.  I shall wait to do that 
when you have gone to the end." 
</p><p>"To what end?" 
</p><p>"To the end of your task." 
</p><p>"Ah! I have a task to fulfil?" 
</p><p>"Decidedly, you have taken the young girl and myself 
on board; good! You have given up your cabin to Miss 
Halliburtt; good! You released me from the cat-o'-nine-tails; nothing could be better.  You are going to take us 
straight to Charleston; that's delightful, but it is not all." 
</p><p>"How not all?" cried James Playfair, amazed at Crockston's 
boldness. 
</p><p>"No, certainly not," replied the latter, with a knowing 
look, "the father is prisoner there." 
</p><p>"Well, what about that?" 
</p><p>"Well, the father must be rescued." 
</p><p>"Rescue Miss Halliburtt's father?" 
</p><p>"Most certainly, and it is worth risking something for 
such a noble man and courageous citizen as he." 
</p><p>"Master Crockston," said James Playfair, frowning, "I 
am not in the humour for your jokes, so have a care what 
you say." 
</p><p>"You misunderstand me, Captain," said the American. 
"I am not joking in the least, but speaking quite seriously. 
What I have proposed may at first seem very absurd to 
you; when you have thought it over, you will see that you 
cannot do otherwise." 
</p><p>"What, do you mean that I must deliver Mr. Halliburtt?" 
</p><p>"Just so.  You can demand his release of General Beauregard, 
who will not refuse you." 
</p><p>"But if he does refuse me?" 
</p><p>"In that case," replied Crockston, in a deliberate tone, 
"we must use stronger measures, and carry off the prisoner 
by force." 
</p><p>"So," cried James Playfair, who was beginning to get 
angry, "so, not content with passing through the Federal 
<pb n="508"/>  
fleets and forcing the blockade of Charleston, I must run 
out to sea again from under the cannon of the forts, and 
this to deliver a gentleman I know nothing of, one of those 
Abolitionists whom I detest, one of those journalists who 
shed ink instead of their blood!" 
</p><p>"Oh, it is but a cannon-shot more or less!" added 
Crockston. 
</p><p>"Master Crockston," said James Playfair, "mind what 
I say: if ever you mention this affair again to me, I will 
send you to the hold for the rest of the passage, to teach 
you manners." 
</p><p>Thus saying, the Captain dismissed the American, who 
went off murmuring, "Ah, well, I am not altogether displeased 
with this conversation: at any rate, the affair is 
broached; it will do, it will do!" 
</p><p>James Playfair had hardly meant it when he said an 
Abolitionist whom I detest; he did not in the least side with 
the Federals, but he did not wish to admit that the question 
of slavery was the predominant reason for the civil war 
of the United States, in spite of President Lincoln's formal 
declaration.  Did he, then, think that the Southern States, 
eight out of thirty-six, were right in separating when they 
had been voluntarily united? Not so; he detested the Northerners, 
and that was all; he detested them as brothers 
separated from the common family &mdash; true Englishmen &mdash; 
who had thought it right to do what he, James Playfair, 
disapproved of with regard to the United States: these were 
the political opinions of the Captain of the <hi rend="italic">Dolphin</hi>.  But, 
more than this, the American war interfered with him personally, 
and he had a grudge against those who had caused 
this war; one can understand, then, how he would receive a 
proposition to deliver an Abolitionist, thus bringing down 
on him the Confederates, with whom he pretended to do 
business. 
</p><p>However, Crockston's insinuation did not fail to disturb 
him; he cast the thought from him, but it returned unceasingly 
to his mind, and when Miss Jenny came on deck 
the next day for a few minutes, he dared not look her in 
the face. 
<pb n="509"/>  
</p><p>And really it was a great pity, for this young girl, with 
the fair hair and sweet, intelligent face, deserved to be 
looked at by a young man of thirty.  But James felt embarrassed 
in her presence; he felt that this charming creature 
who had been educated in the school of misfortune 
possessed a strong and generous soul; he understood that 
his silence towards her inferred a refusal to acquiesce in 
her dearest wishes; besides, Miss Jenny never looked out 
for James Playfair, neither did she avoid him.  Thus for the 
first few days they spoke little or not at all to each other. 
Miss Halliburtt scarcely ever left her cabin, and it is certain 
she would never have addressed herself to the Captain of 
the <hi rend="italic">Dolphin</hi> if it had not been for Crockston's strategy, 
which brought both parties together. 
</p><p>The worthy American was a faithful servant of the 
Halliburtt family; he had been brought up in his master's 
house, and his devotion knew no bounds.  His good sense 
equalled his courage and energy, and, as has been seen, he 
had a way of looking things straight in the face.  He was 
very seldom discouraged, and could generally find a way 
out of the most intricate dangers with a wonderful skill. 
</p><p>This honest fellow had taken it into his head to deliver 
Mr. Halliburtt, to employ the Captain's ship, and the Captain 
himself for this purpose, and to return with him to 
England.  Such was his intention, so long as the young girl 
had no other object than to rejoin her father and share his 
captivity.  It was this Crockston tried to make the Captain 
understand, as we have seen, but the enemy had not yet 
surrendered; on the contrary. 
</p><p>"Now," said he, "it is absolutely necessary that Miss 
Jenny and the Captain come to an understanding; if they 
are going to be sulky like this all the passage we shall get 
nothing done.  They must speak, discuss; let them dispute 
even, so long as they talk, and I'll be hanged if during their 
conversation James Playfair does not propose himself what 
he refused me to-day." 
</p><p>But when Crockston saw that the young girl and the 
young man avoided each other, he began to be perplexed. 
</p><p>"We must look sharp," said he to himself, and the morning 
<pb n="510"/>  
of the fourth day he entered Miss Halliburtt's cabin, 
rubbing his hands with an air of perfect satisfaction. 
</p><p>"Good news!" cried he, "good news! You will never guess 
what the Captain has proposed to me.  A very noble young 
man he is.  Now try." 
</p><p>"Ah!" replied Jenny, whose heart beat violently, "has he 
proposed to &mdash; " 
</p><p>"To deliver Mr. Halliburtt, to carry him off from the 
Confederates, and bring him to England." 
</p><p>"Is it true?" cried Jenny. 
</p><p>"It is as I say, miss.  What a good-hearted man this 
James Playfair is! These English are either all good or all 
bad.  Ah! he may reckon on my gratitude, and I am ready 
to cut myself in pieces if it would please him." 
</p><p>Jenny's joy was profound on hearing Crockston's words. 
Deliver her father! She had never dared to think of such a 
plan, and the Captain of the <hi rend="italic">Dolphin</hi> was going to risk his 
ship and crew! 
</p><p>"That's what he is," added Crockston; "and this, Miss 
Jenny, is well worth an acknowledgment from you." 
</p><p>"More than an acknowledgment," cried the young girl; 
"a lasting friendship!" 
</p><p>And immediately she left the cabin to find James Playfair, 
and express to him the sentiments which flowed from 
her heart. 
</p><p>"Getting on by degrees," muttered the American. 
</p><p>James Playfair was pacing to and fro on the poop, and, 
as may be thought, he was very much surprised, not to 
say amazed, to see the young girl come up to him, her eyes 
moist with grateful tears, and, holding out her hand to him, 
saying: 
</p><p>"Thank you, sir, thank you for your kindness, which 
I should never have dared to expect from a stranger." 
</p><p>"Miss," replied the Captain, as if he understood nothing 
of what she was talking, and could not understand, "I do 
not know &mdash; " 
</p><p>"Nevertheless, sir, you are going to brave many dangers, 
perhaps compromise your interests for me, and you have 
<pb n="511"/>  
done so much already in offering me on board an hospitality 
to which I have no right whatever &mdash; " 
</p><p>"Pardon me, Miss Jenny," interrupted James Playfair, 
"but I protest again I do not understand your words.  I 
have acted towards you as any well-bred man would towards 
a lady, and my conduct deserves neither so many thanks 
nor so much gratitude." 
</p><p>"Mr.  Playfair," said Jenny, "it is useless to pretend any 
longer; Crockston has told me all!" 
</p><p>"Ah!" said the Captain, "Crockston has told you all; 
then I understand less than ever the reason for your leaving 
your cabin, and saying these words which &mdash; " 
</p><p>Whilst speaking the Captain felt very much embarrassed; 
he remembered the rough way in which he had received 
the American's overtures, but Jenny, fortunately for him, 
did not give him time for further explanation; she interrupted 
him, holding out her hand and saying: 
</p><p>"Mr.  James, I had no other object in coming on board 
your ship except to go to Charleston, and there, however 
cruel the slave-holders may be, they will not refuse to let 
a poor girl share her father's prison; that was all.  I had 
never thought of a return as possible; but, since you are so 
generous as to wish for my father's deliverance, since you 
will attempt everything to save him, be assured you have 
my deepest gratitude." 
</p><p>James did not know what to do or what part to assume; 
he bit his lip; he dared not take the hand offered him; he 
saw perfectly that Crockston had compromised him, so that 
escape was impossible.  At the same time he had no thoughts 
of delivering Mr. Halliburtt, and getting complicated in a 
disagreeable business: but how dash to the ground the hope 
which had arisen in this poor girl's heart? How refuse the 
hand which she held out to him with a feeling of such profound 
friendship? How change to tears of grief the tears of 
gratitude which filled her eyes? 
</p><p>So the young man tried to reply evasively, in a manner 
which would ensure his liberty of action for the future. 
</p><p>"Miss Jenny," said he, "rest assured I will do everything 
in my power for &mdash; " 
<pb n="512"/>  
</p><p>And he took the little hand in both of his, but with the 
gentle pressure he felt his heart melt and his head grow 
confused: words to express his thoughts failed him.  He 
stammered out some incoherent words: 
</p><p>"Miss &mdash; Miss Jenny &mdash; for you &mdash; " 
</p><p>Crockston, who was watching him, rubbed his hands, grinning 
and repeating to himself: 
</p><p>"It will come! it will come! it has come!" 
</p><p>How James Playfair would have managed to extricate 
himself from his embarrassing position no one knows, but 
fortunately for him, if not for the <hi rend="italic">Dolphin</hi>, the man on 
watch was heard crying: 
</p><p>"Ahoy, officer of the watch!" 
</p><p>"What now?" asked Mr. Mathew. 
</p><p>"A sail to windward!" 
</p><p>James Playfair, leaving the young girl, immediately 
sprang to the shrouds of the mainmast. 
</p></div1><div1 type="chapter" n="5" id="d9"> 
<head>THE SHOT FROM THE "IROQUOIS," AND MISS JENNY'S 
ARGUMENTS</head> 
<p>UNTIL now the navigation of the <hi rend="italic">Dolphin</hi> had been very 
fortunate.  Not one ship had been signalled before the sail 
hailed by the man on watch. 
</p><p>The <hi rend="italic">Dolphin</hi> was then in 32d 51' lat., and 57d 43' W. 
long.  For forty-eight hours a fog, which now began to rise, 
had covered the ocean.  If this mist favoured the <hi rend="italic">Dolphin</hi> by 
hiding her course, it also prevented any observations at a 
distance being made, and, without being aware of it, she 
might be sailing side by side, so to speak, with the ships she 
wished most to avoid. 
</p><p>Now this is just what had happened, and when the ship 
was signalled she was only three miles to windward. 
</p><p>When James Playfair had reached the cross-trees, he saw 
distinctly, through an opening in the mist, a large Federal 
corvette in full pursuit of the <hi rend="italic">Dolphin</hi>. 
<pb n="513"/>  
</p><p>After having carefully examined her, the Captain came 
down on deck again, and called to the first officer. 
</p><p>"Mr.  Mathew," said he, "what do you think of this ship?" 
</p><p>"I think, Captain, that it is a Federal cruiser, which suspects 
our intentions." 
</p><p>"There is no possible doubt of her nationality," said 
James Playfair.  "Look!" 
</p><p>At this moment the starry flag of the North United States 
appeared on the gaff-yards of the corvette, and the latter 
asserted her colours with a cannon-shot. 
</p><p>"An invitation to show ours," said Mr. Mathew.  "Well, 
let us show them; there is nothing to be ashamed of." 
</p><p>"What's the good?" replied James Playfair.  "Our flag 
will hardly protect us, and it will not hinder those people 
from paying us a visit.  No; let us go ahead." 
</p><p>"And go quickly," replied Mr. Mathew, "for, if my eyes 
do not deceive me, I have already seen that corvette lying 
off Liverpool, where she went to watch the ships in building: 
my name is not Mathew, if that is not the <hi rend="italic">Iroquois</hi> on her 
taffrail." 
</p><p>"And is she fast?" 
</p><p>"One of the fastest vessels of the Federal marine." 
</p><p>"What guns does she carry?" 
</p><p>"Eight." 
</p><p>"Pooh!" 
</p><p>"Oh, don't shrug your shoulders, Captain," said Mr. 
Mathew, in a serious tone; "two out of those eight guns are 
rifled, one is a sixty-pounder on the forecastle, and the other 
a hundred-pounder on deck." 
</p><p>"Upon my soul!" exclaimed James Playfair, "they are 
Parrott's, and will carry three miles." 
</p><p>"Yes, and farther than that, Captain." 
</p><p>"Ah, well! Mr. Mathew, let their guns be sixty or only 
four-pounders, and let them carry three miles or five hundred 
yards, it is all the same if we can go fast enough to 
avoid their shot.  We will show this <hi rend="italic">Iroquois</hi> how a ship can 
go when she is built on purpose to go.  Have the fires drawn 
forward, Mr. Mathew." 
</p><p>The first officer gave the Captain's orders to the engineer, 
<pb n="514"/>  
and soon volumes of black smoke curled from the steamer's 
chimneys. 
</p><p>This proceeding did not seem to please the corvette, for 
she made the <hi rend="italic">Dolphin</hi> the signal to lie to, but James Playfair 
paid no attention to this warning, and did not change his 
ship's course. 
</p><p>"Now," said he, "we shall see what the <hi rend="italic">Iroquois</hi> will do; 
here is a fine opportunity for her to try her guns.  Go ahead 
full speed!" 
</p><p>"Good!" exclaimed Mr. Mathew; "she will not be long 
in saluting us." 
</p><p>Returning to the poop, the Captain saw Miss Halliburtt 
sitting quietly near the bulwarks. 
</p><p>"Miss Jenny," said he, "we shall probably be chased by 
that corvette you see to windward, and as she will speak 
to us with shot, I beg to offer you my arm to take you to 
your cabin again." 
</p><p>"Thank you, very much, Mr. Playfair," replied the young 
girl, looking at him, "but I am not afraid of cannon-shots." 
</p><p>"However, miss, in spite of the distance, there may be 
some danger." 
</p><p>"Oh, I was not brought up to be fearful; they accustom 
us to everything in America, and I assure you that the shot 
from the <hi rend="italic">Iroquois</hi> will not make me lower my head." 
</p><p>"You are brave, Miss Jenny." 
</p><p>"Let us admit, then, that I am brave, and allow me to 
stay by you." 
</p><p>"I can refuse you nothing, Miss Halliburtt," replied the 
Captain, looking at the young girl's calm face. 
</p><p>These words were hardly uttered when they saw a line 
of white smoke issue from the bulwarks of the corvette; before 
the report had reached the <hi rend="italic">Dolphin</hi> a projectile whizzed 
through the air in the direction of the steamer. 
</p><p>At about twenty fathoms from the <hi rend="italic">Dolphin</hi> the shot, the 
speed of which had sensibly lessened, skimmed over the 
surface of the waves, marking its passage by a series of 
water-jets; then, with another burst, it rebounded to a 
certain height, passed over the <hi rend="italic">Dolphin</hi>, grazing the mizzen-<pb n="515"/>  
yards on the starboard side, fell at thirty fathoms beyond, 
and was buried in the waves. 
</p><p>"By Jove!" exclaimed James Playfair, "we must get 
along; another slap like that is not to be waited for." 
</p><p>"Oh!" exclaimed Mr. Mathew, "they will take some time 
to reload such pieces." 
</p><p>"Upon my honour, it is an interesting sight," said Crockston, 
who, with arms crossed, stood perfectly at his ease looking 
at the scene. 
</p><p>"Ah! that's you," cried James Playfair, scanning the 
American from head to foot. 
</p><p>"It is me, Captain," replied the American, undisturbed. 
"I have come to see how these brave Federals fire; not badly, 
in truth, not badly." 
</p><p>The Captain was going to answer Crockston sharply, but 
at this moment a second shot struck the sea on the starboard 
side. 
</p><p>"Good!" cried James Playfair, "we have already gained 
two cables on this <hi rend="italic">Iroquois</hi>.  Your friends sail like a buoy; 
do you hear, Master Crockston?" 
</p><p>"I will not say they don't," replied the American, "and 
for the first time in my life it does not fail to please me." 
</p><p>A third shot fell still farther astern, and in less than ten 
minutes the <hi rend="italic">Dolphin</hi> was out of range of the corvette's guns. 
</p><p>"So much for patent-logs, Mr. Mathew," said James 
Playfair; "thanks to those shot we know how to rate our 
speed.  Now have the fires lowered; it is not worth while to 
waste our coal uselessly." 
</p><p>"It is a good ship that you command," said Miss Halliburtt 
to the young Captain. 
</p><p>"Yes, Miss Jenny, my good <hi rend="italic">Dolphin</hi> makes her seventeen 
knots, and before the day is over we shall have lost sight of 
that corvette." 
</p><p>James Playfair did not exaggerate the sailing qualities 
of his ship, and the sun had not set before the masts of the 
American ship had disappeared below the horizon. 
</p><p>This incident allowed the Captain to see Miss Halliburtt's 
character in a new light; besides, the ice was broken, 
henceforward, during the whole of the voyage; the interviews 
<pb n="516"/>  
between the Captain and his passenger were frequent 
and prolonged; be found her to be a young girl, calm, strong, 
thoughtful, and intelligent, speaking with great ease, having 
her own ideas about everything, and expressing her thoughts 
with a conviction which unconsciously penetrated James 
Playfair's heart. 
</p><p>She loved her country, she was zealous in the great cause 
of the Union, and expressed herself on the civil war in the 
United States with an enthusiasm of which no other woman 
would have been capable.  Thus it happened, more than once, 
that James Playfair found it difficult to answer her, even 
when questions purely mercantile arose in connection with 
the war: Miss Jenny attacked them none the less vigorously, 
and would come to no other terms whatever.  At first James 
argued a great deal, and tried to uphold the Confederates 
against the Federals, to prove that the Secessionists were 
in the right, and that if the people were united voluntarily 
they might separate in the same manner.  But the young girl 
would not yield on this point; she demonstrated that the 
question of slavery was predominant in the struggle between 
the North and South Americans, that it was far more a 
war in the cause of morals and humanity than politics, and 
James could make no answer.  Besides, during these discussions, 
which he listened to attentively, it is difficult to say 
whether he was more touched by Miss Halliburtt's arguments 
or the charming manner in which she spoke; but at 
last he was obliged to acknowledge, among other things, that 
slavery was the principal feature in the war, that it must 
be put an end to decisively, and the last horrors of barbarous 
times abolished. 
</p><p>It has been said that the political opinions of the Captain 
did not trouble him much.  He would have sacrificed his 
most serious opinion before such enticing arguments and 
under like circumstances; he made a good bargain of his 
ideas for the same reason, but at last he was attacked in his 
tenderest point; this was the question of the traffic in which 
the <hi rend="italic">Dolphin</hi> was being employed, and, consequently, the 
ammunition which was being carried to the Confederates. 
</p><p>"Yes, Mr. James," said Miss Halliburtt, "gratitude does 
<pb n="517"/>  
not hinder me from speaking with perfect frankness; on the 
contrary, you are a brave seaman, a clever merchant, the 
house of Playfair is noted for its respectability; but in this 
case it fails in its principles, and follows a trade unworthy 
of it." 
</p><p>"How!" cried James, "the house of Playfair ought not to 
attempt such a commercial enterprise?" 
</p><p>"No! it is taking ammunition to the unhappy creatures 
in revolt against the government of their country, and it is 
lending arms to a bad cause." 
</p><p>"Upon my honour, Miss Jenny, I will not discuss the 
right of the Confederates with you; I will only answer you 
with one word: I am a merchant, and as such I only occupy 
myself with the interests of my house; I look for gain 
wherever there is an opportunity of getting it." 
</p><p>"That is precisely what is to be blamed, Mr. James," 
replied the young girl; "profit does not excuse it; thus, 
when you supply arms to the Southerners, with which to 
continue a criminal war, you are quite as guilty as when 
you sell opium to the Chinese, which stupefies them." 
</p><p>"Oh, for once, Miss Jenny, this is too much, and I cannot 
admit &mdash; " 
</p><p>"No; what I say is just, and when you consider it, when 
you understand the part you are playing, when you think 
of the results for which you are responsible, you will yield 
to me in this point, as in so many others." 
</p><p>James Playfair was dumfounded at these words; he left 
the young girl, a prey to angry thoughts, for he felt his 
powerlessness to answer; then he sulked like a child for half 
an hour, and an hour later he returned to the singular young 
girl who could overwhelm him with convincing arguments 
with quite a pleasant smile. 
</p><p>In short, however it may have come about, and although 
he would not acknowledge it to himself, Captain James 
Playfair belonged to himself no longer; he was no longer 
commander-in-chief on board his own ship. 
</p><p>Thus, to Crockston's great joy, Mr. Halliburtt's affairs 
appeared to be in a good way; the Captain seemed to have 
decided to undertake everything in his power to deliver 
<pb n="518"/>  
Miss Jenny's father, and for this he would be obliged to 
compromise the <hi rend="italic">Dolphin</hi>, his cargo, his crew, and incur the 
displeasure of his worthy Uncle Vincent. 
</p></div1><div1 type="chapter" n="6" id="d10"> 
<head>SULLIVAN ISLAND CHANNEL</head> 
<p>Two days after the meeting with the <hi rend="italic">Iroquois</hi>, the <hi rend="italic">Dolphin</hi> 
found herself abreast of the Bermudas, where she was 
assailed by a violent squall.  These isles are frequently visited 
by hurricanes, and are celebrated for shipwrecks.  It is here 
that Shakespeare has placed the exciting scene of his drama, 
<hi rend="italic">The Tempest</hi>, in which Ariel and Caliban dispute for the 
empire of the floods. 
</p><p>The squall was frightful; James Playfair thought once 
of running for one of the Bermudas, where the English had 
a military post: it would have been a sad waste of time, 
and therefore especially to be regretted; happily the <hi rend="italic">Dolphin</hi> 
behaved herself wonderfully well in the storm, and, 
after flying a whole day before the tempest, she was able to 
resume her course towards the American coast. 
</p><p>But if James Playfair had been pleased with his ship, he 
had not been less delighted with the young girl's bravery; 
Miss Halliburtt had passed the worst hours of the storm at 
his side, and James knew that a profound, imperious, irresistible 
love had taken possession of his whole being. 
</p><p>"Yes," said he, "this brave girl is mistress on board; 
she turns me like the sea a ship in distress &mdash; I feel that I am 
foundering! What will Uncle Vincent say? Ah! poor 
nature, I am sure that if Jenny asked me to throw all this 
cursed cargo into the sea, I should do it without hesitating, 
for love of her." 
</p><p>Happily for the firm of Playfair &amp; Co., Miss Halliburtt 
did not demand this sacrifice; nevertheless, the poor Captain 
had been taken captive, and Crockston, who read his 
heart like an open book, rubbed his hands gleefully. 
<pb n="519"/>  
</p><p>"We will hold him fast!" he muttered to himself, "and 
before a week has passed my master will be quietly installed 
in one of the best cabins of the <hi rend="italic">Dolphin</hi>." 
</p><p>As for Miss Jenny, did she perceive the feelings which she 
inspired? Did she allow herself to share them? No one 
could say, and James Playfair least of all; the young girl 
kept a perfect reserve, and her secret remained deeply 
buried in her heart. 
</p><p>But whilst love was making such progress in the heart of 
the young Captain, the <hi rend="italic">Dolphin</hi> sped with no less rapidity 
towards Charleston. 
</p><p>On the 13th of January, the watch signalled land ten 
miles to the west.  It was a low-lying coast, and almost 
blended with the line of the sea in the distance.  Crockston 
was examining the horizon attentively, and about nine 
o'clock in the morning he cried: 
</p><p>"Charleston lighthouse!" 
</p><p>Now that the bearings of the <hi rend="italic">Dolphin</hi> were set, James 
Playfair had but one thing to do, to decide by which channel 
he would run into Charleston Bay. 
</p><p>"If we meet with no obstacles," said he, "before three 
o'clock we shall be in safety in the docks of the port." 
</p><p>The town of Charleston is situated on the banks of an 
estuary seven miles long and two broad, called Charleston 
Harbour, the entrance to which is rather difficult.  It is enclosed 
between Morris Island on the south and Sullivan 
Island on the north.  At the time when the <hi rend="italic">Dolphin</hi> attempted 
to force the blockade Morris Island already belonged to 
the Federal troops, and General Gillmore had caused batteries 
to be erected overlooking the harbour.  Sullivan Island, 
on the contrary, was in the hands of the Confederates, who 
were also in possession of Moultrie Fort, situated at the 
extremity of the island; therefore it would be advantageous 
to the <hi rend="italic">Dolphin</hi> to go as close as possible to the northern 
shores to avoid the firing from the forts on Morris Island. 
</p><p>Five channels led into the estuary, Sullivan Island Channel, 
the Northern Channel, the Overall Channel, the Principal 
Channel, and lastly, the Lawford Channel; but it was 
<pb n="520"/>  
useless for strangers, unless they had skilful pilots on board, 
or ships drawing less than seven feet of water, to attempt 
this last; as for Northern and Overall Channels, they were 
in range of the Federalist batteries, so that it was no good 
thinking of them.  If James Playfair could have had his 
choice, he would have taken his steamer through the Principal 
Channel, which was the best, and the bearings of which 
were easy to follow; but it was necessary to yield to circumstances, 
and to decide according to the event.  Besides, 
the Captain of the <hi rend="italic">Dolphin</hi> knew perfectly all the secrets 
of this bay, its dangers, the depths of its water at low tide, 
and its currents, so that he was able to steer his ship with the 
greatest safety as soon as he entered one of these narrow 
straits.  The great question was to get there. 
</p><p>Now this work demanded an experienced seaman, and 
one who knew exactly the qualities of the <hi rend="italic">Dolphin</hi>. 
</p><p>In fact, two Federal frigates were now cruising in the 
Charleston waters.  Mr. Mathew soon drew James Playfair's 
attention to them. 
</p><p>"They are preparing to ask us what we want on these 
shores," said he. 
</p><p>"Ah, well! we won't answer them," replied the Captain, 
"and they will not get their curiosity satisfied." 
</p><p>In the meanwhile the cruisers were coming on full steam 
towards the <hi rend="italic">Dolphin</hi>, who continued her course, taking care 
to keep out of range of their guns.  But in order to gain time 
James Playfair made for the south-west, wishing to put the 
enemies' ships off their guard; the latter must have thought 
that the <hi rend="italic">Dolphin</hi> intended to make for Morris Island Channel. 
Now there they had batteries and guns, a single shot 
from which would have been enough to sink the English 
ship; so the Federals allowed the <hi rend="italic">Dolphin</hi> to run towards the 
south-west, contenting themselves by observing her without 
following closely. 
</p><p>Thus for an hour the respective situations of the ships did 
not change, for James Playfair, wishing to deceive the cruisers 
as to the course of the <hi rend="italic">Dolphin</hi>, had caused the fires 
to be moderated, so that the speed was decreased.  However, 
<pb n="521"/>  
from the thick volumes of smoke which escaped from 
the chimneys, it might have been thought that he was trying 
to get his maximum pressure, and, consequently his maximum 
of rapidity. 
</p><p>"They will be slightly astonished presently," said James 
Playfair, "when they see us slip through their fingers!" 
</p><p>In fact, when the Captain saw that he was near enough 
to Morris Island, and before a line of guns, the range of 
which he did not know, he turned his rudder quickly, and 
the ship resumed her northerly course, leaving the cruisers 
two miles to windward of her; the latter, seeing this 
manoeuvre, understood the steamer's object, and began to 
pursue her in earnest, but it was too late.  The <hi rend="italic">Dolphin</hi> 
doubled her speed under the action of the screws, and 
distanced them rapidly.  Going nearer to the coast, a few 
shell were sent after her as an acquittal of conscience, but 
the Federals were outdone, for their projectiles did not 
reach half-way.  At eleven o'clock in the morning, the 
steamer ranging near Sullivan Island, thanks to her small 
draft, entered the narrow strait full steam; there she was in 
safety, for no Federalist cruiser dared follow her in this 
channel, the depth of which, on an average, was only eleven 
feet at low tide. 
</p><p>"How!" cried Crockston, "and is that the only difficulty?" 
</p><p>"Oh! oh! Master Crockston," said James Playfair, "the 
difficulty is not in entering, but in getting out again." 
</p><p>"Nonsense!" replied the American, "that does not make 
me at all uneasy; with a boat like the <hi rend="italic">Dolphin</hi> and a Captain 
like Mr. James Playfair, one can go where one likes, 
and come out in the same manner." 
</p><p>Nevertheless, James Playfair, with telescope in his hand, 
was attentively examining the route to be followed.  He had 
before him excellent coasting guides, with which he could 
go ahead without any difficulty or hesitation. 
</p><p>Once his ship was safely in the narrow channel which 
runs the length of Sullivan Island, James steered bearing 
towards the middle of Fort Moultrie as far as the Pickney 
Castle, situated on the isolated island of Shute's Folly; 
<pb n="522"/>  
on the other side rose Fort Johnson, a little way to the north 
of Fort Sumter. 
</p><p>At this moment the steamer was saluted by some shot 
which did not reach her, from the batteries on Morris 
Island.  She continued her course without any deviation, 
passed before Moultrieville, situated at the extremity of 
Sullivan Island, and entered the bay. 
</p><p>Soon Fort Sumter on the left protected her from the batteries 
of the Federalists. 
</p><p>This fort, so celebrated in the civil war, is situated three 
miles and a half from Charleston, and about a mile from 
each side of the bay: it is nearly pentagonal in form, built 
on an artificial island of Massachusetts granite; it took ten 
years to construct and cost more than 900,000 dollars. 
</p><p>It was from this fort, on the 13th of April, 1861, that 
Anderson and the Federal troops were driven, and it was 
against it that the first shot of the Confederates was fired. 
It is impossible to estimate the quantity of iron and lead 
which the Federals showered down upon it.  However, it 
resisted for almost three years, but a few months after the 
passage of the <hi rend="italic">Dolphin</hi> it fell beneath General Gillmore's 
three hundred-pounders on Morris Island. 
</p><p>But at this time it was in all its strength, and the Confederate 
flag floated proudly above it. 
</p><p>Once past the fort, the town of Charleston appeared, 
lying between Ashley and Cooper Rivers. 
</p><p>James Playfair threaded his way through the buoys which 
mark the entrance of the channel, leaving behind the 
Charleston lighthouse, visible above Morris Island.  He had 
hoisted the English flag, and made his way with wonderful 
rapidity through the narrow channels.  When he had passed 
the quarantine buoy, he advanced freely into the centre of 
the bay.  Miss Halliburtt was standing on the poop, looking 
at the town where her father was kept prisoner, and her 
eyes filled with tears. 
</p><p>At last the steamer's speed was moderated by the Captain's 
orders; the <hi rend="italic">Dolphin</hi> ranged along the end of the 
south and east batteries, and was soon moored at the quay 
of the North Commercial Wharf. 
<pb n="523"/>  
</p></div1><div1 type="chapter" n="7" id="d11"> 
<head>A SOUTHERN GENERAL</head> 
<p>THE <hi rend="italic">Dolphin</hi>, on arriving at the Charleston quay, had 
been saluted by the cheers of a large crowd.  The inhabitants 
of this town, strictly blockaded by sea, were not accustomed 
to visits from European ships.  They asked each other, not 
without astonishment, what this great steamer, proudly bearing 
the English flag, had come to do in their waters; but 
when they learned the object of her voyage, and why she 
had just forced the passage Sullivan, when the report spread 
that she carried a cargo of smuggled ammunition, the 
cheers and joyful cries were redoubled. 
</p><p>James Playfair, without losing a moment, entered into 
negotiation with General Beauregard, the military commander 
of the town.  The latter eagerly received the young 
Captain of the <hi rend="italic">Dolphin</hi>, who had arrived in time to provide 
the soldiers with the clothes and ammunition they were so 
much in want of.  It was agreed that the unloading of the 
ship should take place immediately, and numerous hands 
came to help the English sailors. 
</p><p>Before quitting his ship James Playfair had received from 
Miss Halliburtt the most pressing injunctions with regard 
to her father, and the Captain had placed himself entirely 
at the young girl's service. 
</p><p>"Miss Jenny," he had said, "you may rely on me; I will 
do the utmost in my power to save your father, but I hope 
this business will not present many difficulties.  I shall go 
and see General Beauregard to-day, and, without asking 
him at once for Mr. Halliburtt's liberty, I shall learn in 
what situation he is, whether he is on bail or a prisoner." 
</p><p>"My poor father!" replied Jenny, sighing; "he little 
thinks his daughter is so near him.  Oh that I could fly into 
his arms!" 
</p><p>"A little patience, Miss Jenny; you will soon embrace 
your father.  Rely upon my acting with the most entire devotion, 
but also with prudence and consideration." 
</p><p>This is why James Playfair, after having delivered the 
<pb n="524"/>  
cargo of the <hi rend="italic">Dolphin</hi> up to the General, and bargained for 
an immense stock of cotton, faithful to his promise, turned 
the conversation to the events of the day. 
</p><p>"So," said he, "you believe in the triumph of the slave-holders?" 
</p><p>"I do not for a moment doubt of our final success, and, 
as regards Charleston, Lee's army will soon relieve it: besides, 
what do you expect from the Abolitionists? Admitting 
that which will never be, that the commercial towns of Virginia, 
the two Carolinas, Georgia, Alabama, fall under their 
power, what then? Will they be masters of a country they 
can never occupy? No, certainly not; and for my part, if 
they are ever victorious, they shall pay dearly for it." 
</p><p>"And you are quite sure of your soldiers?" asked the 
Captain.  "You are not afraid that Charleston will grow 
weary of a siege which is ruining her?" 
</p><p>"No, I do not fear treason; besides, the traitors would 
be punished remorselessly, and I would destroy the town itself 
by sword or fire if I discovered the least Unionist movement. 
Jefferson Davis confided Charleston to me, and you 
may be sure that Charleston is in safe hands." 
</p><p>"Have you any Federal prisoners?" asked James Playfair, 
coming to the interesting object of the conversation. 
</p><p>"Yes, Captain," replied the General, "it was at Charleston 
that the first shot of separation was fired.  The Abolitionists 
who were here attempted to resist, and, after being 
defeated, they have been kept as prisoners of war." 
</p><p>"And have you many?" 
</p><p>"About a hundred." 
</p><p>"Free in the town?" 
</p><p>"They were until I discovered a plot formed by them: 
their chief succeeded in establishing a communication with 
the besiegers, who were thus informed of the situation of 
affairs in the town.  I was then obliged to lock up these 
dangerous guests, and several of them will only leave their 
prison to ascend the slope of the citadel, where ten confederate 
balls will reward them for their federalism." 
</p><p>"What! to be shot!" cried the young man, shuddering 
involuntarily. 
<pb n="525"/>  
</p><p>"Yes, and their chief first of all.  He is a very dangerous 
man to have in a besieged town.  I have sent his letters to 
the President at Richmond, and before a week is passed his 
sentence will be irrevocably passed." 
</p><p>"Who is this man you speak of?" asked James Playfair, 
with an assumed carelessness. 
</p><p>"A journalist from Boston, a violent Abolitionist with 
the confounded spirit of Lincoln." 
</p><p>"And his name?" 
</p><p>"Jonathan Halliburtt." 
</p><p>"Poor wretch!" exclaimed James, suppressing his emotion. 
"Whatever he may have done, one cannot help pitying 
him.  And you think that he will be shot?" 
</p><p>"I am sure of it," replied Beauregard.  "What can you 
expect? War is war; one must defend oneself as best one 
can." 
</p><p>"Well, it is nothing to me," said the Captain.  "I shall 
be far enough away when this execution takes place." 
</p><p>"What! you are thinking of going away already." 
</p><p>"Yes, General, business must be attended to; as soon as 
my cargo of cotton is on board I shall be out to sea again. 
I was fortunate enough to enter the bay, but the difficulty 
is in getting out again.  The <hi rend="italic">Dolphin</hi> is a good ship; she 
can beat any of the Federal vessels for speed, but she does 
not pretend to distance cannon-balls, and a shell in her hull 
or engine would seriously affect my enterprise." 
</p><p>"As you please, Captain," replied Beauregard; "I have 
no advice to give you under such circumstances.  You are 
doing your business, and you are right.  I should act in the 
same manner were I in your place; besides, a stay at Charleston 
is not very pleasant, and a harbour where shells are 
falling three days out of four is not a safe shelter for your 
ship; so you will set sail when you please; but can you tell 
me what is the number and the force of the Federal vessels 
cruising before Charleston?" 
</p><p>James Playfair did his best to answer the General, and 
took leave of him on the best of terms; then he returned 
to the <hi rend="italic">Dolphin</hi> very thoughtful and very depressed from 
what he had just heard. 
<pb n="526"/>  
</p><p>"What shall I say to Miss Jenny? Ought I to tell her of 
Mr. Halliburtt's terrible situation? Or would it be better 
to keep her in ignorance of the trial which is awaiting her? 
Poor child!" 
</p><p>He had not gone fifty steps from the governor's house 
when he ran against Crockston.  The worthy American had 
been watching for him since his departure. 
</p><p>"Well, Captain?" 
</p><p>James Playfair looked steadily at Crockston, and the latter 
soon understood he had no favourable news to give him. 
</p><p>"Have you seen Beauregard?" he asked. 
</p><p>"Yes," replied James Playfair. 
</p><p>"And have you spoken to him about Mr. Halliburtt?" 
</p><p>"No, it was he who spoke to me about him." 
</p><p>"Well, Captain?" 
</p><p>"Well, I may as well tell you everything, Crockston." 
</p><p>"Everything, Captain." 
</p><p>"General Beauregard has told me that your master will 
be shot within a week." 
</p><p>At this news anyone else but Crockston would have grown 
furious or given way to bursts of grief, but the American, 
who feared nothing, only said, with almost a smile on his 
lips: 
</p><p>"Pooh! what does it matter?" 
</p><p>"How! what does it matter?" cried James Playfair.  "I 
tell you that Mr. Halliburtt will be shot within a week, and 
you answer, what does it matter?" 
</p><p>"And I mean it &mdash; if in six days he is on board the <hi rend="italic">Dolphin</hi>, 
and if in seven days the <hi rend="italic">Dolphin</hi> is on the open sea." 
</p><p>"Right!" exclaimed the Captain, pressing Crockston's 
hand.  "I understand, my good fellow, you have got some 
pluck; and for myself, in spite of Uncle Vincent, I would 
throw myself overboard for Miss Jenny." 
</p><p>"No one need be thrown overboard," replied the American, 
"only the fish would gain by that: the most important business 
now is to deliver Mr. Halliburtt." 
</p><p>"But you must know that it will be difficult to do so." 
</p><p>"Pooh!" exclaimed Crockston. 
<pb n="527"/>  
</p><p>"It is a question of communicating with a prisoner strictly 
guarded." 
</p><p>"Certainly." 
</p><p>"And to bring about an almost miraculous escape." 
</p><p>"Nonsense," exclaimed Crockston; "a prisoner thinks 
more of escaping than his guardian thinks of keeping him; 
that's why, thanks to our help, Mr. Halliburtt will be saved." 
</p><p>"You are right, Crockston." 
</p><p>"Always right." 
</p><p>"But now what will you do? There must be some plan: 
and there are precautions to be taken." 
</p><p>"I will think about it." 
</p><p>"But when Miss Jenny learns that her father is condemned 
to death, and that the order for his execution may 
come any day &mdash; " 
</p><p>"She will know nothing about it, that is all." 
</p><p>"Yes, it will be better for her and for us to tell her 
nothing." 
</p><p>"Where is Mr. Halliburtt imprisoned?" asked Crockston. 
</p><p>"In the citadel," replied James Playfair. 
</p><p>"Just so! . . . On board now?" 
</p><p>"On board, Crockston!" 
</p></div1><div1 type="chapter" n="8" id="d12"> 
<head>THE ESCAPE</head> 
<p>Miss JENNY, sitting at the poop of the <hi rend="italic">Dolphin</hi>, was 
anxiously waiting the Captain's return; when the latter went 
up to her she could not utter a word, but her eyes questioned 
James Playfair more eagerly than her lips could have done. 
The latter, with Crockston's help, informed the young girl 
of the facts relating to her father's imprisonment.  He said 
that he had carefully broached the subject of the prisoners 
of war to Beauregard, but, as the General did not seem 
disposed at all in their favour, he had thought it better to 
say no more about it, but think the matter over again. 
</p><p>"Since Mr. Halliburtt is not free in the town, his escape 
<pb n="528"/>  
will be more difficult; but I will finish my task, and I 
promise you, Miss Jenny, that the <hi rend="italic">Dolphin</hi> shall not leave 
Charleston without having your father on board." 
</p><p>"Thank you, Mr. James; I thank you with my whole 
heart." 
</p><p>At these words James Playfair felt a thrill of joy through 
his whole being. 
</p><p>He approached the young girl with moist eyes and quivering 
lips; perhaps he was going to make an avowal of the 
sentiments he could no longer repress, when Crockston interfered: 
</p><p>"This is no time for grieving," said he; "we must go to 
work, and consider what to do." 
</p><p>"Have you any plan, Crockston?" asked the young girl. 
</p><p>"I always have a plan," replied the American: "it is my 
peculiarity." 
</p><p>"But a good one?" said James Playfair. 
</p><p>"Excellent! and all the ministers in Washington could 
not devise a better; it is almost as good as if Mr. Halliburtt 
was already on board." 
</p><p>Crockston spoke with such perfect assurance, at the same 
time with such simplicity, that it must have been the most 
incredulous person who could doubt his words. 
</p><p>"We are listening, Crockston," said James Playfair. 
</p><p>"Good! You, Captain, will go to General Beauregard, and 
ask a favour of him which he will not refuse you." 
</p><p>"And what is that?" 
</p><p>"You will tell him that you have on board a tiresome 
subject, a scamp who has been very troublesome during the 
voyage, and excited the crew to revolt.  You will ask of him 
permission to shut him up in the citadel; at the same time, 
on the condition that he shall return to the ship on her departure, 
in order to be taken back to England, to be delivered 
over to the justice of his country." 
</p><p>"Good!" said James Playfair, half smiling, "I will do 
all that, and Beauregard will grant my request very 
willingly." 
</p><p>"I am perfectly sure of it," replied the American. 
</p><p>"But," resumed Playfair, "one thing is wanting." 
<pb n="529"/>  
</p><p>"What is that?" 
</p><p>"The scamp." 
</p><p>"He is before you, Captain." 
</p><p>"What, the rebellious subject?" 
</p><p>"Is myself; don't trouble yourself about that." 
</p><p>"Oh! you brave, generous heart," cried Jenny, pressing 
the American's rough hands between her small white palms. 
</p><p>"Go, Crockston," said James Playfair; "I understand 
you, my friend; and I only regret one thing &mdash; that is, that 
I cannot take your place." 
</p><p>"Everyone his part," replied Crockston; "if you put 
yourself in my place you would be very much embarrassed, 
which I shall not be; you will have enough to do later on 
to get out of the harbour under the fire of the Feds and 
Rebs, which, for my part, I should manage very badly." 
</p><p>"Well, Crockston, go on." 
</p><p>"Once in the citadel &mdash; I know it &mdash; I shall see what to do, 
and rest assured I shall do my best; in the meanwhile, you 
will be getting your cargo on board." 
</p><p>"Oh, business is now a very unimportant detail," said the 
Captain. 
</p><p>"Not at all! And what would your Uncle Vincent say to 
that? We must join sentiment with work; it will prevent suspicion; 
but do it quickly.  Can you be ready in six days?" 
</p><p>"Yes." 
</p><p>"Well, let the <hi rend="italic">Dolphin</hi> be ready to start on the 22nd." 
</p><p>"She shall be ready." 
</p><p>"On the evening of the 22nd of January, you understand, 
send a gig with your best men to White Point, at the end 
of the town; wait there till nine o'clock, and then you will 
see Mr. Halliburtt and your servant." 
</p><p>"But how will you manage to effect Mr. Halliburtt's 
deliverance, and also escape yourself?" 
</p><p>"That's my look-out." 
</p><p>"Dear Crockston, you are going to risk your life then, 
to save my father!" 
</p><p>"Don't be uneasy, Miss Jenny, I shall risk absolutely 
nothing, you may believe me." 
<pb n="530"/>  
</p><p>"Well," asked James Playfair, "when must I have you 
locked up?" 
</p><p>"To-day &mdash; you understand &mdash; I demoralise your crew; 
there is no time to be lost." 
</p><p>"Would you like any money? It may be of use to you 
in the citadel." 
</p><p>"Money to buy the gaoler! Oh, no, it would be a poor 
bargain; when one goes there the gaoler keeps the money 
and the prisoner! No, I have surer means than that; however, 
a few dollars may be useful; one must be able to drink, 
if needs be." 
</p><p>"And intoxicate the gaoler." 
</p><p>"No, an intoxicated gaoler would spoil everything.  No, 
I tell you I have an idea; let me work it out." 
</p><p>"Here, my good fellow, are ten dollars." 
</p><p>"It is too much, but I will return what is over." 
</p><p>"Well, then, are you ready?" 
</p><p>"Quite ready to be a downright rogue." 
</p><p>"Let us go to work, then." 
</p><p>"Crockston," said the young girl, in a faltering voice, 
"you are the best man on earth." 
</p><p>"I know it," replied the American, laughing good-humouredly.  "By the by, Captain, an important item." 
</p><p>"What is that?" 
</p><p>"If the General proposes to hang your rebel &mdash; you know 
that military men like sharp work &mdash; " 
</p><p>"Well, Crockston?" 
</p><p>"Well, you will say that you must think about it." 
</p><p>"I promise you I will." 
</p><p>The same day, to the great astonishment of the crew, who 
were not in the secret, Crockston, with his feet and hands 
in irons, was taken on shore by a dozen sailors, and half 
an hour after, by Captain James Playfair's request, he was 
led through the streets of the town, and, in spite of his 
resistance, was imprisoned in the citadel. 
</p><p>During this and the following days the unloading of the 
<hi rend="italic">Dolphin</hi> was rapidly accomplished; the steam cranes lifted 
out the European cargo to make room for the native goods. 
The people of Charleston, who were present at this interesting 
<pb n="531"/>  
work, helped the sailors, whom they held in great 
respect, but the Captain did not leave the brave fellows 
much time for receiving compliments; he was constantly 
behind them, and urged them on with a feverish activity, 
the reason of which the sailors could not suspect. 
</p><p>Three days later, on the 18th of January, the first bales 
of cotton began to be packed in the hold: although 
James Playfair troubled himself no more about it, the firm 
of Playfair and Co. were making an excellent bargain, having 
obtained the cotton which encumbered the Charleston 
wharves at very far less than its value. 
</p><p>In the meantime no news had been heard of Crockston. 
Jenny, without saying anything about it, was a prey to 
incessant fears; her pale face spoke for her, and James 
Playfair endeavoured his utmost to ease her mind. 
</p><p>"I have all confidence in Crockston," said he; "he is a 
devoted servant, as you must know better than I do, Miss 
Jenny.  You must make yourself quite at ease; believe me, 
in three days you will be folded in your father's arms." 
</p><p>"Ah! Mr. James," cried the young girl, "how can I ever 
repay you for such devotion? How shall we ever be able to 
thank you?" 
</p><p>"I will tell you when we are in English seas," replied 
the young Captain. 
</p><p>Jenny raised her tearful face to him for a moment, then 
her eyelids drooped, and she went back to her cabin. 
</p><p>James Playfair hoped that the young girl would know 
nothing of her father's terrible situation until he was in 
safety, but she was apprised of the truth by the involuntary 
indiscretion of a sailor. 
</p><p>The reply from the Richmond cabinet had arrived by a 
courier who had been able to pass the line of outposts; the 
reply contained Jonathan Halliburtt's death-warrant.  The 
news of the approaching execution was not long in spreading 
through the town, and it was brought on board by one 
of the sailors of the <hi rend="italic">Dolphin</hi>; the man told the Captain, 
without thinking that Miss Halliburtt was within hearing; 
the young girl uttered a piercing cry, and fell unconscious 
<pb n="532"/>  
on the deck.  James Playfair carried her to her cabin, but 
the most assiduous care was necessary to restore her to life. 
</p><p>When she opened her eyes again, she saw the young 
Captain, who, with a finger on his lips, enjoined absolute 
silence.  With difficulty she repressed the outburst of her 
grief, and James Playfair, leaning towards her, said gently: 
</p><p>"Jenny, in two hours your father will be in safety near 
you, or I shall have perished in endeavouring to save him!" 
</p><p>Then he left the cabin, saying to himself, "And now he 
must be carried off at any price, since I must pay for his 
liberty with my own life and those of my crew." 
</p><p>The hour for action had arrived, the loading of the cotton 
cargo had been finished since morning; in two hours the 
ship would be ready to start. 
</p><p>James Playfair had left the North Commercial Wharf 
and gone into the roadstead, so that he was ready to make 
use of the tide, which would be high at nine o'clock in the 
evening. 
</p><p>It was seven o'clock when James left the young girl, and 
began to make preparations for departure.  Until the present 
time the secret had been strictly kept between himself, 
Crockston, and Jenny; but now he thought it wise to inform 
Mr. Mathew of the situation of affairs, and he did so immediately. 
</p><p>"Very well, sir," replied Mr. Mathew, without making 
the least remark, "and nine o'clock is the time?" 
</p><p>"Nine o'clock, and have the fires lit immediately, and 
the steam got up." 
</p><p>"It shall be done, Captain." 
</p><p>"The <hi rend="italic">Dolphin</hi> may remain at anchor; we will cut our 
moorings and sheer off, without losing a moment." 
</p><p>"Just so." 
</p><p>"Have a lantern placed at the mainmast-head; the night 
is dark, and will be foggy; we must not risk losing our way 
in returning.  You had better have the bell for starting rung 
at nine o'clock." 
</p><p>"Your orders shall be punctually attended to, Captain." 
</p><p>"And now, Mr. Mathew, have a shore-boat manned with 
six of our best men.  I am going to set out directly for White 
<pb n="533"/>  
Point.  I leave Miss Jenny in your charge, and may God 
protect us!" 
</p><p>"May God protect us!" repeated the first officer. 
</p><p>Then he immediately gave the necessary orders for the 
fires to be lighted, and the shore-boat provided with men. 
In a few minutes the boat was ready, and James Playfair, 
after bidding Jenny good-bye, stepped into it, whilst at the 
same time he saw volumes of black smoke issuing from the 
chimneys of the ship, and losing itself in the fog. 
</p><p>The darkness was profound; the wind had fallen, and 
in the perfect silence the waters seemed to slumber in the 
immense harbour, whilst a few uncertain lights glimmered 
through the mist.  James Playfair had taken his place at the 
rudder, and with a steady hand he guided his boat towards 
White Point.  It was a distance of about two miles; during 
the day James had taken his bearings perfectly, so that he 
was able to make direct for Charleston Point. 
</p><p>Eight o'clock struck from the church of St. Philip when 
the shore-boat ran aground at White Point. 
</p><p>There was an hour to wait before the exact time fixed 
by Crockston; the quay was deserted, with the exception 
of the sentinel pacing to and fro on the south and east 
batteries.  James Playfair grew impatient, and the minutes 
seemed hours to him. 
</p><p>At half-past eight he heard the sound of approaching 
steps; he left his men with their oars clear and ready to 
start, and went himself to see who it was; but he had not 
gone ten feet when he met a band of coastguards, in all 
about twenty men.  James drew his revolver from his waist, 
deciding to make use of it, if needs be; but what could he 
do against these soldiers, who were coming on to the quay? 
</p><p>The leader came up to him, and, seeing the boat, asked: 
</p><p>"Whose craft is that?" 
</p><p>"It is a gig belonging to the <hi rend="italic">Dolphin</hi>," replied the young 
man. 
</p><p>"And who are you?" 
</p><p>"Captain James Playfair." 
</p><p>"I thought you had already started, and were now in 
the Charleston channels." 
<pb n="534"/>  
</p><p>"I am ready to start.  I ought even now to be on my 
way but &mdash; " 
</p><p>"But &mdash; " persisted the coastguard. 
</p><p>A bright idea shot through James's mind, and he 
answered: 
</p><p>"One of my sailors is locked up in the citadel, and, to 
tell the truth, I had almost forgotten him; fortunately I 
thought of him in time, and I have sent my men to bring 
him." 
</p><p>"Ah! that troublesome fellow; you wish to take him back 
to England?" 
</p><p>"Yes. 
</p><p>"He might as well be hung here as there," said the coast-guard, laughing at his joke. 
</p><p>"So I think," said James Playfair, "but it is better to 
have the thing done in the regular way." 
</p><p>"Not much chance of that, Captain, when you have to 
face the Morris Island batteries." 
</p><p>"Don't alarm yourself.  I got in and I'll get out again." 
</p><p>"Prosperous voyage to you!" 
</p><p>"Thank you." 
</p><p>With this the men went off, and the shore was left silent. 
</p><p>At this moment nine o'clock struck; it was the appointed 
moment.  James felt his heart beat violently; a whistle was 
heard; he replied to it, then he waited, listening, with his 
hand up to enjoin perfect silence on the sailors.  A man 
appeared enveloped in a large cloak, and looking from one 
side to another.  James ran up to him. 
</p><p>"Mr. Halliburtt?" 
</p><p>"I am he," replied the man with the cloak. 
</p><p>"God be praised!" cried James Playfair.  "Embark without 
losing a minute.  Where is Crockston?" 
</p><p>"Crockston!" exclaimed Mr. Halliburtt, amazed.  "What 
do you mean?" 
</p><p>"The man who has saved you and brought you here was 
your servant Crockston." 
</p><p>"The man who came with me was the gaoler from the 
citadel," replied Mr. Halliburtt. 
<pb n="535"/>  
</p><p>"The gaoler!" cried James Playfair. 
</p><p>Evidently he knew nothing about it, and a thousand fears 
crowded in his mind. 
</p><p>"Quite right, the gaoler," cried a well-known voice.  "The 
gaoler is sleeping like a top in my cell." 
</p><p>"Crockston! you! Can it be you?" exclaimed Mr. 
Halliburtt. 
</p><p>"No time to talk now, master; we will explain everything 
to you afterwards.  It is a question of life or death.  Get in 
quick!" 
</p><p>The three men took their places in the boat. 
</p><p>"Push off!" cried the captain. 
</p><p>Immediately the six oars dipped into the water; the boat 
darted like a fish through the waters of Charleston Harbour. 
</p></div1><div1 type="chapter" n="9" id="d13"> 
<head>BETWEEN TWO FIRES</head> 
<p>THE boat, pulled by six robust oarsmen, flew over the 
water.  The fog was growing dense, and it was with difficulty 
that James Playfair succeeded in keeping to the line of his 
bearings.  Crockston sat at the bows, and Mr. Halliburtt at 
the stern, next the Captain.  The prisoner, only now informed 
of the presence of his servant, wished to speak to 
him, but the latter enjoined silence. 
</p><p>However, a few minutes later, when they were in the middle 
of the harbour, Crockston determined to speak, knowing 
what thoughts were uppermost in Mr. Halliburtt's mind. 
</p><p>"Yes, my dear master," said he, "the gaoler is in my 
place in the cell, where I gave him two smart blows, one on 
the head and the other on the stomach, to act as a sleeping 
draught, and this when he was bringing me my supper; 
there is gratitude for you.  I took his clothes and his keys, 
found you, and let you out of the citadel, under the soldiers' 
noses.  That is all I have done." 
</p><p>"But my daughter &mdash; ?" asked Mr. Halliburtt. 
<pb n="536"/>  
</p><p>"Is on board the ship which is going to take you to 
England." 
</p><p>"My daughter there! there!" cried the American, springing 
from his seat. 
</p><p>"Silence!" replied Crockston, "a few minutes, and we 
shall be saved." 
</p><p>The boat flew through the darkness, but James Playfair 
was obliged to steer rather by guess, as the lanterns of the 
<hi rend="italic">Dolphin</hi> were no longer visible through the fog.  He was 
undecided what direction to follow, and the darkness was 
so great that the rowers could not even see to the end of 
their oars. 
</p><p>"Well, Mr. James?" said Crockston. 
</p><p>"We must have made more than a mile and a half," 
replied the Captain.  "You don't see anything, Crockston?" 
</p><p>"Nothing; nevertheless, I have good eyes; but we shall 
get there all right.  They don't suspect anything out there." 
</p><p>These words were hardly finished when the flash of a gun 
gleamed for an instant through the darkness, and vanished 
in the mist. 
</p><p>"A signal!" cried James Playfair. 
</p><p>"Whew!" exclaimed Crockston.  "It must have come from 
the citadel.  Let us wait." 
</p><p>A second, then a third shot was fired in the direction of 
the first, and almost the same signal was repeated a mile in 
front of the gig. 
</p><p>"That is from Fort Sumter," cried Crockston, "and it 
is the signal of escape.  Urge on the men; everything is discovered." 
</p><p>"Pull for your lives, my men!" cried James Playfair, 
urging on the sailors, "those gun-shots cleared my route. 
The <hi rend="italic">Dolphin</hi> is eight hundred yards ahead of us.  Stop! I 
hear the bell on board.  Hurrah, there it is again! Twenty 
pounds for you if we are back in five minutes!" 
</p><p>The boat skimmed over the waves under the sailors' 
powerful oars.  A cannon boomed in the direction of the 
town.  Crockston heard a ball whiz past them. 
</p><p>The bell on the <hi rend="italic">Dolphin</hi> was ringing loudly.  A few more 
<pb n="537"/>  
strokes and the boat was alongside.  A few more seconds and 
Jenny fell into her father's arms. 
</p><p>The gig was immediately raised, and James Playfair 
sprang on to the poop. 
</p><p>"Is the steam up, Mr. Mathew?" 
</p><p>"Yes, Captain." 
</p><p>"Have the moorings cut at once." 
</p><p>A few minutes later the two screws carried the steamer 
towards the principal channel, away from Fort Sumter. 
</p><p>"Mr.  Mathew," said James, "we must not think of taking 
the Sullivan Island channel; we should run directly 
under the Confederate guns.  Let us go as near as possible 
to the right side of the harbour out of range of the Federal 
batteries.  Have you a safe man at the helm?" 
</p><p>"Yes, Captain." 
</p><p>"Have the lanterns and the fires on deck extinguished; 
there is a great deal too much light, but we cannot help the 
reflection from the engine-rooms." 
</p><p>During this conversation the <hi rend="italic">Dolphin</hi> was going at a 
great speed; but in altering her course to keep to the right 
side of the Charleston Harbour she was obliged to enter a 
channel which took her for a moment near Fort Sumter; 
and when scarcely half a mile off all the guns bearing on 
her were discharged at the same time, and a shower of shot 
and shell passed in front of the <hi rend="italic">Dolphin</hi> with a thundering 
report. 
</p><p>"Too soon, stupids," cried James Playfair, with a burst of 
laughter.  "Make haste, make haste, Mr. Engineer! We shall 
get between two fires." 
</p><p>The stokers fed the furnaces, and the <hi rend="italic">Dolphin</hi> trembled 
all over with the effort of the engine as if she was on the 
point of exploding. 
</p><p>At this moment a second report was heard, and another 
shower of balls whizzed behind the <hi rend="italic">Dolphin</hi>. 
</p><p>"Too late, stupids," cried the young Captain, with a 
regular roar. 
</p><p>Then Crockston, who was standing on the poop, cried, 
"That's one passed.  A few minutes more, and we shall have 
done with the Rebs." 
<pb n="538"/>  
</p><p>"Then do you think we have nothing more to fear from 
Fort Sumter?" asked James. 
</p><p>"Nothing at all, but everything from Fort Moultrie, at 
the end of Sullivan Island; but they will only get a chance 
at us for half a minute, and then they must choose their 
time well, and shoot straight if they want to reach us.  We 
are getting near." 
</p><p>"Right; the position of Fort Moultrie will allow us to 
go straight for the principal channel.  Fire away then, fire 
away!" 
</p><p>At the same moment, and as if in obedience to James 
Playfair, the fort was illuminated by a triple line of lightning. 
A frightful crash was heard; then a crackling sound 
on board the steamer. 
</p><p>"Touched this time!" exclaimed Crockston. 
</p><p>"Mr.  Mathew!" cried the Captain to his second, who was 
stationed at the bows, "what has been damaged?" 
</p><p>"The bowsprit broken." 
</p><p>"Any wounded?" 
</p><p>"No, Captain." 
</p><p>"Well, then, the masts may go to Jericho.  Straight into 
the pass! Straight! and steer towards the island." 
</p><p>"We have passed the Rebs!" cried Crockston; "and, if 
we must have balls in our hull, I would much rather have 
the Northerners; they are more easily digested." 
</p><p>In fact, the <hi rend="italic">Dolphin</hi> could not yet consider herself out of 
danger; for, if Morris Island was not fortified with the 
formidable pieces of artillery which were placed there a few 
months later, nevertheless its guns and mortars could easily 
have sunk a ship like the <hi rend="italic">Dolphin</hi>. 
</p><p>The alarm had been given to the Federals on the island, 
and to the blockading squadron, by the firing from Forts 
Sumter and Moultrie.  The besiegers could not make out 
the reason of this night attack; it did not seem to be directed 
against them.  However, they were obliged to consider 
it so, and were ready to reply. 
</p><p>It occupied James Playfair's thoughts whilst making towards 
the passes of Morris Island; and he had reason to 
<pb n="539"/>  
fear, for in a quarter of an hour's time lights gleamed 
rapidly through the darkness.  A shower of small shell fell 
round the steamer, scattering the water over her bulwarks; 
some of them even struck the deck of the <hi rend="italic">Dolphin</hi>, but not 
on their points, which saved the ship from certain ruin.  In 
fact, these shell, as it was afterwards discovered, could break 
into a hundred fragments, and each cover a superficial area 
of a hundred and twenty square feet with Greek fire, which 
would burn for twenty minutes, and nothing could extinguish 
it.  One of these shell alone could set a ship on fire. 
Fortunately for the <hi rend="italic">Dolphin</hi>, they were a new invention, and 
as yet far from perfect.  Once thrown into the air, a false 
rotary movement kept them inclined, and, when falling, instead 
of striking on their points, where is the percussion 
apparatus, they fell flat.  This defect in construction alone 
saved the <hi rend="italic">Dolphin</hi>.  The falling of these shells did her little 
harm, and under the pressure of her over-heated boilers she 
continued to advance into the pass. 
</p><p>At this moment, and in spite of his orders, Mr. Halliburtt 
and his daughter went to James Playfair on the poop; the 
latter urged them to return to their cabins, but Jenny declared 
that she would remain by the Captain.  As for Mr. 
Halliburtt, who had just learnt all the noble conduct of his 
deliverer, he pressed his hand without being able to utter a 
word. 
</p><p>The <hi rend="italic">Dolphin</hi> was speeding rapidly towards the open sea. 
There were only three miles more before she would be in 
the waters of the Atlantic; if the pass was free at its entrance, 
she was saved.  James Playfair was wonderfully well 
acquainted with all the secrets of Charleston Bay, and he 
guided his ship through the darkness with an unerring 
hand.  He was beginning to think his daring enterprise successful, 
when a sailor on the forecastle cried: 
</p><p>"A ship!" 
</p><p>"A ship?" cried James. 
</p><p>"Yes, on the larboard side." 
</p><p>The fog had cleared off, and a large frigate was seen 
making towards the pass, in order to obstruct the passage 
<pb n="540"/>  
of the <hi rend="italic">Dolphin</hi>.  It was necessary, cost what it might, to 
distance her, and urge the steam-engine to an increase of 
speed, or all was lost. 
</p><p>"Port the helm at once!" cried the Captain. 
</p><p>Then he sprang on to the bridge above the engine.  By 
his orders one of the screws was stopped, and under the action 
of the other the <hi rend="italic">Dolphin</hi>, veering with an extraordinary 
rapidity, avoided running foul of the frigate, and advanced 
like her to the entrance of the pass.  It was now a question of 
speed. 
</p><p>James Playfair understood that in this lay his own safety, 
Miss Jenny's, her father's, and that of all his crew. 
</p><p>The frigate was considerably in advance of the <hi rend="italic">Dolphin</hi>. 
It was evident from the volumes of black smoke issuing from 
her chimneys that she was getting up her steam.  James 
Playfair was not the man to be left in the background. 
</p><p>"How are the engines?" cried he to the engineer. 
</p><p>"At the maximum speed," replied the latter; "the steam 
is escaping by all the valves." 
</p><p>"Fasten them down," ordered the Captain. 
</p><p>And his orders were executed at the risk of blowing up 
the ship. 
</p><p>The <hi rend="italic">Dolphin</hi> again increased her speed; the pistons 
worked with frightful rapidity; the metal plates on which 
the engine was placed trembled under the terrific force of 
their blows.  It was a sight to make the boldest shudder. 
</p><p>"More pressure!" cried James Playfair; "put on more 
pressure!" 
</p><p>"Impossible!" replied the engineer.  "The valves are 
tightly closed; our furnaces are full up to the mouths." 
</p><p>"What difference! Fill them with cotton soaked in spirits; 
we must pass that frigate at any price." 
</p><p>At these words the most daring of the sailors looked at 
each other, but did not hesitate.  Some bales of cotton were 
thrown into the engine-room, a barrel of spirits broached 
over them, and this expensive fuel placed, not without 
danger, in the red-hot furnaces.  The stokers could no longer 
hear each other speak for the roaring of the flames.  Soon 
<pb n="541"/>  
the metal plates of the furnaces became red-hot; the pistons 
worked like the pistons of a locomotive; the steamgauge 
showed a frightful tension; the steamer flew over the water; 
her boards creaked, and her chimneys threw out volumes of 
smoke mingled with flames.  She was going at a headlong 
speed, but, nevertheless, she was gaining on the frigate &mdash; 
passed her, distanced her, and in ten minutes was out of the 
channel. 
</p><p>"Saved!" cried the Captain. 
</p><p>"Saved!" echoed the crew, clapping their hands. 
</p><p>Already the Charleston beacon was disappearing in the 
south-west; the sound of firing from the batteries grew 
fainter, and it might with reason be thought that the danger 
was all past, when a shell from a gun-boat cruising at large 
was hurled whizzing through the air.  It was easy to trace 
its course, thanks to the line of fire which followed it. 
</p><p>Then was a moment of anxiety impossible to describe; 
every one was silent, and each watched fearfully the arch 
described by the projectile.  Nothing could be done to escape 
it, and in a few seconds it fell with a frightful noise on the 
fore-deck of the <hi rend="italic">Dolphin</hi>. 
</p><p>The terrified sailors crowded to the stern, and no one 
dared move a step, whilst the shell was burning with a brisk 
crackle. 
</p><p>But one brave man alone among them ran up to the 
formidable weapon of destruction.  It was Crockston; he took 
the shell in his strong arms, whilst showers of sparks were 
falling from it; then, with a superhuman effort, he threw it 
overboard. 
</p><p>Hardly had the shell reached the surface of the water 
when it burst with a frightful report. 
</p><p>"Hurrah! hurrah!" cried the whole crew of the <hi rend="italic">Dolphin</hi> 
unanimously, whilst Crockston rubbed his hands. 
</p><p>Some time later the steamer sped rapidly through the 
waters of the Atlantic; the American coast disappeared in 
the darkness, and the distant lights which shot across the 
horizon indicated that the attack was general between the 
batteries of Morris Island and the forts of Charleston 
Harbour. 
<pb n="542"/>  
</p></div1><div1 type="chapter" n="10" id="d14"> 
<head>ST. MUNGO</head> 
<p>THE next day at sunrise the American coast had disappeared; 
not a ship was visible on the horizon, and the 
<hi rend="italic">Dolphin</hi>, moderating the frightful rapidity of her speed, 
made quietly towards the Bermudas. 
</p><p>It is useless to recount the passage across the Atlantic, 
which was marked by no accidents, and ten days after the 
departure from Queenstown the French coast was hailed. 
</p><p>What passed between the Captain and the young girl 
may be imagined, even by the least observant individuals. 
How could Mr. Halliburtt acknowledge the devotion and 
courage of his deliverer, if it was not by making him the 
happiest of men? James Playfair did not wait for English 
seas to declare to the father and daughter the sentiments 
which overflowed his heart, and, if Crockston is to be believed, 
Miss Jenny received his confession with a happiness 
she did not try to conceal. 
</p><p>Thus it happened that on the 14th of February, 18 &mdash; , 
a numerous crowd was collected in the dim aisles of St. 
Mungo, the old cathedral of Glasgow.  There were seamen, 
merchants, manufacturers, magistrates, and some of every 
denomination gathered here.  There was Miss Jenny in bridal 
array and beside her the worthy Crockston, resplendent in 
apple-green clothes, with gold buttons, whilst Uncle Vincent 
stood proudly by his nephew. 
</p><p>In short, they were celebrating the marriage of James 
Playfair, of the firm of Vincent Playfair &amp; Co., of Glasgow, 
with Miss Jenny Halliburtt, of Boston. 
</p><p>The ceremony was accomplished amidst great pomp. 
Everyone knew the history of the <hi rend="italic">Dolphin</hi>, and everyone 
thought the young Captain well recompensed for his devotion. 
He alone said that his reward was greater than he 
deserved. 
</p><p>In the evening there was a grand ball and banquet at 
Uncle Vincent's house, with a large distribution of shillings 
to the crowd collected in Gordon Street.  Crockston did 
<pb n="543"/>  
ample justice to this memorable feast, while keeping himself 
perfectly within bounds. 
</p><p>Everyone was happy at this wedding; some at their own 
happiness, and others at the happiness around them, which 
is not always the case at ceremonies of this kind. 
</p><p>Late in the evening, when the guests had retired, James 
Playfair took his uncle's hand. 
</p><p>"Well, Uncle Vincent," said he to him. 
</p><p>"Well, Nephew James?" 
</p><p>"Are you pleased with the charming cargo I brought you 
on board the <hi rend="italic">Dolphin</hi>?" continued Captain Playfair, showing 
him his brave young wife. 
</p><p>"I am quite satisfied," replied the worthy merchant; "I 
have sold my cotton at three hundred and seventy-five per 
cent. profit." 
</p> 
 
</div1> 
</body> 
</text> 
</TEI.2> 
