<?xml version="1.0"?>

<?dlps id="WalChro"?>
<?dlps page-images="none" figure-images="no"?>
<?dlps transcription="other"?>

<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/tei-p4/tei2.dtd" [
<!ENTITY % POSTKB "INCLUDE">
<!ENTITY % TEI.extensions.ent SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.ent">
<!ENTITY % TEI.extensions.dtd SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.dtd">
<!ENTITY % ISOnum SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/charent/iso-num.ent"> %ISOnum;
<!ENTITY % ISOpub SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/charent/iso-pub.ent"> %ISOpub;
]> 
 
<TEI.2 id="WalChro"> 
<teiHeader type="migrated" creator="Etext">
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title type="main">From the United States chronicle, Thursday, February 19, 1784.</title>
<title type="sort">from the united states chronicle, thursday february 19 1784</title>
<author>Wallace, George</author>
<respStmt>
<resp>Creation of machine-readable version:</resp> 
<name>Readex &mdash; a division of NewsBank Inc.</name>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt> 
<extent>ca. <num type="kilobytes">10</num> kilobytes</extent> 
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>University of Virginia Library</publisher>
<pubPlace>Charlottesville, Virginia</pubPlace> 
<date value="1995">1995</date> 
<idno type="ETC">WalChro</idno>
<availability status="public">
<p n="copyright">Copyright &copy; 1995 by the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia</p>
<p n="access">Publicly accessible</p>
</availability>
<idno type="uva-pid">uva-lib:476450</idno>
</publicationStmt>
<seriesStmt>
<title>University of Virginia Library, Text collection</title>
<idno type="uva-set">UVA-LIB-Text</idno>
</seriesStmt> 
<seriesStmt>
<p>Documentary Sources Database.  American Multiculturalism 
series.  Unit one.  Documenting the African American Experience.</p>
</seriesStmt> 
<sourceDesc>
<biblFull>
<titleStmt>
<title type="main">From the United States chronicle, Thursday, 
February 19, 1784. In this paper last week a clear confutation of the 
original claim to the right of slavery was given, by ... Judge 
Blackstone,&mdash;the subject is now concluded with the sentiments of that 
ingenious lawyer and excellent writer George Wallis [i.e., Wallace] as 
published in his "System of the laws of Scotland" ...  Stating that slavery 
is neither legally nor morally justifiable, and recommending the 
liberation of Negro slaves in America.</title>
<title type="sort">from the united states chronicle, thursday february 19 1784 in this paper last week a clear confutation of the original claim to the right of slavery was given by judge blackstone &mdash;the subject is now concluded with the sentiments of that ingenious lawyer and excellent writer george wallis i e wallace as published in his system of the laws of scotland stating that slavery is neither legally nor morally justifiable and recommending the liberation of negro slaves in america</title>
<author>Wallace, George, 1727-1805.</author>
</titleStmt> 
<extent>1 sheet ([1] p.)</extent> 
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>Printed by Bennett Wheeler</publisher> 
<pubPlace>Providence</pubPlace> 
<date value="1784">1784</date>
</publicationStmt> 
<seriesStmt>
<p>Early American Imprints, 1st series, no. 44623 (filmed)</p>
</seriesStmt> 
<notesStmt>
<note>
<p>Print text in two columns. No illustrations in print text.</p>
</note>
</notesStmt>
</biblFull>
</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc> 
<encodingDesc>
<projectDesc>
<p>Prepared by TextBase in consultation with David Seaman, 
University of Virginia Library Electronic Text Center</p>
</projectDesc> 
<editorialDecl>
<p>milestone tag records a pagination number that runs consecutively 
for the whole project.</p>
</editorialDecl>
</encodingDesc> 
<profileDesc>
<creation>
<date value="1784">1784</date>
</creation> 
<langUsage>
<language id="eng" usage="main">English</language>
</langUsage> 
<textClass>
<keywords>
<term type="references">Bristol B5996.</term> 
<term type="references">Shipton &amp; Mooney 44623.</term> 
<term type="references">Alden, J.E.  Rhode Island, 1000.</term> 
<term type="subjects">Slavery.</term> 
<term type="subjects">Slavery&mdash;United States&mdash;Controversial literature&mdash;1784.</term> 
<term type="subjects">Afro-Americans&mdash;Legal status, laws, etc.</term> 
 <term type="genres">Broadsides.</term> 
 <term type="additional">Wallace, George, 1727-1805. System of the principles of the 
laws of Scotland ...</term> 
 <term type="additional">United States chronicle (Providence, R.I.). 1784 Feb. 
19.</term> 
 <term type="printer">Wheeler, Bennett, 1756-1806, printer.</term> 
<term type="pubplace">United States&mdash;Rhode Island&mdash;Providence.</term> 
<term type="record">w001347</term> 
<term>African American</term>
</keywords>
</textClass>
</profileDesc> 
<revisionDesc>
<change>
<date value="2005-07">July 2005</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>Corrector</resp>
<name>Margaret Konkol</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Converted SGML to XML and fixed tagging.</item>
</change>
<change>
<date value="2007-09">September 2007</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>Migration</resp>
<name>Ethan Gruber, University of Virginia Library</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Converted XML markup from TEI Lite to uva-dl-tei (TEI P4 with local customizations).</item>
</change>
<change>
<date value="2008-01">January 2008</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>Migration</resp>
<name>Greg Murray, University of Virginia Library</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Programmatically updated TEI header markup (but not header content) for minimal compliance with current QA requirements.</item>
</change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader> 
<text id="d1"> 
 
<body id="d2"> 
<div1 type="section" id="d3">
<head>From the United States Chronicle,<lb/> 
<date value="1784-02-19">Thursday, February 19, 1784.</date></head> 


<milestone unit="seriespage" n="000087"/>  
<p> 
<hi rend="bold">I</hi>N this Page last Week a clear Consutation of 
the original Claim to the Right of Slavery was given, by that Ornament 
of his Profession Judge BLACKSTONE,&mdash;the Subject is now 
concluded with the Sentiments of that ingenious Lawyer and excellent 
Writer GEORGE WALLIS as published in his &laquo;
<hi rend="italic">System of the Laws of Sreeland:</hi>&raquo; &mdash; 
Speaking of the Negroes that are purchased from their Princes, who 
pretend to have a Right to dispose of them, and that they are like other 
Commodities, transported by the Merchants, who have bought them, into 
America, in Order to be exposed to Sale, he says:&mdash;&laquo;If 
this Trade admits of a rational or a moral Justification, every Crime, 
even the most atrocious, may be justified. Government was instituted for 
the Good of Mankind; Kings, Princes, Governors, are not Proprietors of 
those who are subject to their Authority; they have not a Right to make 
them miserable. On the contrary, their Authority is rested in them, that 
they may, by the just, Exercise of it, promote the Happiness of their 
People. Of course they have not a Right to dispose of their Liberty, and 
to sell them for Slaves. 
</p><p> 
Besides, no Man has a Right to acquire or to purchase them, Men, and 
their Liberty, are not <hi rend="italic">in commerce</hi>; they are not 
either saleable or purchaseable. One, therefore, has no body but himself 
to blame, in Case, he shall find himself deprived of a Man, whom he 
thought he had, by buying for a Price, made his own; for he dealt in a 
Trade which was illicit, and was prohibited by the most obvious Dictates 
of Humanity. For these Reasons every one of those unfortunate Men, 
who are pretended to be Slaves, has a Right to be declared to be Free, 
for he never lost his Liberty; he could not lose it; his Prince had no 
Power to dispose of him. Of course the Sale was <hi rend="italic">Ipse 
Jure</hi> Void. This Right he carries about with him, and is entitled 
every where to get it declared. As soon, therefore, as he comes into a 
Country in which the Judges are not forgetful of their own Humanity, it 
is their Duty to remember that he is a Man; and to declare him to be 
Free. 
</p><p> 
&laquo;I know it has been said, that Questions concerning the State of 
Persons ought to be determined by the Law of the Country to which they 
belong; and that, therefore, one who would be declared to be a Slave in 
America, ought, in Case he should be imported into Britain, to be 
adjudged according to the Law of America to be a Slave; a Doctrine than 
which nothing can be more barbarous. Ought the Judges of any Country, 
out of Respect to the Law of another, to show no Respect to their Kind, 
and to Humanity? Out of respect to a Law, which is in no Sort 
obligatory upon them, ought they to disregard the Law of Nature which 
is obligatory on all Men, at all Times, and in all Places? Are any Laws 
to binding as the eternal Laws of Justice? Is it doubtful, whether a Judge 
ought to pay greater Regard to them than to those arbitrary and inhuman 
L'aws which prevail in a distant Land? Aye, but our Colonies would be 
ruined if Slavery was abolished. Be it so, would it not from hence 
follow, that the Bulk of Mankind ought to be abused, that our Pockets 
may be filled with Money, or our Mouths with Delicacies? The Purses of 
Highwaymen would be empty in Case Robberies were totally abolished; 
but have Men a Right to acquire Money by going out to the Highway? 
Have Men a Right to acquire it by rendering their Fellow-creatures 
miserable? Is it lawful to abuse Mankind that the Avarice, the Vanity, or 
the Passions of a few may be gratified? No, there is  such a Thing as 
Justice, to which the most sacred Regard is due as it ought to be 
inviolably observed. Have not these unhappy Men a better Right to their 
Liberty, and to their Happiness than our American Merchants have to the 
Profits which they make by their Kind? Let, therefore, our Colonies be 
ruined, but let us not render so many Men miserable. Would not any of 
us, who should be inatched by Pirates from his native Land, think 
himself cruelly abused, and all Times entitled to be Free. Have not these 
unfortunate Africans, who meet with the same cruel fate, the same 
Right? Are not they Men as well as we, and have they not the same 
Sensibility? Let us not, therefore; defend or support a Usage which is 
contrary to all the Laws of Humanity. &laquo;But it is false, that either 
we or our Colonies would be ruined by the Abolition of Slavery. It 
might occasion a Stagnation of Business for a short Time. Every great 
Alteration produces that Effect; because Mankind cannot, on a sudden, 
find Ways of disposing of themselves and their affairs ; But it would 
produce many happy Effects. It is the Slavery which is permitted in 
America, that has  hindered it from becoming so soon populous as it 
would otherwise have done. Let the Negroes Free, and in a few 
Generations this vast and fertile Continent would be crowded with 
Inhabitants; Learning, Arts, and every Thing would flourish amongst 
them; instead of being inhabited by wild Beasts and by Savages, it would 
be peopled by Philosophers, and by Men.&raquo; 
</p> 
<trailer>PROVIDENCE: Printed by BENNETT WHEELER.</trailer> 

</div1> 
</body> 
</text> 
</TEI.2> 
