<?xml version="1.0"?>

<?dlps id="WasAwak"?>
<?dlps page-images="none" figure-images="no"?>
<?dlps transcription="other"?>

<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/tei-p4/tei2.dtd" [
<!ENTITY % POSTKB "INCLUDE">
<!ENTITY % TEI.extensions.ent SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.ent">
<!ENTITY % TEI.extensions.dtd SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.dtd">
<!ENTITY % ISOnum SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/charent/iso-num.ent"> %ISOnum;
<!ENTITY % ISOpub SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/charent/iso-pub.ent"> %ISOpub;
]> 
<TEI.2 id="WasAwak"> 
<teiHeader type="migrated" creator="Etext">
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title type="main">The Awakening of the Negro</title>
<title type="sort">awakening of the negro</title>
<author>Washington, Booker T.</author>
<respStmt>
<resp>Creation of machine-readable version:</resp> 
<name>Judy Boss</name> 
<resp>Conversion to TEI.2-conformant markup:</resp> 
<name>University of Virginia Library Electronic Text Center.</name>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt> 
<extent>ca. <num type="kilobytes">28</num> kilobytes</extent> 
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>University of Virginia Library</publisher>
<pubPlace>Charlottesville, Virginia</pubPlace> 
<idno type="ETC">WasAwak</idno> 
<date value="1994">1994</date>
<availability status="public">
<p n="copyright">Copyright &copy; 1994 by the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia</p>
<p n="access">Publicly accessible</p>
</availability>
<idno type="uva-pid">uva-lib:476458</idno>
</publicationStmt>
<seriesStmt>
<title>University of Virginia Library, Text collection</title>
<idno type="uva-set">UVA-LIB-Text</idno>
</seriesStmt> 
<sourceDesc>
<biblFull>
<titleStmt>
<title type="main">The Awakening of the Negro</title>
<title level="j">Atlantic Monthly</title>
<title type="sort">awakening of the negro</title>
<author>Booker T. Washington</author>
</titleStmt> 
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>Atlantic Monthly</publisher> 
<pubPlace>New York</pubPlace> 
<date value="1896">1896</date>
</publicationStmt> 
<seriesStmt>
<p>Volume 78, pp 322-32</p>
</seriesStmt> 
</biblFull>
</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc> 
<encodingDesc>
<projectDesc>
<p>Prepared for the University of Virginia Library Electronic Text Center.</p>
</projectDesc> 
<editorialDecl>
<p>Spell-check and verification made against printed text</p> 
<p>All unambiguous end-of-line hyphens have been removed, and the 
trailing part of a word has been joined to the preceding line.</p> 
<p id="ETC">Keywords in the header are a local Electronic Text Center scheme to aid in establishing analytical groupings.</p>
</editorialDecl> 
<refsDecl>
<p>ID elements are given for each page element and are composed of the 
text's unique cryptogram and the given page number, as in AusEmma1 for page one of 
Jane Austen's Emma.</p>
</refsDecl> 
</encodingDesc> 
<profileDesc>
<creation>
<date value="1896">1896</date>
</creation> 
<langUsage>
<language id="eng" usage="main">English</language>
</langUsage> 
<textClass>
<keywords>
<term>CORD</term> 
<term>democracy</term>
</keywords> 
<keywords>
<term>non-fiction;  prose</term> 
<term>African-American</term>
</keywords> 
</textClass>
</profileDesc> 
<revisionDesc>
<change>
<date value="1994-04">April 1994</date> 
<respStmt>
<resp>corrector</resp> 
<name>Timothy Jarrett, University of Virginia Library Electronic Text Center.</name>
</respStmt> 
<item>minimal TEI markup</item>
</change> 
<change>
<date value="2005-07">July 2005</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>Corrector</resp>
<name>Margaret Konkol</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Converted SGML to XML and fixed tagging.</item>
</change>
<change>
<date value="2007-09">September 2007</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>Migration</resp>
<name>Ethan Gruber, University of Virginia Library</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Converted XML markup from TEI Lite to uva-dl-tei (TEI P4 with local customizations).</item>
</change>
<change>
<date value="2008-01">January 2008</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>Migration</resp>
<name>Greg Murray, University of Virginia Library</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Programmatically updated TEI header markup (but not header content) for minimal compliance with current QA requirements.</item>
</change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader> 
 
<text id="d1"> 
 
<body id="d2"> 

<div1 type="essay" id="d3">
 <pb n="322"/> 
<p>WHEN a mere boy, I saw a young colored man, who had spent 
several years in school, sitting in a common cabin in the South, 
studying a French grammar.  I noted the poverty, the untidiness, the 
want of system and thrift, that existed about the cabin, 
notwithstanding his knowledge of French and other academic 
subjects.  Another time, when riding on the outer edges of a town in 
the South, I heard the sound of a piano coming from a cabin of the 
same kind.  Contriving some excuse, I entered, and began a 
conversation with the young colored woman who was playing, and 
who had recently returned from a boarding-school, where she had 
been studying instrumental music among other things.  Despite the 
fact that her parents were living in a rented cabin, eating poorly 
cooked food, surrounded with poverty, and having almost none of the 
conveniences of life, she had persuaded them to rent a piano for four 
or five dollars per month.  Many such instances as these, in 
connection with my own struggles, impressed upon me the importance 
of making a study of our needs as a race, and applying the remedy 
accordingly.</p> 
<p>Some one may be tempted to ask, Has not the negro boy or girl 
as good a right to study a French grammar and instrumental music as 
the white youth?  I answer, Yes, but in the present condition of the 
negro race in this country there is need of something more.  Perhaps 
I may be forgiven for the seeming egotism if I mention the expansion 
of my own life partly as an example of what I mean.  My earliest 
recollection is of a small one-room log hut on a large slave plantation 
in Virginia.  After the close of the war, while working in the 
coal-mines of West Virginia for the support of my mother, I heart in 
some accidental way of the Hampton Institute.  When I learned that 
it was an institution where a black boy could study, could have a 
chance to work for his board, and at the same time be taught how to 
work and to realize the dignity of labor, I resolved to go there. 
Bidding my mother good-by, I started out one morning to find my 
way to Hampton, though I was almost penniless and had no definite 
idea where Hampton was.  By walking, begging rides, and paying for 
a portion of the journey on the steam-cars, I finally succeeded in 
reaching the city of Richmond, Virginia.  I was without money or 
friends.  I slept under a sidewalk, and by working on a vessel next day 
I earned money to continue my way to the institute, where I arrived 
with a surplus of fifty cents.  At Hampton I found the opportunity &mdash; 
in the way of buildings, teachers, and industries provided by the 
generous &mdash; to get training in the class-room and by practical touch 
with industrial life, to learn thrift, economy, and push.  I was 
surrounded by an atmosphere of business, Christian influence, and a 
spirit of self-help that seemed to have awakened every faculty in me, 
and caused me for the first time to realize what it meant to be a man 
instead of a piece of property.</p> 
<p>While there I resolved that when I had finished the course of 
training I would go into the far South, into the Black Belt of the 
South, and give my life to providing the same kind of opportunity for 
self-reliance and self-awakening that I had found provided for me at 
Hampton.  My work began at Tuskegee, Alabama, in 1881, in a small 
shanty and church, with one teacher and thirty students, without a 
dollar's worth of property.  The spirit of work and of industrial thrift, 
with aid from the State and generosity from the North, has enabled 
us to develop an institution of eight 
 
<pb n="323"/>  hundred students gathered from nineteen States, with 
seventy-nine instructors, fourteen hundred acres of land, and thirty 
buildings, including large and small; in all, property valued at 
$280,000.  Twenty-five industries have been organized, and the whole 
work is carried on at an annual cost of about $80,000 in cash; two 
fifths of the annual expense so far has gone into permanent 
plant.</p> 
<p>What is the object of all this outlay?  First, it must be borne in 
mind that we have in the South a peculiar and unprecedented state of 
things.  It is of the utmost importance that our energy be given to 
meeting conditions that exist right about us rather than conditions 
that existed centuries ago or that exist in countries a thousand miles 
away.  What are the cardinal needs among the seven millions of 
colored people in the South, most of whom are to be found on the 
plantations?  Roughly, these needs may be stated as food, clothing, 
shelter, education, proper habits, and a settlement of race relations. 
The seven millions of colored people of the South cannot be reached 
directly by any missionary agency, but they can be reached by sending 
out among them strong selected young men and women, with the 
proper training of head, hand, and heart, who will live among these 
masses and show them how to lift themselves up.</p> 
<p>The problem that the Tuskegee Institute keeps before itself 
constantly is how to prepare these leaders.  From the outset, in 
connection with religious and academic training, it has emphasized 
industrial or hand training as a means of finding the way out of 
present conditions.  First, we have found the industrial teaching useful 
in giving the student a chance to work out a portion of his expenses 
while in school.  Second, the school furnishes labor that has an 
economic value, and at the same time gives the student a chance to 
acquire knowledge and skill while performing the labor.  Most of all, 
we find the industrial system valuable in teaching economy, thrift, and 
the dignity of labor, and in giving moral backbone to students.  The 
fact that a student goes out into the world conscious of his power to 
build a house or a wagon, or to make a harness, gives him a certain 
confidence and moral independence that he would not possess 
without such training.</p> 
<p>A more detailed example of our methods at Tuskegee may be of 
interest.  For example, we cultivate by student labor six hundred and 
fifty acres of land.  The object is not only to cultivate the land in a 
way to make it pay our boarding department, but at the same time to 
teach the students, in addition to the practical work, something of the 
chemistry of the soil, the best methods of drainage, dairying, the 
cultivation of fruit, the care of livestock and tools, and scores of other 
lessons needed by a people whose main dependence is on agriculture. 
Notwithstanding that eighty-five per cent of the colored people in the 
South live by agriculture in some form, aside from what has been 
done by Hampton, Tuskegee, and one or two other institutions 
practically nothing has been attempted in the direction of teaching 
them about the very industry from which the masses of our people 
must get their subsistence.  Friends have recently provided means for 
the erection of a large new chapel at Tuskegee.  Our students have 
made the bricks for this chapel.  A large part of the timber is sawed 
by students at our own sawmill, the plans are drawn by our teacher of 
architecture and mechanical drawing, and students do the brick-masonry, plastering, painting, carpentry work, tinning, slating, and 
make most of the furniture.  Practically, the whole chapel will be built 
and furnished by student labor; in the end the school will have the 
building for permanent use, and the students will have a knowledge 
of the trades employed in its construction.  In this way all but three of 
the thirty buildings on 
 
<pb n="324"/>  the grounds have been erected.  While the young 
men do the kinds of work I have mentioned, the young women to a 
large extent make, mend, and launder the clothing of the young men, 
and thus are taught important industries.</p> 
<p>One of the objections sometimes urged against industrial 
education for the negro is that it aims merely to teach him to work 
on the same plan that he was made to follow when in slavery.  This is 
far from being the object at Tuskegee.  At the head of each of the 
twenty-five industrial departments we have an intelligent and 
competent instructor, just as we have in our history classes, so that 
the student is taught not only practical brick-masonry, for example, 
but also the underlying principles of that industry, the mathematics 
and the mechanical and architectural drawing.  Or he is taught how 
to become master of the forces of nature so that, instead of 
cultivating corn in the old way, he can use a corn cultivator, that lays 
off the furrows, drops the corn into them, and covers it, and in this 
way he can do more work than three men by the old process of 
corn-planting; at the same time much of the toil is eliminated and 
labor is dignified.  In a word, the constant aim is to show the student 
how to put brains into every process of labor; how to bring his 
knowledge of mathematics and the sciences into farming, carpentry, 
forging, foundry work; how to dispense as soon as possible with the 
old form of ante-bellum labor.  In the erection of the chapel just 
referred to, instead of letting the money which was given us go into 
outside hands, we make it accomplish three objects: first, it provides 
the chapel; second, it gives the students a chance to get a practical 
knowledge of the trades connected with building; and third, it enables 
them to earn something toward the payment of board while receiving 
academic and industrial training.</p> 
<p>Having been fortified at Tuskegee by education of mind, skill of 
hand, Christian character, ideas of thrift, economy, and push, and a 
spirit of independence, the student is sent out to become a centre of 
influence and light in showing the masses of our people in the Black 
Belt of the South how to lift themselves up.  How can this be done? 
I give but one or two examples.  Ten years ago a young colored man 
came to the institute from one of the large plantation districts; he 
studied in the class-room a portion of the time, and received practical 
and theoretical training on the farm the remainder of the time. 
Having finished his course at Tuskegee, he returned to his plantation 
home, which was in a county where the colored people outnumber 
the whites six to one, as is true of many of the counties in the Black 
Belt of the South.  He found the negroes in debt.  Ever since the war 
they had been mortgaging their crops for the food on which to live 
while the crops were growing.  The majority of them were living from 
hand to mouth on rented land, in small, one-room log cabins, and 
attempting to pay a rate of interest on their advances that ranged 
from fifteen to forty per cent per annum.  The school had been 
taught in a wreck of a log cabin, with no apparatus, and had never 
been in session longer than three months out of twelve.  With as 
many as eight or ten persons of all ages and conditions and of both 
sexes huddled together in one cabin year after year, and with a 
minister whose only aim was to work upon the emotions of the 
people, one can imagine something of the moral and religious state of 
the community.</p> 
<p>But the remedy.  In spite of the evil, the negro got the habit of 
work from slavery.  The rank and file of the race, especially those on 
the Southern plantations, work hard, but the trouble is, what they 
earn gets away from them in high rents, crop mortgages, whiskey, 
snuff, cheap jewelry, and the like.  The young man just referred to 
had been trained at Tuskegee, as most of our graduates 
 
<pb n="325"/>  are, to meet just this condition of things.  He took 
the three months' public school as a nucleus for his work.  Then he 
organized the older people into a club, or conference, that held 
meetings every week.  In these meetings he taught the people in a 
plain, simple manner how to save their money, how to farm in a 
better way, how to sacrifice, &mdash; to live on bread and potatoes, if need 
be, till they could get out of debt, and begin the buying of 
lands.</p> 
<p>Soon a large proportion of the people were in condition to make 
contracts for the buying of homes (land is very cheap in the South), 
and to live without mortgaging their crops.  Not only this: under the 
guidance and leadership of this teacher, the first year that he was 
among them they learned how, by contributions in money and labor, 
to build a neat, comfortable schoolhouse that replaced the wreck of a 
log cabin formerly used.  The following year the weekly meetings 
were continued, and two months were added to the original three 
months of school.  The next year two more months were added.  The 
improvement has gone on, until now these people have every year an 
eight months' school.</p> 
<p>I wish my readers could have the chance that I have had of 
going into this community.  I wish they could look into the faces of 
the people and see them beaming with hope and delight.  I wish they 
could see the two or three room cottages that have taken the place of 
the usual one-room cabin, the well-cultivated farms, and the religious 
life of the people that now means something more than the name. 
The teacher has a good cottage and a well-kept farm that serve as 
models.  In a word, a complete revolution has been wrought in the 
industrial, educational, and religious life of this whole community by 
reason of the fact that they have had this leader, this guide and 
object-lesson, to show them how to take the money and effort that 
had hitherto been scattered to the wind in mortgages and high rents, 
in whiskey and gewgaws, and concentrate them in the direction of 
their own uplifting.  One community on its feet presents an 
object-lesson for the adjoining communities, and soon improvements 
show themselves in other places.</p> 
<p>Another student who received academic and industrial training 
at Tuskegee established himself, three years ago, as a blacksmith and 
wheelwright in a community, and, in addition to the influence of his 
successful business enterprise, he is fast making the same kind of 
changes in the life of the people about him that I have just recounted. 
It would be easy for me to fill many pages describing the influence of 
the Tuskegee graduates in every part of the South.  We keep it 
constantly in the minds of our students and graduates that the 
industrial or material condition of the masses of our people must be 
improved, as well as the intellectual, before there can be any 
permanent change in their moral and religious life.  We find it a 
pretty hard thing to make a good Christian of a hungry man.  No 
matter how much our people "get happy" and "shout" in church, if 
they go home at night from church hungry, they are tempted to find 
something before morning.  This is a principle of human nature, and 
is not confined to the negro.</p> 
<p>The negro has within him immense power for self-uplifting, but 
for years it will be necessary to guide and stimulate him.  The 
recognition of this power led us to organize, five years ago, what is 
now known as the Tuskegee Negro Conference, &mdash; a gathering that 
meets every February, and is composed of about eight hundred 
representative colored men and women from all sections of the Black 
Belt.  They come in ox-carts, mule-carts, buggies, on muleback and 
horseback, on foot, by railroad: some traveling all night in order to be 
present.  The matters considered at the conferences are those that 
the colored people have it 
 
<pb n="326"/>  within their own power to control: such as the evils 
of the mortgage system, the one-room cabin, buying on credit, the 
importance of owning a home and of putting money in the bank, how 
to build schoolhouses and prolong the school term, and how to 
improve their moral and religious condition.</p> 
<p>As a single example of the results, one delegate reported that 
since the conferences were started five years ago eleven people in his 
neighborhood had bought homes, fourteen had got out of debt, and a 
number had stopped mortgaging their crops.  Moreover, a 
schoolhouse had been built by the people themselves, and the school 
term had been extended from three to six months; and with a look of 
triumph he exclaimed, "We is done stopped libin' in de ashes!"</p> 
<p>Besides this Negro Conference for the masses of the people, we 
now have a gathering at the same time known as the Workers' 
Conference, composed of the officers and instructors in the leading 
colored schools of the South.  After listening to the story of the 
conditions and needs from the people themselves, the Workers' 
Conference finds much food for thought and discussion.</p> 
<p>Nothing else so soon brings about right relations between the 
two races in the South as the industrial progress of the negro. 
Friction between the races will pass away in proportion as the black 
man, by reason of his skill, intelligence, and character, can produce 
something that the white man wants or respects in the commercial 
world.  This is another reason why at Tuskegee we push the industrial 
training.  We find that as every year we put into a Southern 
community colored men who can start a brick-yard, a sawmill, a 
tin-shop, or a printing-office, &mdash; men who produce something that 
makes the white man partly dependent upon the negro, instead of all 
the dependence being on the other side, &mdash; a change takes place in 
the relations of the races.</p> 
<p>Let us go on for a few more years knitting our business and 
industrial relations into those of the white man, till a black man gets 
a mortgage on a white man's house that he can foreclose at will.  The 
white man on whose house the mortgage rests will not try to prevent 
that negro from voting when he goes to the polls.  It is through the 
dairy farm, the truck garden, the trades, and commercial life, largely, 
that the negro is to find his way to the enjoyment of all his rights. 
Whether he will or not, a white man respects a negro who owns a 
two-story brick house.</p> 
<p>What is the permanent value of the Tuskegee system of training 
to the South in a broader sense?  In connection with this, it is well to 
bear in mind that slavery taught the white man that labor with the 
hands was something fit for the negro only, and something for the 
white man to come into contact with just as little as possible.  It is 
true that there was a large class of poor white people who labored 
with the hands, but they did it because they were not able to secure 
negroes to work for them; and these poor whites were constantly 
trying to imitate the slave-holding class in escaping labor, and they 
too regarded it as anything but elevating.  The negro in turn looked 
down upon the poor whites with a certain contempt because they had 
to work.  The negro, it is to be borne in mind, worked under constant 
protest, because he felt that his labor was being unjustly required, and 
he spent almost as much effort in planning how to escape work as in 
learning how to work.  Labor with him was a badge of degradation. 
The white man was held up before him as the highest type of 
civilization, but the negro noted that this highest type of civilization 
himself did no labor; hence he argued that the less work he did, the 
more nearly he would be like a white man.  Then, in addition to 
these influences, the slave system discouraged labor-saving machinery. 
To use labor-saving 
 
<pb n="327"/> machinery intelligence was required, and intelligence 
and slavery were not on friendly terms; hence the negro always 
associated labor with toil, drudgery, something to be escaped.  When 
the negro first became free, his idea of education was that it was 
something that would soon put him in the same position as regards 
work that his recent master had occupied.  Out of these conditions 
grew the Southern habit of putting off till to-morrow and the day 
after the duty that should be done promptly to-day.  The leaky house 
was not repaired while the sun shone, for then the rain did not come 
through.  While the rain was falling, no one cared to expose himself 
to stop the leak.  The plough, on the same principle, was left where 
the last furrow was run, to rot and rust in the field during the winter. 
There was no need to repair the wooden chimney that was exposed to 
the fire, because water could be thrown on it when it was on fire. 
There was no need to trouble about the payment of a debt to-day, for 
it could just as well be paid next week or next year.  Besides these 
conditions, the whole South, at the close of the war, was without 
proper food, clothing, and shelter, &mdash; was in need of habits of thrift 
and economy and of something laid up for a rainy day.</p> 
<p>To me it seemed perfectly plain that here was a condition of 
things that could not be met by the ordinary process of education.  At 
Tuskegee we became convinced that the thing to do was to make a 
careful systematic study of the condition and needs of the South, 
especially the Black Belt, and to bend our efforts in the direction of 
meeting these needs, whether we were following a well-beaten track, 
or were hewing out a new path to meet conditions probably without a 
parallel in the world.  After fourteen years of experience and 
observation, what is the result?  Gradually but surely, we find that all 
through the South the disposition to look upon labor as a disgrace is 
on the wane, and the parents who themselves sought to escape work 
are so anxious to give their children training in intelligent labor that 
every institution which gives training in the handicrafts is crowded, 
and many (among them Tuskegee) have to refuse admission to 
hundreds of applicants.  The influence of the Tuskegee system is 
shown again by the fact that almost every little school at the remotest 
cross-roads is anxious to be known as an industrial school, or, as some 
of the colored people call it, an "industrus" school.</p> 
<p>The social lines that were once sharply drawn between those 
who labored with the hand and those who did not are disappearing. 
Those who formerly sought to escape labor, now when they see that 
brains and skill rob labor of the toil and drudgery once associated 
with it, instead of trying to avoid it are willing to pay to be taught 
how to engage in it.  The South is beginning to see labor raised up, 
dignified and beautified, and in this sees its salvation.  In proportion 
as the love of labor grows, the large idle class which has long been 
one of the curses of the South disappears.  As its members become 
absorbed in occupations, they have less time to attend to everybody 
else's business, and more time for their own.</p> 
<p>The South is still an undeveloped and unsettled country, and for 
the next half century and more the greater part of the energy of the 
masses will be needed to develop its material opportunities.  Any 
force that brings the rank and file of the people to a greater love of 
industry is therefore especially valuable.  This result industrial 
education is surely bringing about.  It stimulates production and 
increases trade, &mdash; trade between the races, &mdash; and in this new and 
engrossing relation both forget the past.  The white man respects the 
vote of the colored man who does $10,000 worth of business, and the 
more business the colored man has, the more careful he is how he 
votes.</p> 
<p>Immediately after the war, there was a large class of Southern 
people who 
 
<pb n="328"/>  feared that the opening of the free schools to the 
freedmen and the poor whites &mdash; the education of the head alone &mdash; 
would result merely in increasing the class who sought to escape 
labor, and that the South would soon be overrun by the idle and 
vicious.  But as the results of industrial combined with academic 
training begin to show themselves in hundreds of communities that 
have been lifted up through the medium of the Tuskegee system, 
these former prejudices against education are being removed.  Many 
of those who a few years ago opposed general education are now 
among its warmest advocates.</p> 
<p>This industrial training, emphasizing as it does the idea of 
economic production, is gradually bringing the South to the point 
where it is feeding itself.  Before the war, and long after it, the South 
made what little profit was received from the cotton crop, and sent its 
earnings out of the South to purchase food supplies, &mdash; meat, bread, 
canned vegetables, and the like; but the improved methods of 
agriculture are fast changing this habit.  With the newer methods of 
labor, which teach promptness and system, and emphasize the worth 
of the beautiful, &mdash; the moral value of the well-painted house, and 
the fence with every paling and nail in its place, &mdash; we are bringing to 
bear upon the South an influence that is making it a new country in 
industry, education, and religion. </p> 
 
</div1> 
</body> 
</text> 
</TEI.2> 
 
