<?xml version="1.0"?>

<?dlps id="WasCase"?>
<?dlps page-images="none" figure-images="no"?>
<?dlps transcription="other"?>

<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/tei-p4/tei2.dtd" [
<!ENTITY % POSTKB "INCLUDE">
<!ENTITY % TEI.extensions.ent SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.ent">
<!ENTITY % TEI.extensions.dtd SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.dtd">
<!ENTITY % ISOnum SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/charent/iso-num.ent"> %ISOnum;
<!ENTITY % ISOpub SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/charent/iso-pub.ent"> %ISOpub;
]> 
<TEI.2 id="WasCase"> 
<teiHeader type="migrated" creator="Etext">
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title type="main">The Case of the Negro</title>
<title type="sort">case of the negro</title>
<author>Washington, Booker T.</author>
<respStmt>
<resp>Creation of machine-readable version:</resp> 
<name>Judy Boss, University of Omaha</name> 
<resp>Conversion to TEI.2-conformant markup:</resp> 
<name>University of Virginia Library Electronic Text Center.</name>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt> 
<extent>ca. <num type="kilobytes">44</num> kilobytes</extent> 
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>University of Virginia Library</publisher>
<pubPlace>Charlottesville, Virginia</pubPlace> 
<idno type="ETC">WasCase</idno> 
<date value="1995">1995</date>
<availability status="public">
<p n="copyright">Copyright &copy; 1995 by the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia</p>
<p n="access">Publicly accessible</p>
</availability>
<idno type="uva-pid">uva-lib:476459</idno>
</publicationStmt>
<seriesStmt>
<title>University of Virginia Library, Text collection</title>
<idno type="uva-set">UVA-LIB-Text</idno>
</seriesStmt> 
<sourceDesc>
<biblFull>
<titleStmt>
<title type="main">The Case of the Negro</title>
<title level="j">Atlantic Monthly</title>
<title type="sort">case of the negro</title>
<author>Booker T. Washington</author>
</titleStmt> 
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>Atlantic Monthly</publisher> 
<pubPlace>New York</pubPlace> 
<date value="1899">1899</date>
</publicationStmt> 
<seriesStmt>
<p>Volume 84, 577-587</p>
</seriesStmt> 
</biblFull>
</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc> 
<encodingDesc>
<projectDesc>
<p>Prepared for the University of Virginia Library Electronic Text Center.</p>
</projectDesc> 
<editorialDecl>
<p>Spell-check and verification made against printed text</p> 
<p>All unambiguous end-of-line hyphens have been removed, and the 
trailing part of a word has been joined to the preceding line.</p> 
<p id="ETC">Keywords in the header are a local Electronic Text Center scheme to aid in establishing analytical groupings.</p>
</editorialDecl> 
<refsDecl>
<p>ID elements are given for each page element and are composed of the 
text's unique cryptogram and the given page number, as in AusEmma1 for page one of 
Jane Austen's Emma.</p>
</refsDecl> 
</encodingDesc> 
<profileDesc>
<creation>
<date value="1899">1899</date>
</creation> 
<langUsage>
<language id="eng" usage="main">English</language>
</langUsage> 
<textClass>
<keywords>
<term>CORD</term> 
<term>democracy</term>
</keywords> 
<keywords>
<term>non-fiction; prose</term> 
<term>African-American</term>
</keywords> 
</textClass>
</profileDesc> 
<revisionDesc>
<change>
<date value="1994-06">June 1994</date> 
<respStmt>
<resp>corrector</resp> 
<name>Steve Shoemaker, University of Virginia Library Electronic Text Center.</name>
</respStmt> 
<item>TEI tagging and header added</item>
</change> 
<change>
<date value="2005-07">July 2005</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>Corrector</resp>
<name>Margaret Konkol</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Converted SGML to XML and fixed tagging.</item>
</change>
<change>
<date value="2007-09">September 2007</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>Migration</resp>
<name>Ethan Gruber, University of Virginia Library</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Converted XML markup from TEI Lite to uva-dl-tei (TEI P4 with local customizations).</item>
</change>
<change>
<date value="2008-01">January 2008</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>Migration</resp>
<name>Greg Murray, University of Virginia Library</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Programmatically updated TEI header markup (but not header content) for minimal compliance with current QA requirements.</item>
</change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader> 
 
<text id="d1"> 
<body id="d2"> 

<div1 type="essay" id="d3"> <pb n="577"/> 
<head>Washington, Booker T.  "The Case of the Negro." <lb/> 
<hi rend="italic"> Atlantic Monthly</hi> 84 (1899): 577-587.</head> 
 
<p>ALL attempts to settle the question of the Negro in the South 
by his removal from this country have so far failed, and I think 
that they are likely to fail.  The next census will probably show 
that we have nearly ten million black people in the United States, 
about eight millions of whom are in the Southern states.  In fact, 
we have almost a nation within a nation.  The Negro population in 
the United States lacks but two millions of being as large as the 
whole population of Mexico, and is nearly twice as large as that of 
Canada.  Our black people equal in number the combined populations 
of Switzerland, Greece, Honduras, Nicaragua, Cuba, Uraguay [sic], 
Santo Domingo, Paraguay, and Costa Rica.  When we consider, in 
connection with these facts, that the race has doubled itself since 
its freedom, and is still increasing, it hardly seems possible for 
any one to take seriously any scheme of emigration from America as 
a method of solution.  At most, even if the government were to 
provide the means, but a few hundred thousand could be transported 
each year.  The yearly increase in population would more than 
likely overbalance the number transported.  Even if it did not, the 
time required to get rid of the Negro by this method would perhaps 
be fifty or seventy-five years.</p> 
<p>Some have advised that the Negro leave the South, and take up 
his residence in the Northern states.  I question whether this 
would make him any better off than he is in the South, when all 
things are considered.  It has been my privilege to study the 
condition of our people in nearly every part of America; and I say 
without hesitation that, with some exceptional cases, the Negro is 
at his best in the Southern states.  While he enjoys certain 
privileges in the North that he does not have in the South, when it 
comes to the matter of securing property, enjoying business 
advantages and employment, the South presents a far better 
opportunity than the North.  Few colored men from the South are as 
yet able to stand up against the severe and increasing competition 
that exists in the North, to say nothing of the unfriendly 
influence of labor organizations, which in some way prevents black 
men in the North, as a rule, from securing occupation in the line 
of skilled labor.</p> 
<p>Another point of great danger for the colored man who goes 
North is the matter of morals, owing to the numerous temptations by 
which he finds himself surrounded.  More ways offer in which he can 
spend money than in the South, but fewer avenues of employment for 
earning money are open to him.  The fact that at the North the 
Negro is almost confined to one line of occupation often tends to 
discourage and demoralize the strongest who go from the South, and 
makes them an easy prey for temptation.  A few years ago, I made an 
examination into the condition of a settlement of Negroes who left 
the South and went into Kansas about twenty years since, when there 
was a good deal of excitement in the South concerning 
<pb n="578"/> 
emigration from the West, and found it much below the standard of 
that of similar communities in the South.  The only conclusion 
which any one can reach, from this and like instances, is that the 
Negroes are to remain in the Southern states.  As a race they do 
not want to leave the South, and the Southern white people do not 
want them to leave.  We must therefore find some basis of 
settlement that will be constitutional, just, manly; that will be 
fair to both races in the South and to the whole country.  This 
cannot be done in a day, a year, or any short period of time.  We 
can, however, with the present light, decide upon a reasonably safe 
method of solving the problem, and turn our strength and effort in 
that direction.  In doing this, I would not have the Negro deprived 
of any privilege guaranteed to him by the Constitution of the 
United States.  It is not best for the Negro that he relinquish any 
of his constitutional rights; it is not best for the Southern white 
man that he should, as I shall attempt to show in this article.</p> 
<p>In order that we may concentrate our forces upon a wise 
object, without loss of time or effort, I want to suggest what 
seems to me and many others the wisest policy to be pursued.  I 
have reached these conclusions not only by reason of my own 
observations and experience, but after eighteen years of direct 
contact with leading and influential colored and white men in most 
parts of our country.  But I wish first to mention some elements of 
danger in the present situation, which all who desire the permanent 
welfare of both races in the South should carefully take into 
account.</p> 
<p>First.  There is danger that a certain class of impatient 
extremists among the Negroes in the North, who have little 
knowledge of the actual conditions in the South, may do the entire 
race injury by attempting to advise their brethren in the South to 
resort to armed resistance or the use of the torch, in order to 
secure justice.  All intelligent and well-considered discussion of 
any important question, or condemnation of any wrong, whether in 
the North or the South, from the public platform and through the 
press, is to be commended and encouraged; but ill-considered and 
incendiary utterances from black men in the North will tend to add 
to the burdens of our people in the South rather than to relieve 
them.  We must not fall into the temptation of believing that we 
can raise ourselves by abusing some one else.</p> 
<p>Second.  Another danger in the South which should be guarded 
against is that the whole white South, including the wise, 
conservative, law-abiding element, may find itself represented 
before the bar of public opinion by the mob or lawless element, 
which gives expression to its feelings and tendency in a manner 
that advertises the South throughout the world; while too often 
those who have no sympathy with such disregard of law are either 
silent, or fail to speak in a sufficiently emphatic manner to 
offset in any large degree the unfortunate reputation which the 
lawless have made for many portions of the South.</p> 
<p>Third.  No race or people ever got upon its feet without 
severe and constant struggle, often in the face of the greatest 
discouragement.  While passing through the present trying period of 
its history, there is danger that a large and valuable element of 
the Negro race may become discouraged in the effort to better its 
condition.  Every possible influence should be exerted to prevent 
this.</p> 
<p>Fourth.  There is a possibility that harm may be done to the 
South and to the Negro by exaggerated newspaper articles which are 
written near the scene or in the midst of specially aggravating 
occurrences.  Often these reports are written by newspaper men, who 
give the impression that there is a race conflict throughout the 
South, and that all Southern white people are opposed to the 
Negro's progress; overlooking the fact that though in some 
<pb n="579"/> 
sections there is trouble, in most parts of the South, if matters 
are not yet in all respects as we would have them, there is 
nevertheless a very large measure of peace, good will, and mutual 
helpfulness.  In the same relation, much can be done to retard the 
progress of the Negro by a certain class of Southern white people, 
who in the midst of excitement speak or write in a manner that 
gives the impression that all Negroes are lawless, untrustworthy, 
and shiftless.  For example, a Southern writer said, not long ago, 
in a communication to the New York Independent: "Even in small 
towns the husband cannot venture to leave his wife alone for an 
hour at night.  At no time, in no place, is the white woman safe 
from the insults and assaults of these creatures."  These 
statements, I presume, represented the feelings and the conditions 
that existed, at the time of the writing, in one community or 
county in the South; but thousands of Southern white men and women 
would be ready to testify that this is not the condition throughout 
the South, nor throughout any Southern state.</p> 
<p>Fifth.  Owing to the lack of school opportunities for the 
Negro in the rural districts of the South, there is danger that 
ignorance and idleness may increase to the extent of giving the 
Negro race a reputation for crime, and that immorality may eat its 
way into the fibre of the race so as to retard its progress for 
many years.  In judging the Negro we must not be too harsh.  We 
must remember that it has been only within the last thirty-four 
years that the black father and mother have had the responsibility, 
and consequently the experience, of training their own children. 
That perfection has not been reached in one generation, with the 
obstacles that the parents have been compelled to overcome, is not 
to be wondered at.</p> 
<p>Sixth.  Finally, I would mention my fear that some of the 
white people of the South may be led to feel that the way to settle 
the race problem is to repress the aspirations of the Negro by 
legislation of a kind that confers certain legal or political 
privileges upon an ignorant and poor white man, and withholds the 
same privileges from a black man in a similar condition.  Such 
legislation injures and retards the progress of both races.  It is 
an injustice to the poor white man, because it takes from him 
incentive to secure education and property as prerequisites for 
voting.  He feels that because he is a white man, regardless of his 
possessions, a way will be found for him to vote.  I would label 
all such measures "laws to keep the poor white man in ignorance and 
poverty."</p> 
<p>The Talladega News Reporter, a Democratic newspaper of 
Alabama, recently said: "But it is a weak cry when the white man 
asks odds on intelligence over the Negro.  When nature has already 
so handicapped the African in the race for knowledge, the cry of 
the boasted Anglo-Saxon for still further odds seems babyish.  What 
wonder that the world looks on in surprise, if not disgust?  It 
cannot help but say, If our contention be true that the Negro is an 
inferior race, then the odds ought to be on the other side, if any 
are to be given.  And why not?  No; the thing to do &mdash; the only thing 
that will stand the test of time &mdash; is to do right, exactly right, 
let come what will.  And that right thing, as it seems to us, is to 
place a fair educational qualification before every citizen, &mdash; one 
that is self-testing, and not dependent on the wishes of weak men, 
&mdash;letting all who pass the test stand in the proud ranks of American 
voters, whose votes shall be counted as cast, and whose sovereign 
will shall be maintained as law by all the powers that be.  Nothing 
short of this will do.  Every exemption, on whatsoever ground, is 
an outrage that can only rob some legitimate voter of his rights."</p> 
<p>Such laws have been made, &mdash; in Mississippi, for example, &mdash; with 
the "understanding" clause, hold out a temptation 
<pb n="580"/> 
for the election officer to perjure and degrade himself by too often 
deciding that the ignorant white man does understand the 
Constitution when it is read to him, and that the ignorant black 
man does not.  By such a law, the state not only commits a wrong 
against its black citizens; it injures the morals of its white 
citizens by conferring such a power upon any white man who may 
happen to be a judge of elections.</p> 
<p>Such laws are hurtful, again, because they keep alive in the 
heart of the black man the feeling that the white man means to 
oppress him.  The only safe way out is to set a high standard as a 
test of citizenship, and require blacks and whites alike to come up 
to it.  When this is done, both will have a higher respect for the 
election laws, and for those who make them.  I do not believe that, 
with his centuries of advantage over the Negro in the opportunity 
to acquire property and education as prerequisites for voting, the 
average white man in the South desires that any special law be 
passed to give him further advantage over one who has had but a 
little more than thirty years in which to prepare himself for 
citizenship.  In this relation, another point of danger is that the 
Negro has been made to feel that it is his duty continually to 
oppose the Southern white man in politics, even in matters where no 
principle is involved; and that he is only loyal to his own race 
and acting in a manly way in thus opposing the white man.  Such a 
policy has proved very hurtful to both races.  Where it is a matter 
of principle, where a question of right or wrong is involved, I 
would advise the Negro to stand by principle at all hazards.  A 
Southern white man has no respect for or confidence in a Negro who 
acts merely for policy's sake; but there are many cases, and the 
number is growing, where the Negro has nothing to gain, and much to 
lose, by opposing the Southern white man in matters that relate to 
government.</p> 
<p>Under the foregoing six heads I believe I have stated some of 
the main points which, all high-minded white men and black men, 
North and South, will agree, need our most earnest and thoughtful 
consideration, if we would hasten, and not hinder, the progress of 
our country.</p> 
<p>Now as to the policy that should be pursued.  On this subject 
I claim to possess no superior wisdom or unusual insight.  I may be 
wrong; I may be in some degree right.</p> 
<p>In the future we want to impress upon the Negro, more than we 
have done in the past, the importance of identifying himself more 
closely with the interests of the South; of making himself part of 
the South, and at home in it.  Heretofore, for reasons which were 
natural, and for which no one is especially to blame, the colored 
people have been too much like a foreign nation residing in the 
midst of another nation.  If William Lloyd Garrison, Wendell 
Phillips, or George L. Stearns were alive to-day, I feel sure that 
he would advise the Negroes to identify their interests as closely 
as possible with those of their white neighbors, &mdash; always 
understanding that no question of right and wrong is involved.  In 
no other way, it seems to me, can we get a foundation for peace and 
progress.  He who advises against this policy will advise the Negro 
to do that which no people in history, who have succeeded, have 
done.  The white man, North or South, who advises the Negro against 
it advises him to do that which he himself has not done.  The bed 
rock upon which every individual rests his chances for success in 
life is the friendship, the confidence, the respect, of his next-door 
neighbor in the little community in which he lives.  The 
problem of the Negro in the South turns on whether he can make 
himself of such indispensable service to his neighbor and the 
community that no one can fill his place better in the body 
politic.  There is at present no other safe course for the black 
man to pursue.  If the Negro in the South has a friend in 
<pb n="581"/> 
his white neighbor, and a still larger number of friends in his own 
community, he has a protection and a guarantee of his rights that 
will be more potent and more lasting than any our Federal Congress 
or any outside power can confer.</p> 
<p>The London Times, in a recent editorial discussing affairs in 
the Transvaal, where Englishmen have been denied certain privileges 
by the Boers, says: <q>"England is too sagacious not to prefer a 
gradual reform from within, even should it be less rapid than most 
of us might wish, to the most sweeping redress of grievances 
imposed from without.  Our object is to obtain fair play for the 
Outlanders, but the best way to do it is to enable them to help 
themselves."</q>  This policy, I think, is equally safe when applied to 
conditions in the South.  The foreigner who comes to America 
identifies himself as soon as possible, in business, education, and 
politics, with the community in which he settles.  We have a 
conspicuous example of this in the case of the Jews, who in the 
South, as well as in other parts of our country, have not always 
been justly treated; but the Jews have so woven themselves into the 
business and patriotic interests of the communities in which they 
live, have made themselves so valuable as citizens, that they have 
won a place in the South which they could have obtained in no other 
way.  The Negro in Cuba has practically settled the race question 
there, because he has made himself a part of Cuba in thought and 
action.</p> 
<p>What I have tried to indicate cannot be accomplished by any 
sudden revolution of methods, but it does seem that the tendency 
should be more and more in this direction.  Let me emphasize this 
by a practical example.  The North sends thousands of dollars into 
the South every year for the education of the Negro.  The teachers 
in most of the Southern schools supported by the North are Northern 
men and women of the highest Christian culture and most unselfish 
devotion.  The Negro owes them a debt of gratitude which can never 
be paid.  The various missionary societies in the North have done 
a work which to a large degree has proved the salvation of the 
South, and the results of it will appear more in future generations 
than in this.  We have now reached the point, in the South, where, 
I believe, great good could be accomplished in changing the 
attitude of the white people toward the Negro, and of the Negro 
toward the whites, if a few Southern white teachers, of high 
character, would take an active interest in the work of our higher 
schools.  Can this be done?  Yes.  The medical school connected 
with Shaw University at Raleigh, North Carolina, has from the first 
had as instructors and professors almost exclusively Southern white 
doctors who reside in Raleigh, and they have given the highest 
satisfaction.  This gives the people of Raleigh the feeling that 
the school is theirs, and not something located in, but not a part 
of, the South.  In Augusta, Georgia, the Payne Institute, one of 
the best colleges for our people, is officered and taught almost 
wholly by Southern white men and women.  The Presbyterian 
Theological School at Tuscaloosa, Alabama, has only Southern white 
men as instructors.  Some time ago, at the Calhoun School in 
Alabama, one of the leading white men in the county was given an 
important position; since then the feeling of the white people in 
the county has greatly changed toward the school.</p> 
<p>We must admit the stern fact that at present the Negro, 
through no choice of his own, is living in the midst of another 
race, which is far ahead of him in education, property, and 
experience; and further, that the Negro's present condition makes 
him dependent upon the white people for most of the things 
necessary to sustain life, as well as, in a large measure, for his 
education.  In all history, those who have possessed the property 
<pb n="582"/> 
and intelligence have exercised the greatest control in 
government, regardless of color, race, or geographical location. 
This being the case, how can the black man in the South improve his 
estate?  And does the Southern white man want him to improve it? 
The latter part of this question I shall attempt to answer later in 
this article.</p> 
<p>The Negro in the South has it within his power, if he properly 
utilizes the forces at land, to make of himself such a valuable 
factor in the life of the South that for the most part he need not 
seek privileges, but they will be conferred upon him.  To bring 
this about, the Negro must begin at the bottom and lay a sure 
foundation, and not be lured by any temptation into trying to rise 
on a false footing.  While the Negro is laying this foundation, he 
will need help and sympathy and justice from the law.  Progress by 
any other method will be but temporary and superficial, and the end 
of it will be worse than the beginning.  American slavery was a 
great curse to both races, and I should be the last to apologize 
for it; but in the providence of God I believe that slavery laid 
the foundation for the solution of the problem that is now before 
us in the South.  Under slavery, the Negro was taught every trade, 
every industry, that furnishes the means of earning a living.  Now 
if on this foundation, laid in a rather crude way, it is true, but 
a foundation nevertheless, we can gradually grow and improve, the 
future for us is bright.  Let me be more specific.  Agriculture is 
or has been the basic industry of nearly every race or nation that 
has succeeded.  The Negro got a knowledge of this under slavery: 
hence in a large measure he is in possession of this industry in 
the South to-day.  Taking the whole South, I should say that eighty 
per cent of the Negroes live by agriculture in some form, though it 
is often a very primitive and crude form.  The Negro can buy land 
in the South, as a rule, wherever the white man can buy it, and at 
very low prices.  Now, since the bulk of our people already have a 
foundation in agriculture, are at their best when living in the 
country engaged in agricultural pursuits, plainly, the best thing, 
the logical thing, is to turn the larger part of our strength in a 
direction that will put the Negroes among the most skilled 
agricultural people in the world.  The man who has learned to do 
something better than any one else, has learned to do a common 
thing in an uncommon manner, has power and influence which no 
adverse surroundings can take from him.  It is better to show a man 
how to make a place for himself than to put him in one that some 
one else has made for him.  The Negro who can make himself so 
conspicuous as a successful farmer, a large taxpayer, a wise helper 
of his fellow men, as to be placed in a position of trust and honor 
by natural selection, whether the position be political or not, is 
a hundredfold more secure in that position than one placed there by 
mere outside force or pressure.  I know a Negro, Hon. Isaiah T. 
Montgomery, in Mississippi, who is mayor of a town; it is true that 
the town is composed almost wholly of Negroes.  Mr. Montgomery is 
mayor of this town because his genius, thrift, and foresight have 
created it; and he is held and supported in his office by a charter 
granted by the state of Mississippi, and by the vote and public 
sentiment of the community in which he lives.</p> 
<p>Let us help the Negro by every means possible to acquire such 
an education in farming, dairying, stock-raising, horticulture, 
etc., as will place him near the top in these industries, and the 
race problem will in a large part be settled, or at least stripped 
of many of its most perplexing elements.  This policy would also 
tend to keep the Negro in the country and smaller towns, where he 
succeeds best, and stop the influx into the large cities, where he 
does not succeed so well.  The race, like the individual, 
<pb n="583"/> 
which produces something of superior worth that has a common human 
interest, wins a permanent place, and is bound to be recognized.</p> 
<p>At a county fair in the South, not long ago, I saw a Negro 
awarded the first prize, by a jury of white men, over white 
competitors, for the production of the best specimen of Indian 
corn.  Every white man at the fair seemed to be proud of the 
achievement of the Negro, because it was apparent that he had done 
something that would add to the wealth and comfort of the people of 
both races in that county.  At the Tuskegee Normal and Industrial 
Institute, in Alabama, we have a department devoted to training men 
along the lines of agriculture that I have named; but what we are 
doing is small when compared with what should be done in Tuskegee, 
and at other educational centres.  In a material sense the South is 
still an undeveloped country.  While in some other affairs race 
prejudice is strongly marked, in the matter of business, of 
commercial and industrial development, there are few obstacles in 
the Negro's way.  A Negro who produces or has for sale something 
that the community wants finds customers among white people as well 
as black.  Upon equal security, a Negro can borrow money at the 
bank as readily as a white man can.  A bank in Birmingham, Alabama, 
which has existed ten years, is officered and controlled wholly by 
Negroes.  This bank has white borrowers and white depositors.  A 
graduate of the Tuskegee Institute keeps a well-appointed grocery 
store in Tuskegee, and he tells me that he sells about as many 
goods to one race as to the other.  What I have said of the opening 
that awaits the Negro in the business of agriculture is almost 
equally true of mechanics, manufacturing, and all the domestic 
arts.  The field is before him and right about him.  Will he seize 
upon it?  Will he "cast down his bucket where he is?"  Will his 
friends, North and South, encourage him and prepare him to occupy 
it?  Every city in the South, for example, would give support to a 
first-class architect or housebuilder or contractor of our race. 
The architect or contractor would not only receive support, but 
through his example numbers of young colored men would learn such 
trades as carpentry, brickmasonry, plastering, painting, etc., and 
the race would be put into a position to hold on to many of the 
industries which it is now in danger of losing, because in too many 
cases brain, skill, and dignity are not imparted to the common 
occupations.  Any individual or race that does not fit itself to 
occupy in the best manner the field or service that is right about 
it will sooner or later be asked to move on and let another take 
it.</p> 
<p>But I may be asked, Would you confine the Negro to 
agriculture, mechanics, the domestic arts, etc.?  Not at all; but 
just now and for a number of years the stress should be laid along 
the lines that I have mentioned.  We shall need and must have many 
teachers and ministers, some doctors and lawyers and statesmen, but 
these professional men will have a constituency or a foundation 
from which to draw support just in proportion as the race prospers 
along the economic lines that I have pointed out.  During the first 
fifty or one hundred years of the life of any people, are not the 
economic occupations always given the greater attention?  This is 
not only the historic, but, I think, the common-sense view.  If 
this generation will lay the material foundation, it will be the 
quickest and surest way for enabling later generations to succeed 
in the cultivation of the fine arts, and to surround themselves 
with some of the luxuries of life, if desired.  What the race most 
needs now, in my opinion, is a whole army of men and women well-trained 
to lead, and at the same time devote themselves to 
agriculture, mechanics, domestic employment, and business.  As 
<pb n="584"/> 
to the mental training that these educated leaders should be 
equipped with, I should say, give them all the mental training and 
culture that the circumstances of individuals will allow, &mdash; the more 
the better.  No race can permanently succeed until its mind is 
awakened and strengthened by the ripest thought.  But I would 
constantly have it kept in the minds of those who are educated in 
books that a large proportion of those who are educated should be 
so trained in hand that they can bring this mental strength and 
knowledge to bear upon the physical conditions in the South, which 
I have tried to emphasize.</p> 
<p>Frederick Douglass, of sainted memory, once, in addressing his 
race, used these words:  <q>"We are to prove that we can better our 
own condition.  One way to do this is to accumulate property.  This 
may sound to you like a new gospel.  You have been accustomed to 
hear that money is the root of all evil, etc.; on the other hand, 
property, money, if you please, will purchase for us the only 
condition by which any people can rise to the dignity of genuine 
manhood; for without property there can be no leisure, without 
leisure there can be no thought, without thought there can be no 
invention, without invention there can be no progress."</q></p> 
<p>The Negro should be taught that material development is not an 
end, but merely a means to an end.  As professor W. E. B. Du Bois 
puts it, the idea should not be simply to make men carpenters, but 
to make carpenters men.  The Negro has a highly religious 
temperament; but what he needs more and more is to be convinced of 
the importance of weaving his religion and morality into the 
practical affairs of daily life.  Equally does he need to be taught 
to put so much intelligence into his labor that he will see dignity 
and beauty in the occupation, and love it for its own sake.  The 
Negro needs to be taught to apply more of the religion that 
manifests itself in his happiness in prayer meeting to the 
performance of his daily task.  The man who owns a home, and is in 
the possession of the elements by which he is sure of a daily 
living, has a great aid to a moral and religious life.  What 
bearing will all this have upon the Negro's place in the South, as 
a citizen and in the enjoyment of the privileges which our 
government confers?</p> 
<p>To state in detail just what place the black man will occupy 
in the South as a citizen, when he has developed in the direction 
named, is beyond the wisdom of any one.  Much will depend upon the 
sense of justice which can be kept alive in the breast of the 
American people; almost as much will depend upon the good sense of 
the Negro himself.  That question, I confess, does not give me the 
most concern just now.  The important and pressing question is, 
Will the Negro, with his own help and that of his friends, take 
advantage of the opportunities that surround him?  When he has done 
this, I believe, speaking of his future in general terms, that he 
will be treated with justice, be given the protection of the law 
and the recognition which his usefulness and ability warrant.  If, 
fifty years ago, one had predicted that the Negro would receive the 
recognition and honor which individuals have already received, he 
would have been laughed at as an idle dreamer.  Time, patience, and 
constant achievement are great factors in the rise of a race.</p> 
<p>I do not believe that the world ever takes a race seriously, 
in its desire to share in the government of a nation, until a large 
number of individual members of that race have demonstrated beyond 
question their ability to control and develop their own business 
enterprises.  Once a number of Negroes rise to the point where they 
own and operate the most successful farms, are among the largest 
taxpayers in their county, are moral and intelligent, I do not 
believe that in many portions of the South such men need 
<pb n="585"/> 
long be denied the right of saying by their votes how they prefer 
their property to be taxed, and who are to make and administer the 
laws.</p> 
<p>I was walking the street of a certain town in the South lately 
in company with the most prominent Negro there.  While we were 
together, the mayor of the town sought out the black man, and said, 
"Next week we are going to vote on the question of issuing bonds to 
secure water-works; you must be sure to vote on the day of 
election."  The mayor did not suggest whether he should vote yes or 
no; but he knew that the very fact of this Negro's owning nearly a 
block of the most valuable property in the town was a guarantee 
that he would cast a safe, wise vote on this important proposition. 
The white man knew that because of this Negro's property interests 
he would cast his vote in the way he thought would benefit every 
white and black citizen in the town, and not be controlled by 
influences a thousand miles away.  But a short time ago I read 
letters from nearly every prominent white man in Birmingham, 
Alabama, asking that the Rev. W. R. Pettiford, a Negro, be 
appointed to a certain important federal office.  What is the 
explanation of this?  For nine years Mr. Pettiford has been the 
president of the Negro bank in Birmingham, to which I have alluded. 
During these nine years, the white citizens have had the 
opportunity of seeing that Mr. Pettiford can manage successfully a 
private business, and that he has proved himself a conservative, 
thoughtful citizen, and they are willing to trust him in a public 
office.  Such individual examples will have to be multiplied, till 
they become more nearly the rule than the exception they now are. 
While we are multiplying these examples, the Negro must keep a 
strong and courageous heart.  He cannot improve his condition by 
any short-cut course or by artificial methods.  Above all, he must 
not be deluded into believing that his condition can be permanently 
bettered by a mere battledoor [sic] and shuttlecock of words, or by 
any process of mere mental gymnastics or oratory.  What is desired 
along with a logical defense of his cause are deeds, results, &mdash; 
continued results, in the direction of building himself up, so as 
to leave no doubt in the mind of any one of his ability to succeed.</p> 
<p>An important question often asked is, Does the white man in 
the South want the Negro to improve his present condition?  I say 
yes.  From the Montgomery (Alabama) Daily Advertiser I clip the 
following in reference to the closing of a colored school in a town 
in Alabama: &mdash; </p> 
<p><q>"EUFALA, May 25, 1899.  The closing exercises of the city 
colored public school were held at St. Luke's A. M. E. Church last 
night, and were witnessed by a large gathering, including many 
whites.  The recitations by the pupils were excellent, and the 
music was also an interesting feature.  Rev. R. T. Pollard 
delivered the address, which was quite an able one, and the 
certificates were presented by Professor T. L. McCoy, white, of the 
Sanford Street School.  The success of the exercises reflects great 
credit on Professor S. M. Murphy, the principal, who enjoys a 
deserved good reputation as a capable and efficient educator."</q></p> 
<p>I quote this report, not because it is the exception, but 
because such marks of interest in the education of the Negro on the 
part of the Southern white people may be seen almost every day in 
the local papers.  Why should white people, by their presence, 
words, and actions, encourage the black man to get education, if 
they do not desire him to improve his condition?</p> 
<p>The Payne Institute, an excellent college, to which I have 
already referred, is supported almost wholly by the Southern white 
Methodist church.  The Southern white Presbyterians support a 
theological school for Negroes at Tuscaloosa.  For a number 
<pb n="586"/> 
of years the Southern white Baptists have contributed toward Negro 
education.  Other denominations have done the same.  If these 
people do not want the Negro educated to a higher standard, there 
is no reason why they should pretend they do.</p> 
<p>Though some of the lynchings in the South have indicated a 
barbarous feeling toward Negroes, Southern white men here and 
there, as well as newspapers, have spoken out strongly against 
lynching.  I quote from the address of the Rev. Mr. Vance, of 
Nashville, Tennessee, delivered before the National Sunday School 
Union, in Atlanta, not long since, as an example: &mdash; </p> 
<p><q>"And yet, as I stand here to-night, a Southerner speaking for 
my section and addressing an audience from all sections, there is 
one foul blot upon the fair fame of the South, at the bare mention 
of which the heart turns sick and the cheek is crimsoned with 
shame.  I want to lift my voice to-night in loud and long and 
indignant protest against the awful horror of mob violence, which 
the other day reached the climax of its madness and infamy in a 
deed as black and brutal and barbarous as can be found in the 
annals of human crime.</q></p> 
<p><q>"I have a right to speak on the subject, and I propose to be 
heard.  The time has come for every lover of the South to set the 
might of an angered and resolute manhood against the shame and 
peril of the lynch demon.  These people whose fiendish glee taunts 
their victim as his flesh crackles in the flames do not represent 
the South.  I have not a syllable of apology for the sickening 
crime they meant to avenge.  But it is high time we were learning 
that lawlessness is no remedy for crime.  For one, I dare to 
believe that the people of my section are able to cope with crime, 
however treacherous and defiant, through their courts of justice; 
and I plead for the masterful sway of a righteous and exalted 
public sentiment that shall class lynch law in the category with 
crime."</q></p> 
<p>It is a notable and encouraging fact that no Negro educated in 
any of our larger institutions of learning in the South has been 
charged with any of the recent crimes connected with assaults upon 
women.</p> 
<p>If we go on making progress in the directions that I have 
tried to indicate, more and more the South will be drawn to one 
course.  As I have already said, it is not to the best interests of 
the white race of the South that the Negro be deprived of any 
privilege guaranteed him by the Constitution of the United States. 
This would put upon the South a burden under which no government 
could stand and prosper.  Every article in our Federal Constitution 
was placed there with a view of stimulating and encouraging the 
highest type of citizenship.  To continue to tax the Negro without 
giving him the right to vote, as fast as he qualifies himself in 
education and property for voting, would insure the alienation of 
the affections of the Negro from the state in which he lives, and 
would be the reversal of the fundamental principles of government 
for which our states have stood.  In other ways than this the 
injury would be as great to the white man as to the Negro. 
Taxation without the hope of becoming voters would take away from 
one third of the citizens of the Gulf states their interest in 
government, and a stimulus to become taxpayers or to secure 
education, and thus be able and willing to bear their share of the 
cost of education and government, which now rests so heavily upon 
the white taxpayers of the South.  The more the Negro is stimulated 
and encouraged, the sooner will he be able to bear a larger share 
of the burdens of the South.  We have recently had before us an 
example, in the case of Spain, of a government that left a large 
portion of its citizens in ignorance, and neglected their highest 
interests. <pb n="587"/> </p> 
<p>As I have said elsewhere: "There is no escape, through law of 
man or God, from the inevitable."</p> 
 
<lg type="poem"> 
<l>'The laws of changeless justice bind</l> 
<l>Oppressor with oppressed;</l> 
<l>And close as sin and suffering joined</l> 
<l>We march to fate abreast.'</l> 
</lg> 
 
<p> 
Nearly sixteen millions of hands will aid you in pulling the load 
upwards, or they will pull the load downwards against you.  We 
shall constitute one third and more of the ignorance and crime of 
the South, or one third of its intelligence and progress; we shall 
contribute one third to the business and industrial prosperity of 
the South, or we shall prove a veritable body of death, stagnating, 
depressing, retarding every effort to advance the body politic.</p> 
<p>My own feeling is that the South will gradually reach the 
point where it will see the wisdom and the justice of enacting an 
educational or property qualification, or both, for voting, that 
shall be made to apply honestly to both races.  The industrial 
development of the Negro in connection with education and Christian 
character will help to hasten this end.  When this is done, we 
shall have a foundation, in my opinion, upon which to build a 
government that is honest, and that will be in a high degree 
satisfactory to both races.</p> 
<p>I do not suffer myself to take too optimistic a view of the 
conditions in the South.  The problem is a large and serious one, 
and will require the patient help, sympathy, and advice of our most 
patriotic citizens, North and South, for years to come.  But I 
believe that if the principles which I have tried to indicate are 
followed, a solution of the question will come.  So long as the 
Negro is permitted to get education, acquire property, and secure 
employment, and is treated with respect in the business world, as 
is now true in the greater part of the South, I shall have the 
greatest faith in his working out his own destiny in our Southern 
states.  The education and preparation for citizenship of nearly 
eight millions of people is a tremendous task, and every lover of 
humanity should count it a privilege to help in the solution of a 
problem for which our whole country is responsible. 
</p> 
<closer><signed> Booker T. Washington.</signed></closer> 
</div1> 
 
</body> 
</text> 
</TEI.2> 
