<?xml version="1.0"?>

<?dlps id="WasTusk"?>
<?dlps page-images="none" figure-images="no"?>
<?dlps transcription="other"?>

<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/tei-p4/tei2.dtd" [
<!ENTITY % POSTKB "INCLUDE">
<!ENTITY % TEI.extensions.ent SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.ent">
<!ENTITY % TEI.extensions.dtd SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.dtd">
<!ENTITY % ISOnum SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/charent/iso-num.ent"> %ISOnum;
<!ENTITY % ISOpub SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/charent/iso-pub.ent"> %ISOpub;
]> 
<TEI.2 id="WasTusk"> 
<teiHeader type="migrated" creator="Etext">
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title type="main">Tuskegee: A Retrospect and Prospect</title>
<title type="sort">tuskegee a retrospect and prospect</title>
<author>Washington, Booker T.</author>
<respStmt>
<resp>Judy Boss</resp> 
<name>creator of electronic version</name> 
<resp>Conversion to TEI.2-conformant markup:</resp> 
<name>University of Virginia Library Electronic Text Center</name>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt> 
<extent>ca. <num type="kilobytes">30</num> kilobytes</extent> 
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>University of Virginia Library</publisher>
<pubPlace>Charlottesville, Virginia</pubPlace> 
<idno type="ETC">WasTusk</idno> 
<date value="1995">1995</date>
<availability status="public">
<p n="copyright">Copyright &copy; 1995 by the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia</p>
<p n="access">Publicly accessible</p>
</availability>
<idno type="uva-pid">uva-lib:476464</idno>
</publicationStmt>
<seriesStmt>
<title>University of Virginia Library, Text collection</title>
<idno type="uva-set">UVA-LIB-Text</idno>
</seriesStmt> 
<sourceDesc>
<biblFull>
<titleStmt>
<title type="main">Tuskegee: A Retrospect and Prospect</title>
<title type="sort">tuskegee a retrospect and prospect</title>
<author>Booker T. Washington</author>
</titleStmt> 
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>North American Review Publishing Co.</publisher> 
<pubPlace>New York: Franklin Square</pubPlace> 
<date value="1906-04">April, 1906</date>
</publicationStmt> 
<seriesStmt>
<p>North American Review, Vol. CLXXXII, No. DXCIII, 
April, 1906, pp. 513-523</p>
</seriesStmt> 
</biblFull>
</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc> 
<encodingDesc>
<projectDesc>
<p>Prepared for the University of Virginia Library Electronic Text Center</p>
</projectDesc> 
<editorialDecl>
<p>All quotation marks retained as data</p> 
<p>All unambiguous end-of-line hyphens have been removed, and the 
trailing part of a word has been joined to the preceding line.</p> 
<p id="ETC">Keywords in the header are a local Electronic Text Center 
scheme  to aid in establishing analytical groupings</p>
</editorialDecl> 
<refsDecl>
<p>ID elements are given for each page element and are composed of 
the text's unique cryptogram and the given page number, as in 
AusEmma1 for page one of  Jane Austen's Emma.</p>
</refsDecl>
</encodingDesc> 
<profileDesc>
<creation>
<date value="1906">1906</date>
</creation> 
<langUsage>
<language id="eng" usage="main">English</language>
</langUsage> 
<textClass>
<keywords>
<term>CORD</term> 
<term>democracy</term>
</keywords> 
<keywords>
<term>non-fiction; prose</term>
</keywords>
</textClass>
</profileDesc> 
<revisionDesc>
<change>
<date value="1995">1995</date> 
<respStmt>
<resp>corrector</resp> 
<name>Bryson Clevenger, Jr.</name>
</respStmt> 
<item>Minimal TEI tagging, spellchecking, TEI header</item>
</change> 
<change>
<date value="2005-07">July 2005</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>Corrector</resp>
<name>Margaret Konkol</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Converted SGML to XML and fixed tagging.</item>
</change>
<change>
<date value="2007-09">September 2007</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>Migration</resp>
<name>Ethan Gruber, University of Virginia Library</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Converted XML markup from TEI Lite to uva-dl-tei (TEI P4 with local customizations).</item>
</change>
<change>
<date value="2008-01">January 2008</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>Migration</resp>
<name>Greg Murray, University of Virginia Library</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Programmatically updated TEI header markup (but not header content) for minimal compliance with current QA requirements.</item>
</change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader> 
 
<text id="d1"> 
<body id="d2"> 

<div1 type="essay" id="d3"><pb n="513"/> <head> 
Washington, Booker T.  "Tuskegee: A Retrospect and Prospect." 
<lb/> 
<hi rend="italic">North American Review</hi> 182 (April 1906): 513-523. <lb/> 
BY BOOKER T. WASHINGTON, PRINCIPAL OF THE TUSKEGEE NORMAL 
AND INDUSTRIAL INSTITUTE.</head> 
 
<p>THE Tuskegee Normal and Industrial Institute celebrates this 
year on April 4, 5 and 6, its twenty-fifth birthday.  As I look 
back at its humble beginnings, and its gradual growth into what it 
is, and the promise of what it shall be, it seems to me that one of 
its more important services has been to provide Negroes with an 
unusual opportunity to engage in the education and upbuilding of 
their own race.  This school represents, in a large measure, the 
effort of the Negro race to help itself, and therein is the real 
significance of its work. 
</p><p>From the first, it has been the effort of the Tuskegee 
Institute to teach the lessons of self-help by furnishing an 
example.  With this aim in view, the task of building up and 
maintaining the school has been largely entrusted to its own 
students.  They have, in a large degree, made the bricks and 
erected the buildings.  They have, for the most part, done the work 
of the farm, raised the provisions and cooked the food.  The fact 
that they have done this under the direction of Negro teachers, 
with very little assistance from outside the school, has given them 
self-appreciation and self-reliance and an added respect for their 
race. 
</p><p>In saying this, I do not forget the debt that this school 
owes to Hampton Institute, whence so many of its teachers came, nor 
the debt of gratitude it owes to its friends among the members of 
the white race in the North and in the South who have furnished 
moral and material support.  But it should not be forgotten that 
the success of this school, like that of any other, depends, in the 
last analysis, less upon the effort of any one individual or group 
of individuals than upon the native qualities of its pupils and the 
<pb n="514"/> 
people from whom they sprang.  While the school 
at Tuskegee owes much to others, I believe it is but fair to say 
that it owes most to the patience and persistence of the students, 
and to the simple piety, earnestness and self-sacrifice of their 
fathers and mothers at home on the farm and plantation. 
</p><p>A careful investigation of the records last spring revealed 
the fact that, in addition to its 888 graduates, something like 
6,000 students, who were not able to remain to complete the full 
course of study, have been helped to such an extent that they are 
doing reasonably efficient work.  Of the graduates of the school, 
less than ten per cent., so far as we can ascertain, have been 
unsuccessful in their trades; and special investigations that we 
have made indicate that all have increased their economic 
efficiency, on an average of about three hundred per cent., some 
more and some less.  This shows the increased value that the 
average Southern white man places on the services of a Negro 
educated in the trades.  It indicates what, under reasonably 
favorable circumstances, Negroes can do and what they are doing. 
It ought also to be added, in reply to those who assert that 
education has not improved the Negro, but rather injured him in 
respect to his moral life, that so far as we can learn no graduate 
of Tuskegee has ever been convicted of crime. 
</p><p>The idea uppermost in my mind, when I began the work of 
establishing the school at Tuskegee, was to do something that would 
reach and improve the condition of the masses of the Negro people 
in the South.  Up to that time&mdash;and even to-day to a large extent&mdash; 
education had not touched, in any real and tangible way, the great 
majority of the people in what is known as "The Black Belt.  I had 
not been many days in Alabama before I realized this fact.  As my 
knowledge of conditions grew, I became increasingly convinced that 
any institution which was to be of real service to the millions of 
the lower South must not confine itself to methods that were suited 
to some distant community where conditions of life were vastly 
different.  I made up my mind from the first that a school which 
should perform for the masses the service I had in mind would have 
to teach its students many things that students in the North and 
West were taught in their homes.  I found that the teaching of 
books alone was not sufficient for the students who came to 
Tuskegee to be trained as teachers and leaders.  Our students 
needed to be taught how to sit at table 
<pb n="515"/> 
and eat 
properly, the uses of a napkin, table-cloth, knife and fork, and 
tooth-brush.  Large numbers of them were wholly ignorant of the 
very elements of right living.  In addition to this, they had to be 
taught how to care for tools and animals and how to systematize 
their labor.  The girls had to be trained to an intelligent 
appreciation of the value of housekeeping, cooking, sewing, 
laundering. 
</p><p>From the very outset of my work, it has been my steadfast 
purpose to establish an institution that would provide instruction, 
not for the select few, but for the masses, giving them standards 
and ideals, and inspiring in them hope and courage to go patiently 
forward.  I wanted to give Negro young men and women an education 
that would fit them to take up and carry to greater perfection the 
work that their fathers and mothers had been doing.  I saw clearly 
that an education that filled them with a "divine discontent," 
without ability to change conditions, would leave the students, and 
the masses they were to guide, worse off than they were in their 
unawakened state.  It was my aim to teach the students who came to 
Tuskegee to live a life and to make a living, to the end that they 
might return to their homes after graduation, and find profit and 
satisfaction in building up the communities from which they had 
come, and in developing the latent possibilities of the soil and 
the people.  To establish this idea, the Tuskegee Institute, with 
its 1,500 students, its 156 officers, teachers and employees, its 
86 buildings, and its varied ramifications for extension work, has 
come into existence. 
</p><p>Starting in a shanty and a hen-house, with almost no 
property beyond a hoe and a blind mule, the school has grown up 
gradually, much as a town grows.  We needed food for our tables; 
farming, therefore, was our first industry, started to meet this 
need.  With the need for shelter for our students, courses in 
house-building and carpentry were added.  Out of these, brick-making and brick-masonry naturally grew.  The increasing demand for 
buildings made further specialization in the industries necessary. 
Soon we found ourselves teaching tinsmithing, plastering and 
painting.  Classes in cooking were added, because we needed 
competent persons to prepare the food.  Courses in laundering, 
sewing, dining-room work and nurse-training have been added to meet 
the actual needs of the school community.  This process of 
specialization has continued as the school increased in numbers 
<pb n="516"/> 
and as the more varied wants of a larger 
community created a demand, and instruction is now given in thirty-seven industries. 
</p><p>Although we have constantly emphasized at Tuskegee the 
dignity and the nobility of labor, it has never been my idea that 
the training of the Negro should be limited to trade or industrial 
work.  I have always felt that our students, in connection with 
their technical training, should have their minds thoroughly 
awakened and developed by a severe and systematic training in the 
academic branches. 
</p><p>Here I might add that Tuskegee's emphasis on industrial 
education implies by no means a lack of appreciation of the 
colleges and professional schools.  The race needs both kinds of 
education, and each type of institution complements the work of the 
other. 
</p><p>But it was recognized that something more than industrial or 
academic training was necessary if our students were, in any large 
degree, to make themselves useful in changing the conditions of the 
masses of their people.  They needed an education which not only 
did not educate them out of sympathy with the masses of their 
people, but made them actively and practically interested in 
constructive methods and work among their people.  The better to 
accomplish this end we taught our girls, not only to work at their 
trades in the schoolroom, but to meet the people in their churches 
and other gathering-places on Sunday.  In addition to the ordinary 
duties of the schoolroom, teachers who go out from Tuskegee are 
taught how to conduct monthly farmers' institutes or local farmers' 
conferences.  They are expected to be able to show the farmers how 
to buy land, to assist them by advice in getting out of debt, and 
to encourage them to cease mortgaging their crops, and to take 
active interest in the economic development of their community. 
</p><p>Some months ago, I was rather severely criticised by an 
educated colored man in Washington because I had spoken rather 
frankly to the colored people in this section of the country about 
the habit of buying pianos and organs to put in their rented 
log-cabins.  This man thought the colored people ought to be free 
to buy pianos and organs just the same as the people of any other 
race.  As far as the right of colored people to buy pianos and 
organs is concerned, I think the Negroes should feel that they have 
the same right that any other people have.  I do think, however, 
<pb n="517"/> 
that one is doing them service in telling them 
frankly that, while they have the right, it is hardly the part of 
wisdom for them to waste money in buying musical instruments before 
they get a home in which to put them, and before their children 
have had enough education to use them properly. 
</p><p>During the early days of my work at Tuskegee, I found that 
the Negro people in this section of the country earned a great deal 
of money, and were willing to work, and did, for the most part, 
work hard.  What they needed was stimulation and guidance.  In 
order to reach the masses with the knowledge that they most needed, 
we have worked out several methods of popular education which seem 
to be peculiarly adapted to the needs of the Negro farming 
communities.  Among them we have (1) mothers' meetings, conducted 
by Mrs. Washington; (2) visits of teachers and students to 
communities distant from the school; (3) local Negro conferences, 
which meet once a month in various sections of the South; (4) the 
annual Negro Conference, which brings together at Tuskegee 
Institute every year from 1,200 to 1,400 representatives from 
various sections of the South, to spend a day in discussing the 
conditions and needs of the race; (5) the Worker's Conference, 
composed of officers and teachers of the leading schools for 
Negroes, which meets at Tuskegee the day after the annual Negro 
Conference; (6) the County Farmers' Institute, together with the 
Farmers' Winter Short Course in Agriculture, and the County Fair 
held in the fall; (7) the National Negro Business League, which 
seeks to do for the race as a whole what the local business leagues 
are doing for the 
communities in which they exist. 
</p><p>In addition to the work performed through these 
organizations, we give our cooperation, not only to the graduates 
who are teaching in small country schools, but to a number of large 
institutions like the Institute at Snow Hill, Alabama, and the 
Voorhees Industrial School, at Denmark, South Carolina, that are 
doing in a modified way the kind of work that we are seeking to do 
at Tuskegee.  Sixteen institutions, offshoots of Tuskegee, have 
grown to a size where they have been incorporated by the State 
authorities.  One of our Trustees, the Rev. R. C. Bedford, gives a 
large part of his time to keeping in touch, through correspondence 
and personal visits, with our graduates who are working in these 
schools and elsewhere throughout the South. </p> 
<pb n="518"/> 
 
<p>I have been asked in what way my views of Negro education 
have changed during the twenty-five years and more that I have been 
engaged in this work.  As I look back over the past, I cannot now 
see that my notions have been modified in any material way during 
that time.  I have sought at all times to put into effect at 
Tuskegee the ideas I had imbibed under General Armstrong's 
instruction at Hampton.  Whatever difference there is between the 
work of the Tuskegee and Hampton Institutes grows out of the 
difference in the conditions of life in the territory surrounding 
the two schools.  We, for example, are in a cotton-raising 
district.  Agriculture plays a larger role in Alabama, perhaps, 
than it does in Virginia.  Furthermore, civilizing influences have 
been at work for a shorter time here than at Hampton.  While the 
Tuskegee students have, perhaps, gone further in the direction of 
putting up their own buildings than have the students at Hampton, 
yet the work of the two schools is in all essentials the same. 
Hampton, being older, is more perfect and complete; Tuskegee, still 
in the making, is necessarily imperfect, incomplete. 
</p><p>Although I have not in any appreciable way modified my views 
concerning Negro education within the last twenty-five years, I 
have found it necessary from time to time to correct impressions 
that have somehow got abroad.  I do not, for example, advocate any 
kind of industrial or technical training for the Negro that I would 
not advocate for any other race in the same relative stage of 
civilization.  From time to time, I have thought it necessary to 
say something that would prevent the impression spreading abroad 
that industrial education is class education.  Nothing could be 
more harmful to the cause of industrial or technical education than 
to permit the idea to become current that industrial education was 
created especially for the benefit of the black race. 
</p><p>But, if I have in no important respect changed my views in 
regard to industrial education during the twenty-five years that I 
have been working at Tuskegee, I have become more and more 
convinced, as I have gained a more extended experience, of the 
value of the education that is imparted through systematic training 
of the hand.  Of this I have had constant evidence in my 
acquaintance with a number of students who have appeared dull in 
their books, and yet have shown themselves extremely methodical and 
systematic in their work after they have left us and gone 
<pb n="519"/> 
out into the world to work for themselves. 
This ability to meet conditions may be largely accounted for by the 
fact that our students have studied not merely books, but things. 
</p><p>I do not care to venture here an opinion about the nature of 
knowledge in general; but it will be pretty clear to any one who 
reflects upon the matter that the only kind of knowledge that has 
any sort of value for a race that is trying to get on its feet is 
knowledge that has some definite relation to the daily lives of the 
men and women who are seeking it. 
</p><p>There is constant danger that boys and girls who have grown 
up on the farms, with very little familiarity with books and the 
ideas that one meets in books, will learn to repeat what they hear 
in the class-room or read in books without being able to interpret 
what they read.  One of the best ways of testing the pupil's 
knowledge, in such cases, is to compel him in some way to act.  In 
this way, it is possible to use the training of the hand to give 
definiteness and precision to the ideas acquired in the class-room. 
The pupil can be led to see the necessity of constantly applying 
the ideas he has gathered from books to an actual situation, in 
order to test his knowledge and find out the real significance of 
what he has learned in the class-room.  We have sought to carry out 
this principle of putting everything learned in the class-room to 
the test of action in all departments of the school: to supplement 
and enlarge the knowledge obtained in the industries by studies in 
the class-room, and to give precision and definiteness to the 
things learned in the class-room by the practical application of 
them in the industrial departments. 
</p><p>Even in our Phelps Hall Bible Training School, which, to the 
ordinary student, seems farthest removed from the practical affairs 
of life, we have demanded of students, as a test of the value of 
what they have learned, that they take an active part in one or 
more of the various lines of extension work in which the school is 
engaged.  While we constantly seek to interest all classes of 
students in the work of extending the influence of the school to 
the masses of the people, we have insisted that it was, in a very 
special sense, the duty of the students in the Bible Training 
School, most of whom are preparing themselves to go out into the 
country districts to become leaders of the people, to prove by some 
form of practical work among the people their capacity for their 
professions. 
</p> 
<pb n="520"/> 
 
<p>If I were asked what I consider the most important thing 
that Tuskegee has accomplished, I should say it is the work it has 
done with a view to setting the faces of the masses of our people 
away from the sunset toward the sunrise.  A brief explanation will 
make my meaning clear.  I began my work at Tuskegee at the time 
when the Negro had just been deprived, in a way that is now 
familiar, of many of his political rights.  There was some voting, 
but few Negroes held office when I first came to Alabama.  The 
Negro people for the most part set great store by the political 
privileges that had been granted them during the Reconstruction 
period, and they thought that when they lost these they had lost 
all.  I remember well the sullen sense of despair which seemed to 
have taken possession of the people at this time.  They preserved 
outwardly the same good nature and cheerfulness which had always 
characterized them, but deep down in their hearts they had begun to 
feel that there was no hope for them, and that there was no use for 
them to try. 
</p><p>The most important work that Tuskegee has done has been to 
show the masses of our people that, in agriculture, in the 
industries, in commerce, and in the struggle toward economic 
development, there are opportunities and a great future for them. 
In doing this, we have not sought to give the idea that political 
rights are not valuable or necessary, but rather to impress our 
people with the truth that economic efficiency was the foundation 
for political rights, and that in proportion as they made 
themselves factors in the economic development of the country 
political rights would naturally and necessarily come to them. 
</p><p>The next important work of our school has been to change the 
ideas of the masses of the people concerning labor with the hand. 
When Tuskegee Institute was first opened, practically all the 
colored people in this part of the South were opposed to industrial 
education.  For many months, the hardest task the school had to 
face was to overcome the opposition of the people to the notion of 
a "working-school."  At the present time, that battle has been won. 
So successful have Hampton and Tuskegee been in changing the views 
of the people on this question that a man, in any part of the 
country, who now opposes industrial education for the Negro is so 
exceptional that he is likely to be regarded as eccentric.  The 
students at Tuskegee now count it just as much a part of their 
education to spend a day on the farm or in the 
<pb n="521"/> 
kitchen, in the machine-shop, or in the laundry, as they do to 
spend a day in studying algebra, chemistry or literature. 
</p><p>Something has been accomplished, also, during the past 
twenty-five years in interesting the Southern white men and women 
in a way to let them see and feel the value of educating the black 
man.  For the future of both races, it is just as important to 
bring about a satisfactory understanding in regard to their mutual 
relations as it is to do away with the ignorant, hopeless black 
proletariat which came into existence in the South as one of the 
results of the Civil War.  To me, one of the saddest incidents of 
our present educational effort in the South is the fact that many 
of the Southern white people know less about what is really being 
done for the Negro than do many Northern people living thousands of 
miles away.  In some rational manner, an effort should be made&mdash;and 
we expect to do our part in this direction&mdash;to get hold of the 
thinking and more substantial class of Southern white people, in a 
manner that will let us have the benefit of their sympathy and 
cooperation in a larger degree than we have had in the past. 
</p><p>During the succeeding twenty-five years, it is my earnest 
wish that the whole work at Tuskegee may be more fully perfected 
and rounded out.  I do not mean that we should increase our numbers 
to any great extent, but that we should make the training more 
efficient, and that the whole institution and grounds, buildings, 
apparatus, and teaching-force should be brought to a higher stage 
of perfection.  It is my hope that, sometime during the next 
twenty-five years, we shall secure an endowment of at least five 
million dollars, in order that the head of the institution may give 
a larger part of his time and strength in working immediately for 
the whole people, to the end that the work of bringing the teaching 
of our school home to the masses may be given the widest extension 
possible.  My experience has taught me that wherever I go to speak, 
I not only meet a large number of colored people, but, usually, I 
am able also to speak to the best white people in the community, 
and I find that these meetings go a long way toward bringing about 
better relations between the races and to promote the highest and 
best interests of both. 
</p><p>It is, perhaps, fruitless to attempt, at the present stage 
of progress of the Negro race, to predict or even to suggest what 
can be accomplished during the next twenty-five years for Negro 
<pb n="522"/> 
upbuilding and moral and material regeneration. 
I do not believe, however, that we are justified in taking a 
hopeless or discouraging view of the situation.  It should be borne 
in mind that there are at the present time nearly 10,000,000 
persons of Negro ancestry in the United States.  In twenty-five 
years more, judging by the present rate of increase, the number 
will reach something like 15,000,000 or 16,000,000.  This is 
considerably more than the total population of Belgium and Holland 
combined. 
</p><p>The position of the Negro in the United States is, in some 
respects, like that of the Jewish people in the different countries 
in which they live.  They constitute, in a certain sense, a nation 
within a nation.  But there is this difference&mdash;that there are 
little more than one million Jews in the United States.  I believe 
that, if the work which schools like Hampton, Fisk and Tuskegee are 
doing can be continued and extended, so that the whole Negro 
population may ultimately have the benefit of the training they 
give, we may look forward with some confidence to seeing the masses 
of the Negro population visibly approach, not to the position of 
that marvellously gifted Hebrew race, but to something like the 
thrift, the industry, and the sturdy, thorough-going, self-respecting independence of the Hollanders and the Belgians.  What 
that would mean to the Negro race, to the South, and to the world, 
is something I hardly dare contemplate.  But that is, I believe, 
the thing that we should strive for in the next twenty-five years. 
</p><p>In recent years, this question has been repeatedly and 
insistently asked: "Suppose the Negro succeeds in making himself 
master here in America of the white man's civilization, what will 
be the effect upon the relations of the races?" 
</p><p>Often those who have pressed this question have answered it 
for themselves in the following manner.  They have said: "If the 
Negro is allowed to remain in this country until he is able to 
compete with the members of the white race, in the various forms of 
intellectual and physical labor, one of two consequences will 
follow: either the weaker race will be exterminated by the 
stronger, or the two races will amalgamate." 
</p><p>I do not believe that we have reason to fear either one or 
the other of these consequences.  It should always be borne in mind 
that it takes two races to amalgamate, and the absorption of one by 
the other cannot be accomplished without the consent of both.  I do 
not believe that the Negro is yet willing to disappear; I believe, 
<pb n="523"/> 
rather, that his unwillingness increases in 
proportion to his intellectual and moral advance.  I think it will 
be found to be a fact that the process of amalgamation has been 
going on with much less rapidity under freedom than it did under 
slavery.  So long as the Negro was taught that everything that was 
good was white and everything that was bad was black, so long as he 
remained a mere chattel, it was natural and inevitable that he 
should desire to become in everything&mdash;in style, manners, thought, 
and in the color of his skin&mdash;white.  But now that the Negro is 
beginning to understand his own possibilities, to believe that he 
has an independent mission in the world, and to gain that sort of 
self-respect that comes with the consciousness of that mission, the 
disposition and the willingness to surrender his racial identity 
and to detach himself from the life and the destiny of his own 
people are, I am convinced, steadily decreasing. 
</p><p>The other question, the question of his elimination by 
force, is one that the Negro will have to face, just as other races 
have faced it.  His position in that regard is not so different 
from that of the Jews.  At any rate, it is a question he cannot 
escape by going to any other country.  As a matter of fact, those 
who have studied the situation know that the Negro has less 
protection against the encroachments and the competition of the 
white race in Africa than he has here in America.  The fact that he 
is in the majority does not help him in Africa any more than it has 
helped him elsewhere. 
</p><p>I am convinced that any one who will consider the question 
with patience will come to the conclusion that the only salvation 
for the Negro people, or for any race, is to make themselves so 
useful to the rest of the world, so indispensable to their 
neighbors, that the world will not only tolerate, but desire, their 
presence.  To a large extent, this is already true in the South&mdash; 
more true, I am convinced, than it is in the North, where the Negro 
has much less opportunity to work than he has in the South.  In 
short, there is nothing for the Negro to do but remain where he is 
and struggle on and up.  The whole philosophy of the Negro question 
can be written in three words: patience, persistence, fortitude. 
The really hopeful thing about the situation is that, on the whole, 
the Negro has done, under the circumstances, the best he could. 
</p> 
 <signed>BOOKER T. WASHINGTON</signed> 
 
</div1> 
</body> 
</text> 
</TEI.2> 
