<?xml version="1.0"?>

<?dlps id="WeaNegr"?>
<?dlps page-images="none" figure-images="no"?>
<?dlps transcription="other"?>

<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/tei-p4/tei2.dtd" [
<!ENTITY % POSTKB "INCLUDE">
<!ENTITY % TEI.extensions.ent SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.ent">
<!ENTITY % TEI.extensions.dtd SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.dtd">
<!ENTITY % ISOnum SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/charent/iso-num.ent"> %ISOnum;
<!ENTITY % ISOpub SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/charent/iso-pub.ent"> %ISOpub;

]>
<TEI.2 id="WeaNegr">
<teiHeader type="migrated" creator="Etext">
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title type="main">The Negro as an American</title>
<title type="sort">negro as an american</title>
<author>Weaver, Robert C.</author>
<respStmt>
<resp>Creation of machine-readable version</resp>
<name/>
<resp>Conversion to TEI-conformant markup</resp> 
<name>University of Virginia Library Electronic Text Center</name>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt>
<extent>ca. <num type="kilobytes">32</num> kilobytes</extent>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>University of Virginia Library</publisher>
<pubPlace>Charlottesville, Virginia</pubPlace>
<idno type="ETC">WeaNegr</idno>
<date value="1994">1994</date>
<availability status="public">
<p n="copyright">Copyright &copy; 1994 by the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia</p>
<p n="access">Publicly accessible</p>
</availability>
<idno type="uva-pid">uva-lib:476465</idno>
</publicationStmt>
<seriesStmt>
<title>University of Virginia Library, Text collection</title>
<idno type="uva-set">UVA-LIB-Text</idno>
</seriesStmt>
<sourceDesc>
<biblFull>
<titleStmt>
<title type="main">The Negro as an American</title>
<title type="sort">negro as an american</title>
<author>Robert C. Weaver</author>
</titleStmt>
<publicationStmt>
<p/>
</publicationStmt>
<notesStmt>
<note>
<p>edition unknown</p>
</note>
</notesStmt>
</biblFull>
</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc>
<encodingDesc>
<projectDesc>
<p>Prepared for the University of Virginia Library Electronic Text Center</p>
</projectDesc>
<editorialDecl>
<p>All quotation marks retained as data</p>
<p>All unambiguous end-of-line hyphens have been removed, and the 
trailing part of a word has been joined to the preceding line.</p>
<p id="ETC">Keywords in the header are a local Electronic Text Center
scheme 
to aid in establishing analytical groupings</p>
</editorialDecl>
<refsDecl>
<p>ID elements are given for each page element and are composed of the
text's 
unique cryptogram and the given page number, as in SpeFQue1 for page
one of 
Spenser's Faerie Queene.</p>
</refsDecl>
</encodingDesc>
<profileDesc>
<creation>
<date value="1963-06">June 1963</date>
</creation>
<langUsage>
<language id="eng" usage="main">English</language>
</langUsage>
<textClass>
<keywords>
<term>non-fiction; prose</term>
<term>African American</term>
</keywords>
</textClass>
</profileDesc>
<revisionDesc>
<change>
<date value="1992-02">February 1992</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>corrector</resp>
<name>David Seaman</name>
</respStmt> 
<item>minimal TEI tagging and spell-check.  Paginiation is nominal 
(every 40 lines)</item>
</change>
<change>
<date value="1994-08">August 1994</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>corrector</resp>
<name>Jamie L Spriggs, Electronic Text Center, University of Virginia</name>
</respStmt> 
<item>updated header</item>
</change>
<change>
<date value="2005-07">July 2005</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>Corrector</resp>
<name>Margaret Konkol</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Converted SGML to XML and fixed tagging.</item>
</change>
<change>
<date value="2007-09">September 2007</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>Migration</resp>
<name>Ethan Gruber, University of Virginia Library</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Converted XML markup from TEI Lite to uva-dl-tei (TEI P4 with local customizations).</item>
</change>
<change>
<date value="2008-01">January 2008</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>Migration</resp>
<name>Greg Murray, University of Virginia Library</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Programmatically updated TEI header markup (but not header content) for minimal compliance with current QA requirements.</item>
</change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>
<text id="d1">

<front id="d2">
<div1 type="introduction" id="d3">
<head>INTRODUCTION</head>


<p>On January 13, 1966, President Johnson nominated Robert C. Weaver 
to be the first Secretary of the newly created Department of Housing 
and Urban Development &mdash; and also to be the first Negro ever to serve in 
the Cabinet.  His subsequent confirmation by the Senate, with little 
or no opposition, represented another milestone:  when the late 
President John F. Kennedy had proposed the creation of such a 
department four years earlier, the plan was defeated by a coalition of 
southern Democrats and some Republicans in the House of 
Representatives after it became known that Weaver was the President's 
choice. 
</p><p>The great-grandson of slaves, Weaver worked his way through an 
education culminating in a Harvard Ph.D. in Economics.  His first 
government job was as an Advisor on Negro Affairs in the Interior 
Department during the early new deal years of the 1930's.  Later he 
assumed various posts connected with Housing and Manpower, and during 
World War II was credited with opening up new job opportunities for 
Negroes in defense industries.  When John F. Kennedy entered the White 
House in 1960 he named Weaver as administrator of the Federal Housing 
and Home Finance Agency, a post which he held until his Cabinet 
appointment. 
</p><p>A veteran leader in the field of civil rights (he has been 
National Chairman of the National Association for the Advancement of 
Colored People), Weaver has made many speeches on themes similar to 
the one he delivered in Chicago on June 13, 1963, before the Symposium 
of Challenges to Democracy sponsored by the Fund for the Republic. 
The challenge which he outlined was the challenge to American 
Democracy to practice at home what it preaches to the world:  namely, 
the values of equality, liberty, fraternity, and opportunity. 
</p>
</div1>
</front>
<body id="d4">
<div1 type="speech" id="d5">
<head> THE NEGRO AS AN AMERICAN </head> 
<pb/>
<p>When the average well-informed and well-intentioned white 
American discusses the issue of race with his Negro counterpart there 
are many areas of agreement.  There are also certain significant areas 
of disagreement. 
</p><p>Negro Americans usually feel that whites exaggerate progress; 
while whites frequently feel that Negroes minimize gains.  Then there 
are differences relative to the responsibility of Negro leadership. 
It is in these areas of dispute that some of the most subtle and 
revealing aspects of Negro-white relationships reside.  And it is to 
the subtle and less obvious aspects of this problem that I wish to 
direct my remarks. 
</p><p>Most middle-class white Americans frequently ask, "Why do Negroes 
push so?  They have made phenomenal progress in 100 years of freedom, 
so why don't their leaders do something about the crime rate and 
illegitimacy?"  To them I would reply that when Negroes press for full 
equality now they are behaving as all other Americans would under 
similar circumstances.  Every American has the right to be treated as 
a human being and striving for human dignity is a national 
characteristic.  Also, there is nothing inconsistent in such action 
and realistic self-appraisal.  Indeed, as I shall develop, self-help 
programs among non-whites, if they are to be effective, must go 
hand-in-glove with the opening of new opportunities. 
</p><p>Negroes who are constantly confronted or threatened by 
discrimination and inequality articulate a sense of outrage.  Many 
react with hostility, sometimes translating their feelings into overt 
anti-social actions.  In parts of the Negro community a separate 
culture with deviant values develops.  To the members of this 
subculture I would observe that ours is a middle-class society and 
those who fail to evidence most of its values and behavior are headed 
toward difficulties.  But I am reminded that the rewards for those who 
do are often minimal, providing insufficient inducement for large 
numbers to emulate them. 
</p><p>Until the second decade of the twentieth century, it was 
traditional to compare the then current position of Negroes with that 
of a decade or several decades ago.  The depression revealed the basic 
marginal economic status of colored Americans and repudiated this 
concept of progress.  By the early 1930's Negroes became concerned 
about their relative position in the nation. 
</p><p>Of course, there are those who observe that the average income, 
the incidence of home ownership, the rate of acquisition of 
<pb/>
automobiles, and the like, among Negroes in the United States are 
higher than in some so-called advanced nations.  Such comparisons mean 
little.  Incomes are significant only in relation to the cost of 
living, and the other attainments and acquisitions are significant for 
comparative purposes only when used to reflect the Negro's relative 
position in the world.  The Negro here &mdash; as he has so frequently and 
eloquently demonstrated &mdash; is an American.  And his status, no less than 
his aspirations, can be measured meaningfully only in terms of 
American standards. 
</p><p>Viewed from this point of view what are the facts? 
</p><p>Median family income among non-whites was slightly less than 55 
percent of that for whites in 1959; for individuals the figure was 50 
percent. 
</p><p>Only a third of the Negro families in 1959 earned sufficient to 
sustain an acceptable American standard of living.  Yet this involved 
well over a million Negro families, of which 6,000 earned $25,000 or 
more. 
</p><p>Undergirding these overall figures are many paradoxes.  Negroes 
have made striking gains in historical terms, yet their current rate 
of unemployment is well over double that among whites.  Over 
two-thirds of our colored workers are still concentrated in five major 
unskilled and semi-skilled occupations, as contrasted to slightly over 
a third of the white labor force. 
</p><p>Despite the continuing existence of color discrimination even for 
many of the well prepared, there is a paucity of qualified Negro 
scientists, engineers, mathematicians, and highly-trained clerical and 
stenographic workers.  Lack of college-trained persons is especially 
evident among Negro men.  One is prompted to ask why does this exist? 
</p><p>In 1959 non-white males who were high school graduates earned on 
the average, 32 percent less than whites; for non-white college 
graduates the figure was 38 percent less.  Among women a much 
different situation exists.  Non-white women who were high school 
graduates earned on the average some 24 percent less than whites. 
Non-white female college graduates, however, earned but slightly over 
one percent less average annual salaries than white women college 
graduates.  Significantly, the median annual income of non-white 
female college graduates was more than double that of non-white women 
with only high school education. 
</p><p>Is it any wonder that among non-whites, as contrasted to whites, 
a larger proportion of women than of men attend and finish college? 
<pb/>
The lack of economic rewards for higher education goes far in 
accounting for the paucity of college graduates and the high rate of 
drop-out among non-white males.  It also accounts for the fact that in 
the North, where there are greater opportunities for white-collar 
Negro males, more Negro men than women are finishing college;  whereas 
in the South, where teaching is the greatest employment outlet for 
Negro college graduates, Negro women college graduates outnumber men. 
</p><p>There is much in these situations that reflects the continuing 
matriarchal character of Negro society &mdash; in a situation which had its 
roots in the family composition under slavery where the father, if 
identified, had no established role.  Subsequent and continuing 
economic advantages of Negro women who found steady employment as 
domestics during the post Civil War era and thereafter perpetuated the 
pattern.  This, in conjunction with easy access of white males to 
Negro females, served to emasculate many Negro men economically and 
psychologically.  It also explains, in part, the high prevalence of 
broken homes, illegitimacy, and lack of motivation in the Negro 
community. 
</p><p>The Negro middle-class seems destined to grow and prosper.  At 
the same time, the economic position of the untrained and poorly 
trained Negro &mdash; as of all untrained and poorly trained in our society &mdash;  
will continue to decline.  Non-whites are doubly affected.  First, 
they are disproportionately concentrated in occupations particularly 
susceptible to unemployment at a time when our technology eats up 
unskilled and semi-skilled jobs at a frightening rate.  Secondly, they 
are conditioned to racial job discrimination.  The latter circumstance 
becomes a justification for not trying, occasioning a lack of 
incentive for self-betterment. 
</p><p>The tragedy of discrimination is that it provides an excuse for 
failure while erecting barriers to success. 
</p><p>Most colored Americans still are not only outside the mainstream 
of our society but see no hope of entering it.  The lack of motivation 
and anti-social behavior which result are capitalized upon by the 
champions of the status quo.  They say that the average Negro must 
demonstrate to the average white that the latter's fears are 
groundless.  One proponent of this point of view has stated that Negro 
crime and illegitimacy must decline and Negro neighborhoods must stop 
deteriorating. 
</p><p>In these observations lie a volume on race relations.  In the 
first place, those who articulate this point of view fail to 
<pb/>
differentiate between acceptance as earned by individual merit and 
enjoyment of rights guaranteed to everyone.  Implicit, also, is the 
assumption that Negroes can lift themselves by their bootstraps, and 
that once they become brown counterparts of white middle-class 
Americans, they will be accepted on the basis of individual merit. 
Were this true, our race problem would be no more than a most recent 
phase in the melting pot tradition of the nation. 
</p><p>As compared to the earlier newcomers to our cities from Europe, 
the later ones who are colored face much greater impediments in moving 
from the slums or from the bottom of the economic ladder.  At the same 
time, they have less resources to meet the more difficult problems 
which confront them. 
</p><p>One of the most obvious manifestations of the Negro's paucity of 
internal resources is the absence of widespread integrated patterns of 
voluntary organizations.  The latter, as we know, contributed greatly 
to the adjustment and assimilation of European immigrants.  Both the 
Negro's heritage and the nature of his migration in the United States 
militated against the development of similar institutions. 
</p><p>Slavery and resulting post-civil war dependence upon whites 
stifled self-reliance.  Movement from the rural south to northern 
cities was a far cry from immigration from Europe to the new world. 
This internal migration was not an almost complete break with the 
past, nor were those who participated in it subjected to feelings of 
complete foreignness.  Thus the Negro tended to preserve his old 
institutions when he moved from one part of the nation to another; the 
immigrant created new ones.  And most important, the current 
adjustment of non-whites to an urban environment is occurring at a 
time when public agencies are rapidly supplanting voluntary 
organizations. 
</p><p>Although much is written about crime and family disorganization 
among Negroes, most literate Americans are poorly informed on such 
matters.  The first fallacy which arises is a confusion of what racial 
crime figures reflect.  When people read that more than half the crime 
in a given community is committed by Negroes they unconsciously 
translate this into an equally high proportion of Negroes who are 
criminals.  In fact, the latter proportion is extremely small. 
</p><p>In a similar vein, family stability, as indicated by the presence 
of both husband and wife, which is very low among the poorest 
non-whites, rises sharply as income increases. 
</p><p>Equally revealing is the fact that, in all parts of the country, 
<pb/>
the proportion of non-white families with female heads falls as 
incomes rise.  A good, steady pay check appears to be an important 
element in family stability.  Those Negroes who have been able to 
improve their economic position have generally taken on many of the 
attributes of white middle-class Americans. 
</p><p>But poverty still haunts half of the Negroes in the united 
states, and while higher levels of national productivity are a sine 
qua non for higher levels of employment in the nation, they alone will 
not wipe out unemployment, especially for minorities.  The labor 
reserve of today must be trained if it is to find gainful employment. 
Among non-whites this frequently involves more than exposure to 
vocational training.  Many of them are functionally illiterate and 
require basic education prior to any specialized job preparation. 
</p><p>The very magnitude of these problems illustrates that society 
must take the leadership in solving them.  But society can only 
provide greater opportunities.  The individual must respond to the new 
opportunities.  And he does so, primarily, in terms of visible 
evidence that hard work and sacrifice bring real rewards. 
</p><p>Many white Americans are perplexed, confused, and antagonized by 
Negroes' persistent pressure to break down racial segregation.  Few 
pause to consider what involuntary segregation means to its victims. 
</p><p>To the Negro, as an American, involuntary segregation is 
degrading, inconvenient and costly.  It is degrading because it is a 
tangible and constant reminder of the theory upon which it is based &mdash;  
biological racial inferiority.  It is inconvenient because it means 
long trips to work, exclusion from certain cultural and recreational 
facilities, lack of access to restaurants and hotels conveniently 
located, and, frequently, relegation to grossly inferior 
accommodations.  Sometimes it spells denial of a job and often it 
prevents upgrading based on ability. 
</p><p>But the principal disadvantage of involuntary segregation is its 
costliness.  Nowhere is this better illustrated than in education and 
housing.  By any and all criteria, separate schools are generally 
inferior schools in which the cultural deprivations of the descendants 
of slaves are perpetuated. 
</p><p>Enforced residential segregation, the most stubborn and universal 
of the Negro's disadvantages, often leads to exploitation and effects 
a spatial pattern which facilitates neglect of public services in the 
well-defined areas where Negroes live.  It restricts the opportunities 
of the more successful as well as the least successful in the group, 
<pb/>
augmenting artificially the number of non-whites who live in areas of 
blight and neglect and face impediments to the attainment of values 
and behavior required for upward social and economic mobility. 
</p><p>The most obvious consequence of involuntary residential 
segregation is that the housing dollar in a dark hand usually commands 
less purchasing power than one in a white hand.  Clearly, this is a 
denial of a basic promise of a free economy. 
</p><p>For immigrant groups in the nation, the trend toward improved 
socioeconomic status has gone hand-in-hand with decreasing residential 
segregation.  The reverse has been true of the Negro.  Eli Ginzberg, 
in his book, The Negro Potential, has delineated the consequences:
"It must be recognized that the Negro cannot suddenly take his 
proper place among whites in the adult world if he has never 
lived, played, and studied with them in childhood and young 
adulthood.  Any type of segregation handicaps a person's 
preparation for work and life. . .  Only when Negro and white 
families can live together as neighbors . . . Will the Negro grow 
up properly prepared for his place in the world of work." 
</p><p>Residential segregation based on color cannot be separated from 
residential segregation based upon income.  Both have snob and class 
appeal in contemporary America.  Concentration of higher income 
families in the suburbs means that many of those whose attitudes and 
values dominate our society do not see the poor or needy.  But more 
important, cut off by political boundaries, it is to their interest 
not to see them. 
</p><p>Yet there are over 30,000,000 Americans who experience poverty 
today.  For the most part, we resent them and the outlays required for 
welfare services.  They are a group which is separate from the 
majority of Americans and for whom the latter accept only the minimum 
responsibility.  Thus we have, for the first time, class unemployment 
in the United States. 
</p><p>I happen to have been born a Negro and to have devoted a large 
part of my adult energies to the problem of the role of the Negro in 
America.  But I am also a government administrator, and have devoted 
just as much energy &mdash; if not more &mdash; to problems of government 
administration at the local, the state and the national level. 
</p><p>My responsibilities as a Negro and an American are part of the 
heritage I received from my parents &mdash; a heritage that included a wealth 
of moral and social values that don't have anything to do with my 
race.  My responsibilities as a government administrator don't have 
<pb/>
too much to do with my race, either.  My greatest difficulty in public 
life is combating the idea that somehow my responsibilities as a Negro 
conflict with my responsibilities as a government administrator:  and 
this is a problem which is presented by those Negroes who feel that I 
represent them exclusively, as well as by those whites who doubt my 
capacity to represent all elements in the population.  The fact is 
that my responsibilities as a Negro and a government administrator do 
not conflict; they complement each other. 
</p><p>The challenge frequently thrown to me is why I don't go out into 
the Negro community and exhort Negro youths to prepare themselves for 
present and future opportunities.  My answer is somewhat ambivalent. 
I know that emphasis upon values and behavior conducive to success in 
the dominant culture of America was an important part of my youthful 
training.  But it came largely from my parents in the security and 
love of a middle-class family.  (And believe me, there is nothing more 
middle-class than a middle-class minority family!) 
</p><p>Many of the youth which I am urged to exhort come from broken 
homes.  They live in communities where the fellow who stays in school 
and follows the rules is a "square."  They reside in a neighborhood 
where the most successful are often engaged in shady &mdash; if not illegal &mdash;  
activities.  They know that the very policeman who may arrest them for 
violation of the law is sometimes the pay-off man for the racketeers. 
And they recognize that the majority society, which they frequently 
believe to be the "enemy," condones this situation.  Their experience 
also leads some of them to believe that getting the kind of job the 
residents in the neighborhood hold is unrewarding &mdash; a commitment to 
hard work and poverty.  For almost all of them, the precepts of Ben 
Franklin are lily-like in their applicability. 
</p><p>Included in the group are the third generation of welfare 
clients.  It is in this area &mdash; where they learn all the jargon of the 
social workers and psychologists &mdash; that they demonstrate real 
creativity.  It is in activities which "beat" the system that they are 
most adept &mdash; and where the most visible rewards are concentrated. 
</p><p>All youth is insecure today.  Young people in our slums are not 
only insecure but angry.  Their horizons are limited, and, in 
withdrawing from competing in the larger society, they are creating a 
peculiar, but effective, feeling of something that approaches, or at 
least serves as a viable substitute for, security.  In the process, 
new values and aspirations, a new vocabulary, a new standard of dress, 
and a new attitude toward authority evolve.  Each of these serves to 
<pb/>
demonstrate a separateness from the dominant culture. 
</p><p>As a realist, I know that these youth relate with me primarily in 
a negative sense.  They see me in terms of someone who has been able 
to penetrate, to a degree, the color line, and to them I have bettered 
the "enemy."  If I should attempt to suggest their surmounting the 
restrictions of color, they cite instances of persons they know who 
were qualified &mdash; the relatively few boys or girls in their neighborhood 
who finished high school or even college &mdash; only to be ignored while 
white youths with much less training were selected for good jobs.  And 
such occurrences are not unique or isolated in their experience. 
</p><p>The example which will be an inspiration to the Negro boys and 
girls whose anti-social behavior distresses most whites and many 
Negroes is someone they know who has experienced what they have 
experienced and has won acceptance in the mainstream of America.  When 
the Ralph Bunches, William Hasties, and John Hope Franklins emerge 
from their environment, the achievements of these successful Negroes 
will provide models which have meaning for them. 
</p><p>This is reflected in the occupations which provide the greatest 
incidence of mobility for slum youth.  One thinks immediately of prize 
fighting and jazz music.  In these fields there is a well established 
tradition of Negroes, reared in the ghetto areas of blight and 
poverty, who have gone to the top.  For youth in a similar 
environment, these are heroes with whom they can and do identify and 
relate.  And in these fields, a significant proportion of the 
successful are non-whites.  For only in those pursuits in which native 
genius can surmount (if indeed it does not profit from) lack of high 
level training does the dominant environment of the Negro facilitate 
large-scale achievement. 
</p><p>For many successful older colored Americans, middle-class status 
has been difficult.  Restricted, in large measure, to racial ghettos, 
they have expended great effort to protect their children from falling 
back into the dominant values of that environment.  And these values 
are probably more repugnant to them than to most Americans.  This is 
understandable in terms of their social origins.  For the most part, 
they come from lower-middle class families, where industry, good 
conduct, family ties, and a willingness to postpone immediate rewards 
for future successes are stressed.  Their values and standards of 
conduct are those of success-oriented middle-class Americans. 
</p><p>It is not that responsible Negroes fail to feel shame about 
muggings, illegitimacy, and boisterousness on the part of other 
<pb/>
Negroes.  Many &mdash; particularly the older ones &mdash; feel too much shame in 
this connection.  Accordingly, some either repudiate the "culprits" in 
terms of scathing condemnation or try to escape from the problem lest 
it endanger their none too secure status. 
</p><p>These attitudes, too, are shifting.  The younger middle-class 
Negroes are more secure and consequently place less stress upon the 
quest for respectability.  But few Negroes are immune from the toll of 
upward mobility.  Frequently their struggle has been difficult, and 
the maintenance of their status demands a heavy input.  As long as 
this is true, they will have less energy to devote to the problems of 
the Negro subculture.  It is significant, however, that the sit-ins 
and freedom marches in the south were planned and executed by Negro 
college students most of whom come from middle-class families. 
</p><p>Middle-class Negroes have long led the fight for civil rights; 
today its youthful members do not hesitate to resort to direct action, 
articulating the impatience which is rife throughout the Negro 
community.  In so doing they are forging a new solidarity in the 
struggle for human dignity. 
</p><p>There are today, as there always have been, thousands of 
dedicated colored Americans who don't make the headlines but are 
successful in raising the horizons of Negroes.  These are the less 
well-known leaders who function at the local level.  The teachers, 
social workers, local political leaders, ministers, doctors, and an 
assortment of indigenous leaders &mdash; many among the latter with little 
formal education &mdash; who are effective have familiarized themselves with 
the environmental factors which dull and destroy motivation.  They 
become involved with the total Negro community.  They demonstrate &mdash;  
rather than verbalize &mdash; a concern for Negro youth's problems.  They are 
trying to reach these young people, not by coddling and providing 
excuses for failure, but through identification of their 
potentialities and assistance in the development of these.  Involved 
are both genuine affection and sufficient toughness to facilitate and 
encourage the development of self-reliance. 
</p><p>Those, white and black alike, who reach the newcomers in our 
urban areas avoid value judgments relative to cultural patterns.  When 
they suggest thrift, good deportment, greater emphasis upon education 
and training, they do so as a pragmatic approach.  For them, it is not 
a matter of proselytizing, but in a matter of delineating those values 
and patterns of behavior that accelerate upward mobility in 
contemporary American society.  Such a sophisticated approach enables 
<pb/>
them to identify deviations from dominant values and conduct which are 
not inconsistent with a productive and healthy life in modern urban 
communities.  The latter are left undisturbed, so that there will be a 
minimum adjustment of values and concepts and the maximum functional 
effectiveness on the part of individuals who will not soon become 
middle-class America. 
</p><p>What are the responsibilities of Negro leadership? 
</p><p>Certainly the first is to keep pressing for first-class 
citizenship status &mdash; an inevitable goal of those who accept the values 
of this nation. 
</p><p>Another responsibility of Negro leadership is to encourage and 
assist Negroes to prepare for the opportunities that are now and will 
be opened to them. 
</p><p>The ultimate responsibilities of Negro leadership, however, are 
to show results and maintain a following.  This means that it cannot 
be so "responsible" that it forgets the trials and tribulations of 
others who are less fortunate or less recognized than itself.  It 
cannot stress progress &mdash; the emphasis which is so palatable to the 
majority group &mdash; without, at the same time, delineating the unsolved 
business of democracy.  It cannot provide or identify meaningful 
models unless it effects social changes which facilitate the emergence 
of these models from the environment which typifies so much of the 
Negro community. 
</p><p>But Negro leadership must also face up to the deficiencies which 
plague the Negro community, and it must take effective action to deal 
with resulting problems.  While, of course, crime, poverty, 
illegitimacy and hopelessness can all be explained, in large measure, 
in terms of the Negro's history and current status in America, they do 
exist.  We need no longer be self-conscious in admitting these 
unpleasant facts, for our knowledge of human behavior indicates 
clearly that anti-social activities are not inherent in any people. 
What is required is comprehension of these &mdash; a part of society's 
problems &mdash; and remedial and rehabilitation measures. 
</p><p>Emphasis upon self-betterment if employed indiscriminately by 
Negro leaders is seized upon by white supremacists and their 
apologists to support the assertion that Negroes &mdash; and they mean all 
Negroes &mdash; are not ready for full citizenship.  This, because of the 
nature of our society, Negro leadership must continue to stress rights 
if it is to receive a hearing for programs of self-improvement. 
</p><p>Black muslims, who identify the white man as the devil, can and 
<pb/>
do emphasize &mdash; with a remarkable degree of success &mdash; morality, industry, 
and good conduct.  But, the Negro leader who does not repudiate his or 
his followers' Americanism can do so effectively only as he, too, 
clearly repudiates identification with the white supremacists.  This 
he does, of course, when he champions equal rights, just as the black 
muslims accomplish it by directing hate toward all white people. 
</p><p>Most Negroes in leadership capacities have articulated the fact 
that they and those who follow them are a part of America.  They have 
striven for realization of the American dream.  Most recognize their 
responsibilities as citizens and urge others to follow their example. 
Sophisticated whites realize that the status of Negroes in our society 
depends not only upon what the Negro does to achieve his goals and 
prepare himself for opportunities but, even more, upon what all 
America does to expand these opportunities.  And the quality and 
nature of future Negro leadership depends upon how effective those 
leaders who relate to the total society can be in satisfying the 
yearnings for human dignity which reside in the hearts of all 
Americans.</p>

</div1>
</body>
</text>
</TEI.2>
