<?xml version="1.0"?>

<?dlps id="WhaBoil"?>
<?dlps page-images="none" figure-images="no"?>
<?dlps transcription="other"?>

<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/tei-p4/tei2.dtd" [
<!ENTITY % POSTKB "INCLUDE">
<!ENTITY % TEI.extensions.ent SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.ent">
<!ENTITY % TEI.extensions.dtd SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.dtd">
<!ENTITY % ISOnum SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/charent/iso-num.ent"> %ISOnum;
<!ENTITY % ISOpub SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/charent/iso-pub.ent"> %ISOpub;

]>
 
<TEI.2 id="WhaBoil"> 
<teiHeader type="migrated" creator="Etext">
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title type="main">The Pot-Boiler</title>
<title type="sort">pot boiler</title>
<author>Wharton, Edith, 1862-1937</author>
<respStmt>
<resp>Creation of machine-readable version:</resp> 
<name>Judy Boss</name> 
<resp>Conversion to TEI.2-conformant markup:</resp>  
<name>University of Virginia Library Electronic Text Center</name>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt> 
<extent>ca. <num type="kilobytes">66</num> kilobytes</extent> 
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>University of Virginia Library</publisher>
<pubPlace>Charlottesville, Virginia</pubPlace> 
<idno type="ETC">WhaBoil</idno> 
<date value="1995">1995</date>
<availability status="public">
<p n="copyright">Copyright &copy; 1995 by the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia</p>
<p n="access">Publicly accessible</p>
</availability>
<idno type="uva-pid">uva-lib:476480</idno>
</publicationStmt>
<seriesStmt>
<title>University of Virginia Library, Text collection</title>
<idno type="uva-set">UVA-LIB-Text</idno>
</seriesStmt> 
<sourceDesc>
<biblFull>
<titleStmt>
<title type="main">The Pot-Boiler</title>
<title type="sort">pot boiler</title>
<author>Edith Wharton</author>
</titleStmt> 
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>Scribner's Magazine</publisher> 
<pubPlace>New York</pubPlace> 
<date value="1904-12">December 1904</date>
</publicationStmt> 
<seriesStmt>
<p>36</p>
</seriesStmt> 
<notesStmt>
<note>
<p>Wharton, Edith.  "The Pot-Boiler."  <hi rend="italic">Scribner's  
Magazine</hi> 36 (Dec. 1904): 696-712.</p>
</note>
</notesStmt>
</biblFull>
</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc> 
<encodingDesc>
<projectDesc>
<p>Prepared for the University of Virginia Library Electronic Text Center</p>
</projectDesc> 
<editorialDecl>
<p>All quotation marks retained as data</p> 
<p>All unambiguous end-of-line hyphens have been removed, and the 
trailing part of a word has been joined to the preceding line.</p> 
<p id="ETC">Keywords in the header are a local Electronic Text Center scheme  
to aid in establishing analytical groupings</p>
</editorialDecl> 
<refsDecl>
<p>ID elements are given for each page element and are composed of the text's 
unique cryptogram and the given page number, as in AusEmma1 for page one of  
Jane Austen's Emma.</p>
</refsDecl>
</encodingDesc> 
<profileDesc>
<creation>
<date value="1904-12">December 1904</date>
</creation> 
<langUsage>
<language id="eng" usage="main">English</language>
</langUsage> 
<textClass>
<keywords>
<term>fiction</term>
<term>prose</term> 
<term>Women Writers</term>
</keywords>
</textClass>
</profileDesc> 
<revisionDesc>
<change>
<date value="1995-07">July 1995</date> 
<respStmt>
<resp>corrector</resp> 
<name>Judy Boss, University of Omaha</name>
</respStmt> 
<item>changed "addicited" to "addicted" on p. 708, 
paragraph 10, line 1; I have changed "reman" to "remain" on p. 710, 
paragraph 3, line 2.</item>
</change> 
<change>
<date value="1995-08">August 1995</date> 
<respStmt>
<resp>corrector</resp> 
<name>Monique Dull, Electronic Text Center, University of Virginia</name>
</respStmt> 
<item>tagged divisions and paragraphs with TEI.2-compatible SGML</item>
</change> 
<change>
<date value="1995-08">August 1995</date> 
<respStmt>
<resp>corrector</resp> 
<name>Jamie L Spriggs, Electronic Text Center, University of Virginia</name>
</respStmt> 
<item>added header, finished tagging with TEI.2-compatible SGML, parsed  
against "teilite" dtd</item>
</change> 
<change>
<date value="2005-07">July 2005</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>Corrector</resp>
<name>Margaret Konkol</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Converted SGML to XML and fixed tagging.</item>
</change>
<change>
<date value="2007-09">September 2007</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>Migration</resp>
<name>Ethan Gruber, University of Virginia Library</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Converted XML markup from TEI Lite to uva-dl-tei (TEI P4 with local customizations).</item>
</change>
<change>
<date value="2008-01">January 2008</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>Migration</resp>
<name>Greg Murray, University of Virginia Library</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Programmatically updated TEI header markup (but not header content) for minimal compliance with current QA requirements.</item>
</change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader> 
 
<text id="d1">  
<body id="d2">
<div1 type="story" id="d3"> 
<head> 
THE POT-BOILER 
</head>  <pb n="696"/>  
<div2 type="chapter" n="1" id="d4"> 
<head> 
I 
</head> 
<p>The studio faced north, looking out over a dismal reach of roofs 
and chimneys, and rusty fire-escapes hung with heterogeneous 
garments.  A crust of dirty snow covered the level surfaces, and a 
December sky with more snow in it lowered over them. 
</p><p>The room was bare and gaunt, with blotched walls and a stained 
uneven floor.  On a divan lay a pile of "properties"&mdash;limp 
draperies, an Algerian scarf, a moth-eaten fan of peacock feathers.  
The janitor had forgotten to fill the coal-scuttle over-night, and 
the cast-iron stove projected its cold flanks into the room like a 
black iceberg.  Ned Stanwell, who had just added his hat and great-coat to the miscellaneous heap on the divan, turned from the empty 
stove with a shiver. 
</p><p>"By Jove, this is a little too much like the last act of <hi rend="italic"> 
Boheme</hi>," he said, slipping into his coat again after a vain glance 
at the coal-scuttle.  Much solitude, and a lively habit of mind, 
had bred in him the habit of audible soliloquy, and having flung a 
shout for the janitor down the seven flights dividing the studio 
from the basement, he turned back, picking up the thread of his 
monologue.  "Exactly like <hi rend="italic"> Boheme</hi>, really&mdash;that crack in the 
wall is much more like a stage-crack than a real one&mdash;just the sort 
of crack Mungold would paint if he were doing a Humble Interior." 
</p><p>Mungold, the fashionable portrait-painter of the hour, was the 
favourite object of the younger men's irony. 
</p><p>"It only needs Kate Arran to be borne in dying," Stanwell 
continued with a laugh.  "Much more likely to be poor little 
Caspar, though," he concluded. 
</p><p>His neighbour across the landing&mdash;the little sculptor, Caspar 
Arran, humorously called "Gasper" on account of his bronchial 
asthma&mdash;had lately been joined by a sister, Kate Arran, a strapping 
girl, fresh <pb n="697"/>  from the country, who had installed herself in 
the little room off her brother's studio, keeping house for him 
with a chafing-dish and a coffee-machine, to the mirth and envy of 
the other young men in the building. 
</p><p>Poor little Gasper had been very bad all the autumn, and it 
was surmised that his sister's presence, which he spoke of 
growlingly, as a troublesome necessity devolved on him by the 
inopportune death of an aunt, was really an indication of his 
failing ability to take care of himself.  Kate Arran took his 
complaints with unfailing good-humour, darned his socks, brushed 
his clothes, fed him with steaming broths and foaming milk-punches, 
and listened with reverential assent to his interminable 
disquisitions on art.  Every one in the house was sorry for little 
Gasper, and the other fellows liked him all the more because it was 
so impossible to like his sculpture; but his talk was a bore, and 
when his colleagues ran in to see him they were apt to keep a hand 
on the door-knob and to plead a pressing engagement.  At least they 
had been till Kate came; but now they began to show a disposition 
to enter and sit down.  Caspar, who was no fool, perceived the 
change, and perhaps detected its cause; at any rate, he showed no 
special gratification at the increased cordiality of his friends, 
and Kate, who followed him in everything, took this as a sign that 
guests were to be discouraged. 
</p><p>There was one exception, however: Ned Stanwell, who was 
deplorably good-natured, had always lent a patient ear to Caspar, 
and he now reaped his reward by being taken into Kate's favour.  
Before she had been a month in the building they were on 
confidential terms as to Caspar's health, and lately Stanwell had 
penetrated farther, even to the inmost recesses of her anxiety 
about her brother's career.  Caspar had recently had a bad blow in 
the refusal of his <hi rend="italic"> magnum opus</hi>&mdash;a vast allegorical group&mdash;by 
the Commissioners of the Minneapolis Exhibition.  He took the 
rejection with Promethean irony, proclaimed it as the clinching 
proof of his ability, and abounded in reasons why, even in an age 
of such crass artistic ignorance, a refusal so egregious must react 
to the advantage of its object.  But his sister's indignation, if 
as glowing, was a shade less hopeful.  Of course Caspar was going 
to succeed&mdash;she knew it was only a question of time&mdash;but she paled 
at the word and turned imploring eyes on Stanwell.  <hi rend="italic"> Was there 
time enough?</hi>  It was the one element in the combination that she 
could not count on; and Stanwell, reddening under her look of 
interrogation, and cursing his own glaring robustness, would affirm 
that of course, of course, of course, by everything that was holy 
there was time enough&mdash;with the mental reservation that there 
wouldn't be, even if poor Caspar lived to be a hundred. 
</p><p>"Vos that you yelling for the shanitor, Mr. Sdanwell?" 
inquired an affable voice through the doorway; and Stanwell, 
turning with a laugh, confronted the squat figure of a middle-aged 
man in an expensive fur coat, who looked as if his face secreted 
the oil which he used on his hair. 
</p><p>"Hullo, Shepson&mdash;I should say I was yelling.  Did you ever 
feel such an atmosphere?  That fool has forgotten to light <pb n="698"/>  
the stove.  Come in, but for heaven's sake don't take off your 
coat." 
</p><p>Mr. Shepson glanced about the studio with a look which seemed 
to say that, where so much else was lacking, the absence of a fire 
hardly added to the general sense of destitution. 
</p><p>"Vell, you ain't as vell fixed as Mr. Mungold&mdash;ever been to 
his studio, Mr. Sdanwell?  De most ex<hi rend="italic"> quis</hi>ite blush hangings, 
and a gas-fire, choost as natural&mdash;" 
</p><p>"Oh, hang it, Shepson, do you call <hi rend="italic"> that</hi> a studio?  It's 
like a manicure's parlour&mdash;or a beauty-doctor's.  By George," broke 
off Stanwell, "and that's just what he is!" 
</p><p>"A peauty-doctor?" 
</p><p>"Yes&mdash;oh, well, you wouldn't see," murmured Stanwell, mentally 
storing his epigram for more appreciative ears.  "But you didn't 
come just to make me envious of Mungold's studio, did you?"  And he 
pushed forward a chair for his visitor. 
</p><p>The latter, however, declined it with an affable motion.  "Of 
gourse not, of gourse not&mdash;but Mr. Mungold is a sensible man.  He 
makes a lot of money, you know." 
</p><p>"Is that what you came to tell me?" said Stanwell, still 
humorously. 
</p><p>"My gootness, no&mdash;I was downstairs looking at Holbrook's 
sdained class, and I shoost thought I'd sdep up a minute and take 
a beep at your vork." 
</p><p>"Much obliged, I'm sure&mdash;especially as I assume that you don't 
want any of it."  Try as he would, Stanwell could not keep a note 
of eagerness from his voice.  Mr. Shepson caught the note, and eyed 
him shrewdly through gold-rimmed glasses. 
</p><p>"Vell, vell, vell&mdash;I'm not prepared to commit myself.  Shoost 
let me take a look round, vill you?" 
</p><p>"With the greatest pleasure&mdash;and I'll give another shout for 
the coal." 
</p><p>Stanwell went out on the landing, and Mr. Shepson, left to 
himself, began a meditative progress about the room.  On an easel 
facing the improvised dais stood a canvas on which a young woman's 
head had been blocked in.  It was just in that happy state of semi-evocation when a picture seems to detach itself from the grossness 
of its medium and live a wondrous moment in the actual; and the 
quality of the head in question&mdash;a vigorous dusky youthfulness, a 
kind of virgin majesty&mdash;lent itself to this illusion of vitality.  
Stanwell, who had re-entered the studio, could not help drawing a 
sharp breath as he saw the picture-dealer pausing with tilted head 
before this portrait: it seemed, at one moment, so impossible that 
he should not be struck with it, at the next so incredible that he 
should be. 
</p><p>Shepson cocked his parrot-eye at the canvas with a desultory 
"Vat's dat?" which sent a twinge through the young man. 
</p><p>"That?  Oh&mdash;a sketch of a young lady," stammered Stanwell, 
flushing at the imbecility of his reply.  "It's Miss Arran, you 
know," he added, "the sister of my neighbour here, the sculptor." 
</p><p>"Sgulpture?  There's no market for modern sgulpture except 
tombstones," said Shepson disparagingly, passing on as if he 
included the sister's portrait in his condemnation of her brother's 
trade. 
</p><p>Stanwell smiled, but more at himself than Shepson.  How could 
he ever have supposed that the gross fool would see anything in his 
sketch of Kate Arran?  He stood aside, straining after detachment, 
while the dealer continued his round of exploration, waddling up to 
the canvases on the walls, prodding with his stick at those stacked 
in corners, prying and peering sideways like a great bird rummaging 
for seed.  He seemed to find little nutriment in the course of his 
search, for the sounds he emitted expressed a weary distaste for 
misdirected effort, and he completed his round without having 
thought it worth while to draw a single canvas from its obscurity. 
</p><p>As his visits always had the same result, Stanwell was reduced 
to wondering why he had come again; but Shepson was not the man to 
indulge in vague roamings through the field of art, and it was safe 
to conclude that his purpose would in due course reveal itself.  
His tour brought him at length face to face with the painter, where 
he paused, clasping his plump gloved hands behind his back, and 
shaking an admonitory head. 
</p><p>"Gleffer&mdash;very gleffer, of course&mdash;I suppose you'll let me 
know when you want to sell anything?" 
</p><p>"Let you know?" gasped Stanwell, to whom the room grew so 
glowingly hot that he thought for a moment the janitor must have 
made up the fire. 
</p><p>Shepson gave a dry laugh.  "Vell, it <pb n="699"/>  doesn't sdrike me 
that you want to now&mdash;doing this kind of thing, you know!"  And he 
swept a comprehensive hand about the studio. 
</p><p>"Ah," said Stanwell, who could not keep a note of flatness out 
of his laugh. 
</p><p>"See here, Mr. Sdanwell, vot do you do it for?  If you do it 
for yourself and the other fellows, vell and good&mdash;only don't ask 
me round.  I sell pictures, I don't theorize about them.  Ven you 
vant to sell, gome to me with what my gustomers vant.  You can do 
it&mdash;you're smart enough.  You can do most anything.  Vere's dat 
bortrait of Gladys Glyde dat you showed at the Fake Club last 
autumn?  Dat little thing in de Romney sdyle?  Dat vas a little 
shem, now," exclaimed Mr. Shepson, whose pronunciation became 
increasingly Semitic in moments of excitement. 
</p><p>Stanwell stared.  Called upon a few months previously to 
contribute to an exhibition of skits on well-known artists, he had 
used the photograph of a favourite music-hall "star" as the basis 
of a picture in the pseudo-historical style affected by the popular 
portrait-painters of the day. 
</p><p>"That thing?" he said contemptuously.  "How on earth did you 
happen to see it?" 
</p><p>"I see everything," returned the dealer with an oracular 
smile.  "If you've got it here let me look at it, please." 
</p><p>It cost Stanwell a few minutes' search to unearth his skit&mdash;a 
clever blending of dash and sentimentality, in just the right 
proportion to create the impression of a powerful brush subdued to 
mildness by the charms of the sitter.  Stanwell had thrown it off 
in a burst of imitative frenzy, beginning for the mere joy of the 
satire, but gradually fascinated by the problem of producing the 
requisite mingling of attributes.  He was surprised now to see how 
well he had caught the note, and Shepson's face reflected his 
approval. 
</p><p>"By George!  Dat's something like," the dealer ejaculated. 
</p><p>"Like what?  Like Mungold?" Stanwell laughed. 
</p><p>"Like business!  Like a big order for a bortrait, Mr. 
Sdanwell&mdash;dat's what it's like!" cried Shepson, swinging round on 
him. 
</p><p>Stanwell's stare widened.  "An order for me?" 
</p><p>"Vy not?  Accidents <hi rend="italic"> vill</hi> happen," said Shepson jocosely.  
"De fact is, Mrs. Archer Millington wants to be bainted&mdash;you know 
her sdyle?  Well, she prides herself on her likeness to little 
Gladys.  And so ven she saw dat bicture of yours at de Fake Show 
she made a note of your name, and de udder day she sent for me and 
she says: 'Mr. Shepson, I'm tired of Mungold&mdash;all my friends are 
done by Mungold.  I vant to break away and be orishinal&mdash;I vant to 
be done by the bainter that did Gladys Glyde." 
</p><p>Shepson waited to observe the result of this overwhelming 
announcement, and Stanwell, after a momentary halt of surprise, 
brought out laughingly: "But this <hi rend="italic"> is</hi> a Mungold.  Is this what 
she calls being original?" 
</p><p>"Shoost exactly," said Shepson, with unexpected acuteness.  
"That's vat dey all want&mdash;something different from what all deir 
friends have got, but shoost like it all de same.  Dat's de public 
all over!  Mrs. Millington don't want a Mungold, because 
everybody's got a Mungold, but she wants a picture that's in the 
same sdyle, because dat's <hi rend="italic"> de</hi> sdyle, and she's afraid of any 
oder!" 
</p><p>Stanwell was listening with real enjoyment.  "Ah, you know 
your public," he murmured. 
</p><p>"Vell, you do, too, or you couldn't have painted dat," the 
dealer retorted.  "And I don't say dey're wrong&mdash;mind dat.  I like 
a bretty picture myself.  And I understand the way dey feel.  
Dey're villing to let Sargent take liberties vid them, because it's 
like being punched in de ribs by a King; but if anybody else baints 
them, they vant to look as sweet as an obituary."  He turned 
earnestly to Stanwell.  "The thing is to attract their notice.  
Vonce you got it they von't gif you dime to sleep.  And dat's why 
I'm here to-day&mdash;you've attracted Mrs. Millington's notice, and 
vonce you're hung in dat new ball-room&mdash;dat's vere she vants you, 
in a big gold panel&mdash;vonce you're dere, vy, you'll be like the 
Pianola&mdash;no home gompleat without you.  And I ain't going to charge 
you any commission on the first job!" 
</p><p>He stood before the painter, exuding a mixture of deference 
and patronage in which either element might predominate as events 
developed; but Stanwell could see in the incident only the stuff 
for a good story. <pb n="700"/>  
</p><p>"My dear Shepson," he said, "what are you talking about?  This 
is no picture of mine.  Why don't you ask me to do you a Corot at 
once?  I hear there's a great demand for them still in the West.  
Or an Arthur Schracker&mdash;I can do Schracker as well as Mungold," he 
added, turning around a small canvas at which a paint-pot seemed to 
have been hurled with violence from a considerable distance. 
</p><p>Shepson ignored the allusion to Corot, but screwed his eyes at 
the picture.  "Ah, Schracker&mdash;vell, the Schracker sdyle would take 
first rate if you were a foreigner&mdash;but, for goodness sake, don't 
try it on Mrs. Millington!" 
</p><p>Stanwell pushed the two skits aside.  "Oh, you can trust me," 
he cried humorously.  "The pearls and the eyes very large&mdash;the 
extremities very small.  Isn't that about the size of it?" 
</p><p>Dat's it&mdash;dat's it.  And the cheque as big as you vant to make 
it!  Mrs. Millington vants the picture finished in time for her 
first barty in the new ball-room, and if you rush the job she won't 
sdickle at an extra thousand.  Vill you come along with me now and 
arrange for your first sitting?" 
</p><p>He stood before the young man, urgent, paternal, and so imbued 
with the importance of his mission that his face stretched to a 
ludicrous length of dismay when Stanwell, administering a good-humoured push to his shoulder, cried gaily: "My dear fellow, it 
will make my price rise still higher when the lady hears I'm too 
busy to take any orders at present&mdash;and that I'm actually obliged 
to turn you out now because I'm expecting a sitter!" 
</p><p>It was part of Shepson's business to have a quick ear for the 
note of finality, and he offered no resistance to Stanwell's 
friendly impulsion; but on the threshold he paused to murmur, with 
a regretful glance at the denuded studio: "You could haf done it, 
Mr. Sdanwell&mdash;you could haf done it!" 
</p></div2> 
<div2 type="chapter" n="2" id="d5"> 
<head> 
II 
</head> 
<p>KATE ARRAN was Stanwell's sitter; but the janitor had hardly 
filled the stove when she came in to say that she could not sit.  
Caspar had had a bad night: he was depressed and feverish, and in 
spite of his protests she had resolved to fetch the doctor.  Care 
sat on her usually tranquil features, and Stanwell, as he offered 
to go for the doctor, wished he could have caught in his picture 
the wide gloom of her brow.  There was always a kind of Biblical 
breadth in the expression of her emotions, and today she suggested 
a text from Isaiah. 
</p><p>"But you're not busy?" she hesitated; in the full voice which 
seemed tuned to a solemn rhetoric. 
</p><p>"I meant to be&mdash;with you.  But since that's off I'm quite 
unemployed." 
</p><p>She smiled interrogatively.  "I thought perhaps you had an 
order.  I met Mr. Shepson rubbing his hands on the landing." 
</p><p>"Was he rubbing his hands?  Well, it was not over me.  He says 
that from the style of my pictures he doesn't suppose I want to 
sell." 
</p><p>She looked at him superbly.  "Well, do you?" 
</p><p>He embraced his bleak walls in a circular gesture.  "Judge for 
yourself!" 
</p><p>"Ah, but it's splendidly furnished!" <pb n="701"/>  
</p><p>"With rejected pictures, you mean?" 
</p><p>"With ideals!" she exclaimed in a tone caught from her 
brother, and which would have been irritating to Stanwell if it had 
not been moving. 
</p><p>He gave a slight shrug and took up his hat; but she interposed 
to say that if it didn't make any difference she would prefer to 
have him go and sit with poor Caspar, while she ran for the doctor 
and did some household errands by the way.  Stanwell divined in her 
request the need for a brief respite from Caspar, and though he 
shivered at the thought of her facing the cold in the scant jacket 
which had been her only wear since he had known her, he let her go 
without a protest, and betook himself to Arran's studio. 
</p><p>He found the little sculptor dressed and roaming fretfully 
about the melancholy room in which he and his plastic off-spring 
lodged together.  In one corner, where Kate's chair and work-table 
stood, a scrupulous order prevailed; but the rest of the apartment 
had the dreary untidiness, the damp grey look, which the worker in 
clay usually creates about him.  In the centre of this desert stood 
the shrouded image of Caspar's disappointment: the colossal 
rejected group as to which his friends could seldom remember 
whether it represented Jove hurling a Titan from Olympus or Science 
Subjugating Religion.  Caspar was the sworn foe of religion, which 
he appeared to regard as indirectly connected with his inability to 
sell his statues. 
</p><p>The sculptor was too ill to work, and Stanwell's appearance 
loosed the pent-up springs of his talk. 
</p><p>"Hullo!  What are you doing here?  I thought Kate had gone 
over to sit to you.  She wanted a little fresh air?  I should say 
enough of it came in through these windows.  How like a woman, when 
she's agreed to do a certain thing, to make up her mind at once 
that she's got to do another!  They don't call it caprice&mdash;it's 
always duty: that's the humour of it.  I'll be bound Kate alleged 
a pressing engagement.  Sorry she should waste your time so, my 
dear fellow.  Here am I with plenty of it to burn&mdash;look at my hand 
shake; I can't do a thing!  Well, luckily nobody wants me to&mdash; 
posterity may suffer, but the present generation isn't worrying.  
The present generation wants to be carved in sugar-candy, or 
painted in maple syrup.  It doesn't want to be told the truth about 
itself or about anything in the universe.  The prophets have always 
lived in a garret, my dear fellow&mdash;only the ravens don't always 
find out their address!  Speaking of ravens, though, Kate told me 
she saw old Shepson coming out of your place&mdash;I say, old man, 
you're not meditating an apostasy?  You're not doing the kind of 
thing that Shepson would look at?" 
</p><p>Stanwell laughed.  "Oh, he looked at them&mdash;but only to confirm 
his reasons for rejecting them." 
</p><p>"Ha! ha!  That's right&mdash;he wanted to refresh his memory with 
their badness.  But how on earth did he happen to have any doubts 
on the subject?  I should as soon have thought of his coming in 
here!" 
</p><p>Stanwell winced at the analogy, but replied in Caspar's key: 
"Oh, he's not as sure of any of us as he is of you!" 
</p><p>The sculptor received this tribute with a joyous expletive.  
"By God, no, he's sure of me, as you say!  He and his tribe know 
that I'll starve in my tracks sooner than make a concession&mdash;a 
single concession.  A fellow came after me once to do an angel on 
<pb n="702"/>  a tombstone&mdash;an angel leaning against a broken column, and 
looking as if it was waiting for the elevator and wondering why in 
hell it didn't come.  He said he wanted me to show that the 
deceased was pining to get to heaven.  As she was his wife I didn't 
dispute the proposition, but when I asked him what he understood by 
<hi rend="italic"> heaven</hi> he grabbed his hat and walked out of the studio.  <hi rend="italic"> He</hi> 
didn't wait for the elevator." 
</p><p>Stanwell listened with a practised smile.  The story of the 
man who had come to order the angel was so familiar to Arran's 
friends that its only interest consisted in waiting to see what 
variation he would give to the retort which had put the mourner to 
flight.  It was generally supposed that this visit represented the 
sculptor's nearest approach to an order, and one of his fellow-craftsmen had been heard to remark that if Caspar <hi rend="italic"> had</hi> made the 
tombstone, the lady under it would have tried harder than ever to 
get to heaven.  To Stanwell's present mood, however, there was 
something more than usually irritating in the gratuitous assumption 
that Arran had only to derogate from his altitude to have a press 
of purchasers at his door. 
</p><p>"Well&mdash;what did you gain by kicking your widower out?" he 
objected.  "Why can't a man do two kinds of work&mdash;one to please 
himself and the other to boil the pot?" 
</p><p>Caspar stopped in his jerky walk&mdash;the stride of a tall man 
attempted with short legs (it sometimes appeared to Stanwell to 
symbolize his artistic endeavour). 
</p><p>"Why can't a man&mdash;why can't he?  You ask me that, Stanwell?" 
he blazed out. 
</p><p>"Yes; and what's more, I'll answer you: it isn't everybody who 
can adapt his art as he wants to!" 
</p><p>Caspar stood before him, gasping with incredulous scorn.  
"Adapt his art?  As he wants to?  Unhappy wretch, what lingo are 
you talking?  If you mean that it isn't every honest man who can be 
a renegade&mdash;" 
</p><p>"That's just what I do mean: he can't unless he's clever 
enough to see the other side." 
</p><p>The deep groan with which Caspar met this casuistry was cut 
short by a knock at the studio door, which thereupon opened to 
admit a small dapperly-dressed man with a silky moustache and 
mildly-bulging eyes. 
</p><p>"Ah, Mungold," exclaimed Stanwell, to cover the gloomy silence 
with which Arran received the new-comer; whereat the latter, with 
the air of a man who does not easily believe himself unwelcome, 
bestowed a sympathetic pressure on the sculptor's hand. <pb n="703"/>  
</p><p>"My dear chap, I've just met Miss Arran, and she told me you 
were laid up with a bad cold, so I thought I'd pop in and cheer you 
up a little." 
</p><p>He looked about him with a smile evidently intended as the 
first act in his beneficent programme. 
</p><p>Mr. Mungold, freshly soaped and scented, with a neat glaze of 
gentility extending from his varnished boot-tips to his glossy hat, 
looked like the "flattered" portrait of a common man&mdash;just such an 
idealized presentment as his own brush might have produced.  As a 
rule, however, he devoted himself to the portrayal of the other 
sex, painting ladies in syrup, as Arran said, with marsh-mallow 
children leaning against their knees.  He was as quick as a 
dressmaker at catching new ideas, and the style of his pictures 
changed as rapidly as that of the fashion-plates.  One year all his 
sitters were done on oval canvases, with gauzy draperies and a 
background of clouds; the next they were seated under an immemorial 
elm, caressing enormous dogs obviously constructed out of door-mats.  Whatever their occupation they always looked straight out of 
the canvas, giving the impression that their eyes were fixed on an 
invisible camera.  This gave rise to the rumour that Mungold "did" 
his portraits from photographs; it was even said that he had 
invented a way of transferring an enlarged photograph to the 
canvas, so that all that remained was to fill in the colours.  If 
he heard of this charge he took it calmly, but probably it had not 
reached the high spheres in which he moved, and in which he was 
esteemed for painting pearls better, and making unsuggestive 
children look lovelier, than any of his fellow-craftsmen.  Mr. 
Mungold, in fact, deemed it a part of his professional duty to 
study his sitters in their home-life; and as this life was chiefly 
led in the homes of others, he was too busy dining out and going to 
the opera to mingle much with his colleagues.  But as no one is 
wholly consistent, Mr. Mungold had lately belied his ambitions by 
falling in love with Kate Arran; and with that gentle persistency 
which made him so wonderful in managing obstreperous infantile 
sitters, he had contrived to establish a precarious footing in her 
brother's studio. 
</p><p>Part of his success was due to the fact that he could not 
easily think himself the object of a rebuff.  If it seemed to hit 
him he regarded it as deflected from its aim, and brushed it aside 
with a discreet gesture.  A touch of comedy was lent to the 
situation by the fact that, till Kate Arran's coming, Mungold had 
always served as her brother's Awful Example.  It was a mark of 
Arran's lack of humour that he persisted in regarding the little 
man as a conscious apostate, instead of perceiving that he painted 
as he could, in a world which really looked to him like a vast 
confectioner's window.  Stanwell had never quite divined how 
Mungold had won over the sister, to whom her brother's prejudices 
were a religion; but he suspected the painter of having united a 
deep belief in Caspar's gifts with the occasional offer of 
opportune delicacies&mdash;the port-wine or game which Kate had no other 
means of procuring for her patient. <pb n="704"/>  
</p><p>Stanwell, persuaded that Mungold would stick to his post till 
Miss Arran's return, felt himself freed from his promise to the 
latter and left the incongruous pair to themselves.  There had been 
a time when it amused him to see Caspar submerge the painter in a 
torrent of turbid eloquence, and to watch poor Mungold sputtering 
under the rush of denunciation, yet emitting little bland phrases 
of assent, like a gentleman drowning correctly, in gloves and eye-glasses.  But Stanwell was beginning to find less food for gaiety 
than for envy in the contemplation of his colleague.  After all, 
Mungold held his ground, he did not go under.  Spite of his 
manifest absurdity he had succeeded in propitiating the sister, in 
making himself tolerated by the brother; and the fact that his 
success was due to the ability to purchase port-wine and game was 
not in this case a mitigating circumstance.  Stanwell knew that the 
Arrans really preferred him to Mungold, but the knowledge only 
sharpened his envy of the latter, whose friendship could command 
visible tokens of expression, while poor Stanwell's remained 
gloomily inarticulate.  As he returned to his over-populated studio 
and surveyed anew the pictures of which Shepson had not offered to 
relieve him, he found himself wishing, not for Mungold's lack of 
scruples, for he believed him to be the most scrupulous of men, but 
for that happy mean of talent which so completely satisfied the 
artistic requirements of the inartistic.  Mungold was not to be 
despised as an apostate&mdash;he was to be congratulated as a man whose 
aptitudes were exactly in line with the taste of the persons he 
liked to dine with. 
</p><p>At this point in his meditations, Stanwell's eye fell on the 
portrait of Miss Gladys Glyde.  It was really, as Shepson said, as 
good as a Mungold; yet it could never be made to serve the same 
purpose, because it was the work of a man who knew it was bad art.  
That at least would have been Caspar Arran's contention&mdash;poor 
Caspar, who produced as bad art in the service of the loftiest 
convictions!  The distinction began to look like mere casuistry to 
Stanwell.  He had never been very proud of his own adaptability.  
It had seemed to him to indicate the lack of an individual stand-point, and he had tried to counteract it by the cultivation of an 
aggressively personal style.  But the cursed knack was in his 
fingers&mdash;he was always at the mercy of some other man's sensations, 
and there were moments when he blushed to remember that his 
grandfather had spent a laborious life-time in Rome, copying the 
Old Masters for a generation which lacked the facile resource of 
the camera.  Now, however, it struck him that the ancestral 
versatility might be a useful inheritance.  In art, after all, the 
greatest of them did what they could; and if a man could do several 
things instead of one, why should he not profit by the multiplicity 
of his gifts?  If one had two talents why not serve two masters? 
</p></div2> 
<div2 type="chapter" n="3" id="d6"> 
<head> 
III 
</head> 
<p>STANWELL, while seeing Caspar through the attack which had 
been the cause of his sister's arrival, had struck up a friendship 
with the young doctor who climbed the patient's seven flights with 
unremitting fidelity.  The two, since then, had continued to 
exchange confidences regarding the sculptor's health, and Stanwell, 
anxious to waylay the doctor after his visit, left the studio door 
ajar, and went out when he heard a sound of leave-taking across the 
landing.  But it appeared that the doctor had just come, and that 
it was Mungold who was making his adieux. 
</p><p>The latter at once assumed that Stanwell had been on the alert 
for him, and met the supposed advance by affably inviting himself 
into the studio. 
</p><p>"May I come and take a look around, my dear fellow?  I have 
been meaning to drop in for an age&mdash;"  Mungold always spoke with a 
girlish emphasis and effusiveness&mdash;"but I have been so busy getting 
up Mrs. Van Orley's tableaux&mdash;English eighteenth century portraits, 
you know&mdash;that really, what with that and my sittings, I've hardly 
had time to think.  And then you know you owe me about a dozen 
visits!  But you're a savage&mdash;you don't pay visits.  You stay here 
and <hi rend="italic"> piocher</hi>&mdash;which is wiser, as the results prove.  Ah, you're 
very strong&mdash;immensely strong!"  He paused in the middle of the 
studio, glancing about a little apprehensively, as though he 
thought the stored energy of the pictures might result in an 
explosion.  "Very original&mdash;very striking&mdash;ah, Miss Arran!  A 
powerful head; but&mdash;excuse the suggestion&mdash;isn't there <pb n="705"/>  just 
the least little lack of sweetness?  You don't think she has the 
sweet type?  Perhaps not&mdash;but could she be so lovely if she were 
not intensely feminine?  Just at present, though, she is not 
looking her best&mdash;she is horribly tired.  I am afraid there is very 
little money left&mdash;and poor dear Caspar is so impossible: he won't 
hear of a loan.  Otherwise I should be most happy&mdash;.  But I came 
just now to propose a piece of work&mdash;in fact to give him an order.  
Mrs. Archer Millington has built a new ball-room, as I daresay you 
may have seen in the papers, and she has been kind enough to ask me 
for some hints&mdash;oh, merely as a friend: I don't presume to do more 
than advise.  But her decorator wants to do something with Cupids&mdash; 
something light and playful, you understand.  And so I ventured to 
say that I knew a very clever sculptor&mdash;well, I <hi rend="italic"> do</hi> believe 
Caspar has talent&mdash;latent talent, you know&mdash;and at any rate a job 
of that sort would be a big lift for him.  At least I thought he 
would regard it so; but you should have heard him when I showed him 
the decorator's sketch.  He asked me what the Cupids were to be 
done in&mdash;lard?  And if I thought he had had his training at a 
confectioner's?  And I don't know what more besides&mdash;but he worked 
himself up to such a degree that he brought on a frightful fit of 
coughing, and Miss Arran, I'm afraid, was rather annoyed with me 
when she came in, though I'm sure an order from Mrs. Archer 
Millington is not a thing that would annoy most people!" 
</p><p>Mr. Mungold paused, breathless with the rehearsal of his 
wrongs, and Stanwell said with a smile: "You know poor Caspar is 
terribly stiff on the purity of the artist's aim." 
</p><p>"The artist's aim?"  Mr. Mungold stared.  "What is the 
artist's aim but to please&mdash;isn't that the purpose of all true art?  
But his theories are so extravagant.  I really don't know what I 
shall say to Mrs. Millington&mdash;she is not used to being refused.  I 
suppose I had better put it on the ground of ill-health."  The 
artist glanced at his handsome repeater.  "Dear me, I promised to 
be at Mrs. Van Orley's before twelve o'clock.  We are to settle 
about the curtain before luncheon.  My dear fellow, it has been a 
privilege to see your work.  By the way, you have never done any 
modelling, I suppose?  You're so extraordinarily versatile&mdash;I 
didn't know whether you might care to undertake the Cupids 
yourself." 
 
</p><p>Stanwell had to wait a long time for the doctor; and when the 
latter came out he looked grave.  Worse?  No, he couldn't say that 
Caspar was worse&mdash;but then he wasn't any better.  There was nothing 
mortal the matter, but the question was how long he could hold out.  
It was the kind of case where there is no use in drugs&mdash;he had just 
scribbled a prescription to quiet Miss Arran. 
</p><p>"It's the cold, I suppose," Stanwell groaned.  "He ought to be 
shipped off to Florida." 
</p><p>The doctor made a negative gesture.  "Florida be hanged!  What 
he wants is to sell his group.  That would set him up quicker than 
sitting on the equator." 
</p><p>"Sell his group?" Stanwell echoed.  "But he's so indifferent 
to recognition&mdash;he believes in himself so thoroughly.  I thought at 
first he would be hard hit when the Exhibition Committee refused 
it, but he seems to regard that as another proof of its 
superiority." 
</p><p>His visitor turned on him the penetrating eye of the 
confessor.  "Indifferent to recognition?  He's eating his heart out 
for it.  Can't you see that all that talk is just so much whistling 
to keep his courage up?  The name of his disease is failure&mdash;and I 
can't write the prescription that will cure that complaint.  But if 
somebody would come along and take a fancy to those two naked 
parties who are breaking each other's heads, we'd have Mr. Caspar 
putting on a pound a day." 
</p><p>The truth of this diagnosis became suddenly vivid to Stanwell.  
How dull of him not to have seen before that it was not cold or 
privation which was killing Caspar&mdash;not anxiety for his sister's 
future, nor the ache of watching her daily struggle&mdash;but simply the 
cankering thought that he might die before he had made himself 
known!  It was his vanity that was starving to death, and all 
Mungold's hampers could not appease that hunger.  Stanwell was not 
shocked by the discovery&mdash;he was only the more sorry for the little 
man, who was, after all, denied that solace of self-sufficiency 
which his talk so noisily pro-<pb n="706"/> claimed.  His lot seemed hard 
enough when Stanwell had pictured him as buoyed up by the scorn of 
public opinion&mdash;it became tragic if he was denied that support.  
The artist wondered if Kate had guessed her brother's secret, or if 
she were still the dupe of his stoicism.  Stanwell was sure that 
the sculptor would take no one into his confidence, and least of 
all his sister, whose faith in his artistic independence was the 
chief prop of that tottering pose.  Kate's penetration was not 
great, and Stanwell recalled the incredulous smile with which she 
had heard him defend poor Mungold's "sincerity" against Caspar's 
assaults; but she had the insight of the heart, and where her 
brother's happiness was concerned she might have seen deeper than 
any of them.  It was this last consideration which took the 
strongest hold on Stanwell&mdash;he felt Caspar's sufferings chiefly 
through the thought of his sister's possible disillusionment. 
</p></div2> 
<div2 type="chapter" n="4" id="d7"> 
<head>                                 
IV 
</head> 
<p>WITHIN three months two events had set the studio building 
talking.  Stanwell had painted a full-length portrait of Mrs. 
Archer Millington, and Caspar Arran had received an order to 
execute his group in marble. 
</p><p>The name of the sculptor's patron had not been divulged.  The 
order came through Shepson, who explained that an American customer 
living abroad, having seen a photograph of the group in one of the 
papers, had at once cabled home to secure it.  He intended to 
bestow it on a public building in America, and not wishing to 
advertise his munificence, had preferred that even the sculptor 
should remain ignorant of his name.  The group bought by an 
enlightened compatriot for the adornment of a civic building in his 
native land!  There could hardly be a more complete vindication of 
unappreciated genius, and Caspar made the most of the argument.  He 
was not exultant, he was sublimely magnanimous.  He had always said 
that he could afford to await the Verdict of Posterity, and his 
unknown patron's act clearly shadowed forth that impressive 
decision.  Happily it also found expression in a cheque which it 
would have taken more philosophy to await.  The group was paid for 
in advance, and Kate's joy in her brother's recognition was 
deliciously mingled with the thrill of ordering him some new 
clothes, and coaxing him out to dine succulently at a neighbouring 
restaurant.  Caspar flourished insufferably on this regime: he 
began to strike the attitude of the recognized Great Master, who 
gives advice and encouragement to the struggling neophyte.  He held 
himself up as an example of the reward of disinterestedness, of the 
triumph of the artist who clings obstinately to his convictions. 
</p><p>"A man must believe in his star&mdash;look at Napoleon!  It's the 
dogged trust in one's convictions that tells&mdash;it always ends by 
forcing the public into line.  Only be sure you make no 
concessions&mdash;don't give in to any of their humbug!  An artist who 
lis-<pb n="707"/> tens to the critics is ruined&mdash;they never have any use 
for the poor devils who do what they tell them to.  Run after fame 
and she'll keep you running, but stay in your own corner and do 
your own work, and by George, sir, she'll come crawling up to you 
and ask to have her likeness done!" 
</p><p>These exhortations were chiefly directed to Stanwell, partly 
because the inmates of the other studios were apt to elude them, 
partly also because the rumours concerning Stanwell's portrait of 
Mrs. Millington had begun to disquiet the sculptor.  At first he 
had taken a condescending interest in the fact of his friend's 
receiving an order, and had admonished him not to lose the chance 
of "showing up" his sitter and her environment.  It was a splendid 
opportunity for a fellow with a "message" to be introduced into the 
tents of the Philistine, and Stanwell was charged to drive a long 
sharp nail into the enemy's skull.  But presently Arran began to 
suspect that the portrait was not as comminatory as he could have 
wished.  Mungold, the most kindly of rivals, let drop a word of 
injudicious praise: the picture, he said, promised to be 
delightfully "in keeping" with the decorations of the ball-room, 
and the lady's gown harmonized exquisitely with the window-curtains.  Stanwell, called to account by his monitor, reminded the 
latter that he himself had been selected by Mungold to do the 
Cupids for Mrs. Millington's ball-room, and that the friendly 
artist's praise could, therefore, not be taken as positive evidence 
of incapacity. 
</p><p>"Ah, but I didn't do them&mdash;I kicked him out!" Caspar rejoined; 
and Stanwell could only plead that, even in the cause of art, one 
could hardly kick a lady. 
</p><p>"Ah, that's the worst of it.  If the women get at you you're 
lost.  You're young, you're impressionable, you won't mind my 
saying that you're not built for a stoic, and hang it, they'll 
coddle you, they'll enervate you, they'll sentimentalize you, 
they'll make a Mungold of you!" 
</p><p>"Ah, poor Mungold," Stanwell laughed.  "If he lived the life 
of an anchorite he couldn't help painting pictures that would 
please Mrs. Millington." 
</p><p>"Whereas you could," Kate interjected, raising her head from 
the ironing-board where, Sphinx-like, magnificent, she swung a 
splendid arm above her brother's shirts. 
</p><p>"Oh, well, perhaps I shan't please her; perhaps I shall 
elevate her taste." 
</p><p>Caspar directed a groan to his sister.  "That's what they all 
think at first&mdash;Childe Roland to the Dark Tower came.  But inside 
the Dark Tower there's the Venusberg.  Oh, I don't mean that you'll 
be taken with truffles and plush footmen, like Mungold.  But 
praise, my poor Ned&mdash;praise is a deadly drug!  It's the absinthe of 
the artist&mdash;and they'll stupefy you with it.  You'll wallow in the 
mire of success." 
</p><p>Stanwell raised a protesting hand.  "Really, for one order, 
you're a little lurid!" <pb n="708"/>  
</p><p>"One?  Haven't you already had a dozen others?" 
</p><p>"Only one other, so far&mdash;and I'm not sure I shall do that." 
</p><p>"Not sure&mdash;wavering already!  That's the way the mischief 
begins.  If the women get a fad for you they'll work you like a 
galley-slave.  You'll have to do your round of 'copy' every 
morning.  What becomes of inspiration then?  How are you going to 
loaf and invite the soul?  Don't barter your birthright for a mess 
of pottage!  Oh, I understand the temptation&mdash;I know the taste of 
money and success.  But look at me, Stanwell.  You know how long I 
had to wait for recognition.  Well, now it's come to me I don't 
mean to let it knock me off my feet.  I don't mean to let myself be 
overworked; I have already made it known that I will not be bullied 
into taking more orders than I can do full justice to.  And my 
sister is with me, God bless her; Kate would rather go on ironing 
my shirts in a garret than see me prostitute my art!" 
</p><p>Kate's glance radiantly confirmed this declaration of 
independence, and Stanwell, with his evasive laugh, asked her if, 
meanwhile, she should object to his investing a part of his ill-gotten gains in theatre tickets for the party that evening. 
</p><p>It appeared that Stanwell had also been paid in advance, and 
well paid; for he began to permit himself various mild 
distractions, in which he generally contrived to have the Arrans 
share.  It seemed perfectly natural to Kate that Caspar's friends 
should spend their money for his recreation, and by one of the most 
touching sophistries of her sex she thus reconciled herself to the 
anomaly of taking a little pleasure on her own account.  Mungold 
was less often in the way, for she had never been able to forgive 
him for proposing that Caspar should do Mrs. Millington's Cupids; 
and for a few radiant weeks Stanwell had the undisputed enjoyment 
of her pride in her brother's achievement. 
</p><p>Stanwell had "rushed through" Mrs. Millington's portrait in 
time for the opening of her new ball-room; and it was perhaps in 
return for this favour that she consented to let the picture be 
exhibited at a big Portrait Show which was held in April for the 
benefit of a fashionable charity. 
</p><p>In Mrs. Millington's ball-room the picture had been seen and 
approved only by the distinguished few who had access to that 
social sanctuary; but on the walls of the exhibition it became a 
centre of comment and discussion.  One of the immediate results of 
this publicity was a visit from Shepson, with two or three orders 
in his pocket, as he put it.  He surveyed the studio with fresh 
disgust, asked Stanwell why he did not move, and was impressed 
rather than downcast on learning that the painter had not decided 
whether he would take any more orders that spring. 
</p><p>"You might haf a studio at Newport," he suggested.  "It would 
be rather new to do your sitters out of doors, with the sea behind 
them&mdash;showing they had a blace on the gliffs!" 
</p><p>The picture produced a different and less flattering effect on 
the critics.  They gave it, indeed, more space than they had ever 
before accorded to the artist's efforts, but their estimate seemed 
to confirm Caspar Arran's forebodings, and Stanwell had perhaps 
never despised them so little as when he read their comments on his 
work.  On the whole, however, neither praise nor blame disquieted 
him greatly.  He was engrossed in the contemplation of Kate Arran's 
happiness, and basking in the refracted warmth it shed about her.  
The doctor's prognostications had come true.  Caspar was putting on 
a pound a week, and had plunged into a fresh "creation" more 
symbolic and encumbering than the monument of which he had been so 
opportunely relieved.  If there was any cloud on Stanwell's 
enjoyment of life, it was caused by the discovery that success had 
quadrupled Caspar's artistic energies.  Meanwhile it was delightful 
to see Kate's joy in her brother's recovered capacity for work, and 
to listen to the axioms which, for Stanwell's guidance, she deduced 
from the example of Caspar's heroic pursuit of the ideal.  There 
was nothing repellent in Kate's borrowed didacticism, and if it 
sometimes bored Stanwell to hear her quote her brother, he was sure 
it would never bore him to be quoted by her himself; and there were 
moments when he felt he had nearly achieved that distinction. 
</p><p>Caspar was not addicted to the visiting of art exhibitions.  
He took little interest in any productions save his own, and was 
moreover disposed to believe that good pictures, like clever 
criminals, are apt to go <pb n="709"/>  unhung.  Stanwell therefore 
thought it unlikely that his portrait of Mrs. Millington would be 
seen by Kate, who was not given to independent explorations in the 
field of art; but one day, on entering the exhibition&mdash;which he had 
hitherto rather nervously shunned&mdash;he saw the Arrans at the end of 
the gallery in which the portrait hung.  They were not looking at 
it, they were moving away from it, and to Stanwell's quickened 
perceptions their attitude seemed almost that of flight.  For a 
moment he thought of flying too; then a desperate resolve nerved 
him to meet them, and stemming the crowd, he made a circuit which 
brought him face to face with their retreat. 
</p><p>The room in which they met was momentarily empty, and there 
was nothing to intervene between the shock of their inter-changed 
glances.  Caspar was flushed and bristling: his little body 
quivered like a machine from which the steam has just been turned 
off.  Kate lifted a stricken glance.  Stanwell read in it the 
reflexion of her brother's tirade, but she held out her hand in 
silence. 
</p><p>For a moment Caspar was silent too; then, with a terrible 
smile: "My dear fellow, I congratulate you; Mungold will have to 
look to his laurels," he said. 
</p><p>The shot delivered, he stalked away with his seven-league 
stride, and Kate moved tragically through the room in his wake. 
</p></div2> 
<div2 type="chapter" n="5" id="d8"> 
<head> 
V 
</head> 
<p>SHEPSON took up his hat with a despairing gesture. 
</p><p>"Vell, I gif you up&mdash;I gif you up!" he said. 
</p><p>"Don't&mdash;yet," protested Stanwell from the divan. 
</p><p>It was winter again, and though the janitor had not forgotten 
the fire, the studio gave no other evidence of its master's 
increasing prosperity.  If Stanwell spent his money it was not upon 
himself. 
</p><p>He leaned back against the wall, his hands in his pockets, a 
cigarette between his lips, while Shepson paced the dirty floor or 
halted impatiently before an untouched canvas on the easel. 
</p><p>"I tell you vat it is, Mr. Sdanwell, I can't make you out!" he 
lamented.  "Last vinter you got a sdart that vould have kept most 
men going for years.  After making dat hit vith Mrs. Millington's 
picture you could have bainted half the town.  And here you are 
sitting on your divan and saying you can't make up your mind to 
take another order.  Vell, I can only say that if you take much 
longer to make it up, you'll find some other chap has cut in and 
got your job.  Mrs. Van Orley has been waiting since last August, 
and she dells me you haven't even answered her letter." 
</p><p>"How could I?  I didn't know if I wanted to paint her." 
</p><p>"My goodness!  Don't you know if you vant three thousand 
tollars?" 
</p><p>Stanwell surveyed his cigarette.  "No, I'm not sure I do," he 
said. 
</p><p>Shepson flung out his hands.  "Ask more den&mdash;but do it quick!" 
he exclaimed. 
</p><p>Left to himself, Stanwell stood in silent contemplation of the 
canvas on which the dealer had riveted his reproachful gaze.  It 
had been destined to reflect the opulent image of Mrs. Alpheus Van 
Orley, but some secret reluctance of Stanwell's had stayed the 
execution of the task.  He had painted two of Mrs. Millington's 
friends in the spring, had been much praised and liberally paid for 
his work, and then, declining several recent orders to be executed 
at Newport, had surprised his friends by remaining quietly in town.  
It was not till August that he hired a little cottage on the New 
Jersey coast and invited the Arrans to visit him.  They accepted 
the invitation, and the three had spent together six weeks of 
seashore idleness, during which Stanwell's modest rafters shook 
with Caspar's denunciations of his host's venality, and the 
brightness of Kate's gratitude was tempered by a tinge of reproach.  
But her grief over Stanwell's apostasy could not efface the fact 
that he had offered her brother the means of escape from town, and 
Stanwell himself was consoled by the reflection that but for Mrs. 
Millington's portrait he could not have performed even this 
trifling service for his friends. 
</p><p>When the Arrans left him in September he went to pay a few 
visits in the country, and on his return, a month later, to the 
studio building he found that things had not gone well with Caspar.  
The little sculptor had caught cold, and the labour and expense of 
converting his gigantic off-<pb n="710"/> spring into marble seemed to 
hang heavily upon him.  He and Kate were living in a damp company 
of amorphous clay monsters, unfinished witnesses to the creative 
frenzy which had seized him after the sale of his group; and the 
doctor had urged that his patient should be removed to warmer and 
drier lodgings.  But to uproot Caspar was impossible, and his 
sister could only feed the stove, and swaddle him in mufflers and 
felt slippers. 
</p><p>Stanwell found that during his absence Mungold had reappeared, 
fresh and rosy from a summer in Europe, and as prodigal as ever of 
the only form of attention which Kate could be counted on not to 
resent.  The game and champagne reappeared with him, and he seemed 
as ready as Stanwell to lend a patient ear to Caspar's homilies.  
But Stanwell could see that, even now, Kate had not forgiven him 
for the Cupids.  Stanwell himself had spent the early winter months 
in idleness.  The sight of his tools filled him with a strange 
repugnance, and he absented himself as much as possible from the 
studio.  But Shepson's visit roused him to the fact that he must 
decide on some definite course of action.  If he wished to follow 
up his success of the previous spring he must refuse no more 
orders: he must not let Mrs. Van Orley slip away from him.  He knew 
there were competitors enough ready to profit by his hesitations, 
and since his success was the result of a whim, a whim might undo 
it.  With a sudden gesture of decision he caught up his hat and 
left the studio. 
</p><p>On the landing he met Kate Arran.  She too was going out, 
drawn forth by the sudden radiance of the January afternoon.  She 
met him with a smile which seemed the answer to his uncertainties, 
and he asked abruptly if she had time to take a walk with him. 
</p><p>Yes; for once she had time, for Mr. Mungold was sitting with 
Caspar, and had promised to remain till she came in.  It mattered 
little to Stanwell that Mungold was with Caspar as long as he 
himself was with Kate; and he instantly soared to the suggestion 
that they should prolong the painter's vigil by taking the 
"elevated" to the Park.  In this too his companion acquiesced after 
a moment of surprise: she seemed in a consenting mood, and Stanwell 
augured well from the fact. 
</p><p>The Park was clothed in the double glitter of snow and 
sunshine.  They roamed the hard white alleys to a continuous tinkle 
of sleigh-bells, and Kate brightened with the exhilaration of the 
scene.  It was not often that she permitted herself such an escape 
from routine, and in this new environment, which seemed to detach 
her from her daily setting, Stanwell had his first complete vision 
of her.  To the girl also their unwonted isolation seemed to create 
a sense of fuller communion, for she began presently, as they 
reached the leafless solitude of the Ramble, to speak with sudden 
freedom of her brother.  It appeared that the orders against which 
Caspar had so heroically steeled himself were slow in coming: he 
had received no commission since the sale of his group, and he was 
beginning to suffer from a reaction of discouragement.  Oh, it was 
not the craving for popularity&mdash;Stanwell knew how far above that he 
stood.  But it had been exquisite, yes, exquisite to him to find 
himself believed in, understood.  He had fancied that the purchase 
of the group was the dawn of a tardy recognition&mdash;and now the 
darkness of indifference had set in again, no one spoke of him, no 
one wrote of him, no one cared. 
</p><p>"If he were in good health it would not matter&mdash;he would throw 
off such weakness, he would live only for the joy of his work; but 
he is losing ground, his strength is failing, and he is so afraid 
there will not be time enough left&mdash;time enough for full 
recognition," she explained. 
</p><p>The quiver in her voice silenced Stanwell: he was afraid of 
echoing it with his own.  At length he said: "Oh, more orders will 
come.  Success is a gradual growth." 
</p><p>"Yes, <hi rend="italic"> real</hi> success," she said, with a solemn note in which 
he caught&mdash;and forgave&mdash;a reflection on his own facile triumphs. 
</p><p>"But when the orders do come," she continued, "will he have 
strength to carry them out?  Last winter the doctor thought he only 
needed work to set him up; now he talks of rest instead!  He says 
we ought to go to a warm climate&mdash;but how can Caspar leave the 
group?" 
</p><p>"Oh, hang the group&mdash;let him chuck the order!" cried Stanwell. 
</p><p>She looked at him tragically.  "The money is spent," she said. 
</p><p>He coloured to the roots of his hair. <pb n="711"/>  "But ill-health&mdash;ill-health excuses everything.  If he goes away now he will 
come back good for twice the amount of work in the spring.  A 
sculptor is not expected to deliver a statue on a given day, like 
a package of groceries!  You must do as the doctor says&mdash;you must 
make him chuck everything and go." 
</p><p>They had reached a windless nook above the lake, and, pausing 
in the stress of their talk, she let herself sink on a bench beside 
the path.  The movement encouraged him, and he seated himself at 
her side. 
</p><p>"You must take him away at once," he repeated urgently.  "He 
must be made comfortable&mdash;you must both be free from worry.  And I 
want you to let me manage it for you&mdash;" 
</p><p>He broke off, silenced by her rising blush, her protesting 
murmur. 
</p><p>"Oh, stop, please; let me explain.  I'm not talking of lending 
you money; I'm talking of giving you&mdash;myself.  The offer may be 
just as unacceptable, but it's of a kind to which it's customary to 
accord it a hearing.  I should have made it a year ago&mdash;the first 
day I saw you, I believe!&mdash;but that, then, it wasn't in my power to 
make things easier for you.  But now, you know, I've had a little 
luck.  Since I painted Mrs. Millington things have changed.  I 
believe I can get as many orders as I choose&mdash;there are two or 
three people waiting now.  What's the use of it all, if it doesn't 
bring me a little happiness?  And the only happiness I know is the 
kind that you can give me." 
</p><p>He paused, suddenly losing the courage to look at her, so that 
her pained murmur was framed for him in a glittering vision of the 
frozen lake.  He turned with a start and met the refusal in her 
eyes. 
</p><p>"No&mdash;really no?" he repeated. 
</p><p>She shook her head silently. 
</p><p>"I could have helped you&mdash;I could have helped you!" he sighed. 
</p><p>She flushed distressfully, but kept her eyes on his. 
</p><p>"It's just that&mdash;don't you see?" she reproached him. 
</p><p>"Just that&mdash;the fact that I could be of use to you?" 
</p><p>"The fact that, as you say, things have changed since you 
painted Mrs. Millington.  I haven't seen the later portraits, but 
they tell me&mdash;" 
</p><p>"Oh, they're just as bad!" Stanwell jeered. 
</p><p>"You've sold your talent, and you know it: that's the dreadful 
part.  You did it deliberately," she cried with passion. 
</p><p>"Oh, deliberately," he interjected. 
</p><p>"And you're not ashamed&mdash;you talk of going on." 
</p><p>"I'm not ashamed; I talk of going on." 
</p><p>She received this with a long shuddering sigh, and turned her 
eyes away from him. 
</p><p>"Oh, why&mdash;why&mdash;why?" she lamented. 
</p><p>It was on the tip of Stanwell's tongue to answer, "That I 
might say to you what I am just saying now&mdash;" but he replied 
instead: "A man may paint bad pictures and be a decent fellow.  
Look at Mungold, after all!" 
</p><p>The adjuration had an unexpected effect.  Kate's colour faded 
suddenly, and she sat motionless, with a stricken face. 
</p><p>"There's a difference&mdash;" she began at length abruptly; "the 
difference you've always insisted on.  Mr. Mungold paints as well 
as he can.  He has no idea that his pictures are&mdash;less good than 
they might be." 
</p><p>"Well&mdash;?" 
</p><p>"So he can't be accused of doing what he does for money&mdash;of 
sacrificing anything better."  She turned on him with troubled 
eyes.  "It was you who made me understand that, when Caspar used to 
make fun of him." 
</p><p>Stanwell smiled.  "I'm glad you still think me a better 
painter than Mungold.  But isn't it hard that for that very reason 
I should starve in a hole?  If I painted badly enough you'd see no 
objection to my living at the Waldorf!" 
</p><p>"Ah, don't joke about it," she murmured.  "Don't triumph in 
it." 
</p><p>"I see no reason to at present," said Stanwell drily.  "But I 
won't pretend to be ashamed when I'm not.  I think there are 
occasions when a man is justified in doing what I've done." 
</p><p>She looked at him solemnly.  "What occasions?" 
</p><p>"Why, when he wants money, hang it!" 
</p><p>She drew a deep breath.  "Money&mdash;money?  Has Caspar's example 
been nothing to you, then?" 
</p><p>"It hasn't proved to me that I must starve while Mungold lives 
on truffles!" 
</p><p>Again her face changed and she stirred uneasily, and then rose 
to her feet. <pb n="712"/>  
</p><p>"There is no occasion which can justify an artist's 
sacrificing his convictions!" she exclaimed. 
</p><p>Stanwell rose too, facing her with a mounting urgency which 
sent a flush to his cheek. 
</p><p>"Can't you conceive such an occasion in my case?  The wish, I 
mean, to make things easier for Caspar&mdash;to help you in any way you 
might let me?" 
</p><p>Her face reflected his blush, and she stood gazing at him with 
a wounded wonder. 
</p><p>"Caspar and I&mdash;you imagine we could live on money earned in <hi rend="italic"> 
that</hi> way?" 
</p><p>Stanwell made an impatient gesture.  "You've got to live on 
something&mdash;or he has, even if you don't include yourself!" 
</p><p>Her blush deepened miserably, but she held her head high. 
</p><p>"That's just it&mdash;that's what I came here to say to you."  She 
stood a moment gazing away from him at the lake. 
</p><p>He looked at her in surprise.  "You came here to say something 
to me?" 
</p><p>"Yes.  That we've got to live on something, Caspar and I, as 
you say; and since an artist cannot sacrifice his convictions, the 
sacrifice must&mdash;I mean&mdash;I wanted you to know that I have promised 
to marry Mr. Mungold." 
</p><p>"Mungold!" Stanwell cried with a sharp note of irony; but her 
white look checked it on his lips. 
</p><p>"I know all you are going to say," she murmured, with a kind 
of nobleness which moved him even through his sense of its 
grotesqueness.  "But you must see the distinction, because you 
first made it clear to me.  I can take money earned in good faith&mdash; 
I can let Caspar live on it.  I can marry Mr. Mungold; because, 
though his pictures are bad, he does not prostitute his art." 
</p><p>She began to move away from him slowly, and he followed her in 
silence along the frozen path. 
</p><p>When Stanwell re-entered his studio the dusk had fallen.  He 
lit his lamp and rummaged out some writing-materials.  Having found 
them, he wrote to Shepson to say that he could not paint Mrs. Van 
Orley, and did not care to accept any more orders for the present.  
He sealed and stamped the letter and flung it over the banisters 
for the janitor to post; then he dragged out his unfinished head of 
Kate Arran, replaced it on the easel, and sat down before it with 
a grim smile. 
</p> 
</div2> 
</div1> 
</body> 
</text> 
</TEI.2> 
