<?xml version="1.0"?>

<?dlps id="WhaDian"?>
<?dlps page-images="none" figure-images="no"?>
<?dlps transcription="other"?>

<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/tei-p4/tei2.dtd" [
<!ENTITY % POSTKB "INCLUDE">
<!ENTITY % TEI.extensions.ent SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.ent">
<!ENTITY % TEI.extensions.dtd SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.dtd">
<!ENTITY % ISOnum SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/charent/iso-num.ent"> %ISOnum;
<!ENTITY % ISOpub SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/charent/iso-pub.ent"> %ISOpub;

]>

<TEI.2 id="WhaDian"> 
<teiHeader type="migrated" creator="Etext">
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title type="main">The Daunt Diana</title>
<title type="sort">daunt diana</title>
<author>Wharton, Edith, 1862-1937</author>
<respStmt>
<resp>Creation of machine-readable version:</resp>
<name>Judy Boss</name>
</respStmt>
<respStmt>
<resp>Conversion to TEI-conformant markup:</resp>
<name>University of Virginia Library Electronic Text Center</name>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt> 
<extent>ca. <num type="kilobytes">33</num> kilobytes</extent> 
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>University of Virginia Library</publisher>
<pubPlace>Charlottesville, Virginia</pubPlace>
<idno type="ETC">WhaDian</idno> 
<date value="1995">1995</date>
<availability status="public">
<p n="copyright">Copyright &copy; 1995 by the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia</p>
<p n="access">Publicly accessible</p>
</availability>
<idno type="uva-pid">uva-lib:476488</idno>
</publicationStmt>
<seriesStmt>
<title>University of Virginia Library, Text collection</title>
<idno type="uva-set">UVA-LIB-Text</idno>
</seriesStmt> 
<sourceDesc>
<biblFull>
<titleStmt>
<title type="main">The Daunt Diana</title>
<title type="sort">daunt diana</title>
<author>Wharton, Edith</author>
</titleStmt> 
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>Scribner's Magazine</publisher>
<date value="1909-07">July 1909</date>
</publicationStmt> 
<notesStmt>
<note>
<p>Volume 46</p>
</note>
</notesStmt>
</biblFull>
</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc> 
<encodingDesc>
<projectDesc>
<p>Prepared for the University of Virginia Library Electronic Text Center</p>
</projectDesc> 
<editorialDecl>
<p>All quotation marks retained as data</p> 
<p>Verification made against printed text</p> 
<p id="ETC">Keywords in the header are a local Electronic Text Center scheme  
to aid in establishing analytical groupings</p>
</editorialDecl> 
<refsDecl>
<p>ID elements are given for each page element and are composed of the text's 
unique cryptogram and the given page number, as in SpeFQue1 for page one of  
Spenser's Faerie Queene.</p>
</refsDecl>
</encodingDesc> 
<profileDesc>
<creation>
<date value="1909">1909</date>
</creation> 
<langUsage>
<language id="eng" usage="main">English</language>
</langUsage> 
<textClass>
<keywords>
<term>fiction</term>
<term>prose</term>
</keywords>
</textClass>
</profileDesc> 
<revisionDesc>
<change>
<date value="1995-01">January 1995</date> 
<respStmt>
<resp>corrector</resp>
<name>David Seaman and Kelly Tetterton</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Header and basic TEI SGML encoding added</item>
</change> 
<change>
<date value="2005-07">July 2005</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>Corrector</resp>
<name>Margaret Konkol</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Converted SGML to XML and fixed tagging.</item>
</change>
<change>
<date value="2007-09">September 2007</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>Migration</resp>
<name>Ethan Gruber, University of Virginia Library</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Converted XML markup from TEI Lite to uva-dl-tei (TEI P4 with local customizations).</item>
</change>
<change>
<date value="2008-01">January 2008</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>Migration</resp>
<name>Greg Murray, University of Virginia Library</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Programmatically updated TEI header markup (but not header content) for minimal compliance with current QA requirements.</item>
</change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader> 




<text id="d1">  
<body id="d2"> 
<div1 type="story" id="d3"> 
<head> 
                    <hi rend="italic"> TALES OF MEN</hi> 
<lb/> 
Wharton, Edith.  "The Daunt Diana."   
<lb/> 
<hi rend="italic"> Scribner's Magazine</hi> 46 (July 1909): 35-41. 
</head> 

<pb n="35"/>  
<div2 type="section" n="1" id="d4"> 
<head>                            I 
</head> 
<p>"WHAT'S become of the Daunt Diana?  You mean to say you never heard 
the sequel?" 
</p><p>Ringham Finney threw himself back into his chair with the 
smile of the collector who has a good thing to show.  He knew he 
had a good listener, at any rate.  I don't think much of Ringham's 
snuff-boxes, but his anecdotes are usually worth while.  He's a 
psychologist astray among <hi rend="italic"> bibelots</hi>, and the best bits he brings 
back from his raids on Christie's and the Hotel Drouot are the 
fragments of human nature he picks up on those historic battle-fields.  If his <hi rend="italic"> flair</hi> in enamel had been half as good we should 
have heard of the Finney collection by this time. 
</p><p>He really has&mdash;queer fatuous investigator!&mdash;an unusually 
sensitive touch for the human texture, and the specimens he gathers 
into his museum of heterogeneous memories have almost always some 
mark of the rare and chosen.  I felt, therefore, that I was really 
to be congratulated on the fact that I didn't know what had become 
of the Daunt Diana, and on having before me a long evening in which 
to learn.  I had just led my friend back, after an excellent dinner 
at Foyot's, to the shabby pleasant sitting-room of my <hi rend="italic"> rive-gauche</hi> hotel; and I knew that, once I had settled him in a good 
arm-chair, and put a box of cigars at his elbow, I could trust him 
not to budge till I had the story. 
</p></div2> 
<div2 type="section" n="2" id="d5"> 
<head>                           II 
</head> 
<p>YOU remember old Neave, of course?  Little Humphrey Neave, I 
mean.  We used to see him pottering about Rome years ago.  He lived 
in two tiny rooms over a wine shop, on polenta and lentils, and 
prowled among the refuse of the Ripetta whenever he had a few <hi rend="italic"> 
soldi</hi> to spend.  But you've been out of the collector's world for 
so long that you may not know what happened to him afterward. . . 
</p><p>He was always a queer chap, Neave; years older than you and 
me, of course&mdash;and even when I first knew him, in my raw Roman 
days, he gave me an extraordinary sense of age and experience.  I 
don't think I've ever known any one who was at once so intelligent 
and so simple.  It's the precise combination that results in 
romance; and poor little Neave was romantic. 
</p><p>He told me once how he'd come to Rome.  He was <hi rend="italic"> originaire</hi> 
of Mystic, Connecticut&mdash;and he wanted to get as far away from it as 
possible.  Rome seemed as far as anything on the same planet could 
be; and after he'd worried his way through Harvard&mdash;with shifts and 
shavings that you and I can't imagine&mdash;he contrived to get sent to 
Switzerland as tutor to a chap who'd failed in his examinations.  
With only the Alps between, he wasn't likely to turn back; and he 
got another fellow to take his pupil home, and struck out on foot 
for the seven hills. 
</p><p>I'm telling you these early details merely to give you a 
notion of the man's idealism.  There was a cool persistency and a 
headlong courage in his dash for Rome that one wouldn't have 
guessed in the little pottering chap we used to know.  Once on the 
spot, he got more tutoring, managed to make himself a name for 
coaxing balky youths to take their fences, and was finally able to 
take up the more congenial task of expounding "the antiquities" to 
cultured travellers.  I call it more congenial&mdash;but how it must 
have seared his soul!  Fancy unveiling the sacred scars of Time to 
ladies who murmur: "Was this <hi rend="italic"> actually</hi> the spot&mdash;?" while they 
absently feel for their hatpins!  He used to say that nothing kept 
him at it but the exquisite thought of accumulating the <hi rend="italic"> lire</hi> 
for his collection.  For the Neave collection, my dear fellow, 
began early, began almost with his Roman life, began in a series of 
little nameless odds and ends, broken trinkets, torn embroideries, 
the amputated extremities of maimed marbles: things that even the 
rag-picker had pitched away when he sifted his haul.  But they 
weren't nameless or meaningless to Neave; his strength lay in his 
instinct for identifying, putting together, seeing significant 
<pb n="36"/>  relations.  He was a regular Cuvier of bric-a-brac.  
And during those early years, when he had time to brood over 
trifles and note imperceptible differences, he gradually sharpened 
his instinct, and made it into the delicate and redoubtable 
instrument it is.  Before he had a thousand francs' worth of <hi rend="italic"> 
anticaglie</hi> to his name he began to be known as an expert, and the 
big dealers were glad to consult him.  But we're getting no nearer 
the Daunt Diana. . . 
</p><p>Well, some fifteen years ago, in London, I ran across Neave at 
Christie's.  He was the same little man we'd known, effaced, 
bleached, indistinct, like a poor "impression"&mdash;as unnoticeable as 
one of his own early finds, yet, like them, with a <hi rend="italic"> quality</hi>, if 
one had an eye for it.  He told me he still lived in Rome, and had 
contrived, by fierce self-denial, to get a few decent bits 
together&mdash;"piecemeal, little by little, with fasting and prayer; 
and I mean the fasting literally!" he said. 
</p><p>He had run over to London for his annual "look-round"&mdash;I fancy 
one or another of the big collectors usually paid his journey&mdash;and 
when we met he was on his way to see the Daunt collection.  You 
know old Daunt was a surly brute, and the things weren't easily 
seen; but he had heard Neave was in London, and had sent&mdash;yes, 
actually sent!&mdash;for him to come and give his opinion on a few bits, 
including the Diana.  The little man bore himself discreetly, but 
you can imagine his pride.  In his exultation he asked me to come 
with him&mdash;"Oh, I've the <hi rend="italic"> grandes et petites entrees</hi>, my dear 
fellow: I've made my conditions&mdash;" and so it happened that I saw 
the first meeting between Humphrey Neave and his fate. 
</p><p>For that collection <hi rend="italic"> was</hi> his fate: or, one may say, it was 
embodied in the Diana who was queen and goddess of the realm.  
Yes&mdash;I shall always be glad I was with Neave when he had his first 
look at the Diana.  I see him now, blinking at her through his 
white lashes, and stroking his seedy wisp of a moustache to hide a 
twitch of the muscles.  It was all very quiet, but it was the <hi rend="italic"> 
coup de foudre</hi>.  I could see that by the way his hands trembled 
when he turned away and began to examine the other things.  You 
remember Neave's hands&mdash;thin, sallow, dry, with long inquisitive 
fingers thrown out like antennae?  Whatever they hold&mdash;bronze or 
lace, hard enamel or brittle glass&mdash;they have an air of conforming 
themselves to the texture of the thing, and sucking out of it, by 
every finger-tip, the mysterious essence it has secreted.  Well, 
that day, as he moved about among Daunt's treasures, the Diana 
followed him everywhere.  He didn't look back at her&mdash;he gave 
himself to the business he was there for&mdash;but whatever he touched, 
he felt her.  And on the threshold he turned and gave her his first 
free look&mdash;the kind of look that says: <hi rend="italic"> "You're mine."</hi> 
</p><p>It amused me at the time&mdash;the idea of little Neave making eyes 
at any of Daunt's belongings.  He might as well have coquetted with 
the Kohinoor.  And the same idea seemed to strike him; for as we 
turned away from the big house in Belgravia he glanced up at it and 
said, with a bitterness I'd never heard in him: "Good Lord!  To 
think of that lumpy fool having those things to handle!  Did you 
notice his stupid stumps of fingers?  I suppose he blunted them 
gouging nuggets out of the gold fields.  And in exchange for the 
nuggets he gets all that in a year&mdash;only has to hold out his 
callous palm to have that great ripe sphere of beauty drop into it!  
That's my idea of heaven&mdash;to have a great collection drop into 
one's hand, as success, or love, or any of the big shining things, 
drop suddenly on some men.  And I've had to worry along for nearly 
fifty years, saving and paring, and haggling and intriguing, to get 
here a bit and there a bit&mdash;and not one perfection in the lot!  
It's enough to poison a man's life." 
</p><p>The outbreak was so unlike Neave that I remember every word of 
it: remember, too, saying in answer: "But, look here, Neave, you 
wouldn't take Daunt's hands for yours, I imagine?" 
</p><p>He stared a moment and smiled.  "Have all that, and grope my 
way through it like a blind cave fish?  What a question!  But the 
sense that it's always the blind fish that live in that kind of 
aquarium is what makes anarchists, sir!"  He looked back from the 
corner of the square, where we had paused while he delivered 
himself of this remarkable metaphor.  "God, I'd like to throw a 
bomb at that place, and be in at the looting!" 
</p><p>And with that, on the way home, he unpacked his grievance&mdash; 
pulled the bandage off the wound, and showed me the ugly mark it 
had made on his little white soul. <pb n="37"/>  
</p><p>It wasn't the struggling, stinting, self-denying that galled 
him&mdash;it was the inadequacy of the result.  It was, in short, the 
old tragedy of the discrepancy between a man's wants and his power 
to gratify them.  Neave's taste was too exquisite for his means&mdash; 
was like some strange, delicate, capricious animal, that he 
cherished and pampered and couldn't satisfy. 
</p><p>"Don't you know those little glittering lizards that die if 
they're not fed on some wonderful tropical fly?  Well, my taste's 
like that, with one important difference&mdash;if it doesn't get its 
fly, it simply turns and feeds on me.  Oh, it doesn't die, my 
taste&mdash;worse luck!  It gets larger and stronger and more 
fastidious, and takes a bigger bite of me&mdash;that's all." 
</p><p>That was all.  Year by year, day by day, he had made himself 
into this delicate register of perceptions and sensations&mdash;as far 
above the ordinary human faculty of appreciation as some scientific 
registering instrument is beyond the rough human senses&mdash;only to 
find that the beauty which alone could satisfy him was 
unattainable&mdash;that he was never to know the last deep 
identification which only possession can give.  He had trained 
himself in short, to feel, in the rare great thing&mdash;such an 
utterance of beauty as the Daunt Diana, say&mdash;a hundred elements of 
perfection, a hundred <hi rend="italic"> reasons why</hi>, imperceptible, inexplicable 
even, to the average "artistic" sense; he had reached this point by 
a long austere process of discrimination and rejection, the renewed 
great refusals of the intelligence which perpetually asks more, 
which will make no pact with its self of yesterday, and is never to 
be beguiled from its purpose by the wiles of the next-best-thing.  
Oh, it's a poignant case, but not a common one; for the next-best-thing usually wins. . . 
</p><p>You see, the worst of Neave's state was the fact of his not 
being a mere collector, even the collector raised to his highest 
pitch of efficiency.  The whole thing was blent in him with 
poetry&mdash;his imagination had romanticized the acquisitive instinct, 
as the religious feeling of the Middle Ages turned passion into 
love.  And yet his could never be the abstract enjoyment of the 
philosopher who says: "This or that object is really mine because 
I'm capable of appreciating it."  Neave <hi rend="italic"> wanted</hi> what he 
appreciated&mdash;wanted it with his touch and his sight as well as with 
his imagination. 

</p><p>It was hardly a year afterward that, coming back from a long 
tour in India, I picked up a London paper and read the amazing 
headline: "Mr. Humphrey Neave buys the Daunt collection". . .  I 
rubbed my eyes and read again.  Yes, it could only be our old 
friend Humphrey.  "An American living in Rome . . . one of our most 
discerning collectors"; there was no mistaking the description.  I 
clapped on my hat and bolted out to see the first dealer I could 
find; and there I had the incredible details.  Neave had come into 
a fortune&mdash;two or three million dollars, amassed by an uncle who 
had a corset-factory, and who had attained wealth as the creator of 
the Mystic Super-straight.  (Corset-factory sounds odd, by the way, 
doesn't it?  One had fancied that the corset was a personal, a 
highly specialized garment, more or less shaped on the form it was 
to modify; but, after all, the Tanagras were all made from two or 
three moulds&mdash;and so, I suppose, are the ladies who wear the Mystic 
Super-straight.) 
</p><p>The uncle had a son, and Neave had never dreamed of seeing a 
penny of the money; but the son died suddenly, and the father 
followed, leaving a codicil that gave everything to our friend.  
Humphrey had to go out to "realize" on the corset-factory; and his 
description of <hi rend="italic"> that</hi> . . .  Well, he came back with his money in 
his pocket, and the day he landed old Daunt went to smash.  It all 
fitted in like a Chinese puzzle.  I believe Neave drove straight 
from Euston to Daunt House: at any rate, within two months the 
collection was his, and at a price that made the trade sit up.  
Trust old Daunt for that! 
</p><p>I was in Rome the following spring, and you'd better believe 
I looked him up.  A big porter glared at me from the door of the 
Palazzo Neave: I had almost to produce my passport to get in.  But 
that wasn't Neave's fault&mdash;the poor fellow was so beset by people 
clamouring to see his collection that he had to barricade himself, 
literally.  When I had mounted the state <hi rend="italic"> Scalone</hi>, and come on 
him, at the end of half a dozen echoing saloons, in the farthest, 
smallest <hi rend="italic"> reduit</hi> of the vast suite, I received the same welcome 
that he used to give us in his little den over the wine shop.  
<pb n="38"/>  
</p><p>"Well&mdash;so you've got her?" I said.  For I'd caught sight of 
the Diana in passing, against the bluish blur of an old <hi rend="italic"> 
verdure</hi>&mdash;just the background for her poised loveliness.  Only I 
rather wondered why she wasn't in the room where he sat. 
</p><p>He smiled.  "Yes, I've got her," he returned, more calmly than 
I had expected. 
</p><p>"And all the rest of the loot?" 
</p><p>"Yes.  I had to buy the lump." 
</p><p>"Had to?  But you wanted to, didn't you?  You used to say it 
was your idea of heaven&mdash;to stretch out your hand and have a great 
ripe sphere of beauty drop into it.  I'm quoting your own words, by 
the way." 
</p><p>Neave blinked and stroked his seedy moustache.  "Oh, yes.  I 
remember the phrase.  It's true&mdash;it <hi rend="italic"> is</hi> the last luxury."  He 
paused, as if seeking a pretext for his lack of warmth.  "The thing 
that bothered me was having to move.  I couldn't cram all the stuff 
into my old quarters." 
</p><p>"Well, I should say not!  This is rather a better setting." 
</p><p>He got up.  "Come and take a look round.  I want to show you 
two or three things&mdash;new attributions I've made.  I'm doing the 
catalogue over." 
</p><p>The interest of showing me the things seemed to dispel the 
vague apathy I had felt in him.  He grew keen again in detailing 
his redistribution of values, and above all in convicting old Daunt 
and his advisers of their repeated aberrations of judgment.  "The 
miracle is that he should have got such things, knowing as little 
as he did what he was getting.  And the egregious asses who bought 
for him were no better, were worse in fact, since they had all 
sorts of humbugging wrong reasons for admiring what old Daunt 
simply coveted because it belonged to some other rich man." 
</p><p>Never had Neave had so wondrous a field for the exercise of 
his perfected faculty; and I saw then how in the real, the great 
collector's appreciations the keenest scientific perception is 
suffused with imaginative sensibility, and how it's to the latter 
undefinable quality that in the last resort he trusts himself. 
</p><p>Nevertheless, I still felt the shadow of that hovering apathy, 
and he knew I felt it, and was always breaking off to give me 
reasons for it.  For one thing, he wasn't used to his new 
quarters&mdash;hated their bigness and formality; then the requests to 
show his things drove him mad.  "The women&mdash;oh, the women!" he 
wailed, and interrupted himself to describe a heavy-footed German 
Princess who had marched past his treasures as if she were 
inspecting a cavalry regiment, applying an unmodulated <hi rend="italic"> 
Mugneeficent</hi> to everything from the engraved gems to the Hercules 
torso. 
</p><p>"Not that she was half as bad as the other kind," he added, as 
if with a last effort at optimism.  "The kind who discriminate and 
say: 'I'm not sure if it's Botticelli or Cellini I mean, but <hi rend="italic"> one 
of that school</hi>, at any rate.'  And the worst of all are the ones 
who know&mdash;up to a certain point: have the schools, and the dates 
and the jargon pat, and yet wouldn't know a Phidias if it stood 
where they hadn't expected it." 
</p><p>He had all my sympathy, poor Neave; yet these were trials 
inseparable from the collector's lot, and not always without their 
secret compensations.  Certainly they did not wholly explain my 
friend's attitude; and for a moment I wondered if it were due to 
some strange disillusionment as to the quality of his treasures.  
But no! the Daunt collection was almost above criticism; and as we 
passed from one object to another I saw there was no mistaking the 
genuineness of Neave's pride in his possessions.  The ripe sphere 
of beauty was his, and he had found no flaw in it as yet. . . 

</p><p>A year later came the amazing announcement&mdash;the Daunt 
collection was for sale.  At first we all supposed it was a case of 
weeding out (though how old Daunt would have raged at the thought 
of anybody's weeding <hi rend="italic"> his</hi> collection!)  But no&mdash;the catalogue 
corrected that idea.  Every stick and stone was to go under the 
hammer.  The news ran like wildfire from Rome to Berlin, from Paris 
to London and New York.  Was Neave ruined, then?  Wrong again&mdash;the 
dealers nosed that out in no time.  He was simply selling because 
he chose to sell; and in due time the things came up at Christie's. 
</p><p>But you may be sure the trade had found an answer to the 
riddle; and the answer was that, on close inspection, Neave had 
found the collection less impeccable than he had supposed.  It was 
a preposterous answer&mdash;but then there was no other.  Neave, by this 
time, was pretty generally recognized as having the subtlest <hi rend="italic"> 
flair</hi> of any collector in Europe, and if he didn't choose to keep 
<pb n="39"/>  the Daunt collection it could be only because he had reason 
to think he could do better. 
</p><p>In a flash this report had gone the rounds and the buyers were 
on their guard.  I had run over to London to see the thing through, 
and it was the queerest sale I ever was at.  Some of the things 
held their own, but a lot&mdash;and a few of the best among them&mdash;went 
for half their value.  You see, they'd been locked up in old 
Daunt's house for nearly twenty years, and hardly shown to any one, 
so that the whole younger generation of dealers and collectors knew 
of them only by hearsay.  Then you know the effect of suggestion in 
such cases.  The undefinable sense we were speaking of is a 
ticklish instrument, easily thrown out of gear by a sudden fall of 
temperature; and the sharpest experts grow shy and self-distrustful 
when the cold current of depreciation touches them.  The sale was 
a slaughter&mdash;and when I saw the Daunt Diana fall at the wink of a 
little third-rate <hi rend="italic"> brocanteur</hi> from Vienna I turned sick at the 
folly of my kind. 
</p><p>For my part, I had never believed that Neave had sold the 
collection because he'd "found it out"; and within a year my 
incredulity was justified.  As soon as the things were put in 
circulation they were known for the marvels they are.  There was 
hardly a poor bit in the lot; and my wonder grew at Neave's 
madness.  All over Europe, dealers began to be fighting for the 
spoils; and all kinds of stuff were palmed off on the unsuspecting 
as fragments of the Daunt collection! 
</p><p>Meanwhile, what was Neave doing?  For a long time I didn't 
hear, and chance kept me from returning to Rome.  But one day, in 
Paris, I ran across a dealer who had captured for a song one of the 
best Florentine bronzes in the Daunt collection&mdash;a marvellous <hi rend="italic"> 
plaquette</hi> of Donatello's.  I asked him what had become of it, and 
he said with a grin: "I sold it the other day," naming a price that 
staggered me. 
</p><p>"Ye gods!  Who paid you that for it?" 
</p><p>His grin broadened, and he answered: "Neave." 
</p><p><hi rend="italic">" Neave?</hi>  Humphrey Neave?" 
</p><p>"Didn't you know he was buying back his things?" 
</p><p>"Nonsense!" 
</p><p>"He is, though.  Not in his own name&mdash;but he's doing it." 
</p><p>And he <hi rend="italic"> was</hi>, do you know&mdash;and at prices that would have 
made a sane man shudder!  A few weeks later I ran across his tracks 
in London, where he was trying to get hold of a Penicaud enamel&mdash; 
another of his scattered treasures.  Then I hunted him down at his 
hotel, and had it out with him. 
</p><p>"Look here, Neave, what are you up to?" 
</p><p>He wouldn't tell me at first: stared and laughed and denied.  
But I took him off to dine, and after dinner, while we smoked, I 
happened to mention casually that I had a pull over the man who had 
the Penicaud&mdash;and at that he broke down and confessed. 
</p><p>"Yes, I'm buying them back, Finney&mdash;it's true."  He laughed 
nervously, twitching his moustache.  And then he let me have the 
story. 
</p><p>"You know how I'd hungered and thirsted for the <hi rend="italic"> real 
thing</hi>&mdash;you quoted my own phrase to me once, about the 'ripe sphere 
of beauty.'  So when I got my money, and Daunt lost his, almost at 
the same moment, I saw the hand of Providence in it.  I knew that, 
even if I'd been younger, and had more time, I could never hope, 
nowadays, to form such a collection as <hi rend="italic"> that</hi>.  There was the 
ripe sphere, within reach; and I took it.  But when I got it, and 
began to live with it, I found out my mistake.  It was a <hi rend="italic"> mariage 
de convenance</hi>&mdash;there'd been no wooing, no winning.  Each of my 
little old bits&mdash;the rubbish I chucked out to make room for Daunt's 
glories&mdash;had its own personal history, the drama of my relation to 
it, of the discovery, the struggle, the capture, the first divine 
moment of possession.  There was a romantic secret between us.  And 
then I had absorbed its beauties one by one, they had become a part 
of my imagination, they held me by a hundred threads of far-reaching association.  And suddenly I had expected to create this 
kind of intense personal tie between myself and a roomful of new 
cold alien presences&mdash;things staring at me vacantly from the depths 
of unknown pasts!  Can you fancy a more preposterous hope?  Why, my 
other things, my <hi rend="italic"> own</hi> things, had wooed me as passionately as I 
wooed them: there was a certain little bronze, a little Venus 
Callipyge, who had drawn me, drawn me, drawn me, imploring me to 
rescue her from her unspeakable surroundings in a vulgar bric-a-brac shop at Biarritz, where she shrank out of sight among <pb n="40"/>  
sham Sevres and Dutch silver, as one has seen certain women&mdash;rare, 
shy, exquisite&mdash;made almost invisible by the vulgar splendours 
surrounding them.  Well! that little Venus, who was just a specious 
seventeenth century attempt at the 'antique,' but who had 
penetrated me with her pleading grace, touched me by the easily 
guessed story of her obscure, anonymous origin, was more to me 
imaginatively&mdash;yes! more than the cold bought beauty of the Daunt 
Diana. . ." 
</p><p>"The Daunt Diana!" I broke in.  "Hold up, Neave&mdash;<hi rend="italic"> the Daunt 
Diana?"</hi> 
</p><p>He smiled contemptuously.  "A professional beauty, my dear 
fellow&mdash;expected every head to be turned when she came into a 
room." 
</p><p>"Oh, Neave," I groaned. 
</p><p>"Yes, I know.  You're thinking of what we felt that day we 
first saw her in London.  Many a poor devil has sold his soul as 
the result of such a first sight!  Well, I sold <hi rend="italic"> her</hi> instead.  
Do you want the truth about her?  <hi rend="italic"> Elle etait bete a pleurer."</hi> 
</p><p>He laughed, and stood up with a little shrug of 
disenchantment. 
</p><p>"And so you're impenitent?"  I paused.  "And yet you're buying 
some of the things back?" 
</p><p>Neave laughed again, ironically.  "I knew you'd find me out 
and call me to account.  Well, yes: I'm buying back."  He stood 
before me half sheepish, half defiant.  "I'm buying back because 
there's nothing else as good in the market.  And because I've a 
queer feeling that, this time, they'll be <hi rend="italic"> mine</hi>.  But I'm 
ruining myself at the game!" he confessed. 

</p><p>It was true: Neave was ruining himself.  And he's gone on 
ruining himself ever since, till now the job's nearly done.  Bit by 
bit, year by year, he has gathered in his scattered treasures, at 
higher prices than the dealers ever dreamed of getting.  There are 
fabulous details in the story of his quest.  Now and then I ran 
across him, and was able to help him recover a fragment; and it was 
wonderful to see his delight in the moment of reunion.  Finally, 
about two years ago, we met in Paris, and he told me he had got 
back all the important pieces except the Diana. 
</p><p>"The Diana?  But you told me you didn't care for her." 
</p><p>"Didn't care?"  He leaned across the restaurant table that 
divided us.  "Well, no, in a sense I didn't.  I wanted her to want 
me, you see; and she didn't then!  Whereas now she's crying to me 
to come to her.  You know where she is?" he broke off. 
</p><p>Yes, I knew: in the centre of Mrs. Willy P. Goldmark's yellow 
and gold drawing-room, under a thousand-candle-power chandelier, 
with reflectors aimed at her from every point of the compass.  I 
had seen her wincing and shivering there in her outraged nudity at 
one of the Goldmark "crushes." 
</p><p>"But you can't get her, Neave," I objected. 
</p><p>"No, I can't get her," he said. 

</p><p>Well, last month I was in Rome, for the first time in six or 
seven years, and of course I looked about for Neave.  The Palazzo 
Neave was let to some rich Russians, and the splendid new porter 
didn't know where the proprietor lived.  But I got on his trail 
easily enough, and it led me to a strange old place in the 
Trastevere, an ancient crevassed black palace turned tenement 
house, and fluttering with pauper clothes-lines.  I found Neave 
under the leads, in two or three cold rooms that smelt of the <hi rend="italic"> 
cuisine</hi> of all his neighbours: a poor shrunken little figure, 
seedier and shabbier than ever, yet more alive than when we had 
made the tour of his collection in the Palazzo Neave. 
</p><p>The collection was around him again, not displayed in tall 
cabinets and on marble tables, but huddled on shelves, perched on 
chairs, crammed in corners, putting the gleam of bronze, the 
opalescence of old glass, the pale lustre of marble, into all the 
angles of his low dim rooms.  There they were, the proud presences 
that had stared at him down the vistas of Daunt House, and shone in 
cold transplanted beauty under his own painted cornices: there they 
were, gathered in humble promiscuity about his bent shabby figure, 
like superb wild creatures tamed to become the familiars of some 
harmless old wizard. 
</p><p>As we went from bit to bit, as he lifted one piece after 
another, and held it to the light of his low windows, I saw in his 
hands the same tremor of sensation that I had noticed when he first 
examined the same objects at Daunt House.  All his life was in his 
finger-tips, and it seemed to communi-<pb n="41"/> cate life to the 
exquisite things he touched.  But you'll think me infected by his 
mysticism if I tell you they gained new beauty while he held them. 
. . 
</p><p>We went the rounds slowly and reverently; and then, when I 
supposed our inspection was over, and was turning to take my leave, 
he opened a door I had not noticed, and showed me into a slit of a 
room beyond.  It was a mere monastic cell, scarcely large enough 
for his narrow iron bed and the chest which probably held his few 
clothes; but there, in a niche of the bare wall, facing the foot of 
the bed&mdash;there stood the Daunt Diana. 
</p><p>I gasped at the sight and turned to him; and he looked back at 
me without speaking. 
</p><p>"In the name of magic, Neave, how did you do it?" 
</p><p>He smiled as if from the depths of some secret rapture.  "Call 
it magic, if you like; but I ruined myself doing it," he said. 
</p><p>I stared at him in silence, breathless with the madness and 
the wonder of it; and suddenly, red to the ears, he flung out his 
boyish confession.  "I lied to you that day in London&mdash;the day I 
said I didn't care for her.  I always cared&mdash;always worshipped&mdash; 
always wanted her.  But she wasn't mine then, and I knew it, and 
she knew it . . . and now at last we understand each other."  He 
looked at me shyly, and then glanced about the bare cold cell.  
"The setting isn't worthy of her, I know; she was meant for glories 
I can't give her; but beautiful things, my dear Finney, like 
beautiful spirits, live in houses not made with hands. . ." 
</p><p>His face shone with extraordinary sweetness as he spoke; and 
I saw he'd got hold of the secret we're all after.  No, the setting 
isn't worthy of her, if you like.  The rooms are as shabby and mean 
as those we used to see him in years ago over the wine shop.  I'm 
not sure they're not shabbier and meaner.  But she rules there at 
last, she shines and hovers there above him, and there at night, I 
doubt not, steals down from her cloud to give him the Latmian kiss. 
</p> 
</div2> 
</div1> 
</body> 
</text> 
</TEI.2> 
