<?xml version="1.0"?>

<?dlps id="WhaDebt"?>
<?dlps page-images="none" figure-images="no"?>
<?dlps transcription="other"?>

<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/tei-p4/tei2.dtd" [
<!ENTITY % POSTKB "INCLUDE">
<!ENTITY % TEI.extensions.ent SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.ent">
<!ENTITY % TEI.extensions.dtd SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.dtd">
<!ENTITY % ISOnum SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/charent/iso-num.ent"> %ISOnum;
<!ENTITY % ISOpub SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/charent/iso-pub.ent"> %ISOpub;

]>

<TEI.2 id="WhaDebt"> 
<teiHeader type="migrated" creator="Etext">
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title type="main">The Debt</title>
<title type="sort">debt</title>
<author>Wharton, Edith, 1862-1937</author>
<respStmt>
<resp>Creation of machine-readable version:</resp>
<name>Judy Boss</name>
</respStmt>
<respStmt>
<resp>Conversion to TEI-conformant markup:</resp>
<name>University of Virginia Library Electronic Text Center</name>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt> 
<extent>ca. <num type="kilobytes">35</num> kilobytes</extent> 
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>University of Virginia Library</publisher>
<pubPlace>Charlottesville, Virginia</pubPlace>
<idno type="ETC">WhaDebt</idno> 
<date value="1995">1995</date>
<availability status="public">
<p n="copyright">Copyright &copy; 1995 by the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia</p>
<p n="access">Publicly accessible</p>
</availability>
<idno type="uva-pid">uva-lib:476486</idno>
</publicationStmt>
<seriesStmt>
<title>University of Virginia Library, Text collection</title>
<idno type="uva-set">UVA-LIB-Text</idno>
</seriesStmt> 
<sourceDesc>
<biblFull>
<titleStmt>
<title type="main">The Debt</title>
<title type="sort">debt</title>
<author>Wharton, Edith</author>
</titleStmt> 
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>Scribner's Magazine</publisher>
<date value="1909-08">Aug. 1909</date>
</publicationStmt> 
<notesStmt>
<note>
<p>Vol. 46</p>
</note>
</notesStmt>
</biblFull>
</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc> 
<encodingDesc>
<projectDesc>
<p>Prepared for the University of Virginia Library Electronic Text Center</p>
</projectDesc> 
<editorialDecl>
<p>All quotation marks retained as data</p> 
<p>Verification made against printed text</p> 
<p id="ETC">Keywords in the header are a local Electronic Text Center scheme  
to aid in establishing analytical groupings</p>
</editorialDecl> 
<refsDecl>
<p>ID elements are given for each page element and are composed of the text's 
unique cryptogram and the given page number, as in SpeFQue1 for page one of  
Spenser's Faerie Queene.</p>
</refsDecl>
</encodingDesc> 
<profileDesc>
<creation>
<date value="1909">1909</date>
</creation> 
<langUsage>
<language id="eng" usage="main">English</language>
</langUsage> 
<textClass>
<keywords>
<term>fiction</term>
<term>prose</term>
</keywords>
</textClass>
</profileDesc> 
<revisionDesc>
<change>
<date value="1995-01">January 1995</date> 
<respStmt>
<resp>corrector</resp>
<name>David Seaman and Kelly Tetterton</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Header and basic TEI SGML encoding added</item>
</change>
<change>
<date value="2007-09">September 2007</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>Migration</resp>
<name>Ethan Gruber, University of Virginia Library</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Converted XML markup from TEI Lite to uva-dl-tei (TEI P4 with local customizations).</item>
</change>
<change>
<date value="2008-01">January 2008</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>Migration</resp>
<name>Greg Murray, University of Virginia Library</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Programmatically updated TEI header markup (but not header content) for minimal compliance with current QA requirements.</item>
</change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader> 
<text id="d1">  
<body id="d2"> 
<div1 type="story" id="d3"> 
<head><hi rend="italic"> TALES OF MEN</hi> 
<lb/> 
Wharton, Edith. "The Debt."   
<lb/> 
<hi rend="italic"> Scribner's Magazine</hi> 46 (Aug. 1909): 165-72. 
</head> 
<pb n="165"/>  
<div2 type="section" n="1" id="d4"> 
<head>I</head> 
<p>                            I 

YOU remember&mdash;it's not so long ago&mdash;the talk there was about 
Dredge's "Arrival of the Fittest"?  The talk has subsided, but the 
book of course remains: stands up, in fact, as the tallest thing of 
its kind since&mdash;well, I'd almost said since "The Origin of 
Species." 
</p><p>I'm not wrong, at any rate, in calling it the most important 
contribution yet made to the development of the Darwinian theory, 
or rather to the solution of the awkward problem about which that 
theory has had to make such a circuit.  Dredge's hypothesis will be 
contested, may one day be disproved; but at least it has swept out 
of the way all previous conjectures, including of course Lanfear's 
magnificent attempt; and for our generation of scientific 
investigators it will serve as the first safe bridge across a 
murderous black whirlpool. 
</p><p>It's all very interesting&mdash;there are few things more stirring 
to the imagination than that sudden projection of the new 
hypothesis, light as a cobweb and strong as steel, across the 
intellectual abyss; but, for an idle observer of human motives, the 
other, the personal, side of Dredge's case is even more interesting 
and arresting. 
</p><p>Personal side?  You didn't know there was one?  Pictured him 
simply as a thinking machine, a highly specialized instrument of 
precision, the result of a long series of "adaptations," as his own 
jargon would put it?  Well, I don't wonder&mdash;if you've met him.  He 
does give the impression of being something out of his own 
laboratory: a delicate scientific instrument that reveals wonders 
to the initiated, and is absolutely useless in an ordinary hand. 
</p><p>In his youth it was just the other way.  I knew him twenty 
years ago, as an awkward lout whom young Archie Lanfear had picked 
up at college, and brought home for a visit.  I happened to be 
staying at the Lanfears' when the boys arrived, and I shall never 
forget Dredge's first appearance on the scene.  You know the 
Lanfears always lived very simply.  That summer they had gone to 
Buzzard's Bay, in order that Professor Lanfear might be near the 
Biological Station at Wood's Holl, and they were picnicking in a 
kind of sketchy bungalow without any attempt at elegance.  But 
Galen Dredge couldn't have been more awe-struck if he'd been 
suddenly plunged into a Fifth Avenue ball-room.  He nearly knocked 
his shock head against the low doorway, and in dodging this peril 
trod heavily on Mabel Lanfear's foot, and became hopelessly 
entangled in her mother's draperies&mdash;though how he managed it I 
never knew, for Mrs. Lanfear's dowdy muslins ran to no excess of 
train. 
</p><p>When the Professor himself came in it was ten times worse, and 
I saw then that Dredge's emotion was a tribute to the great man's 
proximity.  That made the boy interesting, and I began to watch.  
Archie, always enthusiastic but vague, had said: "Oh, he's a 
tremendous chap&mdash;you'll see&mdash;" but I hadn't expected to see quite 
so clearly.  Lanfear's vision, of course, was sharper than mine; 
and the next morning he had carried Dredge off to the Biological 
Station.  And that was the way it began. 
</p><p>Dredge is the son of a Baptist minister.  He comes from East 
Lethe, New York State, and was working his way through college&mdash; 
waiting at White Mountain hotels in summer&mdash;when Archie Lanfear ran 
across him.  There were eight children in the family, and the 
mother was an invalid.  Dredge never had a penny from his father 
after he was fourteen; but his mother wanted him to be a scholar, 
and "kept at him," as he put it, in the hope of his going back to 
"teach school" at East Lethe.  He developed slowly, as the 
scientific mind generally does, and was still adrift about <pb n="166"/>  
himself and his tendencies when Archie took him down to Buzzard's 
Bay.  But he had read Lanfear's "Utility and Variation," and had 
always been a patient and curious observer of nature.  And his 
first meeting with Lanfear explained him to himself.  It didn't, 
however, enable him to explain himself to others, and for a long 
time he remained, to all but Lanfear, an object of incredulity and 
conjecture. 
</p><p><hi rend="italic">" Why</hi> my husband wants him about&mdash;" poor Mrs. Lanfear, the 
kindest of women, privately lamented to her friends; for Dredge, at 
that time&mdash;they kept him all summer at the bungalow&mdash;had one of the 
most encumbering personalities you can imagine.  He was as 
inexpressive as he is to-day, and yet oddly obtrusive: one of those 
uncomfortable presences whose silence is an interruption. 
</p><p>The poor Lanfears almost died of him that summer, and the pity 
of it was that he never suspected it, but continued to lavish on 
them a floundering devotion as uncomfortable as the endearments of 
a dripping dog&mdash;all out of gratitude for the Professor's kindness!  
He was full, in those days, of raw enthusiasms, which he forced on 
any one who would listen when his first shyness had worn off.  You 
can't picture him spouting sentimental poetry, can you?  Yet I've 
seen him petrify a whole group of Mrs. Lanfear's callers by 
suddenly discharging on them, in the strident drawl of Western New 
York, "Barbara Frietchie" or "The Queen of the May."  His taste in 
literature was uniformly bad, but very definite, and far more 
assertive than his views on biological questions.  In his 
scientific judgments he showed, even then, a remarkable temperance, 
a precocious openness to the opposite view; but in literature he 
was a furious propagandist, aggressive, disputatious, and extremely 
sensitive to adverse opinion. 
</p><p>Lanfear, of course, had been struck from the first by his gift 
of accurate observation, and by the fact that his eagerness to 
learn was offset by his reluctance to conclude.  I remember 
Lanfear's telling me that he had never known a lad of Dredge's age 
who gave such promise of uniting an aptitude for general ideas with 
the plodding patience of the accumulator of facts.  Of course when 
Lanfear talked like that of a young biologist his fate was sealed.  
There could be no question of Dredge's going back to "teach school" 
at East Lethe.  He must take a course in biology at Columbia, spend 
his vacations at the Wood's Holl laboratory, and then, if possible, 
go to Germany for a year or two. 
</p><p>All this meant his virtual adoption by the Lanfears.  Most of 
Lanfear's fortune went in helping young students to a start, and he 
devoted his heaviest subsidies to Dredge. 
</p><p>"Dredge will be my biggest dividend&mdash;you'll see!" he used to 
say, in the chrysalis days when poor Galen was known to the world 
of science only as a perpetual slouching presence in Mrs. Lanfear's 
drawing-room.  And Dredge, it must be said, took his obligations 
simply, with that kind of personal dignity, and quiet sense of his 
own worth, which in such cases saves the beneficiary from 
abjectness.  He seemed to trust himself as fully as Lanfear trusted 
him. 
</p><p>The comic part of it was that his only idea of making what is 
known as "a return" was to devote himself to the Professor's 
family.  When I hear pretty women lamenting that they can't coax 
Professor Dredge out of his laboratory I remember Mabel Lanfear's 
cry to me: "If Galen would only keep away!"  When Mabel fell on the 
ice and broke her leg, Galen walked seven miles in a blizzard to 
get a surgeon; but if he did her this service one day in the year, 
he bored her by being in the way for the other three hundred and 
sixty-four.  One would have imagined at that time that he thought 
his perpetual presence the greatest gift he could bestow; for, 
except on the occasion of his fetching the surgeon, I don't 
remember his taking any other way of expressing his gratitude. 
</p><p>In love with Mabel?  Not a bit!  But the queer thing was that 
he <hi rend="italic"> did</hi> have a passion in those days&mdash;a blind, hopeless passion 
for Mrs. Lanfear!  Yes: I know what I'm saying.  I mean Mrs. 
Lanfear, the Professor's wife, poor Mrs. Lanfear, with her tight 
hair and her loose figure, her blameless brow and earnest eye-glasses, and her perpetual attitude of mild misapprehension.  I can 
see Dredge cowering, long and many-jointed, in a diminutive 
drawing-room chair, one square-toed shoe coiled round an exposed 
ankle, his knees clasped in a knot of red knuckles, and his 
spectacles perpetually seeking Mrs. Lanfear's eye-glasses.  I never 
knew if the poor lady was aware of the sentiment she inspired, but 
her <pb n="167"/>  children observed it, and it provoked them to 
irreverent mirth.  Galen was the predestined butt of Mabel and 
Archie; and secure in their mother's virtuous obtuseness, and in 
her worshipper's timidity, they allowed themselves a latitude of 
banter that sometimes turned their audience cold.  Dredge meanwhile 
was going on obstinately with his work.  Now and then he had queer 
fits of idleness, when he lapsed into a state of sulky inertia from 
which even Lanfear's admonitions could not rouse him.  Once, just 
before an examination, he suddenly went off to the Maine woods for 
two weeks, came back, and failed to pass.  I don't know if his 
benefactor ever lost hope; but at times his confidence must have 
been sorely strained.  The queer part of it was that when Dredge 
emerged from these eclipses he seemed keener and more active than 
ever.  His slowly growing intelligence probably needed its 
periodical pauses of assimilation; and Lanfear was marvellously 
patient. 
</p><p>At last Dredge finished his course and went to Germany; and 
when he came back he was a new man&mdash;was, in fact, the Dredge we all 
know.  He seemed to have shed his blundering, encumbering 
personality, and come to life as a disembodied intelligence.  His 
fidelity to the Lanfears was unchanged; but he showed it 
negatively, by his discretions and abstentions.  I have an idea 
that Mabel was less disposed to deride him, might even have been 
induced to softer sentiments; but I doubt if Dredge even noticed 
the change.  As for his ex-goddess, he seemed to regard her as a 
motherly household divinity, the guardian genius of the darning 
needle; but on Professor Lanfear he looked with a deepening 
reverence.  If the rest of the family had diminished in his eyes, 
its head had grown even greater. 
</p></div2> 
<div2 type="section" n="2" id="d5"><head>II</head> 

<p>FROM that day Dredge's progress continued steadily.  If not 
always perceptible to the untrained eye, in Lanfear's sight it 
never deviated, and the great man began to associate Dredge with 
his work, and to lean on him more and more.  Lanfear's health was 
already failing, and in my confidential talks with him I saw how he 
counted on Galen Dredge to continue and amplify his doctrine.  If 
he did not describe the young man as his predestined Huxley, it was 
because any such comparison between himself and his great 
predecessors would have been repugnant to his taste; but he 
evidently felt that it would be Dredge's role to reveal him to 
posterity.  And the young man seemed at that time to take the same 
view of his calling.  When he was not busy about Lanfear's work he 
was recording their conversations with the diligence of a 
biographer and the accuracy of a naturalist.  Any attempt to 
question or minimize Lanfear's theories roused in his disciple the 
only flashes of wrath I have ever seen a scientific discussion 
provoke in him.  In defending his master he became almost as 
intemperate as in the early period of his literary passions. 
</p><p>Such filial dedication must have been all the more precious to 
Lanfear because, about that time, it became evident that Archie 
would never carry on his father's work.  He had begun brilliantly, 
you may remember, by a little paper on <hi rend="italic"> Limulus Polyphemus</hi> that 
attracted a good deal of notice when it appeared in the <hi rend="italic"> Central 
Blatt</hi>; but gradually his zoological ardour yielded to an absorbing 
passion for the violin, which was followed by a sudden plunge into 
physics.  At present, after a side-glance at the drama, I 
understand he's devoting what is left of his father's money to 
archaeological explorations in Asia Minor. 
</p><p>"Archie's got a delightful little mind," Lanfear used to say 
to me, rather wistfully, "but it's just a highly polished surface 
held up to the show as it passes.  Dredge's mind takes in only a 
bit at a time, but the bit stays, and other bits are joined to it, 
in a hard mosaic of fact, of which imagination weaves the pattern.  
I saw just how it would be years ago, when my boy used to take my 
meaning in a flash, and answer me with clever objections, while 
Galen disappeared into one of his fathomless silences, and then 
came to the surface like a dripping retriever, a long way beyond 
Archie's objections, and with an answer to them in his mouth." 
</p><p>It was about this time that the crowning satisfaction of 
Lanfear's career came to him: I mean, of course, John Weyman's gift 
to Columbia of the Lanfear Laboratory, and the founding, in 
connection with it, of a chair of Experimental Evolution.  Weyman 
had always taken an interest in Lanfear's work, but no one had 
supposed <pb n="168"/>  that his interest would express itself so 
magnificently.  The honour came to Lanfear at a time when he was 
fighting an accumulation of troubles: failing health, the money 
difficulties resulting from his irrepressible generosity, his 
disappointment about Archie's career, and perhaps also the 
persistent attacks of the new school of German zoologists. 
</p><p>"If I hadn't Galen I should feel the game was up," he said to 
me once, in a fit of half-real, half-mocking despondency.  "But 
he'll do what I haven't time to do myself, and what my boy can't do 
for me." 
</p><p>That meant that he would answer the critics, and triumphantly 
affirm Lanfear's theory, which had been rudely shaken, but not 
displaced. 
</p><p>"A scientific hypothesis lasts till there's something else to 
put in its place.  People who want to get across a river will use 
the old bridge till the new one's built.  And I don't see any one 
who's particularly anxious, in this case, to take a contract for 
the new one," Lanfear ended; and I remember answering with a laugh: 
"Not while Horatius Dredge holds the other." 
</p><p>It was generally known that Lanfear had not long to live, and 
the Laboratory was hardly opened before the question of his 
successor in the chair of Experimental Evolution began to be a 
matter of public discussion.  It was conceded that whoever followed 
him ought to be a man of achieved reputation, some one carrying, as 
the French say, a considerable "baggage."  At the same time, even 
Lanfear's critics felt that he should be succeeded by a man who 
held his views and would continue his teaching.  This was not in 
itself a difficulty, for German criticism had so far been mainly 
negative, and there were plenty of good men who, while they 
questioned the permanent validity of Lanfear's conclusions, were 
yet ready to accept them for their provisional usefulness.  And 
then there was the added inducement of the Laboratory!  The 
Columbia Professor of Experimental Evolution has at his disposal 
the most complete instrument of biological research that modern 
ingenuity has yet produced; and it's not only in theology or 
politics <hi rend="italic"> que Paris vaut bien une messe!</hi>  There was no trouble 
about finding a candidate; but the whole thing turned on Lanfear's 
decision, since it was tacitly understood that, by Weyman's wish, 
he was to select his successor.  And what a cry there was when he 
selected Galen Dredge! 
</p><p>Not in the scientific world, though.  The specialists were 
beginning to know about Dredge.  His remarkable paper on Sexual 
Dimorphism had been translated into several languages, and a 
furious polemic had broken out over it.  When a young fellow can 
get the big men fighting over him his future is pretty well 
assured.  But Dredge was only thirty-four, and some people seemed 
to feel that there was a kind of deflected nepotism in Lanfear's 
choice. 
</p><p>"If he could choose Dredge he might as well have chosen his 
own son," I've heard it said; and the irony was that Archie&mdash;will 
you believe it?&mdash;actually thought so himself!  But Lanfear had 
Weyman behind him, and when the end came the Faculty at once 
appointed Galen Dredge to the chair of Experimental Evolution. 
</p><p>For the first two years things went quietly, along accustomed 
lines.  Dredge simply continued the course which Lanfear's death 
had interrupted.  He lectured well even then, with a persuasive 
simplicity surprising in the slow, inarticulate creature one knew 
him for.  But haven't you noticed that certain personalities reveal 
themselves only in the more impersonal relations of life?  It's as 
if they woke only to collective contacts, and the single 
consciousness were an unmeaning fragment to them. 
</p><p>If there was anything to criticize in that first part of the 
course, it was the avoidance of general ideas, of those brilliant 
rockets of conjecture that Lanfear's students were used to seeing 
him fling across the darkness.  I remember once saying this to 
Archie, who, having recovered from his absurd disappointment, had 
returned to his old allegiance to Dredge. 
</p><p>"Oh, that's Galen all over.  He doesn't want to jump into the 
ring till he has a big swishing knock-down argument in his fist.  
He'll wait twenty years if he has to.  That's his strength: he's 
never afraid to wait." 
</p><p>I thought this shrewd of Archie, as well as generous; and I 
saw the wisdom of Dredge's course.  As Lanfear himself had said, 
his theory was safe enough till somebody found a more attractive 
one; and before that day Dredge would probably have accumulated 
sufficient proof to crystallize the fluid hypothesis.  
</p> 
</div2> 
<pb n="169"/>  
<div2 type="section" n="3" id="d6"><head>III</head> 

<p>THE third winter I was off collecting in Central America, and 
didn't get back till Dredge's course had been going for a couple of 
months.  The very day I turned up in town Archie Lanfear descended 
on me with a summons from his mother.  I was wanted at once at a 
family council. 
</p><p>I found the Lanfear ladies in a state of incoherent distress, 
which Archie's own indignation hardly made more intelligible.  But 
gradually I put together their fragmentary charges, and learned 
that Dredge's lectures were turning into an organized assault on 
his master's doctrine. 
</p><p>"It amounts to just this," Archie said, controlling his women 
with the masterful gesture of the weak man.  "Galen has simply 
turned round and betrayed my father." 
</p><p>"Just for a handful of silver he left us," Mabel sobbed in 
parenthesis, while Mrs. Lanfear tearfully cited Hamlet. 
</p><p>Archie silenced them again.  "The ugly part of it is that he 
must have had this up his sleeve for years.  He must have known 
when he was asked to succeed my father what use he meant to make of 
his opportunity.  What he's doing isn't the result of a hasty 
conclusion: it means years of work and preparation." 
</p><p>Archie broke off to explain himself.  He had returned from 
Europe the week before, and had learned on arriving that Dredge's 
lectures were stirring the world of science as nothing had stirred 
it since Lanfear's "Utility and Variation."  And the incredible 
outrage was that they owed their sensational effect to the fact of 
being an attempted refutation of Lanfear's great work. 
</p><p>I own that I was staggered: the case looked ugly, as Archie 
said.  And there was a veil of reticence, of secrecy, about Dredge, 
that always kept his conduct in a half-light of uncertainty.  Of 
some men one would have said off-hand: "It's impossible!"  But one 
couldn't affirm it of him. 
</p><p>Archie hadn't seen him as yet; and Mrs. Lanfear had sent for 
me because she wished me to be present at the interview between the 
two men.  The Lanfear ladies had a touching belief in Archie's 
violence: they thought him as terrible as a natural force.  My own 
idea was that if there were any broken bones they wouldn't be 
Dredge's; but I was too curious as to the outcome not to be glad to 
offer my services as moderator. 
</p><p>First, however, I wanted to hear one of the lectures; and I 
went the next afternoon.  The hall was jammed, and I saw, as soon 
as Dredge appeared, what increased security and ease the interest 
of his public had given him.  He had been clear the year before, 
now he was also eloquent.  The lecture was a remarkable effort: 
you'll find the gist of it in Chapter VII of "The Arrival of the 
Fittest."  Archie sat at my side in a white rage; he was too clever 
not to measure the extent of the disaster.  And I was almost as 
indignant as he when we went to see Dredge the next day. 
</p><p>I saw at a glance that the latter suspected nothing; and it 
was characteristic of him that he began by questioning me about my 
finds, and only afterward turned to reproach Archie for having been 
back a week without notifying him. 
</p><p>"You know I'm up to my neck in this job.  Why in the world 
didn't you hunt me up before this?" 
</p><p>The question was exasperating, and I could understand Archie's 
stammer of wrath. 
</p><p>"Hunt you up?  Hunt you up?  What the deuce are you made of, 
to ask me such a question instead of wondering why I'm here now?" 
</p><p>Dredge bent his slow calm scrutiny on his friend's quivering 
face; then he turned to me. 
</p><p>"What's the matter?" he said simply. 
</p><p>"The matter?" shrieked Archie, his clenched fist hovering 
excitedly above the desk by which he stood; but Dredge, with 
unwonted quickness, caught the fist as it descended. 
</p><p>"Careful&mdash;I've got a <hi rend="italic"> Kallima</hi> in that jar there."  He 
pushed a chair forward, and added quietly: "Sit down." 
</p><p>Archie, ignoring the gesture, towered pale and avenging in his 
place; and Dredge, after a moment, took the chair himself. 
</p><p>"The matter?" Archie reiterated with rising passion.  "Are you 
so lost to all sense of decency and honour that you can put that 
question in good faith?  Don't you really <hi rend="italic"> know</hi> what's the 
matter?" 
</p><p>Dredge smiled slowly.  "There are so few things one <hi rend="italic"> really 
knows</hi>." 
</p><p>"Oh, damn your scientific hair-splitting!  Don't you know 
you're insulting my father's memory?" <pb n="170"/>  
</p><p>Dredge stared again, turning his spectacles thoughtfully from 
one of us to the other. 
</p><p>"Oh, that's it, is it?  Then you'd better sit down.  If you 
don't see at once it'll take some time to make you." 
</p><p>Archie burst into an ironic laugh. 
</p><p>"I rather think it will!" he conceded. 
</p><p>"Sit down, Archie," I said, setting the example; and he 
obeyed, with a gesture that made his consent a protest. 
</p><p>Dredge seemed to notice nothing beyond the fact that his 
visitors were seated.  He reached for his pipe, and filled it with 
the care which the habit of delicate manipulations gave to all the 
motions of his long, knotty hands. 
</p><p>"It's about the lectures?" he said. 
</p><p>Archie's answer was a deep scornful breath. 
</p><p>"You've only been back a week, so you've only heard one, I 
suppose?" 
</p><p>"It was not necessary to hear even that one.  You must know 
the talk they're making.  If notoriety is what you're after&mdash;" 
</p><p>"Well, I'm not sorry to make a noise," said Dredge, putting a 
match to his pipe. 
</p><p>Archie bounded in his chair.  "There's no easier way of doing 
it than to attack a man who can't answer you!" 
</p><p>Dredge raised a sobering hand.  "Hold on.  Perhaps you and I 
don't mean the same thing.  Tell me first what's in your mind." 
</p><p>The request steadied Archie, who turned on Dredge a 
countenance really eloquent with filial indignation. 
</p><p>"It's an odd question for you to ask; it makes me wonder 
what's in yours.  Not much thought of my father, at any rate, or 
you couldn't stand in his place and use the chance he's given you 
to push yourself at his expense." 
</p><p>Dredge received this in silence, puffing slowly at his pipe. 
</p><p>"Is that the way it strikes you?" he asked at length. 
</p><p>"God!  It's the way it would strike most men." 
</p><p>He turned to me.  "You too?" 
</p><p>"I can see how Archie feels," I said. 
</p><p>"That I'm attacking his father's memory to glorify myself?" 
</p><p>"Well, not precisely: I think what he really feels is that, if 
your convictions didn't permit you to continue his father's 
teaching, you might perhaps have done better to sever your 
connection with the Lanfear lectureship." 
</p><p>"Then you and he regard the Lanfear lectureship as having been 
founded to perpetuate a dogma, not to try and get at the truth?" 
</p><p>"Certainly not," Archie broke in.  "But there's a question of 
taste, of delicacy, involved in the case that can't be decided on 
abstract principles.  We know as well as you that my father meant 
the laboratory and the lectureship to serve the ends of science, at 
whatever cost to his own special convictions; what we feel&mdash;and you 
don't seem to&mdash;is that you're the last man to put them to that use; 
and I don't want to remind you why." 
</p><p>A slight redness rose through Dredge's sallow skin.  "You 
needn't," he said.  "It's because he pulled me out of my hole, woke 
me up, made me, shoved me off from the shore.  Because he saved me 
ten or twenty years of muddled effort, and put me where I am at an 
age when my best working years are still ahead of me.  Every one 
knows that's what your father did for me, but I'm the only person 
who knows the time and trouble that it took." 
</p><p>It was well said, and I glanced quickly at Archie, who was 
never closed to generous emotions. 
</p><p>"Well, then&mdash;?" he said, flushing also. 
</p><p>"Well, then," Dredge continued, his voice deepening and losing 
its nasal edge, "I had to pay him back, didn't I?" 
</p><p>The sudden drop flung Archie back on his prepared attitude of 
irony.  "It would be the natural inference&mdash;with most men." 
</p><p>"Just so.  And I'm not so very different.  I knew your father 
wanted a successor&mdash;some one who'd try and tie up the loose ends.  
And I took the lectureship with that object." 
</p><p>"And you're using it to tear the whole fabric to pieces!" 
</p><p>Dredge paused to re-light his pipe.  "Looks that way," he 
conceded.  "This year anyhow." 
</p><p><hi rend="italic">" This year</hi>&mdash;?" Archie gasped at him. 
</p><p>"Yes.  When I took up the job I saw it just as your father 
left it.  Or rather, I didn't see any other way of going on with 
it.  The change came gradually, as I worked." 
</p><p>"Gradually?  So that you had time to look round you, to know 
where you were, to see you were fatally committed to undoing the 
work he had done?" <pb n="171"/>  
</p><p>"Oh, yes&mdash;I had time," Dredge conceded. 
</p><p>"And yet you kept the chair and went on with the course?" 
</p><p>Dredge refilled his pipe, and then turned in his seat so that 
he looked squarely at Archie. 
</p><p>"What would your father have done in my place?" he asked. 
</p><p>"In your place&mdash;?" 
</p><p>"Yes: supposing he'd found out the things I've found out in 
the last year or two.  You'll see what they are, and how much they 
count, if you'll run over the report of the lectures.  If your 
father'd been alive he might have come across the same facts just 
as easily." 
</p><p>There was a silence which Archie at last broke by saying: "But 
he didn't, and you did.  There's the difference." 
</p><p>"The difference?  What difference?  Would your father have 
suppressed the facts if he'd found them?  It's <hi rend="italic"> you</hi> who insult 
his memory by implying it!  And if I'd brought them to him, would 
he have used his hold over me to get me to suppress them?" 
</p><p>"Certainly not.  But can't you see it's his death that makes 
the difference?  He's not here to defend his case." 
</p><p>Dredge laughed, but not unkindly.  "My dear Archie, your 
father wasn't one of the kind who bother to defend their case.  Men 
like him are the masters, not the servants, of their theories.  
They respect an idea only as long as it's of use to them; when it's 
usefulness ends they chuck it out.  And that's what your father 
would have done." 
</p><p>Archie reddened.  "Don't you assume a good deal in taking it 
for granted that he would have had to in this particular case?" 
</p><p>Dredge reflected.  Yes: I was going too far.  Each of us can 
only answer for himself.  But to my mind your father's theory is 
refuted." 
</p><p>"And you don't hesitate to be the man to do it?" 
</p><p>"Should I have been of any use if I had?  And did your father 
ever ask anything of me but to be of as much use as I could?" 
</p><p>It was Archie's turn to reflect.  "No.  That was what he 
always wanted, of course." 
</p><p>"That's the way I've always felt.  The first day he took me 
away from East Lethe I knew the debt I was piling up against him, 
and I never had any doubt as to how I'd pay it, or how he'd want it 
paid.  He didn't pick me out and train me for any object but to 
carry on the light.  Do you suppose he'd have wanted me to snuff it 
out because it happened to light up a fact he didn't fancy?  I'm 
using <hi rend="italic"> his</hi> oil to feed my torch with: yes, but it isn't really 
his torch or mine, or his oil or mine: they belong to each of us 
till we drop and hand them on." 
</p><p>Archie turned a sobered glance on him.  "I see your point.  
But if the job had to be done I don't see that you need have done 
it from his chair." 
</p><p>"There's where we differ.  If I did it at all I had to do it 
in the best way, and with all the authority his backing gave me.  
If I owe your father anything, I owe him that.  It would have made 
him sick to see the job badly done.  And don't you see that the way 
to honour him, and show what he's done for science, was to spare no 
advantage in my attack on him&mdash;that I'm proving the strength of his 
position by the desperateness of my assault?"  Dredge paused and 
squared his lounging shoulders.  "After all," he added, "he's not 
down yet, and if I leave him standing I guess it'll be some time 
before anybody else cares to tackle him." 
</p><p>There was a silence between the two men; then Dredge continued 
in a lighter tone:  "There's one thing, though, that we're both in 
danger of forgetting: and that is how little, in the long run, it 
all counts either way."  He smiled a little at Archie's outraged 
gesture.  "The most we can any of us do&mdash;even by such a magnificent 
effort as your father's&mdash;is to turn the great marching army a 
hair's breadth nearer what seems to us the right direction; if one 
of us drops out, here and there, the loss of headway's hardly 
perceptible.  And that's what I'm coming to now." 
</p><p>He rose from his seat, and walked across to the hearth; then, 
cautiously resting his shoulder-blades against the mantel-shelf 
jammed with miscellaneous specimens, he bent his musing spectacles 
on Archie. 
</p><p>"Your father would have understood why I've done, what I'm 
doing; but that's no reason why the rest of you should.  And I 
rather think it's the rest of you who've suffered most from me.  He 
always knew what I was <hi rend="italic"> there for</hi>, and that must have been some 
comfort even when I was most in the way; but I was just an ordinary 
nuisance to you and your mother and <pb n="172"/>  Mabel.  You were all 
too kind to let me see it at the time, but I've seen it since, and 
it makes me feel that, after all, the settling of this matter lies 
with you.  If it hurts you to have me go on with my examination of 
your father's theory, I'm ready to drop the lectures to-morrow, and 
trust to the Lanfear Laboratory to breed up a young chap who'll 
knock us both out in time.  You've only got to say the word." 
</p><p>There was a pause while Dredge turned and laid his 
extinguished pipe carefully between a jar of embryo sea-urchins and 
a colony of regenerating planarians. 
</p><p>Then Archie rose and held out his hand. 
</p><p>"No," he said simply; "go on." 
</p> 
 
</div2> 
</div1> 
</body> 
</text> 
</TEI.2> 
