<?xml version="1.0"?>

<?dlps id="WhaDesc"?>
<?dlps page-images="none" figure-images="no"?>
<?dlps transcription="other"?>

<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/tei-p4/tei2.dtd" [
<!ENTITY % POSTKB "INCLUDE">
<!ENTITY % TEI.extensions.ent SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.ent">
<!ENTITY % TEI.extensions.dtd SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.dtd">
<!ENTITY % ISOnum SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/charent/iso-num.ent"> %ISOnum;
<!ENTITY % ISOpub SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/charent/iso-pub.ent"> %ISOpub;

]>

<TEI.2 id="WhaDesc"> 
<teiHeader type="migrated" creator="Etext">
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title type="main">The Descent of Man</title>
<title type="sort">descent of man</title>
<author>Wharton, Edith, 1862-1937</author>
<respStmt>
<resp>Creation of machine-readable version:</resp>
<name>Judy Boss</name>
</respStmt>
<respStmt>
<resp>Conversion to TEI-conformant markup:</resp>
<name>University of Virginia Library Electronic Text Center</name>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt> 
<extent>ca. <num type="kilobytes">48</num> kilobytes</extent> 
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>University of Virginia Library</publisher>
<pubPlace>Charlottesville, Virginia</pubPlace>
<idno type="ETC">WhaDesc</idno> 
<date value="1995">1995</date>
<availability status="public">
<p n="copyright">Copyright &copy; 1995 by the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia</p>
<p n="access">Publicly accessible</p>
</availability>
<idno type="uva-pid">uva-lib:476487</idno>
</publicationStmt>
<seriesStmt>
<title>University of Virginia Library, Text collection</title>
<idno type="uva-set">UVA-LIB-Text</idno>
</seriesStmt> 
<sourceDesc>
<biblFull>
<titleStmt>
<title type="main">The Descent of Man</title>
<title type="sort">descent of man</title>
<author>Wharton, Edith</author>
</titleStmt> 
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>Scribner's Magazine</publisher>
<date value="1904-03">Mar. 1904</date>
</publicationStmt> 
<notesStmt>
<note>
<p>Vol. 35</p>
</note>
</notesStmt>
</biblFull>
</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc> 
<encodingDesc>
<projectDesc>
<p>Prepared for the University of Virginia Library Electronic Text Center</p>
</projectDesc> 
<editorialDecl>
<p>All quotation marks retained as data</p> 
<p>Verification made against printed text</p> 
<p id="ETC">Keywords in the header are a local Electronic Text Center scheme  
to aid in establishing analytical groupings</p>
</editorialDecl> 
<refsDecl>
<p>ID elements are given for each page element and are composed of the text's 
unique cryptogram and the given page number, as in SpeFQue1 for page one of  
Spenser's Faerie Queene.</p>
</refsDecl>
</encodingDesc> 
<profileDesc>
<creation>
<date value="1904">1904</date>
</creation> 
<langUsage>
<language id="eng" usage="main">English</language>
</langUsage> 
<textClass>
<keywords>
<term>fiction</term>
<term>prose</term>
</keywords>
</textClass>
</profileDesc> 
<revisionDesc>
<change>
<date value="1995-01">January 1995</date> 
<respStmt>
<resp>corrector</resp>
<name>David Seaman and Kelly Tetterton</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Header and basic TEI SGML encoding added</item>
</change> 
<change>
<date value="2005-07">July 2005</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>Corrector</resp>
<name>Margaret Konkol</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Converted SGML to XML and fixed tagging.</item>
</change>
<change>
<date value="2007-09">September 2007</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>Migration</resp>
<name>Ethan Gruber, University of Virginia Library</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Converted XML markup from TEI Lite to uva-dl-tei (TEI P4 with local customizations).</item>
</change>
<change>
<date value="2008-01">January 2008</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>Migration</resp>
<name>Greg Murray, University of Virginia Library</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Programmatically updated TEI header markup (but not header content) for minimal compliance with current QA requirements.</item>
</change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader> 
<text id="d1">  
<body id="d2"> 
<div1 type="story" id="d3"> 
<head> 
Wharton, Edith.  "The Descent of Man."   
<lb/><hi rend="italic"> Scribner's Magazine</hi>  
35 (Mar. 1904): 313-22. 
</head> 
<pb n="313"/>  
<div2 type="section" n="1" id="d4"> 
<head>                            I 
</head> 
<p>WHEN Professor Linyard came back from his holiday in the Maine 
woods the air of rejuvenation he brought with him was due less to 
the influences of the climate than to the companionship he had 
enjoyed on his travels.  To Mrs. Linyard's observant eye he had 
appeared to set out alone; but an invisible traveller had in fact 
accompanied him, and if his heart beat high it was simply at the 
pitch of his adventure: for the Professor had eloped with an idea. 
</p><p>No one who has not tried the experiment can divine its 
exhilaration.  Professor Linyard would not have changed places with 
any hero of romance pledged to a flesh-and-blood abduction.  The 
most fascinating female is apt to be encumbered with luggage and 
scruples: to take up a good deal of room in the present and overlap 
inconveniently into the future; whereas an idea can accommodate 
itself to a single molecule of the brain or expand to the 
circumference of the horizon.  The Professor's companion had to the 
utmost this quality of adaptability.  As the express train whirled 
him away from the somewhat inelastic circle of Mrs. Linyard's 
affections, his idea seemed to be sitting opposite him, and their 
eyes met every moment or two in a glance of joyous complicity; yet 
when a friend of the family presently joined him and began to talk 
about college matters, the idea slipped out of sight in a flash, 
and the Professor would have had no difficulty in proving that he 
was alone. 
</p><p>But if, from the outset, he found his idea the most agreeable 
of fellow-travellers, it was only in the aromatic solitude of the 
woods that he tasted the full savour of his adventure.  There, 
during the long cool August days, lying full length on the pine-needles and gazing up into the sky, he would meet the eyes of his 
companion bending over him like a nearer heaven.  And what eyes 
they were!&mdash;clear yet unfathomable, bubbling with inexhaustible 
laughter, yet drawing their freshness and sparkle from the central 
depths of thought!  To a man who for twenty years had faced an eye 
reflecting the obvious with perfect accuracy, these escapes into 
the inscrutable had always been peculiarly inviting; but hitherto 
the Professor's mental infidelities had been restricted by an 
unbroken and relentless domesticity.  Now, for the first time since 
his marriage, chance had given him six weeks to himself, and he was 
coming home with his lungs full of liberty. 
</p><p>It must not be inferred that the Professor's domestic 
relations were defective: they were in fact so complete that it was 
almost impossible to get away from them.  It is the happy husbands 
who are really in bondage; the little rift within the lute is often 
a passage to freedom.  Marriage had given the Professor exactly 
what he had sought in it; a comfortable lining to life.  The 
impossibility of rising to sentimental crises had made him 
scrupulously careful not to shirk the practical obligations of the 
bond.  He took as it were a sociological view of his case, and 
modestly regarded himself as a brick in that foundation on which 
the state is supposed to rest.  Perhaps if Mrs. Linyard had cared 
about entomology, or had taken sides in the war over the 
transmission of acquired characteristics, he might have had a less 
impersonal notion of marriage; but he was unconscious of any 
deficiency in their relation, and if consulted would probably have 
declared that he didn't want any woman bothering with his beetles.  
His real life had always lain in the universe of thought, in that 
enchanted region which, to those who have lingered there, comes to 
have so much more colour and substance than the painted curtain 
hanging before it.  The Professor's particular veil of Maia was a 
narrow strip of homespun woven in a monotonous pattern; but he had 
only to lift it to step into an empire. 
</p><p>This unseen universe was thronged with <pb n="314"/>  the most 
seductive shapes: the Professor moved Sultan-like through a 
seraglio of ideas.  But of all the lovely apparitions that wove 
their spells about him, none had ever worn quite so persuasive an 
aspect as this latest favourite.  For the others were mostly rather 
grave companions, serious-minded and elevating enough to have 
passed muster in a Ladies' Debating Club; but this new fancy of the 
Professor's was simply one embodied laugh.  It was, in other words, 
the smile of relaxation at the end of a long day's toil: the flash 
of irony that the laborious mind projects, irresistibly, over 
labour conscientiously performed.  The Professor had always been a 
hard worker.  If he was an indulgent friend to his ideas, he was 
also a stern task-master to them.  For, in addition to their other 
duties, they had to support his family: to pay the butcher and 
baker, and provide for Jack's schooling and Millicent's dresses.  
The Professor's household was a modest one, yet it tasked his ideas 
to keep it up to his wife's standard.  Mrs. Linyard was not an 
exacting wife, and she took enough pride in her husband's 
attainments to pay for her honours by turning Millicent's dresses 
and darning Jack's socks, and going to the College receptions year 
after year in the same black silk with shiny seams.  It consoled 
her to see an occasional mention of Professor Linyard's remarkable 
monograph on the Ethical Reactions of the Infusoria, or an allusion 
to his investigations into the Unconscious Cerebration of the 
Amoeba. 
</p><p>Still there were moments when the healthy indifference of Jack 
and Millicent reacted on the maternal sympathies; when Mrs. Linyard 
would have made her husband a railway-director, if by this 
transformation she might have increased her boy's allowance and 
given her daughter a new hat, or a set of furs such as the other 
girls were wearing.  Of such moments of rebellion the Professor 
himself was not wholly unconscious.  He could not indeed understand 
why any one should want a new hat; and as to an allowance, he had 
had much less money at college than Jack, and had yet managed to 
buy a microscope and collect a few "specimens"; while Jack was free 
from such expensive tastes!  But the Professor did not let his want 
of sympathy interfere with the discharge of his paternal 
obligations.  He worked hard to keep the wants of his family 
gratified, and it was precisely in the endeavor to attain this end 
that he at length broke down and had to cease from work altogether. 
</p><p>To cease from work was not to cease from thought of it; and in 
the unwonted pause from effort the Professor found himself taking 
a general survey of the field he had travelled.  At last it was 
possible to lift his nose from the loom, to step a moment in front 
of the tapestry he had been weaving.  From this first inspection of 
the pattern so long wrought over from behind, it was natural to 
glance a little farther and seek its reflection in the public eye.  
It was not indeed of his special task that he thought in this 
connection.  He was but one of the great army of weavers at work 
among the threads of that cosmic woof; and what he sought was the 
general impression their labour had produced. 
</p><p>When Professor Linyard first plied his microscope, the 
audience of the man of science had been composed of a few fellow-students, sympathetic or hostile as their habits of mind 
predetermined, but versed in the jargon of the profession and 
familiar with the point of departure.  In the intervening quarter 
of a century, however, this little group had been swallowed up in 
a larger public.  Every one now read scientific books and expressed 
an opinion on them.  The ladies and the clergy had taken them up 
first; now they had passed to the school-room and the kindergarten.  
Daily life was regulated on scientific principles; the daily papers 
had their "Scientific Jottings"; nurses passed examinations in 
hygienic science, and babies were fed and dandled according to the 
new psychology. 
</p><p>The very fact that scientific investigation still had, to some 
minds, a flavour of heterodoxy, gave it a perennial interest.  The 
mob had broken down the walls of tradition to batten in the orchard 
of forbidden knowledge.  The inaccessible goddess whom the 
Professor had served in his youth now offered her charms in the 
market-place.  And yet it was not the same goddess after all, but 
a pseudo-science masquerading in the garb of the real divinity.  
This false goddess had her ritual and her literature.  She had her 
sacred books, written by false priests and sold by millions to the 
faithful.  In the most successful of <pb n="315"/>  these works, ancient 
dogma and modern discovery were depicted in a close embrace under 
the lime-lights of a hazy transcendentalism; and the tableau never 
failed of its effect.  Some of the books designed on this popular 
model had lately fallen into the Professor's hands, and they filled 
him with mingled rage and hilarity.  The rage soon died: he came to 
regard this mass of pseudo-literature as protecting the truth from 
desecration.  But the hilarity remained, and flowed into the form 
of his idea.  And the idea&mdash;the divine, incomparable idea&mdash;was 
simply that he should avenge his goddess by satirizing her false 
interpreters.  He would write a skit on the "popular" scientific 
book; he would so heap platitude on platitude, fallacy on fallacy, 
false analogy on false analogy, so use his superior knowledge to 
abound in the sense of the ignorant, that even the gross crowd 
would join in the laugh against its augurs.  And the laugh should 
be something more than the distension of mental muscles; it should 
be the trumpet-blast bringing down the walls of ignorance, or at 
least the little stone striking the giant between the eyes. 
</p></div2> 
<div2 type="section" n="2" id="d5"> 
<head> 
                           II 
</head> 
<p>THE Professor, on presenting his card, had imagined that it 
would command prompt access to the publisher's sanctuary; but the 
young man who read his name was not moved to immediate action.  It 
was clear that Professor Linyard of Hillbridge University was not 
a specific figure to the purveyors of popular literature.  But the 
publisher was an old friend; and when the card had finally drifted 
to his office on the languid tide of routine he came forth at once 
to greet his visitor. 
</p><p>The warmth of his welcome convinced the Professor that he had 
been right in bringing his manuscript to Ned Harviss.  He and 
Harviss had been at Hillbridge together, and the future publisher 
had been one of the wildest spirits in that band of college outlaws 
which yearly turns out so many inoffensive citizens and kind 
husbands and fathers.  The Professor knew the taming qualities of 
life.  He was aware that many of his most reckless comrades had 
been transformed into prudent capitalists or cowed wage-earners; 
but he was almost sure that he could count on Harviss.  So rare a 
sense of irony, so keen a perception of relative values, could 
hardly have been blunted even by twenty years' intercourse with the 
obvious. 
</p><p>The publisher's appearance was a little disconcerting.  He 
looked as if he had been fattened on popular fiction; and his fat 
was full of optimistic creases.  The Professor seemed to see him 
bowing into his office a long train of spotless heroines laden with 
the maiden tribute of the hundredth thousand volume. 
</p><p>Nevertheless, his welcome was reassuring.  He did not disown 
his early enormities, and capped his visitor's tentative allusions 
by such flagrant references to the past that the Professor produced 
his manuscript without a scruple. 
</p><p>"What&mdash;you don't mean to say you've been doing something in 
our line?" 
</p><p>The Professor smiled.  "You publish scientific books 
sometimes, don't you?" 
</p><p>The publisher's optimistic creases relaxed a little.  "H'm&mdash;it 
all depends&mdash;I'm afraid you're a little <hi rend="italic"> too</hi> scientific for us.  
We have a big sale for scientific breakfast foods, but not for the 
concentrated essences.  In your case, of course, I should be 
delighted to stretch a point; but in your own interest I ought to 
tell you that perhaps one of the educational houses would do you 
better." 
</p><p>The Professor leaned back, still smiling luxuriously. 
</p><p>"Well, look it over&mdash;I rather think you'll take it." 
</p><p>"Oh, we'll <hi rend="italic"> take</hi> it, as I say; but the terms might not&mdash;" 
</p><p>"No matter about the terms&mdash;" 
</p><p>The publisher threw his head back with a laugh.  "I had no 
idea that science was so profitable; we find our popular novelists 
are the hardest hands at a bargain." 
</p><p>"Science is disinterested," the Professor corrected him.  "And 
I have a fancy to have you publish this thing." 
</p><p>"That's immensely good of you, my dear fellow.  Of course your 
name goes with a certain public&mdash;and I rather like the originality 
of our bringing out a work so out of our line.  I daresay it may 
boom us both."  His creases deepened at the thought, and he shone 
encouragingly on the Professor's leave-taking. 
</p><p>Within a fortnight, a line from Harviss <pb n="316"/>  recalled the 
Professor to town.  He had been looking forward with immense zest 
to this second meeting; Harviss's college roar was in his tympanum, 
and he pictured himself following up the protracted chuckle which 
would follow his friend's progress through the manuscript.  He was 
proud of the adroitness with which he had kept his secret from 
Harviss, had maintained to the last the pretense of a serious work, 
in order to give the keener edge to his reader's enjoyment.  Not 
since under-graduate days had the Professor tasted such a draught 
of pure fun as his anticipations now poured for him. 
</p><p>This time his card brought instant admission.  He was bowed 
into the office like a successful novelist, and Harviss grasped him 
with both hands. 
</p><p>"Well&mdash;do you mean to take it?" he asked, with a lingering 
coquetry. 
</p><p>"Take it?  Take it, my dear fellow?  It's in press already&mdash; 
you'll excuse my not waiting to consult you?  There will be no 
difficulty about terms, I assure you, and we had barely time to 
catch the autumn market.  My dear Linyard, why didn't you <hi rend="italic"> tell</hi> 
me?"  His voice sank to a reproachful solemnity, and he pushed 
forward his own arm-chair. 
</p><p>The Professor dropped into it with a chuckle.  "And miss the 
joy of letting you find out?" 
</p><p>"Well&mdash;it <hi rend="italic">was</hi> a joy."  Harviss held out a box of his best 
cigars.  "I don't know when I've had a bigger sensation.  It was so 
deucedly unexpected&mdash;and, my dear fellow, you've brought it so 
exactly to the right shop." 
</p><p>"I'm glad to hear you say so," said the Professor modestly. 
</p><p>Harviss laughed in rich appreciation.  "I don't suppose you 
had a doubt of it; but of course I was quite unprepared.  And it's 
so extraordinarily out of your line&mdash;" 
</p><p>The Professor took off his glasses and rubbed them with a slow 
smile. 
</p><p>"Would you have thought it so&mdash;at college?" 
</p><p>Harviss stared.  "At college?&mdash;Why, you were the most 
iconoclastic devil&mdash;" 
</p><p>There was a perceptible pause.  The Professor restored his 
glasses and looked at his friend.  "Well&mdash;?" he said simply. 
</p><p>"Well&mdash;?" echoed the other, still staring.  "Ah&mdash;I see; you 
mean that that's what explains it.  The swing of the pendulum, and 
so forth.  Well, I admit it's not an uncommon phenomenon.  I've 
conformed myself, for example; most of our crowd have, I believe; 
but somehow I hadn't expected it of you." 
</p><p>The close observer might have detected a faint sadness under 
the official congratulation of his tone; but the Professor was too 
amazed to have an ear for such fine shades. 
</p><p>"Expected it of me?  Expected what of me?" he gasped.  "What 
in heaven do you think this thing is?"  And he struck his fist on 
the manuscript which lay between them. 
</p><p>Harviss had recovered his optimistic creases.  He rested a 
benevolent eye on the document. 
</p><p>"Why, your apologia&mdash;your confession of faith, I should call 
it.  You surely must have seen which way you were going?  You can't 
have written it in your sleep?" 
</p><p>"Oh, no, I was wide awake enough," said the Professor faintly. 
</p><p>"Well, then, why are you staring at me as if I were <hi rend="italic"> not?"</hi>  
Harviss leaned forward to lay a reassuring hand on his visitor's 
worn coat-sleeve.  "Don't mistake me, my dear Linyard.  Don't fancy 
there was the least unkindness in my allusion to your change of 
front.  What is growth but the shifting of the stand-point?  Why 
should a man be expected to look at life with the same eyes at 
twenty and at&mdash;our age?  It never occurred to me that you could 
feel the least delicacy in admitting that you have come round a 
little&mdash;have fallen into line, so to speak." 
</p><p>But the Professor had sprung up as if to give his lungs more 
room to expand; and from them there issued a laugh which shook the 
editorial rafters. 
</p><p>"Oh, Lord, oh Lord&mdash;is it really as good as that?" he gasped. 
</p><p>Harviss had glanced instinctively toward the electric bell on 
his desk; it was evident that he was prepared for an emergency. 
</p><p>"My dear fellow&mdash;" he began in a soothing tone. 
</p><p>"Oh, let me have my laugh out, do," implored the Professor.  
"I'll&mdash;I'll quiet down in a minute; you needn't ring for the young 
man."  He dropped into his chair again, and grasped its arms to 
steady his shaking.  "This is the best laugh I've had <pb n="317"/>  since 
college," he brought out between his paroxysms.  And then, 
suddenly, he sat up with a groan.  "But if it's as good as that 
it's a failure!" he exclaimed. 
</p><p>Harviss, stiffening a little, examined the tip of his cigar.  
"My dear Linyard," he said at length, "I don't understand a word 
you're saying." 
</p><p>The Professor succumbed to a fresh access, from the vortex of 
which he managed to fling out&mdash;"But that's the very core of the 
joke!" 
</p><p>Harviss looked at him resignedly.  "What is?" 
</p><p>"Why, your not seeing&mdash;your not understanding&mdash;" 
</p><p>"Not understanding <hi rend="italic"> what?"</hi> 
</p><p>"Why, what the book is meant to be."  His laughter subsided 
again and he sat gazing thoughtfully at the publisher.  "Unless it 
means," he wound up, "that I've over-shot the mark." 
</p><p>"If I am the mark, you certainly have," said Harviss, with a 
glance at the clock. 
</p><p>The Professor caught the glance and interpreted it.  "The book 
is a skit," he said, rising. 
</p><p>The other stared.  "A skit?  It's not serious, you mean?" 
</p><p>"Not to me&mdash;but it seems you've taken it so." 
</p><p>"You never told me&mdash;" began the publisher in a ruffled tone. 
</p><p>"No, I never told you," said the Professor. 
</p><p>Harviss sat staring at the manuscript between them.  "I don't 
pretend to be up in such recondite forms of humour," he said, still 
stiffly.  "Of course you address yourself to a very small class of 
readers." 
</p><p>"Oh, infinitely small," admitted the Professor, extending his 
hand toward the manuscript. 
</p><p>Harviss appeared to be pursuing his own train of thought.  
"That is," he continued, "if you insist on an ironical 
interpretation." 
</p><p>"If I insist on it&mdash;what do you mean?" 
</p><p>The publisher smiled faintly.  "Well&mdash;isn't the book 
susceptible of another?  If <hi rend="italic"> I</hi> read it without seeing&mdash;" 
</p><p>"Well?" murmured the other, fascinated. 
</p><p>&mdash;"why shouldn't the rest of the world?" declared Harviss 
boldly.  "I represent the Average Reader&mdash;that's my business, 
that's what I've been training myself to do for the last twenty 
years.  It's a mission like another&mdash;the thing is to do it 
thoroughly; not to cheat and compromise.  I know fellows who are 
publishers in business hours and dilettantes the rest of the time.  
Well, they never succeed: convictions are just as necessary in 
business as in religion.  But that's not the point&mdash;I was going to 
say that if you'll let me handle this book as a genuine thing I'll 
guarantee to make it go." 
</p><p>The Professor stood motionless, his hand still on the 
manuscript. 
</p><p>"A genuine thing?" he echoed. 
</p><p>"A serious piece of work&mdash;the expression of your convictions.  
I tell you there's nothing the public likes as much as 
convictions&mdash;they'll always follow a man who believes in his own 
ideas.  And this book is just on the line of popular interest.  
You've got hold of a big thing.  It's full of hope and enthusiasm: 
it's written in the religious key.  There are passages in it that 
would do splendidly in a Birthday Book&mdash;things that popular 
preachers would quote in their sermons.  If you'd wanted to catch 
a big public you couldn't have gone about it in a better way.  The 
thing's perfect for my purpose&mdash;I wouldn't let you alter a word of 
it.  It'll sell like a popular novel if you'll let me handle it in 
the right way." 
</p> 
</div2> 
<div2 type="section" n="3" id="d6"> 
<head>                           III 
</head> 
<p>WHEN the Professor left Harviss's office, the manuscript 
remained behind.  He thought he had been taken by the huge irony of 
the situation&mdash;by the enlarged circumference of the joke.  In its 
original form, as Harviss had said, the book would have addressed 
itself to a very limited circle: now it would include the world.  
The elect would understand; the crowd would not; and his work would 
thus serve a double purpose.  And, after all, nothing was changed 
in the situation; not a word of the book was to be altered.  The 
change was merely in the publisher's point of view, and in the 
"tip" he was to give the reviewers.  The Professor had only to hold 
his tongue and look serious. 
</p><p>These arguments found a strong reinforcement in the large 
premium which expressed Harviss's sense of his opportunity.  As a 
satire, the book would have brought its author nothing; in fact, 
its <pb n="318"/>  cost would have come out of his own pocket, since, as 
Harviss assured him, no publisher would have risked taking it.  But 
as a profession of faith, as the recantation of an eminent 
biologist, whose leanings had hitherto been supposed to be toward 
a cold determinism, it would bring in a steady income to author and 
publisher.  The offer found the Professor in a moment of financial 
perplexity.  His illness, his unwonted holiday, the necessity of 
postponing a course of well-paid lectures, had combined to diminish 
his resources; and when Harviss offered him an advance of a 
thousand dollars the esoteric savour of the joke became 
irresistible.  It was still as a joke that he persisted in 
regarding the transaction; and though he had pledged himself not to 
betray the real intent of the book, he held <hi rend="italic"> in petto</hi> the notion 
of some day being able to take the public into his confidence.  As 
for the initiated, they would know at once: and however long a face 
he pulled, his colleagues would see the tongue in his cheek.  
Meanwhile it fortunately happened that, even if the book should 
achieve the kind of triumph prophesied by Harviss, it would not 
appreciably injure its author's professional standing.  Professor 
Linyard was known chiefly as a microscopist.  On the structure and 
habits of a certain class of coleoptera he was the most 
distinguished living authority; but none save his intimate friends 
knew what generalizations on the destiny of man he had drawn from 
these special studies.  He might have published a treatise on the 
Filioque without disturbing the confidence of those on whose 
approval his reputation rested; and moreover he was sustained by 
the thought that one glance at his book would let them into its 
secret.  In fact, so sure was he of this that he wondered the 
astute Harviss had cared to risk such speedy exposure.  But Harviss 
had probably reflected that even in this reverberating age the 
opinions of the laboratory do not easily reach the street; and the 
Professor, at any rate, was not bound to offer advice on this 
point. 
</p><p>The determining cause of his consent was the fact that the 
book was already in press.  The Professor knew little about the 
workings of the press, but the phrase gave him a sense of finality, 
of having been caught himself in the toils of that mysterious 
engine.  If he had had time to think the matter over, his scruples 
might have dragged him back; but his conscience was eased by the 
futility of resistance. 
</p> 
</div2> 
<div2 type="section" n="4" id="d7"> 
<head>                           IV 
</head> 
<p>MRS. LINYARD did not often read the papers; and there was 
therefore a special significance in her approaching her husband one 
evening after dinner with a copy of the <hi rend="italic"> New York Investigator</hi> 
in her hand.  Her expression lent solemnity to the act: Mrs. 
Linyard had a limited but distinctive set of expressions, and she 
now looked as she did when the President of the University came to 
dine. 
</p><p>"You didn't tell me of this, Samuel," she said in a slightly 
tremulous voice. 
</p><p>"Tell you of what?" returned the Professor, reddening to the 
margin of his baldness. 
</p><p>"That you had published a book&mdash;I might never have heard of it 
if Mrs. Pease hadn't brought me the paper." 
</p><p>Her husband rubbed his eye-glasses with a groan.  "Oh, you 
would have heard of it," he said gloomily. 
</p><p>Mrs. Linyard stared.  "Did you wish to keep it from me, 
Samuel?"  And as he made no answer, she added with irresistible 
pride: "Perhaps you don't know what beautiful things have been said 
about it." 
</p><p>He took the paper with a reluctant hand.  "Has Pease been 
saying beautiful things about it?" 
</p><p>"The Professor?  Mrs. Pease didn't say he had mentioned it." 
</p><p>The author heaved a sigh of relief.  His book, as Harviss had 
prophesied, had caught the autumn market: had caught and captured 
it.  The publisher had conducted the campaign like an experienced 
strategist.  He had completely surrounded the enemy.  Every 
newspaper, every periodical, held in ambush an advertisement of 
"The Vital Thing."  Weeks in advance the great commander had begun 
to form his lines of attack.  Allusions to the remarkable 
significance of the coming work had appeared first in the 
scientific and literary reviews, spreading thence to the 
supplements of the daily journals.  Not a moment passed without a 
quickening touch to the public consciousness: seventy millions of 
people were forced to remember at least once a <pb n="319"/>  day that 
Professor Linyard's book was on the verge of appearing.  Slips 
emblazoned with the question: <hi rend="italic"> Have you read "The Vital Thing"?</hi> 
fell from the pages of popular novels and whitened the floors of 
crowded street-cars.  The query, in large lettering, assaulted the 
traveller at the railway bookstall, confronted him on the walls of 
"elevated" stations, and seemed, in its ascending scale, about to 
supplant the interrogations as to soap and stove-polish which 
animate our rural scenery. 
</p><p>On the day of publication, the Professor had withdrawn to his 
laboratory.  The shriek of the advertisements was in his ears, and 
his one desire was to avoid all knowledge of the event they 
heralded.  A reaction of self-consciousness had set in, and if 
Harviss's cheque had sufficed to buy up the first edition of "The 
Vital Thing" the Professor would gladly have devoted it to that 
purpose.  But the sense of inevitableness gradually subdued him, 
and he received his wife's copy of the <hi rend="italic"> Investigator</hi> with a kind 
of impersonal curiosity.  The review was a long one, full of 
extracts: he saw, as he glanced over them, how well they would look 
in a volume of "Selections."  The reviewer began by thanking his 
author "for sounding with no uncertain voice that note of ringing 
optimism, of faith in man's destiny and the supremacy of good, 
which has too long been silenced by the whining chorus of a 
decadent nihilism. . . .  It is well," the writer continued, "when 
such reminders come to us not from the moralist but from the man of 
science&mdash;when from the desiccating atmosphere of the laboratory 
there rises this glorious cry of faith and reconstruction." 
</p><p>The review was minute and exhaustive.  Thanks no doubt to 
Harviss's diplomacy, it had been given to the <hi rend="italic"> Investigator's</hi> 
"best man," and the Professor was startled by the bold eye with 
which his emancipated fallacies confronted him.  Under the 
reviewer's handling they made up admirably as truths, and their 
author began to understand Harviss's regret that they should be 
used for any less profitable purpose. 
</p><p>The <hi rend="italic"> Investigator</hi>, as Harviss phrased it, "set the pace," 
and the other journals followed, finding it easier to let their 
critical man-of-all-work play a variation on the first reviewer's 
theme than to secure an expert to "do" the book afresh.  But it was 
evident that the Professor had captured his public, for all the 
resources of the profession could not, as Harviss gleefully pointed 
out, have carried the book so straight to the heart of the nation.  
There was something noble in the way in which Harviss belittled his 
own share in the achievement, and insisted on the inutility of 
shoving a book which had started with such headway on. 
</p><p>"All I ask you is to admit that I saw what would happen," he 
said with a touch of professional pride.  "I knew you'd struck the 
right note&mdash;I knew they'd be quoting you from Maine to San 
Francisco.  Good as fiction?  It's better&mdash;it'll keep going 
longer." 
</p><p>"Will it?" said the Professor with a slight shudder.  He was 
resigned to an ephemeral triumph, but the thought of the book's 
persistency frightened him. 
</p><p>"I should say so!  Why, you fit in everywhere&mdash;science, 
theology, natural history&mdash;and then the all-for-the-best element 
which is so popular just now.  Why, you come right in with the How-to-Relax series, and they sell way up in the millions.  And then 
the book's so full of tenderness&mdash;there are such lovely things in 
it about flowers and children.  I didn't know an old Dryasdust like 
you could have such a lot of sentiment in him.  Why, I actually 
caught myself snivelling over that passage about the snowdrops 
piercing the frozen earth; and my wife was saying the other day 
that, since she's read "The Vital Thing," she begins to think you 
must write the "What-Cheer Column in the <hi rend="italic"> Inglenook."</hi>  He threw 
back his head with a laugh which ended in the inspired cry: "And, 
by George, sir, when the thing begins to slow off we'll start 
somebody writing against it, and that will run us straight into 
another hundred thousand." 
</p><p>And as earnest of this belief he drew the Professor a 
supplementary cheque. 
</p></div2> 
<div2 type="section" n="1" id="d8"> 
<head> 
                           V 
</head> 
<p>MRS. LINYARD'S knock cut short the importunities of the lady 
who had been trying to persuade the Professor to be taken by 
flashlight at his study table for the Christmas number of the <hi rend="italic"> 
Inglenook</hi>.  On this point the Professor had fancied himself 
impregnable; but the unwonted <pb n="320"/>  smile with which he welcomed 
his wife's intrusion showed that his defences were weakening. 
</p><p>The lady from the <hi rend="italic"> Inglenook</hi> took the hint with 
professional promptness, but said brightly, as she snapped the 
elastic around her note-book: "I shan't let you forget me, 
Professor." 
</p><p>The groan with which he followed her retreat was interrupted 
by his wife's question: "Do they pay you for these interviews, 
Samuel?" 
</p><p>The Professor looked at her with sudden attention.  "Not 
directly," he said, wondering at her expression. 
</p><p>She sank down with a sigh.  "Indirectly, then?" 
</p><p>"What is the matter, my dear?  I gave you Harviss's second 
cheque the other day&mdash;" 
</p><p>Her tears arrested him.  "Don't be hard on the boy, Samuel!  
I really believe your success has turned his head." 
</p><p>"The boy&mdash;what boy?  My success&mdash;?  Explain yourself, Susan!" 
</p><p>"It's only that Jack has&mdash;has borrowed some money&mdash;which he 
can't repay.  But you mustn't think him altogether to blame, 
Samuel.  Since the success of your book he has been asked about so 
much&mdash;it's given the children quite a different position.  
Millicent says that wherever they go the first question asked is, 
'Are you any relation of the author of "The Vital Thing"?'  Of 
course we're all very proud of the book; but it entails obligations 
which you may not have thought of in writing it." 
</p><p>The Professor sat gazing at the letters and newspaper 
clippings on the study-table which he had just successfully 
defended from the camera of the <hi rend="italic"> Inglenook</hi>.  He took up an 
envelope bearing the name of a popular weekly paper. 
</p><p>"I don't know that the <hi rend="italic"> Inglenook</hi> would help much," he 
said, "but I suppose this might." 
</p><p>Mrs. Linyard's eyes glowed with maternal avidity. 
</p><p>"What is it, Samuel?" 
</p><p>"A series of 'Scientific Sermons' for the Round-the-Gas-Log 
column of <hi rend="italic"> The Woman's World</hi>.  I believe that journal has a 
larger circulation than any other weekly, and they pay in 
proportion." 
</p><p>He had not even asked the extent of Jack's indebtedness.  It 
had been so easy to relieve recent domestic difficulties by the 
timely production of Harviss's two cheques, that it now seemed 
natural to get Mrs. Linyard out of the room by promising further 
reinforcements.  The Professor had indignantly rejected Harviss's 
suggestion that he should follow up his success by a second volume 
on the same lines.  He had sworn not to lend more than a passive 
support to the fraud of "The Vital Thing"; but the temptation to 
free himself from Mrs. Linyard prevailed over his last scruples, 
and within an hour he was at work on the Scientific Sermons. 
</p><p>The Professor was not an unkind man.  He really enjoyed making 
his family happy; and it was his own business if his reward for so 
doing was that it kept them out of his way.  But the success of 
"The Vital Thing" gave him more than this negative satisfaction.  
It enlarged his own existence and opened new doors into other 
lives.  The Professor, during fifty virtuous years, had been 
cognizant of only two types of women: the fond and foolish, whom 
one married, and the earnest and intellectual, whom one did not.  
Of the two, he infinitely preferred the former, even for 
conversational purposes.  But as a social instrument woman was 
unknown to him; and it was not till he was drawn into the world on 
the tide of his literary success that he discovered the 
deficiencies in his classification of the sex.  Then he learned 
with astonishment of the existence of a third type: the woman who 
is fond without foolishness and intellectual without earnestness.  
Not that the Professor inspired, or sought to inspire, sentimental 
emotions; but he expanded in the warm atmosphere of personal 
interest which some of his new acquaintances contrived to create 
about him.  It was delightful to talk of serious things in a 
setting of frivolity, and to be personal without being domestic. 
</p><p>Even in this new world, where all subjects were touched on 
lightly, and emphasis was the only indelicacy, the Professor found 
himself constrained to endure an occasional reference to his book.  
It was unpleasant at first; but gradually he slipped into the habit 
of hearing it talked of, and grew accustomed to telling pretty 
women just how "it had first come to him." 
</p><p>Meanwhile the success of the Scientific <pb n="321"/>  Sermons was 
facilitating his family relations.  His photograph in the <hi rend="italic"> 
Inglenook</hi>, to which the lady of the note-book had succeeded in 
appending a vivid interview, carried his fame to circles 
inaccessible even to "The Vital Thing"; and the Professor found 
himself the man of the hour.  He soon grew used to the functions of 
the office, and gave out hundred-dollar interviews on every 
subject, from labour-strikes to Babism, with a frequency which 
reacted agreeably on the domestic exchequer.  Presently his head 
began to figure in the advertising pages of the magazines.  
Admiring readers learned the name of the only breakfast-food in use 
at his table, of the ink with which "The Vital Thing" had been 
written, the soap with which the author's hands were washed, and 
the tissue-builder which fortified him for further effort.  These 
confidences endeared the Professor to millions of readers, and his 
head passed in due course from the magazine and the newspaper to 
the biscuit-tin and the chocolate-box. 
</p></div2> 
<div2 type="section" n="6" id="d9"> 
<head>                           VI 
</head> 
<p>THE Professor, all the while, was leading a double life.  
While the author of "The Vital Thing" reaped the fruits of popular 
approval, the distinguished microscopist continued his laboratory 
work unheeded save by the few who were engaged in the same line of 
investigations.  His divided allegiance had not hitherto affected 
the quality of his work: it seemed to him that he returned to the 
laboratory with greater zest after an afternoon in a drawing-room 
where readings from "The Vital Thing" had alternated with 
plantation melodies and tea.  He had long ceased to concern himself 
with what his colleagues thought of his literary career.  Of the 
few whom he frequented, none had referred to "The Vital Thing"; and 
he knew enough of their lives to guess that their silence might as 
fairly be attributed to indifference as to disapproval.  They were 
intensely interested in the Professor's views on beetles, but they 
really cared very little what he thought of the Almighty. 
</p><p>The Professor entirely shared their feelings, and one of his 
chief reasons for cultivating the success which accident had 
bestowed on him, was that it enabled him to command a greater range 
of appliances for his real work.  He had known what it was to lack 
books and instruments; and "The Vital Thing" was the magic wand 
which summoned them to his aid.  For some time he had been feeling 
his way along the edge of a discovery: balancing himself with 
professional skill on a plank of hypothesis flung across an abyss 
of uncertainty.  The conjecture was the result of years of patient 
gathering of facts: its corroboration would take months more of 
comparison and classification.  But at the end of the vista victory 
loomed.  The Professor felt within himself that assurance of 
ultimate justification which, to the man of science, makes a life-time seem the mere comma between premiss and deduction.  But he had 
reached the point where his conjectures required formulation.  It 
was only by giving them expression, by exposing them to the comment 
and criticism of his associates, that he could test their final 
value; and this inner assurance was confirmed by the only friend 
whose confidence he invited. 
</p><p>Professor Pease, the husband of the lady who had opened Mrs. 
Linyard's eyes to the triumph of "The Vital Thing," was the 
repository of her husband's scientific experiences.  What he 
thought of "The Vital Thing" had never been divulged; and he was 
capable of such vast exclusions that it was quite possible that 
pervasive work had not yet reached him.  In any case, it was not 
likely to affect his judgment of the author's professional 
capacity. 
</p><p>"You want to put that all in a book, Linyard," was Professor 
Pease's summing-up.  "I'm sure you've got hold of something big; 
but to see it clearly yourself you ought to outline it for others.  
Take my advice&mdash;chuck everything else and get to work tomorrow.  
It's time you wrote a book, anyhow." 
</p><p><hi rend="italic"> It's time you wrote a book, anyhow!</hi>  The words smote the 
Professor with mingled pain and ecstasy: he could have wept over 
their significance.  But his friend's other phrase reminded him 
with a start of Harviss.  "You have got hold of a big thing&mdash;" it 
had been the publisher's first comment on "The Vital Thing."  But 
what a world of meaning lay between the two phrases!  It was the 
world in which the powers who fought for the Professor were 
destined to wage their final battle; and for the moment he had no 
doubt of the outcome. <pb n="322"/>  
</p><p>"By George, I'll do it, Pease!" he said, stretching his hand 
to his friend. 
</p><p>The next day he went to town to see Harviss.  He wanted to ask 
for an advance on the new popular edition of "The Vital Thing."  He 
had determined to drop a course of supplementary lectures at the 
University, and to give himself up for a year to his book.  To do 
this, additional funds were necessary; but thanks to "The Vital 
Thing" they would be forthcoming. 
</p><p>The publisher received him as cordially as usual; but the 
response to his demand was not as prompt as his previous experience 
had entitled him to expect. 
</p><p>"Of course we'll be glad to do what we can for you, Linyard; 
but the fact is, we've decided to give up the idea of the new 
edition for the present." 
</p><p>"You've given up the new edition?" 
</p><p>"Why, yes&mdash;we've done pretty well by 'The Vital Thing,' and 
we're inclined to think it's <hi rend="italic"> your</hi> turn to do something for it 
now." 
</p><p>The Professor looked at him blankly.  "What can I do for it?" 
he asked&mdash;"what <hi rend="italic"> more"</hi> his accent added. 
</p><p>"Why, put a little new life in it by writing something else.  
The secret of perpetual motion hasn't yet been discovered, you 
know, and it's one of the laws of literature that books which start 
with a rush are apt to slow down sooner than the crawlers.  We've 
kept 'The Vital Thing' going for eighteen months&mdash;but, hang it, it 
ain't so vital any more.  We simply couldn't see our way to a new 
edition.  Oh, I don't say it's dead yet&mdash;but it's moribund, and 
you're the only man who can resuscitate it." 
</p><p>The Professor continued to stare.  "I&mdash;what can I do about 
it?" he stammered. 
</p><p>"Do?  Why write another like it&mdash;go it one better: you know 
the trick.  The public isn't tired of you by any means; but you 
want to make yourself heard again before anybody else cuts in.  
Write another book&mdash;write two, and we'll sell them in sets in a 
box: The Vital Thing Series.  That will take tremendously in the 
holidays.  Try and let us have a new volume by October&mdash;I'll be 
glad to give you a big advance if you'll sign a contract on that." 
</p><p>The Professor sat silent: there was too cruel an irony in the 
coincidence. 
</p><p>Harviss looked up at him in surprise. 
</p><p>"Well, what's the matter with taking my advice&mdash;you're not 
going out of literature, are you?" 
</p><p>The Professor rose from his chair.  "No&mdash;I'm going into it," 
he said simply. 
</p><p>"Going into it?" 
</p><p>"I'm going to write a real book&mdash;a serious one." 
</p><p>"Good Lord!  Most people think 'The Vital Thing' 's serious." 
</p><p>"Yes&mdash;but I mean something different." 
</p><p>"In your old line&mdash;beetles and so forth?" 
</p><p>"Yes," said the Professor solemnly. 
</p><p>Harviss looked at him with equal gravity.  "Well, I'm sorry 
for that," he said, "because it takes you out of our bailiwick.  
But I suppose you've made enough money out of 'The Vital Thing' to 
permit yourself a little harmless amusement.  When you want more 
cash come back to us&mdash;only don't put it off too long, or some other 
fellow will have stepped into your shoes.  Popularity don't keep, 
you know; and the hotter the success the quicker the commodity 
perishes." 
</p><p>He leaned back, cheerful and sententious, delivering his 
axioms with conscious kindliness. 
</p><p>The Professor, who had risen and moved to the door, turned 
back with a wavering step. 
</p><p>"When did you say another volume would have to be ready?" he 
faltered. 
</p><p>"I said October&mdash;but call it a month later.  You don't need 
any pushing nowadays." 
</p><p>"And&mdash;you'd have no objection to letting me have a little 
advance now?  I need some new instruments for my real work." 
</p><p>Harviss extended a cordial hand.  "My dear fellow, that's 
talking&mdash;I'll write the cheque while you wait; and I daresay we can 
start up the cheap edition of 'The Vital Thing' at the same time, 
if you'll pledge yourself to give us the book by November.&mdash;How 
much?" he asked, poised above his cheque-book. 
</p><p>In the street, the Professor stood staring about him, 
uncertain and a little dazed. 
</p><p>"After all, it's only putting it off for six months," he said 
to himself; "and I can do better work when I get my new 
instruments." 
</p><p>He smiled and raised his hat to the passing victoria of a lady 
in whose copy of "The Vital Thing" he had recently written: 
</p><p><hi rend="italic"> Labor est etiam ipsa voluptas.</hi> 
</p> 
 
</div2> 
</div1> 
</body> 
</text> 
</TEI.2> 
