<?xml version="1.0"?>

<?dlps id="WhaDuch"?>
<?dlps page-images="none" figure-images="no"?>
<?dlps transcription="other"?>

<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/tei-p4/tei2.dtd" [
<!ENTITY % POSTKB "INCLUDE">
<!ENTITY % TEI.extensions.ent SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.ent">
<!ENTITY % TEI.extensions.dtd SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.dtd">
<!ENTITY % ISOnum SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/charent/iso-num.ent"> %ISOnum;
<!ENTITY % ISOpub SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/charent/iso-pub.ent"> %ISOpub;

]>

<TEI.2 id="WhaDuch"> 
<teiHeader type="migrated" creator="Etext">
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title type="main">The Duchess at Prayer</title>
<title type="sort">duchess at prayer</title>
<author>Wharton, Edith, 1862-1937</author>
<respStmt>
<resp>Creation of machine-readable version:</resp>
<name>Judy Boss</name>
</respStmt>
<respStmt>
<resp>Conversion to TEI-conformant markup:</resp>
<name>University of Virginia Library Electronic Text Center</name>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt> 
<extent>ca. <num type="kilobytes">47</num> kilobytes</extent> 
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>University of Virginia Library</publisher>
<pubPlace>Charlottesville, Virginia</pubPlace>
<idno type="ETC">WhaDuch</idno> 
<date value="1995">1995</date>
<availability status="public">
<p n="copyright">Copyright &copy; 1995 by the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia</p>
<p n="access">Publicly accessible</p>
</availability>
<idno type="uva-pid">uva-lib:476490</idno>
</publicationStmt>
<seriesStmt>
<title>University of Virginia Library, Text collection</title>
<idno type="uva-set">UVA-LIB-Text</idno>
</seriesStmt> 
<notesStmt>
<note>
<p>NOTE: In line 1 of paragraph 8 on page 159 I have changed " to ' 
before "could"; in line 1 of paragraph 13 on page 162 I have 
changed " to "' before "Here's."</p>
</note>
</notesStmt> 
<sourceDesc>
<biblFull>
<titleStmt>
<title type="main">The Duchess at Prayer</title>
<title type="sort">duchess at prayer</title>
<author>Wharton, Edith</author>
<respStmt>
<resp>Edited by</resp>
<name>editor</name>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt> 
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>Scribner's Magazine</publisher>
<date value="1900-08">Aug. 1900</date>
</publicationStmt> 
<notesStmt>
<note>
<p>Vol. 28</p>
</note>
</notesStmt>
</biblFull>
</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc> 
<encodingDesc>
<projectDesc>
<p>Prepared for the University of Virginia Library Electronic Text Center</p>
</projectDesc> 
<editorialDecl>
<p>All quotation marks retained as data</p> 
<p>Verification made against printed text</p> 
<p id="ETC">Keywords in the header are a local Electronic Text Center scheme  
to aid in establishing analytical groupings</p>
</editorialDecl> 
<refsDecl>
<p>ID elements are given for each page element and are composed of the text's 
unique cryptogram and the given page number, as in SpeFQue1 for page one of  
Spenser's Faerie Queene.</p>
</refsDecl>
</encodingDesc> 
<profileDesc>
<creation>
<date value="1900">1900</date>
</creation> 
<langUsage>
<language id="eng" usage="main">English</language>
</langUsage> 
<textClass>
<keywords>
<term>fiction</term>
<term>prose</term>
</keywords>
</textClass>
</profileDesc> 
<revisionDesc>
<change>
<date value="1995-01">January 1995</date> 
<respStmt>
<resp>corrector</resp>
<name>David Seaman and Kelly Tetterton</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Header and basic TEI SGML encoding added</item>
</change> 
<change>
<date value="2005-07">July 2005</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>Corrector</resp>
<name>Margaret Konkol</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Converted SGML to XML and fixed tagging.</item>
</change>
<change>
<date value="2007-09">September 2007</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>Migration</resp>
<name>Ethan Gruber, University of Virginia Library</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Converted XML markup from TEI Lite to uva-dl-tei (TEI P4 with local customizations).</item>
</change>
<change>
<date value="2008-01">January 2008</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>Migration</resp>
<name>Greg Murray, University of Virginia Library</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Programmatically updated TEI header markup (but not header content) for minimal compliance with current QA requirements.</item>
</change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader> 
<text id="d1">  
<body id="d2"> 
<div1 type="story" id="d3"> 
<head> 
Wharton, Edith.  "The Duchess at Prayer."  
<lb/> 
 <hi rend="italic"> Scribner's Magazine</hi> 
28 (Aug. 1900): 151-164. 
</head> 
<pb n="151"/>  
<div2 type="section" n="1" id="d4"><head>I</head> 
<p> 
HAVE you ever questioned the long shuttered front of an old Italian 
house, that motionless mask, smooth, mute, equivocal as the face of 
a priest behind which buzz the secrets of the confessional?  Other 
houses declare the activities they shelter; they are the clear 
expressive cuticle of a life flowing close to the surface; but the 
old palace in its narrow street, the villa on its cypress-hooded 
hill, are as impenetrable as death.  The tall windows are like 
blind eyes, the great door is a shut mouth.  Inside there may be 
sunshine, the scent of myrtles, and a pulse of life through all the 
arteries of the huge frame; or a mortal solitude where bats lodge 
in the disjointed stones, and the keys rust in unused doors. . . . 
</p> 
</div2> 
<div2 type="section" n="2" id="d5"><head>II</head> 

<p> 
FROM the loggia, with its vanishing frescoes, I looked down an 
avenue barred by a ladder of cypress-shadows to the ducal 
escutcheon and mutilated vases of the gate.  Flat noon lay on the 
gardens, on fountains, porticoes and grottoes.  Below the terrace, 
where a chrome-colored lichen had sheeted the balustrade as with 
fine <hi rend="italic"> laminae</hi> of gold, vineyards stooped to the rich valley 
clasped in hills.  The lower slopes were strewn with white villages 
like stars spangling a summer dusk; and beyond these, fold on fold 
of blue mountain, clear as gauze against the sky.  The August air 
was lifeless, but it seemed light and vivifying after the 
atmosphere of the shrouded rooms through which I had been led.  
Their chill was on me and I hugged the sunshine. 
</p><p>"The Duchess's apartments are beyond," said the old man. 
</p><p>He was the oldest man I had ever seen; so sucked back into the 
past that he seemed more like a memory than a living being.  The 
one trait linking him with the actual was the fixity with which his 
small saurian eye held the pocket that, as I entered, had yielded 
a <hi rend="italic"> lira</hi> to the gate-keeper's child.  He went on, without 
removing his eye: 
</p><p>"For two hundred years nothing has been changed in the 
apartments of the Duchess." 
</p><p>"And no one lives here now?" 
</p><p>"No one, sir.  The Duke goes to Como for the summer season." 
</p><p>I had moved to the other end of the loggia.  Below me, through 
hanging groves, white roofs and domes flashed like a smile. 
</p><p>"And that's Vicenza?" 
</p><p><hi rend="italic"> "Proprio!"</hi>  The old man extended <pb n="152"/>  [illustration 
omitted] <pb n="153"/>  fingers as lean as the hands fading from the walls 
behind us.  "You see the palace roof over there, just to the left 
of the Basilica?  The one with the row of statues like birds taking 
flight?  That's the Duke's town palace, built by Palladio." 
</p><p>"And does the Duke come there?" 
</p><p>"Never.  In winter he goes to Rome." 
</p><p>"And the palace and the villa are always closed?" 
</p><p>"As you see&mdash;always." 
</p><p>"How long has this been?" 
</p><p>"Since I can remember." 
</p><p>I looked into his eyes: they were like tarnished metal mirrors 
reflecting nothing.  "That must be a long time," I said, 
involuntarily. 
</p><p>"A long time," he assented. 
</p><p>I looked down on the gardens.  An opulence of dahlias overran 
the box-borders, between cypresses that cut the sunshine like 
basalt shafts.  Bees hung above the lavender; lizards sunned 
themselves on the benches and slipped through the cracks of the dry 
basins.  Everywhere were vanishing traces of that fantastic 
horticulture of which our dull age has lost the art.  Down the 
alleys maimed statues stretched their arms like rows of whining 
beggars; faun-eared terms grinned in the thicket, and above the 
laurustinus walls rose the mock ruin of a temple, falling into real 
ruin in the bright disintegrating air.  The glare was blinding. 
</p><p>"Let us go in," I said. 
</p><p>The old man pushed open a heavy door, behind which the cold 
lurked like a knife. 
</p><p>"The Duchess's apartments," he said. 
</p><p>Overhead and around us the same evanescent frescoes, under 
foot the same scagliola volutes, unrolled themselves interminably.  
Ebony cabinets, with colonnades of precious marbles in cunning 
perspective, alternated down the room with the tarnished 
efflorescence of gilt consoles supporting Chinese monsters; and 
from the chimney-panel a gentleman in the Spanish habit haughtily 
ignored us. 
</p><p>"Duke Ercole II.," the old man explained, "by the Genoese 
Priest." 
</p><p>It was a narrow-browed face, sallow as a wax effigy, high-nosed and cautious-lidded, as though modelled by priestly hands; 
the lips weak and vain rather than cruel; a quibbling mouth that 
would have snapped at verbal errors like a lizard catching flies, 
but had never learned the shape of a round yes or no.  One of the 
Duke's hands rested on the head of a dwarf, a simian creature with 
pearl earrings and fantastic dress; the other turned the pages of 
a folio propped on a skull. 
</p><p>"Beyond is the Duchess's bedroom," the old man reminded me. 
</p><p>Here the shutters admitted but two narrow shafts of light, 
gold bars deepening the subaqueous gloom.  On a dais, the bedstead, 
grim, nuptial, official, lifted its baldachin; a yellow Christ 
agonized between the curtains, and across the room a lady smiled at 
us from the chimney-breast. 
</p><p>The old man unbarred a shutter and the light touched her face.  
Such a face it was, with a flicker of laughter over it like the 
wind on a June meadow, and a singular tender pliancy of mien, as 
though one of Tiepolo's lenient goddesses had been busked into the 
stiff sheath of a seventeenth century dress! 
</p><p>"No one has slept here," said the old man, "since the Duchess 
Violante." 
</p><p>"And she was&mdash;?" 
</p><p>"The lady there&mdash;first Duchess of Duke Ercole II." 
</p><p>He drew a key from his pocket and unlocked a door at the 
farther end of the room.  "The chapel," he said.  "This is the 
Duchess's balcony."  As I turned to follow him the Duchess tossed 
me a sidelong smile. 
</p><p>I stepped into a grated tribune above a chapel festooned with 
stucco.  Pictures of bituminous saints mouldered between the 
pilasters; the artificial roses in the altar-vases were gray with 
dust and age, and under the cobwebby rosettes of the vaulting a 
bird's nest clung.  Before the altar stood a row of tattered arm-chairs, and I drew back at sight of a figure kneeling near them. 
</p><p>"The Duchess," the old man whispered.  "By the Cavaliere 
Bernini." 
</p><p>It was the image of a woman in furred robes and spreading 
fraise, her hands lifted, her face addressed to the tabernacle.  
There was a strangeness in the sight of that immovable presence 
locked in prayer before an abandoned shrine.  Her face was hidden, 
and I wondered <pb n="154"/>  whether it were grief or gratitude that 
raised her hands and drew her eyes to the altar, where no living 
prayer joined her marble invocation.  I followed my guide down the 
tribune steps, impatient to see what mystic version of such 
terrestrial graces the ingenious artist had found&mdash;the Cavaliere 
was master of such arts.  The Duchess's attitude was one of 
transport, as though heavenly airs fluttered her laces and the 
love-locks escaping from her coif.  I saw how admirably the 
sculptor had caught the poise of her head, the tender slope of the 
shoulder; then I crossed over and looked into her face&mdash;it was a 
frozen horror.  Never have hate, revolt, and agony so possessed a 
human countenance. . . . 
</p><p>The old man crossed himself and shuffled his feet on the 
marble. 
</p><p>"The Duchess Violante," he repeated. 
</p><p>"The same as in the picture?" 
</p><p>"Eh&mdash;the same." 
</p><p>"But the face&mdash;what does it mean?" 
</p><p>He shrugged his shoulders and turned deaf eyes on me.  Then he 
shot a glance round the sepulchral place, clutched my sleeve and 
said, close to my ear: "It was not always so." 
</p><p>"What was not?" 
</p><p>"The face&mdash;so terrible." 
</p><p>"The Duchess's face?" 
</p><p>"The statue's.  It changed after&mdash;" 
</p><p>"After?" 
</p><p>"It was put here." 
</p><p>"The statue's face <hi rend="italic"> changed</hi>&mdash;?" 
</p><p>He mistook my bewilderment for incredulity and his 
confidential finger dropped from my sleeve.  "Eh, that's the story.  
I tell what I've heard.  What do I know?"  He resumed his senile 
shuffle across the marble.  "This is a bad place to stay in&mdash;no one 
comes here.  It's too cold.  But the gentleman said, <hi rend="italic"> I must see 
everything!"</hi> 
</p><p>I let the <hi rend="italic"> lire</hi> sound.  "So I must&mdash;and hear everything.  
This story, now&mdash;from whom did you have it?" 
</p><p>His hand stole back.  "One that saw it, by God!" 
</p><p>"That saw it?" 
</p><p>"My grandmother, then.  I'm a very old man." 
</p><p>"Your grandmother?  Your grandmother was&mdash;?" 
</p><p>"The Duchess's serving girl, with respect to you." 
</p><p>"Your grandmother?  Two hundred years ago?" 
</p><p>"Is it too long ago?  That's as God pleases.  I am a very old 
man and she was a very old woman when I was born.  When she died 
she was as black as a miraculous Virgin and her breath whistled 
like the wind in a keyhole.  She told me the story when I was a 
little boy.  She told it to me out there in the garden, on a bench 
by the fish-pond, one summer night of the year she died.  It must 
be true, for I can show you the very bench we sat on. . . ." 
</p> 
</div2> 
<div2 type="section" n="3" id="d6"><head>III</head> 
<p> 

NOON lay heavier on the gardens; not our live humming warmth, but 
the stale exhalation of dead summers.  The very statues seemed to 
drowse like watchers by a death-bed.  Lizards shot out of the 
cracked soil like flames and the bench in the laurustinus-niche was 
strewn with the blue varnished bodies of dead flies.  Before us lay 
the fish-pond, a yellow marble slab above rotting secrets.  The 
villa looked across it, composed as a dead face, with the cypresses 
flanking it for candles. . . . 
</p> 
</div2> 
<div2 type="section" n="4" id="d7"><head>IV</head> 
<p>". . .  Impossible, you say, that my mother's mother should 
have been the Duchess's maid?  What do I know?  It is so long since 
anything has happened here that the old things seem nearer, 
perhaps, than to those who live in cities. . . .  But how else did 
she know about the statue then?  Answer me that, sir!  That she saw 
with her eyes, I can swear to, and never smiled again, so she told 
me, till they put her first child in her arms . . . for she was 
taken to wife by the steward's son, Antonio, the same who had 
carried the letters. . . .  But where am I?  Ah, well . . . she was 
a mere slip, you understand, my grandmother, when the Duchess died, 
a niece of the upper maid, Nencia, and suffered about the Duchess 
because of her pranks and the funny songs she knew.  It's possible, 
you think, she may have <pb n="155"/>  heard from others what she 
afterward fancied she had seen herself?  How that is, it's not for 
an unlettered man to say; though indeed I myself seem to have seen 
many of the things she told me.  This is a strange place.  No one 
comes here, nothing changes, and the old memories stand up as 
distinct as the statues in the garden. . . . 
</p><p>"It began the summer after they came back from the Brenta.  
Duke Ercole had married the lady from Venice, you must know; it was 
a gay city, then, I'm told, with laughter and music on the water, 
and the days slipped by like boats running with the tide.  Well, to 
humor her he took her back the first autumn to the Brenta.  Her 
father, it appears, had a grand palace there, with such gardens, 
bowling-alleys, grottoes and casinos as never were; gondolas 
bobbing at the water-gates, a stable full of gilt coaches, a 
theatre full of players, and kitchens and offices full of cooks and 
lackeys to serve up chocolate all day long to the fine ladies in 
masks and furbelows, with their pet dogs and their blackamoors and 
their <hi rend="italic"> abates</hi>.  Eh!  I know it all as if I'd been there, for 
Nencia, you see, my grandmother's aunt, travelled with the Duchess, 
and came back with her eyes round as platters, and not a word to 
say for the rest of the year to any of the lads who'd courted her 
here in Vicenza. 
</p><p>"What happened there I don't know&mdash;my grandmother could never 
get at the rights of it, for Nencia was mute as a fish where her 
lady was concerned&mdash;but when they came back to Vicenza the Duke 
ordered the villa set in order; and in the spring he brought the 
Duchess here and left her.  She looked happy enough, my grandmother 
said, and seemed no object for pity.  Perhaps, after all, it was 
better than being shut up in Vicenza, in the tall painted rooms 
where priests came and went as softly as cats prowling for birds, 
and the Duke was forever closeted in his library, talking with 
learned men.  The Duke was a scholar; you noticed he was painted 
with a book?  Well, those that can read 'em make out that they're 
full of wonderful things; as a man that's been to a fair across the 
mountains will always tell his people at home it was beyond 
anything <hi rend="italic"> they'll</hi> ever see.  As for the Duchess, she was all for 
music, play-acting, and young company.  The Duke was a silent man, 
stepping quietly, with his eyes down, as though he'd just come from 
confession; when the Duchess's lap-dog yapped at his heels he 
danced like a man in a swarm of hornets; when the Duchess laughed 
he winced as if you'd drawn a diamond across a window-pane.  And 
the Duchess was always laughing. 
</p><p>"When she first came to the villa she was very busy laying out 
the gardens, designing grottoes, planting groves, and planning all 
manner of agreeable surprises in the way of water-jets that 
drenched you unexpectedly, and hermits in caves, and wild men that 
jumped at you out of thickets.  She had a very pretty taste in such 
matters, but after awhile she tired of it, and there being no one 
for her to talk to but her maids and the chaplain&mdash;a clumsy man 
deep in his books&mdash;why, she would have strolling players out from 
Vicenza, mountebanks and fortune-tellers from the market-place, 
travelling doctors and astrologers, and all manner of trained 
animals.  Still it could be seen that the poor lady pined for 
company, and her waiting women, who loved her, were glad when the 
Cavaliere Ascanio, the Duke's cousin, came to live at the vineyard 
across the valley&mdash;you see the pinkish house over there in the 
mulberries, with a red roof and a pigeon-cote? 
</p><p>"The Cavaliere Ascanio was a cadet of one of the great 
Venetian houses, <hi rend="italic"> pezzi grossi</hi> of the Golden Book.  He had been 
meant for the Church, I believe, but what! he set fighting above 
praying and cast in his lot with the captain of the Duke of 
Mantua's <hi rend="italic"> bravi</hi>, himself a Venetian of good standing, but a 
little at odds with the law.  Well, the next I knew, the Cavaliere 
was in Venice again, perhaps not in good odor on account of his 
connection with the gentleman I speak of.  Some say he tried to 
carry off a nun from the convent of Santa Croce; how that may be I 
can't say; but my grandmother declared he had enemies there, and 
the end of it was that on some pretext or other the Ten banished 
him to Vicenza.  There, of course, the Duke, being his kinsman, had 
to show him a civil face; and that was how he first came to the 
villa. 
</p><p>"He was a fine young man, beautiful as <pb n="156"/>  a Saint 
Sebastian, a rare musician, who sang his own songs to the lute in 
a way that used to make my grandmother's heart melt and run through 
her body like mulled wine.  He had a good word for everybody, too, 
and was always dressed in the French fashion, and smelt as sweet as 
a bean-field; and every soul about the place welcomed the sight of 
him. 
</p><p>"Well, the Duchess, it seemed, welcomed it too; youth will 
have youth, and laughter turns to laughter; and the two matched 
each other like the candlesticks on an altar.  The Duchess&mdash;you've 
seen her portrait&mdash;but to hear my grandmother, sir, it no more 
approached her than a weed comes up to a rose.  The Cavaliere, 
indeed, as became a poet, paragoned her in his song to all the 
pagan goddesses of antiquity; and doubtless these were finer to 
look at than mere women; but so, it seemed, was she; for, to 
believe my grandmother, she made other women look no more than the 
big French fashion-doll that used to be shown on Ascension days in 
the Piazza.  She was one, at any rate, that needed no outlandish 
finery to beautify her; whatever dress she wore became her as 
feathers fit the bird; and her hair didn't get its color by 
bleaching on the housetop.  It glittered of itself like the threads 
in an Easter chasuble, and her skin was whiter than fine wheaten 
bread, and her mouth as sweet as a ripe fig. . . . 
</p><p>"Well, sir, you could no more keep them apart than the bees 
and the lavender.  They were always together, singing, bowling, 
playing cup and ball, walking in the gardens, visiting the aviaries 
and petting her grace's trick-dogs and monkeys.  The Duchess was as 
gay as a foal, always playing pranks and laughing, tricking out her 
animals like comedians, disguising herself as a peasant or a nun 
(you should have seen her one day pass herself off to the chaplain 
as a mendicant sister), or teaching the lads and girls of the 
vineyards to dance and sing madrigals together.  The Cavaliere had 
a singular ingenuity in planning such entertainments, and the days 
were hardly long enough for their diversions.  But toward the end 
of the summer the Duchess fell quiet and would hear only sad music, 
and the two sat much together in the gazebo at the end of the 
garden.  It was there the Duke found them one day when he drove out 
from Vicenza in his gilt coach.  He came but once or twice a year 
to the villa, and it was, as my grandmother said, just a part of 
her poor lady's ill-luck to be wearing that day the Venetian habit, 
which uncovered the shoulders in a way the Duke always scowled at, 
and her curls loose and powdered with gold.  Well, the three drank 
chocolate in the gazebo, and what happened no one knew, except that 
the Duke, on taking leave, gave his cousin a seat in his carriage; 
but the Cavaliere never returned. 
</p><p>"Winter approaching, and the poor lady thus finding herself 
once more alone, it was surmised among her women that she must fall 
into a deeper depression of spirits.  But far from this being the 
case, she displayed such cheerfulness and equanimity of humor that 
my grandmother, for one, was half-vexed with her for giving no more 
thought to the poor young man who, all this time, was eating his 
heart out in the house across the valley.  It is true she quitted 
her gold-laced gowns and wore a veil over her head; but Nencia 
would have it she looked the lovelier for the change, and so gave 
the Duke greater displeasure.  Certain it is that the Duke drove 
out oftener to the villa, and though he found his lady always 
engaged in some innocent pursuit, such as embroidery or music, or 
playing games with her young women, yet he always went away with a 
sour look and a whispered word to the chaplain.  Now as to the 
chaplain, my grandmother owned there had been a time when her grace 
had not handled him over-wisely.  For, according to Nencia, it 
seems that his reverence, who seldom approached the Duchess, being 
buried in his library like a mouse in a cheese&mdash;well, one day he 
made bold to appeal to her for a sum of money, a large sum, Nencia 
said, to buy certain tall books, a chest full of them, that a 
foreign pedler had brought him; whereupon the Duchess, who could 
never abide a book, breaks out at him with a laugh and a flash of 
her old spirit&mdash;'Holy Mother of God, must I have more books about 
me?  I was nearly smothered with them in the first year of my 
marriage;' and the chaplain turning red at the affront, she added: 
'You may buy them and welcome, my good chaplain, if you can find 
the money; but as for me, I am yet <pb n="157"/>  seeking a way to pay for 
my turquoise necklace, and the statue of Daphne at the end of the 
bowling-green, and the Indian parrot that my black boy brought me 
last Michaelmas from the Bohemians&mdash;so you see I've no money to 
waste on trifles;' and as he backs out awkwardly she tosses at him, 
over her shoulder: 'You should pray to Saint Blandina to open the 
Duke's pocket!' to which he returned, very quietly, 'Your 
excellency's suggestion is an admirable one, and I have already 
entreated that blessed martyr to open the Duke's understanding.' 
</p><p>"Thereat, Nencia said (who was standing by), the Duchess 
flushed wonderfully red and waved him out of the room; and then 
'Quick!' she cried to my grandmother (who was too glad to run on 
such errands), 'Call me Antonio, the gardener's boy, to the box-garden; I've a word to say to him about the new clove-carnations. 
. . . 
</p><p>"Now, I may not have told you, sir, that in the crypt under 
the chapel there has stood, for more generations than a man can 
count, a stone coffin containing a thigh-bone of the blessed Saint 
Blandina of Lyons, a relic offered, I've been told, by some great 
Duke of France to one of our own dukes when they fought the Turk 
together; and the object, ever since, of particular veneration in 
this illustrious family.  Now, since the Duchess had been left to 
herself, it was observed she affected a fervent devotion to this 
relic, praying often in the chapel and even causing the stone slab 
that covered the entrance to the crypt to be replaced by a wooden 
one, that she might at will descend and kneel by the coffin.  This 
was matter of edification to all the household, and should have 
been peculiarly pleasing to the chaplain; but, with respect to you, 
he was the kind of man who brings a sour mouth to the eating of the 
sweetest apple. 
</p><p>"However that may be, the Duchess, when she dismissed him, was 
seen running to the garden, where she talked earnestly with the boy 
Antonio about the new clove-carnations; and the rest of the day she 
sat in-doors and played sweetly on the virginal.  Now Nencia always 
had it in mind that her Grace had made a mistake in refusing that 
request of the chaplain's; but she said nothing, for to talk reason 
to the Duchess was of no more use than praying for rain in a 
drought. 
</p><p>"Winter came early that year, there was snow on the hills by 
All Souls, the wind stripped the gardens, and the lemon-trees were 
nipped in the lemon-house.  The Duchess kept her room in this black 
season, sitting over the fire, embroidering, reading books of 
devotion (which was a thing she had never done), and praying 
frequently in the chapel.  As for the chaplain, it was a place he 
never set foot in but to say mass in the morning, with the Duchess 
overhead in the tribune, and the servants aching with rheumatism on 
the marble floor.  The chaplain himself hated the cold, and 
galloped through the mass like a man with witches after him.  The 
rest of the day he spent in his library, over a brazier, with his 
eternal books. . . . 
</p><p>"You'll wonder, sir, if I'm ever to get to the gist of the 
story; and I've gone slowly, I own, for fear of what's coming.  
Well, the winter was long and hard.  When it fell cold the Duke 
ceased to come out from Vicenza, and not a soul had the Duchess to 
speak to but her maid-servants and the gardeners about the place.  
Yet it was wonderful, my grandmother said, how she kept her brave 
colors and her spirits; only it was remarked that she prayed longer 
in the chapel, where a brazier was kept burning for her all day.  
When the young are denied their natural pleasures, they turn often 
enough to religion; and it was a mercy, as my grandmother said, 
that she, who had scarce a live sinner to speak to, should take 
such comfort in a dead saint. 
</p><p>"My grandmother seldom saw her that winter, for though she 
showed a brave front to all, she kept more and more to herself, 
choosing to have only Nencia about her, and dismissing even her 
when she went to pray.  For her devotion had that mark of true 
piety, that she wished it not to be observed; so that Nencia had 
strict orders, on the chaplain's approach, to warn her mistress if 
she happened to be in prayer. 
</p><p>"Well, the winter passed, and spring was well forward, when my 
grandmother one evening had a bad fright.  That it was her own 
fault I won't deny, for she'd been down the lime-walk with Antonio 
when her aunt fancied her to be stitching in her chamber; and 
seeing a sudden light in Nencia's win-<pb n="158"/> dow, she took fright 
lest her disobedience be found out, and ran up quickly through the 
laurel-grove to the house.  Her way lay by the chapel, and as she 
crept past it, meaning to slip in through the scullery, and groping 
her way, for the dark had fallen and the moon was scarce up, she 
heard a crash close behind her, as though someone had dropped from 
a window of the chapel.  The young fool's heart turned over, but 
she looked round as she ran, and there, sure enough, was a man 
scuttling across the terrace; and as he doubled the corner of the 
house my grandmother swore she caught the whisk of the chaplain's 
skirts.  Now that was a strange thing, certainly; for why should 
the chaplain be getting out of the chapel window when he might have 
passed through the door?  For you may have noticed, sir, there's a 
door leads from the chapel into the saloon on the ground floor; the 
only other way out being through the Duchess's tribune. 
</p><p>"Well, my grandmother turned the matter over, and next time 
she met Antonio in the lime-walk (which, by reason of her fright, 
was not for some days) she laid before him what had happened; but 
to her surprise he only laughed, and said, 'You little simpleton, 
he wasn't getting out of the window, he was trying to look in;' and 
not another word could she get from him. 
</p><p>"So the season moved on to Easter, and news came the Duke had 
gone to Rome for that holy festivity.  His comings and goings made 
no change at the villa, and yet there was no one there but felt 
easier to think his yellow face was on the far side of the 
Apennines, unless, perhaps, it was the chaplain. 
</p><p>"Well, it was one day in May that the Duchess, who had walked 
long with Nencia on the terrace, rejoicing at the sweetness of the 
prospect and the pleasant scent of the gilly-flowers in the stone 
vases, the Duchess toward midday withdrew to her rooms, giving 
orders that her dinner should be served in her bed-chamber.  My 
grandmother helped to carry in the dishes, and observed, she said, 
the singular beauty of the Duchess, who, in honor of the fine 
weather, had put on a gown of shot-silver and hung her bare 
shoulders with pearls, so that she looked fit to dance at court 
with an emperor.  She had ordered, too, a rare repast for a lady 
that heeded so little what she ate&mdash;jellies, game-pastries, fruits 
in syrup, spiced cakes, and a flagon of Greek wine; and she nodded 
and clapped her hands as the women set it before her, saying, again 
and again, 'I shall eat well to-day.' 
</p><p>"But presently another mood seized her; she turned from the 
table, called for her rosary, and said to Nencia: 'The fine weather 
has made me neglect my devotions.  I must say a litany before I 
dine.' 
</p><p>"She ordered the women out and barred the door, as her custom 
was; and Nencia and my grandmother went down-stairs to work in the 
linen-room. 
</p><p>"Now the linen-room gives on the court-yard, and suddenly my 
grandmother saw a strange sight approaching.  First up the avenue 
came the Duke's carriage (whom all thought to be in Rome), and 
after it, drawn by a long string of mules and oxen, a cart carrying 
what looked like a kneeling figure wrapped in death-clothes.  The 
strangeness of it struck the girl dumb and the Duke's coach was at 
the door before she had the wit to cry out that it was coming.  
Nencia, when she saw it, went white and ran out of the room.  My 
grandmother followed, scared by her face, and the two fled along 
the corridor to the chapel.  On the way they met the chaplain, deep 
in a book, who asked in surprise where they were running, and when 
they said, to announce the Duke's arrival, he fell into such 
astonishment, and asked them so many questions and uttered such ohs 
and ahs that by the time he let them by the Duke was at their 
heels.  Nencia reached the chapel-door first and cried out that the 
Duke was coming; and before she had a reply he was at her side, 
with the chaplain following. 
</p><p>"A moment later the door opened and there stood the Duchess.  
She held her rosary in one hand and had drawn a scarf over her 
shoulders; but they shone through it like the moon in a mist, and 
her countenance sparkled with beauty. 
</p><p>"The Duke took her hand with a bow.  'Madam,' he said, 'I 
could have had no greater happiness than thus to surprise you at 
your devotions.' 
</p><p>"'My own happiness,' she replied, 'would have been greater had 
your excellency prolonged it by giving me notice of your arrival.' 
<pb n="159"/>  
</p><p>"'Had you expected me, Madam,' said he, 'your appearance could 
scarcely have been more fitted to the occasion.  Few ladies of your 
youth and beauty array themselves to venerate a saint as they would 
to welcome a lover.' 
</p><p>"'Sir,' she answered, 'having never enjoyed the latter 
opportunity, I am constrained to make the most of the former.&mdash; 
What's that?' she cried, falling back, and the rosary dropped from 
her hand. 
</p><p>"There was a loud noise at the other end of the saloon, as of 
a heavy object being dragged down the passage; and presently a 
dozen men were seen haling across the threshold the shrouded thing 
from the ox-cart.  The Duke waved his hand toward it.  'That,' said 
he, 'Madam, is a tribute to your extraordinary piety.  I have heard 
with peculiar satisfaction of your devotion to the blessed relics 
in this chapel, and to commemorate a zeal which neither the rigors 
of winter nor the sultriness of summer could abate, I have ordered 
a sculptured image of you, marvellously executed by the Cavaliere 
Bernini, to be placed before the altar over the entrance to the 
crypt.' 
</p><p>"The Duchess, who had grown pale nevertheless smiled playfully 
at this.  'As to commemorating my piety,' she said, 'I recognize 
there one of your excellency's pleasantries&mdash;' 
</p><p>"'A pleasantry?' the Duke interrupted; and he made a sign to 
the men, who had now reached the threshold of the chapel.  In an 
instant the wrappings fell from the figure, and there knelt the 
Duchess to the life.  A cry of wonder rose from all, but the 
Duchess herself stood whiter than the marble. 
</p><p>"'You will see,' says the Duke, 'this is no pleasantry, but a 
triumph of the incomparable Bernini's chisel.  The likeness was 
done from your miniature portrait by the divine Elisabetta Sirani, 
which I sent to the master some six months ago, with what results 
all must admire.' 
</p><p>"'Six months!' cried the Duchess, and seemed about to fall; 
but his excellency caught her by the hand. 
</p><p>"'Nothing,' he said, 'could better please me than the 
excessive emotion you display, for true piety is ever modest, and 
your thanks could not take a form that better became you.  And 
now,' says he to the men, 'let the image be put in place.' 
</p><p>"By this, life seemed to have returned to the Duchess, and she 
answered him with a deep reverence.  'That I should be overcome by 
so unexpected a grace, your excellency admits to be natural; but 
what honors you accord it is my privilege to accept, and I entreat 
only that in mercy to my modesty the image be placed in the 
remotest part of the chapel.' 
</p><p>"At that the Duke darkened.  'What!  You would have this 
masterpiece of a renowned chisel, which, I disguise not, cost me 
the price of a good vineyard in gold pieces, you would have it 
thrust out of sight like the work of a village stone-cutter?' 
</p><p>"'It is my semblance, not the sculptor's work, I desire to 
conceal.' 
</p><p>"'If you are fit for my house, Madam, you are fit for God's, 
and entitled to the place of honor in both.  Bring the statue 
forward, you dawdlers!' he called out to the men. 
</p><p>"The Duchess fell back submissively.  'You are right, sir, as 
always; but I would at least have the image stand on the left of 
the altar, that, looking up, it may behold your excellency's seat 
in the tribune.' 
</p><p>"'A pretty thought, Madam, for which I thank you; but I design 
before long to put my companion image on the other side of the 
altar; and the wife's place, as you know, is at her husband's right 
hand.' 
</p><p>"'True, my lord&mdash;but, again, if my poor presentment is to have 
the unmerited honor of kneeling beside yours, why not place both 
before the altar, where it is our habit to pray in life?' 
</p><p>"'And where, Madam, should we kneel if they took our places?  
Besides,' says the Duke, still speaking very blandly, 'I have a 
more particular purpose in placing your image over the entrance to 
the crypt; for not only would I thereby mark your special devotion 
to the blessed saint who rests there, but, by sealing up the 
opening in the pavement, would assure the perpetual preservation of 
that holy martyr's bones, which hitherto have been too 
thoughtlessly exposed to sacrilegious attempts.' 
</p><p>"'What attempts, my lord?' cries the <pb n="160"/>  Duchess.  'No one 
enters this chapel without my leave.' 
</p><p>"'So I have understood, and can well believe from what I have 
learned of your piety; yet at night a malefactor might break in 
through a window, Madam, and your excellency not know it.' 
</p><p>"'I'm a light sleeper,' said the Duchess. 
</p><p>"The Duke looked at her gravely.  'Indeed?' said he.  'A bad 
sign at your age.  I must see that you are provided with a 
sleeping-draught.' 
</p><p>"The Duchess's eyes filled.  'You would deprive me, then, of 
the consolation of visiting those venerable relics?' 
</p><p>"'I would have you keep eternal guard over them, knowing no 
one to whose care they may more fittingly be entrusted.' 
</p><p>"By this the image was brought close to the wooden slab that 
covered the entrance to the crypt, when the Duchess, springing 
forward, placed herself in the way. 
</p><p>"'Sir, let the statue be put in place to-morrow, and suffer 
me, to-night, to say a last prayer beside those holy bones.' 
</p><p>"The Duke stepped instantly to her side.  'Well thought, 
Madam; I will go down with you now, and we will pray together.' 
</p><p>"'Sir, your long absences have, alas! given me the habit of 
solitary devotion, and I confess that any presence is distracting.' 
</p><p>"'Madam, I accept your rebuke.  Hitherto, it is true, the 
duties of my station have constrained me to long absences; but 
henceforward I remain with you while you live.  Shall we go down 
into the crypt together?' 
</p><p>"'No; for I fear for your excellency's ague.  The air there is 
excessively damp.' 
</p><p>"'The more reason you should no longer be exposed to it; and 
to prevent the intemperance of your zeal I will at once make the 
place inaccessible.' 
</p><p>"The Duchess at this fell on her knees on the slab, weeping 
excessively and lifting her hands to heaven. 
</p><p>"'Oh,' she cried, 'you are cruel, sir, to deprive me of access 
to the sacred relics that have enabled me to support with 
resignation the solitude to which your excellency's duties have 
condemned me; and if prayer and meditation give me any authority to 
pronounce on such matters, suffer me to warn you, sir, that I fear 
the blessed Saint Blandina will punish us for thus abandoning her 
venerable remains!' 
</p><p>"The Duke at this seemed to pause, for he was a pious man, and 
my grandmother thought she saw him exchange a glance with the 
chaplain; who, stepping timidly forward, with his eyes on the 
ground, said, 'There is, indeed, much wisdom in her excellency's 
words, but I would suggest, sir, that her pious wish might be met, 
and the saint more conspicuously honored, by transferring the 
relics from the crypt to a place beneath the altar.' 
</p><p>"'True!' cried the Duke, 'and it shall be done at once.' 
</p><p>"But thereat the Duchess rose to her feet with a terrible 
look. 
</p><p>"'No,' she cried, 'by the body of God!  For it shall not be 
said that, after your excellency has chosen to deny every request 
I addressed to him, I owe his consent to the solicitation of 
another!' 
</p><p>"The chaplain turned red and the Duke yellow, and for a moment 
neither spoke. 
</p><p>"Then the Duke said, 'Here are words enough, Madam.  Do you 
wish the relics brought up from the crypt?' 
</p><p>"'I wish nothing that I owe to another's intervention!' 
</p><p>"'Put the image in place then,' says the Duke, furiously; and 
handed her grace to a chair. 
</p><p>"She sat there, my grandmother said, straight as an arrow, her 
hands locked, her head high, her eyes on the Duke, while the statue 
was dragged to its place; then she stood up and turned away.  As 
she passed by Nencia, 'Call me Antonio,' she whispered; but before 
the words were out of her mouth the Duke stepped between them. 
</p><p>"'Madam,' says he, all smiles now, 'I have travelled straight 
from Rome to bring you the sooner this proof of my esteem.  I lay 
last night at Monselice and have been on the road since daybreak.  
Will you not invite me to sup?' 
</p><p>"'Surely, my lord,' said the Duchess.  'It shall be laid in 
the dining-parlor within the hour.' 
</p><p>"'Why not in your chamber and at once, Madam?  Since I believe 
it is your custom to sup there.' 
</p><p>"'In my chamber?' says the Duchess in disorder. <pb n="161"/>  
[illustration omitted] <pb n="162"/>  
</p><p>"'Have you anything against it?' he asked. 
</p><p>"'Assuredly not, sir, if you will give me time to prepare 
myself.' 
</p><p>"'I will wait in your cabinet,' said the Duke. 
</p><p>"At that, said my grandmother, the Duchess gave one look, as 
the souls in hell may have looked when the gates closed on our 
Lord; then she called Nencia and passed to her chamber. 
</p><p>"What happened there my grandmother could never learn, but 
that the Duchess, in great haste, dressed herself with 
extraordinary splendor, powdering her hair with gold, painting her 
face and bosom, and covering herself with jewels till she shone 
like our Lady of Loreto; and hardly were these preparations 
complete when the Duke entered from the cabinet, followed by the 
servants, carrying supper.  Thereupon the Duchess dismissed Nencia, 
and what follows my grandmother learned from a pantry-lad who 
brought up the dishes and waited in the cabinet; for only the 
Duke's body-servant entered the bed-chamber. 
</p><p>"Well, according to this boy, sir, who was looking and 
listening with his whole body, as it were, because he had never 
before been suffered so near the Duchess, it appears that the noble 
couple sat down in great good humor, the Duchess playfully 
reproving her husband for his long absence, while the Duke swore 
that to look so beautiful was the best way of punishing him.  In 
this tone the talk continued, with such gay sallies on the part of 
the Duchess, such tender advances on the Duke's, that the lad 
declared they were for all the world like a pair of lovers courting 
on a summer's night in the vineyard; and so it went till the 
servant brought in the mulled wine. 
</p><p>"'Ah,' the Duke was saying at that moment, 'this agreeable 
evening repays me for the many dull ones I have spent away from 
you; nor do I remember to have enjoyed such laughter since the 
afternoon last year when we drank chocolate in the gazebo with my 
cousin Ascanio.  And that reminds me,' he said, 'is my cousin in 
good health?' 
</p><p>"'I have no reports of it,' says the Duchess.  'But your 
excellency should taste these figs stewed in malmsey&mdash;' 
</p><p>"'I am in the mood to taste whatever you offer,' said he; and 
as she helped him to the figs he added, 'If my enjoyment were not 
complete as it is, I could almost wish my cousin Ascanio were with 
us.  The fellow is rare good company at supper.  What do you say, 
Madam?  I hear he's still in the country; shall we send for him to 
join us?' 
</p><p>"'Ah,' said the Duchess, with a sigh and a languishing look, 
'I see your excellency wearies of me already.' 
</p><p>"'I, Madam?  Ascanio is a capital good fellow, but to my mind 
his chief merit at this moment is his absence.  It inclines me so 
tenderly to him, that, by God, I could empty a glass to his good 
health.' 
</p><p>"With that the Duke caught up his goblet and signed to the 
servant to fill the Duchess's. 
</p><p>"'Here's to the cousin,' he cried, standing, 'who has the good 
taste to stay away when he's not wanted.  I drink to his very long 
life&mdash;and you, Madam?' 
</p><p>"At this the Duchess, who had sat staring at him with a 
changed face, rose also and lifted her glass to her lips. 
</p><p>"'And I to his happy death,' says she in a wild voice; and as 
she spoke the empty goblet dropped from her hand and she fell face 
down on the floor. 
</p><p>"The Duke shouted to her women that she had swooned, and they 
came and lifted her to the bed. . . .  She suffered horribly all 
night, Nencia said, twisting herself like a heretic at the stake, 
but without a word escaping her.  The Duke watched by her, and 
toward daylight sent for the chaplain; but by this she was 
unconscious and, her teeth being locked, our Lord's body could not 
be passed through them. 
</p><p>.        .        .        .        .        .        . 
</p><p>"The Duke announced to his relations that his lady had died 
after partaking too freely of spiced wine and an omelet of carp's 
roe, at a supper she had prepared in honor of his return; and the 
next year he brought home a new Duchess, who gave him a son and 
five daughters. . . ." 
</p></div2> 
<div2 type="section" n="5" id="d8"><head>V</head> 
<p> 
THE sky had turned to a steel gray, against which the villa stood 
out sallow and inscrutable.  A wind strayed through the gardens, 
loosening here and <pb n="163"/>  there a yellow leaf from the sycamores; 
and the hills across the valley were purple as thunder-clouds. 
</p><p>.        .        .        .        .        .        . 
</p><p>"And the statue&mdash;?" I asked. 
</p><p>"Ah, the statue.  Well, sir, this is what my grandmother told 
me, here on this very bench where we're sitting.  The poor child, 
who worshipped the Duchess as a girl of her years will worship a 
beautiful kind mistress, spent a night of horror, you may fancy, 
shut out from her lady's room, hearing the cries that came from it, 
and seeing, as she crouched in her corner, the women rush to and 
fro with wild looks, the Duke's lean face in the door, and the 
chaplain skulking in the antechamber with his eyes on his breviary.  
No one minded her that night or the next morning; and toward dusk, 
when it became known the Duchess was no more, the poor girl felt 
the pious wish to say a prayer for her dead mistress.  She crept to 
the chapel and stole in unobserved.  The place was empty and dim, 
but as she advanced she heard a low moaning, and coming in front of 
the statue she saw that its face, the day before so sweet and 
smiling, had the look on it that you know&mdash;and the moaning seemed 
to come from its lips.  My grandmother turned cold, but something, 
she said afterward, kept her from calling or shrieking out, and she 
turned and ran from the place.  In the passage she fell in a swoon; 
and when she came to her senses, in her own chamber, she heard that 
the Duke had locked the chapel door and forbidden any to set foot 
there. . . . [illustration omitted] <pb n="164"/>  The place was never 
opened again till the Duke died, some ten years later; and then it 
was that the other servants, going in with the new heir, saw for 
the first time the horror that my grandmother had kept in her 
bosom. . . ." 
</p><p>"And the crypt?" I asked.  "Has it never been opened?" 
</p><p>"Heaven forbid, sir!" cried the old man, crossing himself.  
"Was it not the Duchess's express wish that the relics should not 
be disturbed?" 
</p> 

</div2> 
</div1> 
 
</body> 
</text> 
</TEI.2> 
