<?xml version="1.0"?>

<?dlps id="WhaDead"?>
<?dlps page-images="none" figure-images="no"?>
<?dlps transcription="other"?>

<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/tei-p4/tei2.dtd" [
<!ENTITY % POSTKB "INCLUDE">
<!ENTITY % TEI.extensions.ent SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.ent">
<!ENTITY % TEI.extensions.dtd SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.dtd">
<!ENTITY % ISOnum SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/charent/iso-num.ent"> %ISOnum;
<!ENTITY % ISOpub SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/charent/iso-pub.ent"> %ISOpub;

]>

<TEI.2 id="WhaDead"> 
<teiHeader type="migrated" creator="Etext">
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title type="main">The House of the Dead Hand</title>
<title type="sort">house of the dead hand</title>
<author>Wharton, Edith, 1862-1937</author>
<respStmt>
<resp>Creation of machine-readable version</resp>
<name>Judy Boss</name>
</respStmt>
<respStmt>
<resp>Conversion to TEI-conformant markup</resp>
<name>University of Virginia Library Electronic Text Center</name>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt> 
<extent>ca. <num type="kilobytes">64</num> kilobytes</extent> 
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>University of Virginia Library</publisher>
<pubPlace>Charlottesville, Virginia</pubPlace> 
<idno type="ETC">WhaDead</idno> 
<date value="1994">1994</date>
<availability status="public">
<p n="copyright">Copyright &copy; 1994 by the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia</p>
<p n="access">Publicly accessible</p>
</availability>
<idno type="uva-pid">uva-lib:476485</idno>
</publicationStmt>
<seriesStmt>
<title>University of Virginia Library, Text collection</title>
<idno type="uva-set">UVA-LIB-Text</idno>
</seriesStmt> 
<sourceDesc>
<biblFull>
<titleStmt>
<title type="main">The House of the Dead Hand</title>
<title type="sort">house of the dead hand</title>
<author>Edith Wharton</author>
</titleStmt> 
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>Century Magazine</publisher>
<pubPlace>New York</pubPlace> 
<date value="1904-08">August 1904</date>
</publicationStmt> 
<seriesStmt>
<p>Volume I</p>
</seriesStmt> 
</biblFull>
</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc> 
<encodingDesc>
<projectDesc>
<p>Prepared for the University of Virginia Library Electronic Text Center</p>
</projectDesc> 
<editorialDecl>
<p>All quotation marks retained as data</p> 
<p>All unambiguous end-of-line hyphens have been removed, and the 
trailing part of a word has been joined to the preceding line.</p> 
<p id="ETC">Keywords in the header are a local Electronic Text Center 
scheme 
to aid in establishing analytical groupings</p>
</editorialDecl> 
<refsDecl>
<p>ID elements are given for each page element and are composed of the 
text's 
unique cryptogram and the given page number, as in SpeFQue1 for page one of 
Spenser's Faerie Queene.</p>
</refsDecl>
</encodingDesc> 
<profileDesc>
<creation>
<date value="1904">1904</date>
</creation> 
<langUsage>
<language id="eng" usage="main">English</language>
<language id="la">Latin</language>
<language id="fre">French</language>
<language id="ita">Italian</language>
</langUsage> 
<textClass>
<keywords>
<term>fiction</term>
<term>prose</term>
</keywords>
</textClass>
</profileDesc> 
<revisionDesc>
<change>
<date value="1994-10">October 1994</date> 
<respStmt>
<resp>corrector</resp>
<name>Monique Dull</name>
</respStmt>
<item>conversion to basic TEI-conformant markup</item>
</change> 
<change>
<date value="2005-07">July 2005</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>Corrector</resp>
<name>Margaret Konkol</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Converted SGML to XML and fixed tagging.</item>
</change>
<change>
<date value="2007-09">September 2007</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>Migration</resp>
<name>Ethan Gruber, University of Virginia Library</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Converted XML markup from TEI Lite to uva-dl-tei (TEI P4 with local customizations).</item>
</change>
<change>
<date value="2008-01">January 2008</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>Migration</resp>
<name>Greg Murray, University of Virginia Library</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Programmatically updated TEI header markup (but not header content) for minimal compliance with current QA requirements.</item>
</change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader> 
 
<text id="d1">  
 
<body id="d2"> 
 

 
<div1 type="chapter" n="1" id="d3">
<pb n="145"/>  
<head type="main"> 
Wharton, Edith.  "The House of the Dead Hand."  
<lb/><hi rend="italic"> Atlantic Monthly</hi> 94 (Aug. 1904): 145-160. 
</head>
	
<head type="sub">I </head> 
<p>"Above all," the letter ended, "don't leave Siena without 
seeing Doctor Lombard's Leonardo.  Lombard is a queer old 
Englishman, a mystic or a madman (if the two are not synonymous), 
and a devout student of the Italian Renaissance.  He has lived for 
years in Italy, exploring its remotest corners, and has lately 
picked up an undoubted Leonardo, which came to light in a farmhouse 
near Bergamo.  It is believed to be one of the missing pictures 
mentioned by Vasari, and is at any rate, according to the most 
competent authorities, a genuine and almost untouched example of 
the best period. 
</p><p>"Lombard is a queer stick, and jealous of showing his 
treasures; but we struck up a friendship when I was working on the 
Sodomas in Siena three years ago, and if you will give him the 
enclosed line you may get a peep at the Leonardo.  Probably not 
more than a peep, though, for I hear he refuses to have it 
reproduced.  I want badly to use it in my monograph on the Windsor 
drawings, so please see what you can do for me, and if you can't 
persuade him to let you take a photograph or make a sketch, at 
least jot down a detailed description of the picture and get from 
him all the facts you can.  I hear that the French and Italian 
governments have offered him a large advance on his purchase, but 
that he refuses to sell at any price, though he certainly can't 
afford such luxuries; in fact, I don't see where he got enough 
money to buy the picture.  He lives in the Via Papa Giulio." 
</p><p>Wyant sat at the table d'hote of his hotel, re-reading his 
friend's letter over a late luncheon.  He had been five days in 
Siena without having found time to call on Doctor Lombard; not from 
any indifference to the opportunity presented, but because it was 
his first visit to the strange red city and he was still under the 
spell of its more conspicuous wonders &mdash; the brick palaces flinging 
out their wrought-iron torch-holders with a gesture of arrogant 
suzerainty; the great council-chamber emblazoned with civic 
allegories; the pageant of Pope Julius on the Library walls; the 
Sodomas smiling balefully through the dusk of mouldering chapels &mdash; 
and it was only when his first hunger was appeased that he 
remembered that one course in the banquet was still untasted. 
</p><p>He put the letter in his pocket and turned to leave the room, 
with a nod to its only other occupant, an olive-skinned young man 
with lustrous eyes and a low collar, who sat on the other side of 
the table, perusing the <hi rend="italic">Fanfulla di Domenica</hi>.  This gentleman, 
his daily vis-a-vis, returned the nod with a Latin eloquence of 
gesture, and Wyant passed on to the ante-chamber, where he paused 
to light a cigarette.  He was just restoring the case to his pocket 
when he heard a hurried step behind him, and the lustrous-eyed 
young man advanced through the glass doors of the dining-room. 
</p><p>"Pardon me, sir," he said in measured English, and with an 
intonation of exquisite politeness; "you have let this letter 
fall." <pb n="146"/>  
</p><p>Wyant, recognizing his friend's note of introduction to Doctor 
Lombard, took it with a word of thanks, and was about to turn away 
when he perceived that the eyes of his fellow diner remained fixed 
on him with a gaze of melancholy interrogation. 
</p><p>"Again pardon me," the young man at length ventured, "but are 
you by chance the friend of the illustrious Doctor Lombard?" 
</p><p>"No," returned Wyant, with the instinctive Anglo-Saxon 
distrust of foreign advances.  Then, fearing to appear rude, he 
said with a guarded politeness: "Perhaps, by the way, you can tell 
me the number of his house.  I see it is not given here." 
</p><p>The young man brightened perceptibly.  "The number of the 
house is thirteen; but any one can indicate it to you &mdash; it is well 
known in Siena.  It is called," he continued after a moment, "the 
House of the Dead Hand." 
</p><p>Wyant stared.  "What a queer name!" he said. 
</p><p>"The name comes from an antique hand of marble which for many 
hundred years has been above the door." 
</p><p>Wyant was turning away with a gesture of thanks, when the 
other added: "If you would have the kindness to ring twice." 
</p><p>"To ring twice?" 
</p><p>"At the doctor's."  The young man smiled.  "It is the custom." 
</p><p>It was a dazzling March afternoon, with a shower of sun from 
the mid-blue, and a marshalling of slaty clouds behind the umber-colored hills.  For nearly an hour Wyant loitered on the Lizza, 
watching the shadows race across the naked landscape and the 
thunder blacken in the west; then he decided to set out for the 
House of the Dead Hand.  The map in his guidebook showed him that 
the Via Papa Giulio was one of the streets which radiate from the 
Piazza, and thither he bent his course, pausing at every other step 
to fill his eye with some fresh image of weather-beaten beauty. 
The clouds had rolled upward, obscuring the sunshine and hanging 
like a funereal baldachin above the projecting cornices of Doctor 
Lombard's street, and Wyant walked for some distance in the shade 
of the beetling palace fronts before his eye fell on a doorway 
surmounted by a sallow marble hand.  He stood for a moment staring 
up at the strange emblem.  The hand was a woman's &mdash; a dead drooping 
hand, which hung there convulsed and helpless, as though it had 
been thrust forth in denunciation of some evil mystery within the 
house, and had sunk struggling into death. 
</p><p>A girl who was drawing water from the well in the court said 
that the English doctor lived on the first floor, and Wyant, 
passing through a glazed door, mounted the damp degrees of a 
vaulted stairway with a plaster AEsculapius mouldering in a niche 
on the landing.  Facing the AEsculapius was another door, and as 
Wyant put his hand on the bell-rope he remembered his unknown 
friend's injunction, and rang twice. 
</p><p>His ring was answered by a peasant woman with a low forehead 
and small close-set eyes, who, after a prolonged scrutiny of 
himself, his card, and his letter of introduction, left him 
standing in a high, cold ante-chamber floored with brick.  He heard 
her wooden pattens click down an interminable corridor, and after 
some delay she returned and told him to follow her. 
</p><p>They passed through a long saloon, bare as the ante-chamber, 
but loftily vaulted, and frescoed with a seventeenth-century 
Triumph of Scipio or Alexander &mdash; martial figures following Wyant 
with the filmed melancholy gaze of shades in limbo.  At the end of 
this apartment he was admitted to a smaller room, with the same 
atmosphere of mortal cold, but showing more obvious signs of 
occupancy.  The walls were covered with tapestry which had faded to 
the gray-brown tints of decaying vegetation, so that the young man 
felt as though he were entering a sunless autumn wood.  Against 
these <pb n="147"/>  hangings stood a few tall cabinets on heavy gilt 
feet, and at a table in the window three persons were seated: an 
elderly lady who was warming her hands over a brazier, a girl bent 
above a strip of needle-work, and an old man. 
</p><p>As the latter advanced toward Wyant, the young man was 
conscious of staring with unseemly intentness at his small round-backed figure, dressed with shabby disorder and surmounted by a 
wonderful head, lean, vulpine, eagle-beaked as that of some art-loving despot of the Renaissance: a head combining the venerable 
hair and large prominent eyes of the humanist with the greedy 
profile of the adventurer.  Wyant, in musing on the Italian 
portrait-medals of the fifteenth century, had often fancied that 
only in that period of fierce individualism could types so 
paradoxical have been produced; yet the subtle craftsmen who 
committed them to the bronze had never drawn a face more strangely 
stamped with contradictory passions than that of Doctor Lombard. 
</p><p>"I am glad to see you," he said to Wyant, extending a hand 
which seemed a mere framework held together by knotted veins.  "We 
lead a quiet life here and receive few visitors, but any friend of 
Professor Clyde's is welcome."  Then, with a gesture which included 
the two women, he added dryly: "My wife and daughter often talk of 
Professor Clyde." 
</p><p>"Oh yes &mdash; he used to make me such nice toast; they don't 
understand toast in Italy," said Mrs. Lombard in a high plaintive 
voice. 
</p><p>It would have been difficult, from Doctor Lombard's manner and 
appearance to guess his nationality; but his wife was so 
inconsciently and ineradicably English that even the silhouette of 
her cap seemed a protest against Continental laxities.  She was a 
stout fair woman, with pale cheeks netted with red lines.  A brooch 
with a miniature portrait sustained a bogwood watch-chain upon her 
bosom, and at her elbow lay a heap of knitting and an old copy of 
<hi rend="italic"> The Queen</hi>. 
</p><p>The young girl, who had remained standing, was a slim replica 
of her mother, with an apple-cheeked face and opaque blue eyes. 
Her small head was prodigally laden with braids of dull fair hair, 
and she might have had a kind of transient prettiness but for the 
sullen droop of her round mouth.  It was hard to say whether her 
expression implied ill-temper or apathy; but Wyant was struck by 
the contrast between the fierce vitality of the doctor's age and 
the inanimateness of his daughter's youth. 
</p><p>Seating himself in the chair which his host advanced, the 
young man tried to open the conversation by addressing to Mrs. 
Lombard some random remark on the beauties of Siena.  The lady 
murmured a resigned assent, and Doctor Lombard interposed with a 
smile: "My dear sir, my wife considers Siena a most salubrious 
spot, and is favorably impressed by the cheapness of the marketing; 
but she deplores the total absence of muffins and cannel coal, and 
cannot resign herself to the Italian method of dusting furniture." 
</p><p>"But they don't, you know &mdash; they don't dust it!" Mrs. Lombard 
protested, without showing any resentment of her husband's manner. 
</p><p>"Precisely &mdash; they don't dust it.  Since we have lived in Siena 
we have not once seen the cobwebs removed from the battlements of 
the Mangia.  Can you conceive of such housekeeping?  My wife has 
never yet dared to write it home to her aunts at Bonchurch." 
</p><p>Mrs. Lombard accepted in silence this remarkable statement of 
her views, and her husband, with a malicious smile at Wyant's 
embarrassment, planted himself suddenly before the young man. 
</p><p>"And now," said he, "do you want to see my Leonardo?" 
</p><p><hi rend="italic">" Do</hi> I?" cried Wyant, on his feet in a flash. 
</p><p>The doctor chuckled.  "Ah," he said, with a kind of crooning 
deliberation, "that's the way they all behave &mdash; that's what they all 
come for."  He turned to <pb n="148"/>  his daughter with another 
variation of mockery in his smile.  "Don't fancy it's for your 
<hi rend="italic">beaux yeux</hi>, my dear; or for the mature charms of Mrs. Lombard," he 
added, glaring suddenly at his wife, who had taken up her knitting 
and was softly murmuring over the number of her stitches. 
</p><p>Neither lady appeared to notice his pleasantries, and he 
continued, addressing himself to Wyant: "They all come &mdash; they all 
come; but many are called and few are chosen."  His voice sank to 
solemnity.  "While I live," he said, "no unworthy eye shall 
desecrate that picture.  But I will not do my friend Clyde the 
injustice to suppose that he would send an unworthy representative. 
He tells me he wishes a description of the picture for his book; 
and you shall describe it to him &mdash; if you can." 
</p><p>Wyant hesitated, not knowing whether it was a propitious 
moment to put in his appeal for a photograph. 
</p><p>"Well, sir," he said, "you know Clyde wants me to take away 
all I can of it." 
</p><p>Doctor Lombard eyed him sardonically.  "You're welcome to take 
away all you can carry," he replied; adding, as he turned to his 
daughter: "That is, if he has your permission, Sybilla." 
</p><p>The girl rose without a word, and laying aside her work, took 
a key from a secret drawer in one of the cabinets, while the doctor 
continued in the same note of grim jocularity: "For you must know 
that the picture is not mine &mdash; it is my daughter's." 
</p><p>He followed with evident amusement the surprised glance which 
Wyant turned on the young girl's impassive figure. 
</p><p>"Sybilla," he pursued, "is a votary of the arts; she has 
inherited her fond father's passion for the unattainable.  Luckily, 
however, she also recently inherited a tidy legacy from her 
grandmother; and having seen the Leonardo, on which its discoverer 
had placed a price far beyond my reach, she took a step which 
deserves to go down to history: she invested her whole inheritance 
in the purchase of the picture, thus enabling me to spend my 
closing years in communion with one of the world's masterpieces. 
My dear sir, could Antigone do more?" 
</p><p>The object of this strange eulogy had meanwhile drawn aside 
one of the tapestry hangings, and fitted her key into a concealed 
door. 
</p><p>"Come," said Doctor Lombard, "let us go before the light fails 
us." 
</p><p>Wyant glanced at Mrs. Lombard, who continued to knit 
impassively. 
</p><p>"No, no," said his host, "my wife will not come with us.  You 
might not suspect it from her conversation, but my wife has no 
feeling for art &mdash; Italian art, that is; for no one is fonder of our 
early Victorian school." 
</p><p>"Frith's <hi rend="italic"> Railway Station</hi>, you know," said Mrs. Lombard, 
smiling.  "I like an animated picture." 
</p><p>Miss Lombard, who had unlocked the door, held back the 
tapestry to let her father and Wyant pass out; then she followed 
them down a narrow stone passage with another door at its end. 
This door was iron-barred, and Wyant noticed that it had a 
complicated patent lock.  The girl fitted another key into the 
lock, and Doctor Lombard led the way into a small room.  The dark 
panelling of this apartment was irradiated by streams of yellow 
light slanting through the disbanded thunder clouds, and in the 
central brightness hung a picture concealed by a curtain of faded 
velvet. 
</p><p>"A little too bright, Sybilla," said Doctor Lombard.  His face 
had grown solemn, and his mouth twitched nervously as his daughter 
drew a linen drapery across the upper part of the window. 
</p><p>"That will do &mdash; that will do."  He turned impressively to 
Wyant.  "Do you see the pomegranate bud in this rug?  Place 
yourself there &mdash; keep your left foot on it, please.  And now, 
Sybilla, draw the cord." 
</p><p>Miss Lombard advanced and placed her hand on a cord hidden 
behind the velvet curtain. 
</p><p>"Ah," said the doctor, "one moment: <pb n="149"/>  I should like you, 
while looking at the picture, to have in mind a few lines of verse. 
Sybilla &mdash; " 
</p><p>Without the slightest change of countenance, and with a 
promptness which proved her to be prepared for the request, Miss 
Lombard began to recite, in a full round voice like her mother's, 
St. Bernard's invocation to the Virgin, in the thirty-third canto 
of the <hi rend="italic"> Paradise</hi>. 
</p><p>"Thank you, my dear," said her father, drawing a deep breath 
as she ended.  "That unapproachable combination of vowel sounds 
prepares one better than anything I know for the contemplation of 
the picture." 
</p><p>As he spoke the folds of velvet slowly parted, and the 
Leonardo appeared in its frame of tarnished gold: 
</p><p>From the nature of Miss Lombard's recitation Wyant had 
expected a sacred subject, and his surprise was therefore great as 
the composition was gradually revealed by the widening division of 
the curtain. 
</p><p>In the background a steel-colored river wound through a pale 
calcareous landscape; while to the left, on a lonely peak, a 
crucified Christ hung livid against indigo clouds.  The central 
figure of the foreground, however, was that of a woman seated in an 
antique chair of marble with bas-reliefs of dancing maenads.  Her 
feet rested on a meadow sprinkled with minute wild-flowers, and her 
attitude of smiling majesty recalled that of Dosso Dossi's Circe. 
She wore a red robe, flowing in closely fluted lines from under a 
fancifully embroidered cloak.  Above her high forehead the crinkled 
golden hair flowed sideways beneath a veil; one hand drooped on the 
arm of her chair; the other held up an inverted human skull, into 
which a young Dionysus, smooth, brown and sidelong as the St. John 
of the Louvre, poured a stream of wine from a high-poised flagon. 
At the lady's feet lay the symbols of art and luxury: a flute and 
a roll of music, a platter heaped with grapes and roses, the torso 
of a Greek statuette, and a bowl overflowing with coins and jewels; 
behind her, on the chalky hilltop, hung the crucified Christ.  A 
scroll in a corner of the foreground bore the legend: <hi rend="italic"> Lux 
Mundi</hi>. 
</p><p>Wyant, emerging from the first plunge of wonder, turned 
inquiringly toward his companions.  Neither had moved.  Miss 
Lombard stood with her hand on the cord, her lids lowered, her 
mouth drooping; the doctor, his strange Thoth-like profile turned 
toward his guest, was still lost in rapt contemplation of his 
treasure. 
</p><p>Wyant addressed the young girl. 
</p><p>"You are fortunate," he said, "to be the possessor of anything 
so perfect." 
</p><p>"It is considered very beautiful," she said coldly. 
</p><p>"Beautiful &mdash; <hi rend="italic"> beautiful!"</hi> the doctor burst out.  "Ah, the 
poor, worn out, over-worked word!  There are no adjectives in the 
language fresh enough to describe such pristine brilliancy; all 
their brightness has been worn off by misuse.  Think of the things 
that have been called beautiful, and then look at <hi rend="italic"> that!"</hi> 
</p><p>"It is worthy of a new vocabulary," Wyant agreed. 
</p><p>"Yes," Doctor Lombard continued, "my daughter is indeed 
fortunate.  She has chosen what Catholics call the higher life &mdash; the 
counsel of perfection.  What other private person enjoys the same 
opportunity of understanding the master?  Who else lives under the 
same roof with an untouched masterpiece of Leonardo's?  Think of 
the happiness of being always under the influence of such a 
creation; of living <hi rend="italic"> into</hi> it; of partaking of it in daily and 
hourly communion!  This room is a chapel; the sight of that picture 
is a sacrament.  What an atmosphere for a young life to unfold 
itself in!  My daughter is singularly blessed.  Sybilla, point out 
some of the details to Mr. Wyant; I see that he will appreciate 
them." 
</p><p>The girl turned her dense blue eyes toward Wyant; then, 
glancing away from him, she pointed to the canvas. 
</p><p>"Notice the modeling of the left hand," she began in a 
monotonous voice; "it recalls the hand of the Mona Lisa. <pb n="150"/>  
The head of the naked genius will remind you of that of the St. 
John of the Louvre, but it is more purely pagan and is turned a 
little less to the right.  The embroidery on the cloak is symbolic: 
you will see that the roots of this plant have burst through the 
vase.  This recalls the famous definition of Hamlet's character in 
<hi rend="italic"> Wilhelm Meister</hi>.  Here are the mystic rose, the flame, and the 
serpent, emblem of eternity.  Some of the other symbols we have not 
yet been able to decipher." 
</p><p>Wyant watched her curiously; she seemed to be reciting a 
lesson. 
</p><p>"And the picture itself?" he said.  "How do you explain that? 
<hi rend="italic"> Lux Mundi</hi> &mdash; what a curious device to connect with such a 
subject!  What can it mean?" 
</p><p>Miss Lombard dropped her eyes: the answer was evidently not 
included in her lesson. 
</p><p>"What, indeed?" the doctor interposed.  "What does life mean? 
As one may define it in a hundred different ways, so one may find 
a hundred different meanings in this picture.  Its symbolism is as 
many-faceted as a well-cut diamond.  Who, for instance, is that 
divine lady?  Is it she who is the true <hi rend="italic"> Lux Mundi</hi> &mdash; the light 
reflected from jewels and young eyes, from polished marble and 
clear waters and statues of bronze?  Or is that the Light of the 
World, extinguished on yonder stormy hill, and is this lady the 
Pride of Life, feasting blindly on the wine of iniquity, with her 
back turned to the light which has shone for her in vain? 
Something of both these meanings may be traced in the picture; but 
to me it symbolizes rather the central truth of existence: that all 
that is raised in incorruption is sown in corruption; art, beauty, 
love, religion; that all our wine is drunk out of skulls, and 
poured for us by the mysterious genius of a remote and cruel past." 
</p><p>The doctor's face blazed: his bent figure seemed to straighten 
itself and become taller. 
</p><p>"Ah," he cried, growing more dithyrambic, "how lightly you ask 
what it means!  How confidently you expect an answer!  Yet here am 
I who have given my life to the study of the Renaissance; who have 
violated its tomb, laid open its dead body, and traced the course 
of every muscle, bone, and artery; who have sucked its very soul 
from the pages of poets and humanists; who have wept and believed 
with Joachim of Flora, smiled and doubted with AEneas Sylvius 
Piccolomini; who have patiently followed to its source the least 
inspiration of the masters, and groped in neolithic caverns and 
Babylonian ruins for the first unfolding tendrils of the arabesques 
of Mantegna and Crivelli; and I tell you that I stand abashed and 
ignorant before the mystery of this picture.  It means nothing &mdash; it 
means all things.  It may represent the period which saw its 
creation; it may represent all ages past and to come.  There are 
volumes of meaning in the tiniest emblem on the lady's cloak; the 
blossoms of its border are rooted in the deepest soil of myth and 
tradition.  Don't ask what it means, young man, but bow your head 
in thankfulness for having seen it!" 
</p><p>Miss Lombard laid her hand on his arm. 
</p><p>"Don't excite yourself, father," she said in the detached tone 
of a professional nurse. 
</p><p>He answered with a despairing gesture.  "Ah, it's easy for you 
to talk.  You have years and years to spend with it; I am an old 
man, and every moment counts!" 
</p><p>"It's bad for you," she repeated with gentle obstinacy. 
</p><p>The doctor's sacred fury had in fact burnt itself out.  He 
dropped into a seat with dull eyes and slackening lips, and his 
daughter drew the curtain across the picture. 
</p><p>Wyant turned away reluctantly.  He felt that his opportunity 
was slipping from him, yet he dared not refer to Clyde's wish for 
a photograph.  He now understood the meaning of the laugh with 
which Doctor Lombard had given him leave to carry away all the 
details he <pb n="151"/>  could remember.  The picture was so dazzling, so 
unexpected, so crossed with elusive and contradictory suggestions, 
that the most alert observer, when placed suddenly before it, must 
lose his coordinating faculty in a sense of confused wonder.  Yet 
how valuable to Clyde the record of such a work would be!  In some 
ways it seemed to be the summing up of the master's thought, the 
key to his enigmatic philosophy. 
</p><p>The doctor had risen and was walking slowly toward the door. 
His daughter unlocked it, and Wyant followed them back in silence 
to the room in which they had left Mrs. Lombard.  That lady was no 
longer there, and he could think of no excuse for lingering. 
</p><p>He thanked the doctor, and turned to Miss Lombard, who stood 
in the middle of the room as though awaiting farther orders. 
</p><p>"It is very good of you," he said, "to allow one even a 
glimpse of such a treasure." 
</p><p>She looked at him with her odd directness.  "You will come 
again?" she said quickly; and turning to her father she added: "You 
know what Professor Clyde asked.  This gentleman cannot give him 
any account of the picture without seeing it again." 
</p><p>Doctor Lombard glanced at her vaguely; he was still like a 
person in a trance. 
</p><p>"Eh?" he said, rousing himself with an effort. 
</p><p>"I said, father, that Mr. Wyant must see the picture again if 
he is to tell Professor Clyde about it," Miss Lombard repeated with 
extraordinary precision of tone. 
</p><p>Wyant was silent.  He had the puzzled sense that his wishes 
were being divined and gratified for reasons with which he was in 
no way connected. 
</p><p>"Well, well," the doctor muttered, "I don't say no &mdash; I don't 
say no.  I know what Clyde wants &mdash; I don't refuse to help him."  He 
turned to Wyant.  "You may come again &mdash; you may make notes," he 
added with a sudden effort.  "Jot down what occurs to you.  I'm 
willing to concede that." 
</p><p>Wyant again caught the girl's eye, but its emphatic message 
perplexed him. 
</p><p>"You're very good," he said tentatively, "but the fact is the 
picture is so mysterious &mdash; so full of complicated detail &mdash; that I'm 
afraid no notes I could make would serve Clyde's purpose as well 
as &mdash; as a photograph, say.  If you would allow me &mdash; " 
</p><p>Miss Lombard's brow darkened, and her father raised his 
furiously. 
</p><p>"A photograph?  A photograph, did you say?  Good God, man, not 
ten people have been allowed to set foot in that room!  A <hi rend="italic"> 
photograph</hi>?" 
</p><p>Wyant saw his mistake, but saw also that he had gone too far 
to retreat. 
</p><p>"I know, sir, from what Clyde has told me, that you object to 
having any reproduction of the picture published; but he hoped you 
might let me take a photograph for his personal use &mdash; not to be 
reproduced in his book, but simply to give him something to work 
by.  I should take the photograph myself, and the negative would of 
course be yours.  If you wished it, only one impression would be 
struck off, and that one Clyde could return to you when he had done 
with it." 
</p><p>Doctor Lombard interrupted him with a snarl.  "When he had 
done with it?  Just so: I thank thee for that word!  When it had 
been re-photographed, drawn, traced, autotyped, passed about from 
hand to hand, defiled by every ignorant eye in England, vulgarized 
by the blundering praise of every art-scribbler in Europe!  Bah! 
I'd as soon give you the picture itself: why don't you ask for 
that?" 
</p><p>"Well, sir," said Wyant calmly, "if you will trust me with it, 
I'll engage to take it safely to England and back, and to let no 
eye but Clyde's see it while it is out of your keeping." 
</p><p>The doctor received this remarkable proposal in silence; then 
he burst into a laugh. 
</p><p>"Upon my soul!" he said with sardonic good humor. <pb n="152"/>  
</p><p>It was Miss Lombard's turn to look perplexedly at Wyant.  His 
last words and her father's unexpected reply had evidently carried 
her beyond her depth. 
</p><p>"Well, sir, am I to take the picture?" Wyant smilingly 
pursued. 
</p><p>"No, young man; nor a photograph of it.  Nor a sketch, either; 
mind that, &mdash; nothing that can be reproduced.  Sybilla," he cried 
with sudden passion, "swear to me that the picture shall never be 
reproduced!  No photograph, no sketch &mdash; now or afterward.  Do you 
hear me?" 
</p><p>"Yes, father," said the girl quietly. 
</p><p>"The vandals," he muttered, "the desecrators of beauty; if I 
thought it would ever get into their hands I'd burn it first, by 
God!"  He turned to Wyant, speaking more quietly.  "I said you 
might come back &mdash; I never retract what I say.  But you must give me 
your word that no one but Clyde shall see the notes you make." 
</p><p>Wyant was growing warm. 
</p><p>"If you won't trust me with a photograph I wonder you trust me 
not to show my notes!" he exclaimed. 
</p><p>The doctor looked at him with a malicious smile. 
</p><p>"Humph!" he said; "would they be of much use to anybody?" 
</p><p>Wyant saw that he was losing ground and controlled his 
impatience. 
</p><p>"To Clyde, I hope, at any rate," he answered, holding out his 
hand.  The doctor shook it without a trace of resentment, and Wyant 
added: "When shall I come, sir?" 
</p><p>"To-morrow &mdash; to-morrow morning," cried Miss Lombard, speaking 
suddenly. 
</p><p>She looked fixedly at her father, and he shrugged his 
shoulders. 
</p><p>"The picture is hers," he said to Wyant. 
</p><p>In the ante-chamber the young man was met by the woman who had 
admitted him.  She handed him his hat and stick, and turned to 
unbar the door.  As the bolt slipped back he felt a touch on his 
arm. 
</p><p>"You have a letter?" she said in a low tone. 
</p><p>"A letter?"  He stared.  "What letter?" 
</p><p>She shrugged her shoulders, and drew back to let him pass. 
</p> 
</div1> 
<div1 type="chapter" n="2" id="d4">                           
<head>II 
</head> 
<p>As Wyant emerged from the house he paused once more to glance 
up at its scarred brick facade.  The marble hand drooped tragically 
above the entrance: in the waning light it seemed to have relaxed 
into the passiveness of despair, and Wyant stood musing on its 
hidden meaning.  But the Dead Hand was not the only mysterious 
thing about Doctor Lombard's house.  What were the relations 
between Miss Lombard and her father?  Above all, between Miss 
Lombard and her picture?  She did not look like a person capable of 
a disinterested passion for the arts; and there had been moments 
when it struck Wyant that she hated the picture. 
</p><p>The sky at the end of the street was flooded with turbulent 
yellow light, and the young man turned his steps toward the church 
of San Domenico, in the hope of catching the lingering brightness 
on Sodoma's St. Catherine. 
</p><p>The great bare aisles were almost dark when he entered, and he 
had to grope his way to the chapel steps.  Under the momentary 
evocation of the sunset, the saint's figure emerged pale and 
swooning from the dusk, and the warm light gave a sensual tinge to 
her ecstasy.  The flesh seemed to glow and heave, the eyelids to 
tremble; Wyant stood fascinated by the accidental collaboration of 
light and color. 
</p><p>Suddenly he noticed that something white had fluttered to the 
ground at his feet.  He stooped and picked up a small thin sheet of 
note-paper, folded and sealed like an old-fashioned letter, and 
bearing the superscription: &mdash; 
</p><p><hi rend="italic"> To the Count Ottaviano Celsi.</hi> 
</p><p>Wyant stared at this mysterious document.  Where had it come 
from?  He was distinctly conscious of having seen it fall <pb n="153"/>  
through the air, close to his feet.  He glanced up at the dark 
ceiling of the chapel; then he turned and looked about the church. 
There was only one figure in it, that of a man who knelt near the 
high altar. 
</p><p>Suddenly Wyant recalled the question of Doctor Lombard's maid-servant.  Was this the letter she had asked for?  Had he been 
unconsciously carrying it about with him all the afternoon?  Who 
was Count Ottaviano Celsi, and how came Wyant to have been chosen 
to act as that nobleman's ambulant letter-box? 
</p><p>Wyant laid his hat and stick on the chapel steps and began to 
explore his pockets, in the irrational hope of finding there some 
clue to the mystery; but they held nothing which he had not himself 
put there, and he was reduced to wondering how the letter, 
supposing some unknown hand to have bestowed it on him, had 
happened to fall out while he stood motionless before the picture. 
</p><p>At this point he was disturbed by a step on the floor of the 
aisle, and turning, he saw his lustrous-eyed neighbor of the table 
d'hote. 
</p><p>The young man bowed and waved an apologetic hand. 
</p><p>"I do not intrude?" he inquired suavely. 
</p><p>Without waiting for a reply, he mounted the steps of the 
chapel, glancing about him with the affable air of an afternoon 
caller. 
</p><p>"I see," he remarked with a smile, "that you know the hour at 
which our saint should be visited." 
</p><p>Wyant agreed that the hour was indeed felicitous. 
</p><p>The stranger stood beamingly before the picture. 
</p><p>"What grace!  What poetry!" he murmured, apostrophizing the 
St. Catherine, but letting his glance slip rapidly about the chapel 
as he spoke. 
</p><p>Wyant, detecting the manoeuvre, murmured a brief assent. 
</p><p>"But it is cold here &mdash; mortally cold; you do not find it so?" 
The intruder put on his hat.  "It is permitted at this hour &mdash; when 
the church is empty.  And you, my dear sir &mdash; do you not feel the 
dampness?  You are an artist, are you not?  And to artists it is 
permitted to cover the head when they are engaged in the study of 
the paintings." 
</p><p>He darted suddenly toward the steps and bent over Wyant's hat. 
</p><p>"Permit me &mdash; cover yourself!" he said a moment later, holding 
out the hat with an ingratiating gesture. 
</p><p>A light flashed on Wyant. 
</p><p>"Perhaps," he said, looking straight at the young man, "you 
will tell me your name.  My own is Wyant." 
</p><p>The stranger, surprised, but not disconcerted, drew forth a 
coroneted card, which he offered with a low bow.  On the card was 
engraved: &mdash; 
</p><p><hi rend="italic"> Il Conte Ottaviano Celsi.</hi> 
</p><p>"I am much obliged to you," said Wyant; "and I may as well 
tell you that the letter which you apparently expected to find in 
the lining of my hat is not there, but in my pocket." 
</p><p>He drew it out and handed it to its owner, who had grown very 
pale. 
</p><p>"And now," Wyant continued, "you will perhaps be good enough 
to tell me what all this means." 
</p><p>There was no mistaking the effect produced on Count Ottaviano 
by this request.  His lips moved, but he achieved only an 
ineffectual smile. 
</p><p>"I suppose you know," Wyant went on, his anger rising at the 
sight of the other's discomfiture, "that you have taken an 
unwarrantable liberty.  I don't yet understand what part I have 
been made to play, but it's evident that you have made use of me to 
serve some purpose of your own, and I propose to know the reason 
why." 
</p><p>Count Ottaviano advanced with an imploring gesture. 
</p><p>"Sir," he pleaded, "you permit me to speak?" 
</p><p>"I expect you to," cried Wyant.  "But not here," he added, 
hearing the clank of the verger's keys.  "It is growing dark,  
<pb n="154"/>  
and we shall be turned out in a few minutes." 
</p><p>He walked across the church, and Count Ottaviano followed him 
out into the deserted square. 
</p><p>"Now," said Wyant, pausing on the steps. 
</p><p>The Count, who had regained some measure of self-possession, 
began to speak in a high key, with an accompaniment of conciliatory 
gesture. 
</p> 
<p>"My dear sir &mdash; my dear Mr. Wyant &mdash; you find me in an abominable 
position &mdash; that, as a man of honor, I immediately confess.  I have 
taken advantage of you &mdash; yes!  I have counted on your amiability, 
your chivalry &mdash; too far, perhaps?  I confess it!  But what could I 
do?  It was to oblige a lady" &mdash; he laid a hand on his heart &mdash; "a lady 
whom I would die to serve!"  He went on with increasing volubility, 
his deliberate English swept away by a torrent of Italian, through 
which Wyant, with some difficulty, struggled to a comprehension of 
the case. 
</p><p>Count Ottaviano, according to his own statement, had come to 
Siena some months previously, on business connected with his 
mother's property; the paternal estate being near Orvieto, of which 
ancient city his father was syndic.  Soon after his arrival in 
Siena the young Count had met the incomparable daughter of Doctor 
Lombard, and falling deeply in love with her, had prevailed on his 
parents to ask her hand in marriage.  Doctor Lombard had not 
opposed his suit, but when the question of settlements arose it 
became known that Miss Lombard, who was possessed of a small 
property in her own right, had a short time before invested the 
whole amount in the purchase of the Bergamo Leonardo.  Thereupon 
Count Ottaviano's parents had politely suggested that she should 
sell the picture and thus recover her independence; and this 
proposal being met by a curt refusal from Doctor Lombard, they had 
withdrawn their consent to their son's marriage.  The young lady's 
attitude had hitherto been one of passive submission; she was 
horribly afraid of her father, and would never venture openly to 
oppose him; but she had made known to Ottaviano her intention of 
not giving him up, of waiting patiently till events should take a 
more favorable turn.  She seemed hardly aware, the Count said with 
a sigh, that the means of escape lay in her own hands; that she was 
of age, and had a right to sell the picture, and to marry without 
asking her father's consent.  Meanwhile her suitor spared no pains 
to keep himself before her, to remind her that he, too, was waiting 
and would never give her up. 
</p><p>Doctor Lombard, who suspected the young man of trying to 
persuade Sybilla to sell the picture, had forbidden the lovers to 
meet or to correspond; they were thus driven to clandestine 
communication, and had several times, the Count ingenuously avowed, 
made use of the doctor's visitors as a means of exchanging letters. 
</p><p>"And you told the visitors to ring twice?" Wyant interposed. 
</p><p>The young man extended his hands in a deprecating gesture. 
Could Mr. Wyant blame him?  He was young, he was ardent, he was 
enamored!  The young lady had done him the supreme honor of avowing 
her attachment, of pledging her unalterable fidelity; should he 
suffer his devotion to be outdone?  But his purpose in writing to 
her, he admitted, was not merely to reiterate his fidelity; he was 
trying by every means in his power to induce her to sell the 
picture.  He had organized a plan of action; every detail was 
complete; if she would but have the courage to carry out his 
instructions he would answer for the result.  His idea was that she 
should secretly retire to a convent of which his aunt was the 
Mother Superior, and from that stronghold should transact the sale 
of the Leonardo.  He had a purchaser ready, who was willing to pay 
a large sum; a sum, Count Ottaviano whispered, considerably in 
excess of the young lady's original inheritance; once the picture 
sold, it could, if necessary, be removed by force from Doctor Lom-<pb n="155"/> bard's house, and his daughter, being safely in the convent, 
would be spared the painful scenes incidental to the removal. 
Finally, if Doctor Lombard were vindictive enough to refuse his 
consent to her marriage, she had only to make a <hi rend="italic"> sommation 
respectueuse</hi>, and at the end of the prescribed delay no power on 
earth could prevent her becoming the wife of Count Ottaviano. 
</p><p>Wyant's anger had fallen at the recital of this simple 
romance.  It was absurd to be angry with a young man who confided 
his secrets to the first stranger he met in the streets, and placed 
his hand on his heart whenever he mentioned the name of his 
betrothed.  The easiest way out of the business was to take it as 
a joke.  Wyant had played the wall to this new Pyramus and Thisbe, 
and was philosophic enough to laugh at the part he had unwittingly 
performed. 
</p><p>He held out his hand with a smile to Count Ottaviano. 
</p><p>"I won't deprive you any longer," he said, "of the pleasure of 
reading your letter." 
</p><p>"Oh, sir, a thousand thanks!  And when you return to the casa 
Lombard, you will take a message from me &mdash; the letter she expected 
this afternoon?" 
</p><p>"The letter she expected?"  Wyant paused.  "No, thank you.  I 
thought you understood that where I come from we don't do that kind 
of thing &mdash; knowingly." 
</p><p>"But, sir, to serve a young lady!" 
</p><p>"I'm sorry for the young lady, if what you tell me is true" &mdash; 
the Count's expressive hands resented the doubt &mdash; "but remember that 
if I am under obligations to any one in this matter, it is to her 
father, who has admitted me to his house and has allowed me to see 
his picture." 
</p><p><hi rend="italic">" His</hi> picture?  Hers!" 
</p><p>"Well, the house is his, at all events." 
</p><p>"Unhappily &mdash; since to her it is a dungeon!" 
</p><p>"Why doesn't she leave it, then?" exclaimed Wyant impatiently. 
</p><p>The Count clasped his hands.  "Ah, how you say that &mdash; with what 
force, with what virility!  If you would but say it to <hi rend="italic"> her</hi> in 
that tone &mdash; you, her countryman!  She has no one to advise her; the 
mother is an idiot; the father is terrible; she is in his power; it 
is my belief that he would kill her if she resisted him.  Mr. 
Wyant, I tremble for her life while she remains in that house!" 
</p><p>"Oh, come," said Wyant lightly, "they seem to understand each 
other well enough.  But in any case, you must see that I can't 
interfere &mdash; at least you would if you were an Englishman," he added 
with an escape of contempt. 
</p> 
</div1> 
<div1 type="chapter" n="3" id="d5"> 
<head>III 
</head> 
<p>Wyant's affiliations in Siena being restricted to an 
acquaintance with his land-lady, he was forced to apply to her for 
the verification of Count Ottaviano's story. 
</p><p>The young nobleman had, it appeared, given a perfectly correct 
account of his situation.  His father, Count Celsi-Mongirone, was 
a man of distinguished family and some wealth.  He was syndic of 
Orvieto, and lived either in that town or on his neighboring estate 
of Mongirone.  His wife owned a large property near Siena, and 
Count Ottaviano, who was the second son, came there from time to 
time to look into its management.  The eldest son was in the army, 
the youngest in the Church; and an aunt of Count Ottaviano's was 
Mother Superior of the Visitandine convent in Siena.  At one time 
it had been said that Count Ottaviano, who was a most amiable and 
accomplished young man, was to marry the daughter of the strange 
Englishman, Doctor Lombard, but difficulties having arisen as to 
the adjustment of the young lady's dower, Count Celsi-Mongirone had 
very properly broken off the match.  It was sad for the young man, 
however, who was said to be deeply in love, and to find frequent 
excuses for coming to Siena to inspect his mother's estate. <pb n="156"/>  
</p><p>Viewed in the light of Count Ottaviano's personality the story 
had a tinge of opera bouffe; but the next morning, as Wyant mounted 
the stairs of the House of the Dead Hand, the situation insensibly 
assumed another aspect.  It was impossible to take Doctor Lombard 
lightly; and there was a suggestion of fatality in the appearance 
of his gaunt dwelling.  Who could tell amid what tragic records of 
domestic tyranny and fluttering broken purposes the little drama of 
Miss Lombard's fate was being played out?  Might not the 
accumulated influences of such a house modify the lives within it 
in a manner unguessed by the inmates of a suburban villa with 
sanitary plumbing and a telephone? 
</p><p>One person, at least, remained unperturbed by such fanciful 
problems; and that was Mrs. Lombard, who, at Wyant's entrance, 
raised a placidly wrinkled brow from her knitting.  The morning was 
mild, and her chair had been wheeled into a bar of sunshine near 
the window, so that she made a cheerful spot of prose in the poetic 
gloom of her surroundings. 
</p><p>"What a nice morning!" she said; "it must be delightful 
weather at Bonchurch." 
</p><p>Her dull blue glance wandered across the narrow street with 
its threatening house fronts, and fluttered back baffled, like a 
bird with clipped wings.  It was evident, poor lady, that she had 
never seen beyond the opposite houses. 
</p><p>Wyant was not sorry to find her alone.  Seeing that she was 
surprised at his reappearance he said at once: "I have come back to 
study Miss Lombard's picture." 
</p><p>"Oh, the picture &mdash; "  Mrs. Lombard's face expressed a gentle 
disappointment, which might have been boredom in a person of acuter 
sensibilities.  "It's an original Leonardo, you know," she said 
mechanically. 
</p><p>"And Miss Lombard is very proud of it, I suppose?  She seems 
to have inherited her father's love for art." 
</p><p>Mrs. Lombard counted her stitches, and he went on: "It's 
unusual in so young a girl.  Such tastes generally develop later." 
</p><p>Mrs. Lombard looked up eagerly.  "That's what I say!  I was 
quite different at her age, you know.  I liked dancing, and doing 
a pretty bit of fancy-work.  Not that I couldn't sketch, too; I had 
a master down from London.  My aunts have some of my crayons hung 
up in their drawing-room now &mdash; I did a view of Kenilworth which was 
thought pleasing.  But I liked a picnic, too, or a pretty walk 
through the woods with young people of my own age.  I say it's more 
natural, Mr. Wyant; one may have a feeling for art, and do crayons 
that are worth framing, and yet not give up everything else.  I was 
taught that there were other things." 
</p><p>Wyant, half-ashamed of provoking these innocent confidences, 
could not resist another question.  "And Miss Lombard cares for 
nothing else?" 
</p><p>Her mother looked troubled. 
</p><p>"Sybilla is so clever &mdash; she says I don't understand.  You know 
how self-confident young people are!  My husband never said that of 
me, now &mdash; he knows I had an excellent education.  My aunts were very 
particular; I was brought up to have opinions, and my husband has 
always respected them.  He says himself that he wouldn't for the 
world miss hearing my opinion on any subject; you may have noticed 
that he often refers to my tastes.  He has always respected my 
preference for living in England; he likes to hear me give my 
reasons for it.  He is so much interested in my ideas that he often 
says he knows just what I am going to say before I speak.  But 
Sybilla does not care for what I think &mdash; " 
</p><p>At this point Doctor Lombard entered.  He glanced sharply at 
Wyant.  "The servant is a fool; she didn't tell me you were here." 
His eye turned to his wife.  "Well, my dear, what have you been 
telling Mr. Wyant?  About the aunts at Bonchurch, I'll be bound!" 
</p><p>Mrs. Lombard looked triumphantly at Wyant, and her husband 
rubbed his hooked fingers, with a smile.  <pb n="157"/>  
</p><p>"Mrs. Lombard's aunts are very superior women.  They subscribe 
to the circulating library, and borrow <hi rend="italic"> Good Words</hi> and the 
<hi rend="italic">Monthly Packet</hi> from the curate's wife across the way.  They have 
the rector to tea twice a year, and keep a page-boy, and are 
visited by two baronets' wives.  They devoted themselves to the 
education of their orphan niece, and I think I may say without 
boasting that Mrs. Lombard's conversation shows marked traces of 
the advantages she enjoyed." 
</p><p>Mrs. Lombard colored with pleasure. 
</p><p>"I was telling Mr. Wyant that my aunts were very particular." 
</p><p>"Quite so, my dear; and did you mention that they never sleep 
in anything but linen, and that Miss Sophia puts away the furs and 
blankets every spring with her own hands?  Both those facts are 
interesting to the student of human nature."  Doctor Lombard 
glanced at his watch.  "But we are missing an incomparable moment; 
the light is perfect at this hour." 
</p><p>Wyant rose, and the doctor led him through the tapestried door 
and down the passageway. 
</p><p>The light was, in fact, perfect, and the picture shone with an 
inner radiancy, as though a lamp burned behind the soft screen of 
the lady's flesh.  Every detail of the foreground detached itself 
with jewel-like precision.  Wyant noticed a dozen accessories which 
had escaped him on the previous day. 
</p><p>He drew out his note-book, and the doctor, who had dropped his 
sardonic grin for a look of devout contemplation, pushed a chair 
forward, and seated himself on a carved settle against the wall. 
</p><p>"Now, then," he said, "tell Clyde what you can; but the letter 
killeth." 
</p><p>He sank down, his hands hanging on the arm of the settle like 
the claws of a dead bird, his eyes fixed on Wyant's notebook with 
the obvious intention of detecting any attempt at a surreptitious 
sketch. 
</p><p>Wyant, nettled at this surveillance, and disturbed by the 
speculations which Doctor Lombard's strange household excited, sat 
motionless for a few minutes, staring first at the picture and then 
at the blank pages of the note-book.  The thought that Doctor 
Lombard was enjoying his discomfiture at length roused him, and he 
began to write. 
</p><p>He was interrupted by a knock on the iron door.  Doctor 
Lombard rose to unlock it, and his daughter entered. 
</p><p>She bowed hurriedly to Wyant, without looking at him. 
</p><p>"Father, had you forgotten that the man from Monte Amiato was 
to come back this morning with an answer about the bas-relief?  He 
is here now; he says he can't wait." 
</p><p>"The devil!" cried her father impatiently.  "Didn't you tell 
him &mdash; " 
</p><p>"Yes; but he says he can't come back.  If you want to see him 
you must come now." 
</p><p>"Then you think there's a chance? &mdash; " 
</p><p>She nodded. 
</p><p>He turned and looked at Wyant, who was writing assiduously. 
</p><p>"You will stay here, Sybilla; I shall be back in a moment." 
</p><p>He hurried out, locking the door behind him. 
</p><p>Wyant had looked up, wondering if Miss Lombard would show any 
surprise at being locked in with him; but it was his turn to be 
surprised, for hardly had they heard the key withdrawn when she 
moved close to him, her small face pale and tumultuous. 
</p><p>"I arranged it &mdash; I must speak to you," she gasped.  "He'll be 
back in five minutes." 
</p><p>Her courage seemed to fail, and she looked at him helplessly. 
</p><p>Wyant had a sense of stepping among explosives.  He glanced 
about him at the dusky vaulted room, at the haunting smile of the 
strange picture overhead, and at the pink-and-white girl whispering 
of conspiracies in a voice meant to exchange platitudes with a 
curate. 
</p><p>"How can I help you?" he said with a rush of compassion. 
</p><p>"Oh, if you would!  I never have a chance to speak to any one; 
it's so difficult<pb n="158"/>  &mdash; he watches me &mdash; he'll be back 
immediately." 
</p><p>"Try to tell me what I can do." 
</p><p>"I don't dare; I feel as if he were behind me."  She turned 
away, fixing her eyes on the picture.  A sound startled her. 
"There he comes, and I haven't spoken!  It was my only chance; but 
it bewilders me so to be hurried." 
</p><p>"I don't hear any one," said Wyant, listening.  "Try to tell 
me." 
</p><p>"How can I make you understand?  It would take so long to 
explain."  She drew a deep breath, and then with a plunge &mdash; "Will 
you come here again this afternoon &mdash; at about five?" she whispered. 
</p><p>"Come here again?" 
</p><p>"Yes &mdash; you can ask to see the picture, &mdash; make some excuse.  He 
will come with you, of course; I will open the door for you &mdash; and &mdash; 
and lock you both in" &mdash; she gasped. 
</p><p>"Lock us in?" 
</p><p>"You see?  You understand?  It's the only way for me to leave 
the house &mdash; if I am ever to do it" &mdash;   She drew another difficult 
breath.  "The key will be returned &mdash; by a safe person &mdash; in half an 
hour, &mdash; perhaps sooner &mdash; " 
</p><p>She trembled so much that she was obliged to lean against the 
settle for support. 
</p><p>"Wyant looked at her steadily; he was very sorry for her. 
</p><p>"I can't, Miss Lombard," he said at length. 
</p><p>"You can't?" 
</p><p>"I'm sorry; I must seem cruel; but consider &mdash; " 
</p><p>He was stopped by the futility of the word: as well ask a 
hunted rabbit to pause in its dash for a hole! 
</p><p>Wyant took her hand; it was cold and nerveless. 
</p><p>"I will serve you in any way I can; but you must see that this 
way is impossible.  Can't I talk to you again?  Perhaps &mdash; " 
</p><p>"Oh," she cried, starting up, "there he comes!" 
</p><p>Doctor Lombard's step sounded in the passage. 
</p><p>Wyant held her fast.  "Tell me one thing: he won't let you 
sell the picture?" 
</p><p>"No &mdash; hush!" 
</p><p>"Make no pledges for the future, then; promise me that." 
</p><p>"The future?" 
</p><p>"In case he should die: your father is an old man.  You 
haven't promised?" 
</p><p>She shook her head. 
</p><p>"Don't, then; remember that." 
</p><p>She made no answer, and the key turned in the lock. 
</p><p>As he passed out of the house, its scowling cornice and facade 
of ravaged brick looked down on him with the startlingness of a 
strange face, seen momentarily in a crowd, and impressing itself on 
the brain as part of an inevitable future.  Above the doorway, the 
marble hand reached out like the cry of an imprisoned anguish. 
</p><p>Wyant turned away impatiently. 
</p><p>"Rubbish!" he said to himself.  <hi rend="italic">" She</hi> isn't walled in; she 
can get out if she wants to." 
</p> 
</div1> 
<div1 type="chapter" n="4" id="d6">                           
<head>IV 
</head> 
<p>Wyant had any number of plans for coming to Miss Lombard's 
aid: he was elaborating the twentieth when, on the same afternoon, 
he stepped into the express train for Florence.  By the time the 
train reached Certaldo he was convinced that, in thus hastening his 
departure, he had followed the only reasonable course; at Empoli, 
he began to reflect that the priest and the Levite had probably 
justified themselves in much the same manner. 
</p><p>A month later, after his return to England, he was 
unexpectedly relieved from these alternatives of extenuation and 
approval.  A paragraph in the morning paper announced the sudden 
death of Doctor Lombard, the distinguished English dilettante who 
had long resided in Siena.  Wyant's justification was complete. 
Our blindest impulses become evidence of perspicacity when they 
fall in with the course of events. 
</p><p>Wyant could now comfortably speculate<pb n="159"/>  on the 
particular complications from which his foresight had probably 
saved him.  The climax was unexpectedly dramatic.  Miss Lombard, on 
the brink of a step which, whatever its issue, would have burdened 
her with retrospective compunction, had been set free before her 
suitor's ardor could have had time to cool, and was now doubtless 
planning a life of domestic felicity on the proceeds of the 
Leonardo.  One thing, however, struck Wyant as odd &mdash; he saw no 
mention of the sale of the picture.  He had scanned the papers for 
an immediate announcement of its transfer to one of the great 
museums; but presently concluding that Miss Lombard, out of filial 
piety, had wished to avoid an appearance of unseemly haste in the 
disposal of her treasure, he dismissed the matter from his mind. 
Other affairs happened to engage him; the months slipped by, and 
gradually the lady and the picture dwelt less vividly in his mind. 
</p><p>It was not till five or six years later, when chance took him 
again to Siena, that the recollection started from some inner fold 
of memory.  He found himself, as it happened, at the head of Doctor 
Lombard's street, and glancing down that grim thoroughfare, caught 
an oblique glimpse of the doctor's house front, with the Dead Hand 
projecting above its threshold. 
</p><p>The sight revived his interest, and that evening, over an 
admirable <hi rend="italic"> frittata</hi>, he questioned his landlady about Miss 
Lombard's marriage. 
</p><p>"The daughter of the English doctor?  But she has never 
married, signore." 
</p><p>"Never married?  What, then, became of Count Ottaviano?" 
</p><p>"For a long time he waited; but last year he married a noble 
lady of the Maremma." 
</p><p>"But what happened &mdash; why was the marriage broken?" 
</p><p>The landlady enacted a pantomime of baffled interrogation. 
</p><p>"And Miss Lombard still lives in her father's house?" 
</p><p>"Yes, signore; she is still there." 
</p><p>"And the Leonardo &mdash; " 
</p><p>"The Leonardo, also, is still there." 
</p><p>The next day, as Wyant entered the House of the Dead Hand, he 
remembered Count Ottaviano's injunction to ring twice, and smiled 
mournfully to think that so much subtlety had been vain.  But what 
could have prevented the marriage?  If Doctor Lombard's death had 
been long delayed, time might have acted as a dissolvent, or the 
young lady's resolve have failed; but it seemed impossible that the 
white heat of ardor in which Wyant had left the lovers should have 
cooled in a few short weeks. 
</p><p>As he ascended the vaulted stairway the atmosphere of the 
place seemed a reply to his conjectures.  The same numbing air fell 
on him, like an emanation from some persistent will-power, a 
something fierce and imminent which might reduce to impotence every 
impulse within its range.  Wyant could almost fancy a hand on his 
shoulder, guiding him upward with the ironical intent of 
confronting him with the evidence of its work. 
</p><p>A strange servant opened the door, and he was presently 
introduced to the tapestried room, where, from their usual seats in 
the window, Mrs. Lombard and her daughter advanced to welcome him 
with faint ejaculations of surprise. 
</p><p>Both had grown oddly old, but in a dry, smooth way, as fruits 
might shrivel on a shelf instead of ripening on the tree.  Mrs. 
Lombard was still knitting, and pausing now and then to warm her 
swollen hands above the brazier; and Miss Lombard, in rising, had 
laid aside a strip of needle-work which might have been the same on 
which Wyant had first seen her engaged. 
</p><p>Their visitor inquired discreetly how they had fared in the 
interval, and learned that they had thought of returning to 
England, but had somehow never done so. 
</p><p>"I am sorry not to see my aunts again," Mrs. Lombard said 
resignedly; "but Sybilla thinks it best that we should not go this 
year." 
</p><p>"Next year, perhaps," murmured Miss <pb n="160"/>  Lombard, in a 
voice which seemed to suggest that they had a great waste of time 
to fill. 
</p><p>She had returned to her seat, and sat bending over her work. 
Her hair enveloped her head in the same thick braids, but the rose 
color of her cheeks had turned to blotches of dull red, like some 
pigment which has darkened in drying. 
</p><p>"And Professor Clyde &mdash; is he well?" Mrs. Lombard asked affably; 
continuing, as her daughter raised a startled eye: "Surely, 
Sybilla, Mr. Wyant was the gentleman who was sent by Professor 
Clyde to see the Leonardo?" 
</p><p>Miss Lombard was silent, but Wyant hastened to assure the 
elder lady of his friend's well-being. 
</p><p>"Ah &mdash; perhaps, then, he will come back some day to Siena," she 
said, sighing.  Wyant declared that it was more than likely; and 
there ensued a pause, which he presently broke by saying to Miss 
Lombard: "And you still have the picture?" 
</p><p>She raised her eyes and looked at him.  "Should you like to 
see it?" she asked. 
</p><p>On his assenting, she rose, and extracting the same key from 
the same secret drawer, unlocked the door beneath the tapestry. 
They walked down the passage in silence, and she stood aside with 
a grave gesture, making Wyant pass before her into the room.  Then 
she crossed over and drew the curtain back from the picture. 
</p><p>The light of the early afternoon poured full on it: its 
surface appeared to ripple and heave with a fluid splendor.  The 
colors had lost none of their warmth, the outlines none of their 
pure precision; it seemed to Wyant like some magical flower which 
had burst suddenly from the mould of darkness and oblivion. 
</p><p>He turned to Miss Lombard with a movement of comprehension. 
</p><p>"Ah, I understand &mdash; you couldn't part with it, after all!" he 
cried. 
</p><p>"No &mdash; I couldn't part with it," she answered. 
</p><p>"It's too beautiful, &mdash; too beautiful," &mdash; he assented. 
</p><p>"Too beautiful?"  She turned on him with a curious stare.  "I 
have never thought it beautiful, you know." 
</p><p>He gave back the stare.  "You have never &mdash; " 
</p><p>She shook her head.  "It's not that.  I hate it; I've always 
hated it.  But he wouldn't let me &mdash; he will never let me now." 
</p><p>Wyant was startled by her use of the present tense.  Her look 
surprised him, too: there was a strange fixity of resentment in her 
innocuous eye.  Was it possible that she was laboring under some 
delusion?  Or did the pronoun not refer to her father? 
</p><p>"You mean that Doctor Lombard did not wish you to part with 
the picture?" 
</p><p>"No &mdash; he prevented me; he will always prevent me." 
</p><p>There was another pause.  "You promised him, then, before his 
death &mdash; " 
</p><p>"No; I promised nothing.  He died too suddenly to make me." 
Her voice sank to a whisper.  "I was free &mdash; perfectly free &mdash; or I 
thought I was till I tried." 
</p><p>"Till you tried?" 
</p><p>"To disobey him &mdash; to sell the picture.  Then I found it was 
impossible.  I tried again and again; but he was always in the room 
with me." 
</p><p>She glanced over her shoulder as though she had heard a step; 
and to Wyant, too, for a moment, the room seemed full of a third 
presence. 
</p><p>"And you can't" &mdash; he faltered, unconsciously dropping his voice 
to the pitch of hers. 
</p><p>She shook her head, gazing at him mystically.  "I can't lock 
him out; I can never lock him out now.  I told you I should never 
have another chance." 
</p><p>Wyant felt the chill of her words like a cold breath in his 
hair. 
</p><p>"Oh" &mdash; he groaned; but she cut him off with a grave gesture. 
</p><p>"It is too late," she said; "but you ought to have helped me 
that day." 
</p> 
 
</div1> 
</body> 
</text> 
</TEI.2> 
 
