<?xml version="1.0"?>

<?dlps id="WhaFull"?>
<?dlps page-images="none" figure-images="no"?>
<?dlps transcription="other"?>

<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/tei-p4/tei2.dtd" [
<!ENTITY % POSTKB "INCLUDE">
<!ENTITY % TEI.extensions.ent SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.ent">
<!ENTITY % TEI.extensions.dtd SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.dtd">
<!ENTITY % ISOnum SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/charent/iso-num.ent"> %ISOnum;
<!ENTITY % ISOpub SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/charent/iso-pub.ent"> %ISOpub;

]>

<TEI.2 id="WhaFull"> 
<teiHeader type="migrated" creator="Etext">
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title type="main">Full Circle</title>
<title type="sort">full circle</title>
<author>Wharton, Edith, 1862-1937</author>
<respStmt>
<resp>Creation of machine-readable version:</resp>
<name>Judy Boss</name>
</respStmt>
<respStmt>
<resp>Conversion to TEI-conformant markup:</resp>
<name>University of Virginia Library Electronic Text Center</name>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt> 
<extent>ca. <num type="kilobytes">55</num> kilobytes</extent> 
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>University of Virginia Library</publisher>
<pubPlace>Charlottesville, Virginia</pubPlace>
<idno type="ETC">WhaFull</idno> 
<date value="1995">1995</date>
<availability status="public">
<p n="copyright">Copyright &copy; 1995 by the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia</p>
<p n="access">Publicly accessible</p>
</availability>
<idno type="uva-pid">uva-lib:476493</idno>
</publicationStmt>
<seriesStmt>
<title>University of Virginia Library, Text collection</title>
<idno type="uva-set">UVA-LIB-Text</idno>
</seriesStmt> 
<sourceDesc>
<biblFull>
<titleStmt>
<title type="main">Full Circle</title>
<title type="sort">full circle</title>
<author>Wharton, Edith</author>
</titleStmt> 
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>Scribner's Magazine</publisher>
<date value="1909-10">Oct. 1909</date>
</publicationStmt> 
<notesStmt>
<note>
<p>Vol. 46</p>
</note>
</notesStmt>
</biblFull>
</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc> 
<encodingDesc>
<projectDesc>
<p>Prepared for the University of Virginia Library Electronic Text Center</p>
</projectDesc> 
<editorialDecl>
<p>All quotation marks retained as data</p> 
<p>Verification made against printed text</p> 
<p id="ETC">Keywords in the header are a local Electronic Text Center scheme  
to aid in establishing analytical groupings</p>
</editorialDecl> 
<refsDecl>
<p>ID elements are given for each page element and are composed of the text's 
unique cryptogram and the given page number, as in SpeFQue1 for page one of  
Spenser's Faerie Queene.</p>
</refsDecl>
</encodingDesc> 
<profileDesc>
<creation>
<date value="1909">1909</date>
</creation> 
<langUsage>
<language id="eng" usage="main">English</language>
</langUsage> 
<textClass>
<keywords>
<term>fiction</term>
<term>prose</term>
</keywords>
</textClass>
</profileDesc> 
<revisionDesc>
<change>
<date value="1995-01">January 1995</date> 
<respStmt>
<resp>corrector</resp>
<name>David Seaman and Kelly Tetterton</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Header and basic TEI SGML encoding added</item>
</change> 
<change>
<date value="2005-07">July 2005</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>Corrector</resp>
<name>Margaret Konkol</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Converted SGML to XML and fixed tagging.</item>
</change>
<change>
<date value="2007-09">September 2007</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>Migration</resp>
<name>Ethan Gruber, University of Virginia Library</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Converted XML markup from TEI Lite to uva-dl-tei (TEI P4 with local customizations).</item>
</change>
<change>
<date value="2008-01">January 2008</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>Migration</resp>
<name>Greg Murray, University of Virginia Library</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Programmatically updated TEI header markup (but not header content) for minimal compliance with current QA requirements.</item>
</change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader> 
<text id="d1">  
<body id="d2"> 
<div1 type="story" id="d3"> 
<head> 
                 <hi rend="italic"> TALES OF MEN</hi> 
<lb/> 
Wharton, Edith.  "Full Circle."   
<lb/> 
<hi rend="italic"> Scribner's Magazine</hi> 46 (Oct. 1909): 408-419. 
</head> 
<pb n="408"/>  
<div2 type="section" n="1" id="d4"> 

<head>                            I 
</head> 
<p> 
GEOFFREY BETTON woke rather late&mdash;so late that the winter sunlight 
sliding across his warm red carpet struck his eyes as he turned on 
the pillow. 
</p><p>Strett, the valet, had been in, drawn the bath in the 
adjoining dressing-room, placed the crystal and silver cigarette-box at his side, put a match to the fire, and thrown open the 
windows to the bright morning air.  It brought in, on the glitter 
of sun, all the shrill crisp morning noises&mdash;those piercing notes 
of the American thoroughfare that seem to take a sharper vibration 
from the clearness of the medium through which they pass. 
</p><p>Betton raised himself languidly.  That was the voice of Fifth 
Avenue below his windows.  He remembered that when he moved into 
his rooms eighteen months before, the sound had been like music to 
him: the complex orchestration to which the tune of his new life 
was set.  Now it filled him with horror and weariness, since it had 
become the symbol of the hurry and noise of that new life.  He had 
been far less hurried in the old days when he had to be up by 
seven, and down at the office sharp at nine.  Now that he got up 
when he chose, and his life had no fixed framework of duties, the 
hours hunted him like a pack of blood-hounds. 
</p><p>He dropped back on his pillows with a groan.  Yes&mdash;not a year 
ago there had been a positively sensuous joy in getting out of bed, 
feeling under his bare feet the softness of the sunlit carpet, and 
entering the shining tiled sanctuary where his great porcelain bath 
proffered its renovating flood.  But then a year ago he could still 
call up the horror of the communal plunge at his earlier lodgings: 
the listening for other bathers, the dodging of shrouded ladies in 
"crimping"-pins, the cold wait on the landing, the reluctant 
descent into a blotchy tin bath, and the effort to identify one's 
soap and nail-brush among the promiscuous <pb n="409"/>  implements of 
ablution.  That memory had faded now, and Betton saw only the dark 
hours to which his blue and white temple of refreshment formed a 
kind of glittering antechamber.  For after his bath came his 
breakfast, and on the breakfast-tray his letters.  His letters! 
</p><p>He remembered&mdash;and <hi rend="italic"> that</hi> memory had not faded!&mdash;the thrill 
with which he had opened the first missive in a strange feminine 
hand: the letter beginning: "I wonder if you'll mind an unknown 
reader's telling you all that your book has been to her?" 
</p><p><hi rend="italic"> Mind?</hi>  Ye gods, he minded now!  For more than a year after 
the publication of "Diadems and Faggots" the letters, the inane 
indiscriminate letters of condemnation, of criticism, of 
interrogation, had poured in on him by every post.  Hundreds of 
unknown readers had told him with unsparing detail all that his 
book had been to them.  And the wonder of it was, when all was said 
and done, that it had really been so little&mdash;that when their thick 
broth of praise was strained through the author's anxious vanity 
there remained to him so small a sediment of definite specific 
understanding!  No&mdash;it was always the same thing, over and over and 
over again&mdash;the same vague gush of adjectives, the same 
incorrigible tendency to estimate his effort according to each 
writer's personal preferences, instead of regarding it as a work of 
art, a thing to be measured by objective standards! 
</p><p>He smiled to think how little, at first, he had felt the 
vanity of it all.  He had found a savour even in the grosser 
evidences of popularity: the advertisements of his book, the daily 
shower of "clippings," the sense that, when he entered a restaurant 
or a theatre, people nudged each other and said "That's Betton."  
Yes, the publicity had been sweet to him&mdash;at first.  He had been 
touched by the sympathy of his fellow-men: had thought indulgently 
of the world, as a better place than the failures and the 
dyspeptics would acknowledge.  And then his success began to 
submerge him: he gasped under the thickening shower of letters.  
His admirers were really unappeasable.  And they wanted him to do 
such preposterous things&mdash;to give lectures, to head movements, to 
be tendered receptions, to speak at banquets, to address mothers, 
to plead for orphans, to go up in balloons, to lead the struggle 
for sterilized milk.  They wanted his photograph for literary 
supplements, his autograph for charity bazaars, his name on 
committees, literary, educational, and social; above all, they 
wanted his opinion on everything: on Christianity, Buddhism, tight 
lacing, the drug-habit, democratic government, female suffrage and 
love.  Perhaps the chief benefit of this demand was his 
incidentally learning from it how few opinions he really had: the 
only one that remained with him was a rooted horror of all forms of 
correspondence.  He had been unutterably thankful when the letters 
began to fall off. 
</p><p>"Diadems and Faggots" was now two years old, and the moment 
was at hand when its author might have counted on regaining the 
blessed shelter of oblivion&mdash;if only he had not written another 
book!  For it was the worst part of his plight that his first 
success had goaded him to the perpetration of this particular 
folly&mdash;that one of the incentives (hideous thought!) to his new 
work had been the desire to extend and perpetuate his popularity.  
And this very week the book was to come out, and the letters, the 
cursed letters, would begin again! 
</p><p>Wistfully, almost plaintively, he contemplated the breakfast-tray with which Strett presently appeared.  It bore only two notes 
and the morning journals, but he knew that within the week it would 
groan under its epistolary burden.  The very newspapers flung the 
fact at him as he opened them. 

</p><p>                    READY ON MONDAY. 

</p><p>               GEOFFREY BETTON'S NEW NOVEL 

</p><p>                       ABUNDANCE. 

</p><p>          BY THE AUTHOR OF DIADEMS AND FAGGOTS 

</p><p>              FIRST EDITION OF ONE HUNDRED AND 
</p><p>            FIFTY THOUSAND ALREADY SOLD OUT. 

</p><p>                       ORDER NOW. 

</p><p>A hundred and fifty thousand volumes!  And an average of three 
readers to each!  Half a million of people would be reading him 
within a week, and every one of them would write to him, and their 
friends and relations would write too.  He laid down the paper with 
a shudder. 
</p><p>The two notes looked harmless enough, and the calligraphy of 
one was vaguely <pb n="410"/>  familiar.  He opened the envelope and 
looked at the signature: <hi rend="italic"> Duncan Vyse</hi>.  He had not seen the name 
in years&mdash;what on earth could Duncan Vyse have to say?  He ran over 
the page and dropped it with a wondering exclamation, which the 
watchful Strett, re-entering, met by a tentative "Yes, sir?" 
</p><p>"Nothing.  Yes&mdash;that is&mdash;"  Betton picked up the note.  
"There's a gentleman, a Mr. Vyse, coming to see me at ten." 
</p><p>Strett glanced at the clock.  "Yes, sir.  You'll remember that 
ten was the hour you appointed for the secretaries to call, sir." 
</p><p>Betton nodded.  "I'll see Mr. Vyse first.  My clothes, 
please." 
</p><p>As he got into them, in the state of irritable hurry that had 
become almost chronic with him, he continued to think about Duncan 
Vyse.  They had seen a lot of each other for the few years after 
both had left Harvard: the hard happy years when Betton had been 
grinding at his business and Vyse&mdash;poor devil!&mdash;trying to write.  
The novelist recalled his friend's attempts with a smile; then the 
memory of one small volume came back to him.  It was a novel: "The 
Lifted Lamp."  There was stuff in that, certainly.  He remembered 
Vyse's tossing it down on his table with a gesture of despair when 
it came back from the last publisher.  Betton, taking it up 
indifferently, had sat riveted till daylight.  When he ended, the 
impression was so strong that he said to himself: "I'll tell 
Apthorn about it&mdash;I'll go and see him to-morrow."  His own secret 
literary yearnings gave him a passionate desire to champion Vyse, 
to see him triumph over the ignorance and timidity of the 
publishers.  Apthorn was the youngest of the guild, still capable 
of opinions and the courage of them, a personal friend of Betton's, 
and, as it happened, the man afterward to become known as the 
privileged publisher of "Diadems and Faggots."  Unluckily the next 
day something unexpected turned up, and Betton forgot about Vyse 
and his manuscript.  He continued to forget for a month, and then 
came a note from Vyse, who was ill, and wrote to ask what his 
friend had done.  Betton did not like to say "I've done nothing," 
so he left the note unanswered, and vowed again: "I'll see 
Apthorn." 

</p><p>The following day he was called to the West on business, and 
was gone a month.  When he came back, there was another note from 
Vyse, who was still ill, and desperately hard up.  "I'll take 
anything for the book, if they'll advance me two hundred dollars."  
Betton, full of compunction, would gladly have advanced the sum 
himself; but he was hard up too, and could only swear inwardly: 
"I'll write to Apthorn."  Then he glanced again at the manuscript, 
and reflected: "No&mdash;there are things in it that need explaining.  
I'd better see him." 
</p><p>Once he went so far as to telephone Apthorn, but the publisher 
was out.  Then he finally and completely forgot. 
</p><p>One Sunday he went out of town, and on his return, rummaging 
among the papers on his desk, he missed "The Lifted Lamp," which 
had been gathering dust there for half a year.  What the deuce 
could have become of it?  Betton spent a feverish hour in vainly 
increasing the disorder of his documents, and then bethought 
himself of calling the maid-servant, who first indignantly denied 
having touched anything ("I can see that's true from the dust," 
Betton scathingly interjected), and then mentioned with hauteur 
that a young lady had called in his absence and asked to be allowed 
to get a book. 
</p><p>"A lady?  Did you let her come up?" 
</p><p>"She said somebody'd sent her." 
</p><p>Vyse, of course&mdash;Vyse had sent her for his manuscript!  He was 
always mixed up with some woman, and it was just like him to send 
the girl of the moment to Betton's lodgings, with instructions to 
force the door in his absence.  Vyse had never been remarkable for 
delicacy.  Betton, furious, glanced over his table to see if any of 
his own effects were missing&mdash;one couldn't tell, with the company 
Vyse kept!&mdash;and then dismissed the matter from his mind, with a 
vague sense of magnanimity in doing so.  He felt himself exonerated 
by Vyse's conduct. 
</p><p>The sense of magnanimity was still uppermost when the valet 
opened the door to announce "Mr. Vyse," and Betton, a moment later, 
crossed the threshold of his pleasant library. 
</p><p>His first thought was that the man facing him from the hearth-rug was the very Duncan Vyse of old: small, starved, bleached-looking, with the same sidelong movements, the same queer air of 
anaemic truculence.  Only he had grown shabbier, and bald. <pb n="411"/>  
</p><p>Betton held out a hospitable hand. 
</p><p>"This is a good surprise!  Glad you looked me up, my dear 
fellow." 
</p><p>Vyse's palm was damp and bony: he had always had a 
disagreeable hand. 
</p><p>"You got my note?  You know what I've come for?" he said. 
</p><p>"About the secretaryship?  (Sit down.)  Is that really 
serious?" 
</p><p>Betton lowered himself luxuriously into one of his vast Maple 
arm-chairs.  He had grown stouter in the last year, and the cushion 
behind him fitted comfortably into the crease of his nape.  As he 
leaned back he caught sight of his image in the mirror between the 
windows, and reflected uneasily that Vyse would not find <hi rend="italic"> him</hi> 
unchanged. 
</p><p>"Serious?" Vyse rejoined.  "Why not?  Aren't <hi rend="italic"> you?"</hi> 
</p><p>"Oh, perfectly."  Betton laughed apologetically.  "Only&mdash;well, 
the fact is, you may not understand what rubbish a secretary of 
mine would have to deal with.  In advertising for one I never 
imagined&mdash;I didn't aspire to any one above the ordinary hack." 
</p><p>"I'm the ordinary hack," said Vyse drily. 
</p><p>Betton's affable gesture protested.  "My dear fellow&mdash;.  You 
see it's not business&mdash;what I'm in now," he continued with a laugh. 
</p><p>Vyse's thin lips seemed to form a noiseless <hi rend="italic">"Isn't</hi> it?" 
which they instantly transposed into the audibly reply: "I inferred 
from your advertisement that you want some one to relieve you in 
your literary work.  Dictation, short-hand&mdash;that kind of thing?" 
</p><p>"Well, no: not that either.  I type my own things.  What I'm 
looking for is somebody who won't be above tackling my 
correspondence." 
</p><p>Vyse looked slightly surprised.  "I should be glad of the 
job," he then said. 
</p><p>Betton began to feel a vague embarrassment.  He had supposed 
that such a proposal would be instantly rejected.  "It would be 
only for an hour or two a day&mdash;if you're doing any writing of your 
own?" he threw out interrogatively. 
</p><p>"No.  I've given all that up.  I'm in an office now&mdash;business.  
But it doesn't take all my time, or pay enough to keep me alive." 
</p><p>"In that case, my dear fellow&mdash;if you could come every 
morning; but it's mostly awful bosh, you know," Betton again broke 
off, with growing awkwardness. 
</p><p>Vyse glanced at him humorously.  "What you want me to write?" 
</p><p>"Well, that depends&mdash;"  Betton sketched the obligatory smile.  
"But I was thinking of the letters you'll have to answer.  Letters 
about my books, you know&mdash;I've another one appearing next week.  
And I want to be beforehand now&mdash;dam the flood before it swamps me.  
Have you any idea of the deluge of stuff that people write to a 
successful novelist?" 
</p><p>As Betton spoke, he saw a tinge of red on Vyse's thin cheek, 
and his own reflected it in a richer glow of shame.  "I mean&mdash;I 
mean&mdash;" he stammered helplessly. 
</p><p>"No, I haven't," said Vyse; "but it will be awfully jolly 
finding out." 
</p><p>There was a pause, groping and desperate on Betton's part, 
sardonically calm on his visitor's. 
</p><p>"You&mdash;you've given up writing altogether?" Betton continued. 
</p><p>"Yes; we've changed places, as it were."  Vyse paused.  "But 
about these letters&mdash;you dictate the answers?" 
</p><p>"Lord, no!  That's the reason why I said I wanted somebody&mdash; 
er&mdash;well used to writing.  I don't want to have anything to do with 
them&mdash;not a thing!  You'll have to answer them as if they were 
written to <hi rend="italic"> you</hi>&mdash;"  Betton pulled himself up again, and rising 
in confusion jerked open one of the drawers of his writing-table. 
</p><p>"Here&mdash;this kind of rubbish," he said, tossing a packet of 
letters onto Vyse's knee. 
</p><p>"Oh&mdash;you keep them, do you?" said Vyse simply. 
</p><p>"I&mdash;well&mdash;some of them; a few of the funniest only." 
</p><p>Vyse slipped off the band and began to open the letters.  
While he was glancing over them Betton again caught his own 
reflection in the glass, and asked himself what impression he had 
made on his visitor.  It occurred to him for the first time that 
his high-coloured well-fed person presented the image of commercial 
rather than of intellectual achievement.  He did not look like his 
own idea of the author of "Diadems and Faggots"&mdash;and he wondered 
why. 
</p><p>Vyse laid the letters aside.  "I think I can do it&mdash;if you'll 
give me a notion of the tone I'm to take." <pb n="412"/>  
</p><p>"The tone?" 
</p><p>"Yes&mdash;that is, if I'm to sign your name." 
</p><p>"Oh, of course: I expect you to sign for me.  As for the tone, 
say just what you'd&mdash;well, say all you can without encouraging them 
to answer." 
</p><p>Vyse rose from his seat.  "I could submit a few specimens," he 
suggested. 
</p><p>"Oh, as to that&mdash;you always wrote better than I do," said 
Betton handsomely. 
</p><p>"I've never had this kind of thing to write.  When do you wish 
me to begin?" Vyse enquired, ignoring the tribute. 
</p><p>"The book's out on Monday.  The deluge will begin about three 
days after.  Will you turn up on Thursday at this hour?"  Betton 
held his hand out with real heartiness.  "It was great luck for me, 
your striking that advertisement.  Don't be too harsh with my 
correspondents&mdash;I owe them something for having brought us 
together." 
</p> 
</div2> 
<div2 type="section" n="1" id="d5"> 
<head> 
                           II 
</head> 
<p>THE deluge began punctually on the Thursday, and Vyse, 
arriving as punctually, had an impressive pile of letters to 
attack.  Betton, on his way to the Park for a ride, came into the 
library, smoking the cigarette of indolence, to look over his 
secretary's shoulder. 
</p><p>"How many of 'em?  Twenty?  Good Lord!  It's going to be worse 
than 'Diadems.'  I've just had my first quiet breakfast in two 
years&mdash;time to read the papers and loaf.  How I used to dread the 
sight of my letter-box!  Now I sha'n't know I have one." 
</p><p>He leaned over Vyse's chair, and the secretary handed him a 
letter. 
</p><p>"Here's rather an exceptional one&mdash;lady, evidently.  I thought 
you might want to answer it yourself&mdash;" 
</p><p>"Exceptional?"  Betton ran over the mauve pages and tossed 
them down.  "Why, my dear man, I get hundreds like that.  You'll 
have to be pretty short with her, or she'll send her photograph." 
</p><p>He clapped Vyse on the shoulder and turned away, humming a 
tune.  "Stay to luncheon," he called back gaily from the threshold. 
</p><p>After luncheon Vyse insisted on showing a few of his answers 
to the first batch of letters.  "If I've struck the note I won't 
bother you again," he urged; and Betton groaningly consented. 
</p><p>"My dear fellow, they're beautiful&mdash;too beautiful.  I'll be 
let in for a correspondence with every one of these people." 
</p><p>Vyse, at this, meditated for a while above a blank sheet.  
"All right&mdash;how's this? he said, after another interval of rapid 
writing. 
</p><p>Betton glanced over the page.  "By George&mdash;by George!  Won't 
she <hi rend="italic"> see</hi> it?" he exulted, between fear and rapture. 
</p><p>"It's wonderful how little people see," said Vyse 
reassuringly. 

</p><p>The letters continued to pour in for several weeks after the 
appearance of "Abundance."  For five or six blissful days Betton 
did not even have his mail brought to him, trusting to Vyse to 
single out his personal correspondence, and to deal with the rest 
according to their agreement.  During those days he luxuriated in 
a sense of wild and lawless freedom; then, gradually, he began to 
feel the need of fresh restraints to break, and learned that the 
zest of liberty lies in the escape from specific obligations.  At 
first he was conscious only of a vague hunger, but in time the 
craving resolved into a shame-faced desire to see his letters. 
</p><p>"After all, I hated them only because I had to answer them"; 
and he told Vyse carelessly that he wished all his letters 
submitted to him before the secretary answered them. 
</p><p>At first he pushed aside those beginning: "I have just laid 
down 'Abundance' after a third reading," or: "Every day for the 
last month I have been telephoning my bookseller to know when your 
novel would be out."  But little by little the freshness of his 
interest revived, and even this stereotyped homage began to arrest 
his eye.  At last a day came when he read all the letters, from the 
first word to the last, as he had done when "Diadems and Faggots" 
appeared.  It was really a pleasure to read them, now that he was 
relieved of the burden of replying: his new relation to his 
correspondents had the glow of a love-affair unchilled by the 
contingency of marriage. 
</p><p>One day it struck him that the letters were coming in more 
slowly and in smaller numbers.  Certainly there had been more of a 
rush when "Diadems and Faggots" <pb n="413"/>  came out.  Betton began to 
wonder if Vyse were exercising an unauthorized discrimination, and 
keeping back the communications he deemed least important.  This 
sudden conjecture carried the novelist straight to his library, 
where he found Vyse bending over the writing-table with his usual 
inscrutable pale smile.  But once there, Betton hardly knew how to 
frame his question, and blundered into an enquiry for a missing 
invitation. 
</p><p>"There's a note&mdash;a personal note&mdash;I ought to have had this 
morning.  Sure you haven't kept it back by mistake among the 
others?" 
</p><p>Vyse laid down his pen.  "The others?  But I never keep back 
any." 
</p><p>Betton had foreseen the answer.  "Not even the worst twaddle 
about my book?" he suggested lightly, pushing the papers about. 
</p><p>"Nothing.  I understood you wanted to go over them all first." 
</p><p>"Well, perhaps it's safer," Betton conceded, as if the idea 
were new to him.  With an embarrassed hand he continued to turn 
over the letters at Vyse's elbow. 
</p><p>"Those are yesterday's," said the secretary; "here are to-day's," he added, pointing to a meagre trio. 
</p><p>"H'm&mdash;only these?"  Betton took them and looked them over 
lingeringly.  "I don't see what the deuce that chap means about the 
first part of 'Abundance' 'certainly justifying the title'&mdash;do 
you?" 
</p><p>Vyse was silent, and the novelist continued irritably: "Damned 
cheek, his writing, if he doesn't like the book.  Who cares what he 
thinks about it, anyhow?" 
</p><p>And his morning ride was embittered by the discovery that it 
was unexpectedly disagreeable to have Vyse read any letters which 
did not express unqualified praise of his books.  He began to fancy 
there was a latent rancour, a kind of baffled sneer, under Vyse's 
manner; and he decided to return to the practice of having his mail 
brought straight to his room.  In that way he could edit the 
letters before his secretary saw them. 
</p><p>Vyse made no comment on the change, and Betton was reduced to 
wondering whether his imperturbable composure were the mask of 
complete indifference or of a watchful jealousy.  The latter view 
being more agreeable to his employer's self-esteem, the next step 
was to conclude that Vyse had not forgotten the episode of "The 
Lifted Lamp," and would naturally take a vindictive joy in any 
unfavourable judgments passed on his rival's work.  This did not 
simplify the situation, for there was no denying that unfavourable 
criticisms preponderated in Betton's correspondence.  "Abundance" 
was neither meeting with the unrestricted welcome of "Diadems and 
Faggots," nor enjoying the alternative of an animated controversy: 
it was simply found dull, and its readers said so in language not 
too tactfully tempered by regretful comparisons with its 
predecessor.  To withhold unfavourable comments from Vyse was, 
therefore, to make it appear that correspondence about the book had 
died out; and its author, mindful of his unguarded predictions, 
found this even more embarrassing.  The simplest solution would be 
to get rid of Vyse; and to this end Betton began to address his 
energies. 
</p><p>One evening, finding himself unexpectedly disengaged, he asked 
Vyse to dine; it had occurred to him that, in the course of an 
after-dinner chat, he might delicately hint his feeling that the 
work he had offered his friend was unworthy so accomplished a hand. 
</p><p>Vyse surprised him by a momentary hesitation.  "I may not have 
time to dress." 
</p><p>Betton stared.  "What's the odds?  We'll dine here&mdash;and as 
late as you like." 
</p><p>Vyse thanked him, and appeared, punctually at eight, in all 
the shabbiness of his daily wear.  He looked paler and more shyly 
truculent than usual, and Betton, from the height of his florid 
stature, said to himself, with the sudden professional instinct for 
"type": "He might be an agent of something&mdash;a chap who carries 
deadly secrets." 
</p><p>Vyse, it was to appear, did carry a deadly secret; but one 
less perilous to society than to himself.  He was simply poor&mdash; 
inexcusably, irremediably poor.  Everything failed him, had always 
failed him: whatever he put his hand to went to bits. 
</p><p>This was the confession that, reluctantly, yet with a kind of 
white-lipped bravado, he flung at Betton in answer to the latter's 
tentative suggestion that, really, the letter-answering job wasn't 
worth bothering him with&mdash;a thing that any type-writer could do. 
</p><p>"If you mean you're paying me more <pb n="414"/>  than it's worth, 
I'll take less," Vyse rushed out after a pause. 
</p><p>"Oh, my dear fellow&mdash;" Betton protested, flushing. 
</p><p>"What <hi rend="italic"> do</hi> you mean, then?  Don't I answer the letters as 
you want them answered?" 
</p><p>Betton anxiously stroked his silken ankle.  "You do it 
beautifully, too beautifully.  I mean what I say: the work's not 
worthy of you.  I'm ashamed to ask you&mdash;" 
</p><p>"Oh, hang shame," Vyse interrupted.  "Do you know why I said 
I shouldn't have time to dress to-night?  Because I haven't any 
evening clothes.  As a matter of fact, I haven't much but the 
clothes I stand in.  One thing after another's gone against me; all 
the infernal ingenuities of chance.  It's been a slow Chinese 
torture, the kind where they keep you alive to have more fun 
killing you."  He straightened himself with a sudden blush.  "Oh, 
I'm all right now&mdash;getting on capitally.  But I'm still walking 
rather a narrow plank; and if I do your work well enough&mdash;if I take 
your idea&mdash;" 
</p><p>Betton stared into the fire without answering.  He knew next 
to nothing of Vyse's history, of the mischance or mis-management 
that had brought him, with his brains and his training, to so 
unlikely a pass.  But a pang of compunction shot through him as he 
remembered the manuscript of "The Lifted Lamp" gathering dust on 
his table for half a year. 
</p><p>"Not that it would have made any earthly difference&mdash;since 
he's evidently never been able to get the thing published."  But 
this reflection did not wholly console Betton, and he found it 
impossible, at the moment, to tell Vyse that his services were not 
needed. 
</p> 
</div2> 
<div2 type="section" n="3" id="d6"> 
<head>                           III 
</head> 

<p>DURING the ensuing weeks the letters grew fewer and fewer, and 
Betton foresaw the approach of the fatal day when his secretary, in 
common decency, would have to say: "I can't draw my pay for doing 
nothing." 
</p><p>What a triumph for Vyse! 
</p><p>The thought was intolerable, and Betton cursed his weakness in 
not having dismissed the fellow before such a possibility arose. 
</p><p>"If I tell him I've no use for him now, he'll see straight 
through it, of course;&mdash;and then, hang it, he looks so poor!" 
</p><p>This consideration came after the other, but Betton, in 
rearranging them, put it first, because he thought it looked better 
there, and also because he immediately perceived its value in 
justifying a plan of action that was beginning to take shape in his 
mind. 
</p><p>"Poor devil, I'm damned if I don't do it for him!" said 
Betton, sitting down at his desk. 
</p><p>Three or four days later he sent word to Vyse that he didn't 
care to go over the letters any longer, and that they would once 
more be carried directly to the library. 
</p><p>The next time he lounged in, on his way to his morning ride, 
he found his secretary's pen in active motion. 
</p><p>"A lot to-day," Vyse told him cheerfully. 
</p><p>His tone irritated Betton: it had the inane optimism of the 
physician reassuring a discouraged patient. 
</p><p>"Oh, Lord&mdash;I thought it was almost over," groaned the 
novelist. 
</p><p>"No: they've just got their second wind.  Here's one from a 
Chicago publisher&mdash;never heard the name&mdash;offering you thirty per 
cent. on your next novel, with an advance royalty of twenty 
thousand.  And here's a chap who wants to syndicate it for a bunch 
of Sunday papers: big offer, too.  That's from Ann Arbor.  And 
this&mdash;oh, <hi rend="italic"> this</hi> one's funny!" 
</p><p>He held up a small scented sheet to Betton, who made no 
movement to receive it. 
</p><p>"Funny?  Why's it funny?" he growled. 
</p><p>"Well, it's from a girl&mdash;a lady&mdash;and she thinks she's the only 
person who understands 'Abundance'&mdash;has the clue to it.  Says she's 
never seen a book so misrepresented by the critics&mdash;" 
</p><p>"Ha, ha!  That <hi rend="italic"> is</hi> good!" Betton agreed with too loud a 
laugh. 
</p><p>"This one's from a lady, too&mdash;married woman.  Says she's 
misunderstood, and would like to correspond." 
</p><p>"Oh, Lord," said Betton.&mdash;"What are you looking at?" he added 
sharply, as Vyse continued to bend his blinking gaze on the 
letters. 
</p><p>"I was only thinking I'd never seen such short letters from 
women.  Neither one fills the first page." 
</p><p>"Well, what of that?" queried Betton. 
</p><p>Vyse reflected.  "I'd like to meet a <pb n="415"/>  woman like that," 
he said wearily; and Betton laughed again. 
</p><p>The letters continued to pour in, and there could be no 
farther question of dispensing with Vyse's services.  But one 
morning, about three weeks later, the latter asked for a word with 
his employer, and Betton, on entering the library, found his 
secretary with half a dozen documents spread out before him. 
</p><p>"What's up?" queried Betton, with a touch of impatience. 
</p><p>Vyse was attentively scanning the outspread letters. 
</p><p>"I don't know: can't make out."  His voice had a faint note of 
embarrassment.  "Do you remember a note signed <hi rend="italic">Hester Macklin</hi> 
that came three or four weeks ago?  Married&mdash;misunderstood&mdash;Western 
army post&mdash;wanted to correspond?" 
</p><p>Betton seemed to grope among his memories; then he assented 
vaguely. 
</p><p>"A short note," Vyse went on: "the whole story in half a page.  
The shortness struck me so much&mdash;and the directness&mdash;that I wrote 
her: wrote in my own name, I mean." 
</p><p>"In your own name?"  Betton stood amazed; then he broke into 
a groan. 
</p><p>"Good Lord, Vyse&mdash;you're incorrigible!" 
</p><p>The secretary pulled his thin moustache with a nervous laugh.  
"If you mean I'm an ass, you're right.  Look here."  He held out an 
envelope stamped with the words: "Dead Letter Office."  "My 
effusion has come back to me marked 'unknown.'  There's no such 
person at the address she gave you." 
</p><p>Betton seemed for an instant to share his secretary's 
embarrassment; then he burst into an uproarious laugh. 
</p><p>"Hoax, was it?  That's rough on you, old fellow!" 
</p><p>Vyse shrugged his shoulders.  "Yes; but the interesting 
question is&mdash;why on earth didn't <hi rend="italic"> your</hi> answer come back, too?" 
</p><p>"My answer?" 
</p><p>"The official one&mdash;the one I wrote in your name.  If she's 
unknown, what's become of <hi rend="italic"> that?"</hi> 
</p><p>Betton stared at him with eyes wrinkled by amusement.  
"Perhaps she hadn't disappeared then." 
</p><p>Vyse disregarded the conjecture.  "Look here&mdash;I believe <hi rend="italic"> 
all</hi> these letters are a hoax," he broke out. 
</p><p>Betton stared at him with a face that turned slowly red and 
angry.  "What are you talking about?  All what letters?" 
</p><p>"These I've spread out here: I've been comparing them.  And I 
believe they're all written by one man." 
</p><p>Burton's redness turned to a purple that made his ruddy 
moustache seem pale.  "What the devil are you driving at?" he 
asked. 
</p><p>"Well, just look at it," Vyse persisted, still bent above the 
letters.  "I've been studying them carefully&mdash;those that have come 
within the last two or three weeks&mdash;and there's a queer likeness in 
the writing of some of them.  The <hi rend="italic">g</hi>'s are all like corkscrews.  
And the same phrases keep recurring&mdash;the Ann Arbor news-agent uses 
the same expressions as the President of the Girls' College at 
Euphorbia, Maine." 
</p><p>Betton laughed.  "Aren't the critics always groaning over the 
shrinkage of the national vocabulary?  Of course we all use the 
same expressions." 
</p><p>"Yes," said Vyse obstinately.  "But how about using the same 
<hi rend="italic"> g</hi>'s?" 
</p><p>Betton laughed again, but Vyse continued without heeding him: 
"Look here, Betton&mdash;could Strett have written them?" 
</p><p>"Strett?" Betton roared.  <hi rend="italic">" Strett?"</hi>  He threw himself into 
his arm-chair to shake out his mirth at greater ease. 
</p><p>"I'll tell you why.  Strett always posts all my answers.  He 
comes in for them every day before I leave.  He posted the letter 
to the misunderstood party&mdash;the letter from <hi rend="italic"> you</hi> that the Dead 
Letter Office didn't return.  <hi rend="italic"> I</hi> posted my own letter to her; 
and that came back." 
</p><p>A measurable silence followed the emission of this ingenious 
conjecture; then Betton observed with gentle irony: "Extremely 
neat.  And of course it's no business of yours to supply any valid 
motive for this remarkable attention on my valet's part." 
</p><p>Vyse cast on him a slanting glance. 
</p><p>"If you've found that human conduct's generally based on valid 
motives&mdash;!" 
</p><p>"Well, outside of mad-houses it's supposed to be not quite 
incalculable." 
</p><p>Vyse had an odd smile under his thin moustache.  "Every house 
is a mad-house at some time or another." 
</p><p>Betton rose with a careless shake of the shoulders.  "This one 
will be if I talk to you much longer," he said, moving away with a 
laugh. <pb n="416"/>  


</p><p>                           IV 

</p><p>BETTON did not for a moment believe that Vyse suspected the 
valet of having written the letters. 
</p><p>"Why the devil don't he say out what he thinks?  He was always 
a tortuous chap," he grumbled inwardly. 
</p><p>The sense of being held under the lens of Vyse's mute scrutiny 
became more and more exasperating.  Betton, by this time, had 
squared his shoulders to the fact that "Abundance" was a failure 
with the public: a confessed and glaring failure.  The press told 
him so openly, and his friends emphasized the fact by their 
circumlocutions and evasions.  Betton minded it a good deal more 
than he had expected, but not nearly as much as he minded Vyse's 
knowing it.  That remained the central twinge in his diffused 
discomfort.  And the problem of getting rid of his secretary once 
more engaged him. 
</p><p>He had set aside all sentimental pretexts for retaining Vyse; 
but a practical argument replaced them.  "If I ship him now he'll 
think it's because I'm ashamed to have him see that I'm not getting 
any more letters." 
</p><p>For the letters had ceased again, almost abruptly, since Vyse 
had hazarded the conjecture that they were the product of Strett's 
devoted pen.  Betton had reverted only once to the subject&mdash;to ask 
ironically, a day or two later: "Is Strett writing to me as much as 
ever?"&mdash;and, on Vyse's replying with a neutral head-shake, had 
added with a laugh: "If you suspect <hi rend="italic">him</hi> you might as well think 
I write the letters myself!" 
</p><p>"There are very few to-day," said Vyse, with his irritating 
evasiveness; and Betton rejoined squarely: "Oh, they'll stop soon.  
The book's a failure." 
</p><p>A few mornings later he felt a rush of shame at his own 
tergiversations, and stalked into the library with Vyse's sentence 
on his tongue. 
</p><p>Vyse started back with one of his anaemic blushes.  "I was 
hoping you'd be in.  I wanted to speak to you.  There've been no 
letters the last day or two," he explained. 
</p><p>Betton drew a quick breath of relief.  The man had some sense 
of decency, then!  He meant to dismiss himself. 
</p><p>"I told you so, my dear fellow; the book's a flat failure," he 
said, almost gaily. 
</p><p>Vyse made a deprecating gesture.  "I don't know that I should 
regard the absence of letters as the ultimate test.  But I wanted 
to ask you if there isn't something else I can do on the days when 
there's no writing."  He turned his glance toward the book-lined 
walls.  "Don't you want your library catalogued?" he asked 
insidiously. 
</p><p>"Had it done last year, thanks."  Betton glanced away from 
Vyse's face.  It was piteous, how he needed the job! 
</p><p>"I see. . . .  Of course this is just a temporary lull in the 
letters.  They'll begin again&mdash;as they did before.  The people who 
read carefully read slowly&mdash;you haven't heard yet what <hi rend="italic"> they</hi> 
think." 
</p><p>Betton felt a rush of puerile joy at the suggestion.  
Actually, he hadn't thought of that! 
</p><p>"There <hi rend="italic"> was</hi> a big second crop after 'Diadems and Faggots,'" 
he mused aloud. 
</p><p>"Of course.  Wait and see," said Vyse confidently. 

</p><p>The letters in fact began again&mdash;more gradually and in smaller 
numbers.  But their quality was different, as Vyse had predicted.  
And in two cases Betton's correspondents, not content to compress 
into one rapid communication the thoughts inspired by his work, 
developed their views in a succession of really remarkable letters.  
One of the writers was a professor in a Western college; the other 
was a girl in Florida.  In their language, their point of view, 
their reasons for appreciating "Abundance," they differed almost 
diametrically; but this only made the unanimity of their approval 
the more striking.  The rush of correspondence evoked by Betton's 
earlier novel had produced nothing so personal, so exceptional as 
these communications.  He had gulped the praise of "Diadems and 
Faggots" as undiscriminatingly as it was offered; now he knew for 
the first time the subtler pleasures of the palate.  He tried to 
feign indifference, even to himself; and to Vyse he made no sign.  
But gradually he felt a desire to know what his secretary thought 
of the letters, and, above all, what he was saying in reply to 
them.  And he resented acutely the possibility of Vyse's <pb n="417"/>  
starting one of his clandestine correspondences with the girl in 
Florida.  Vyse's notorious lack of delicacy had never been more 
vividly present to Betton's imagination; and he made up his mind to 
answer the letters himself. 
</p><p>He would keep Vyse on, of course: there were other 
communications that the secretary could attend to.  And, if 
necessary, Betton would invent an occupation: he cursed his 
stupidity in having betrayed the fact that his books were already 
catalogued. 
</p><p>Vyse showed no surprise when Betton announced his intention of 
dealing personally with the two correspondents who showed so 
flattering a reluctance to take their leave.  But Betton 
immediately read a criticism in his lack of comment, and put forth, 
on a note of challenge: "After all, one must be decent!" 
</p><p>Vyse looked at him with an evanescent smile.  "You'll have to 
explain that you didn't write the first answers." 
</p><p>Betton halted.  "Well&mdash;I&mdash;I more or less dictated them, didn't 
I?" 
</p><p>"Oh, virtually, they're yours, of course." 
</p><p>"You think I can put it that way?" 
</p><p>"Why not?"  The secretary absently drew an arabesque on the 
blotting-pad.  "Of course they'll keep it up longer if you write 
yourself," he suggested. 
</p><p>Betton blushed, but faced the issue.  "Hang it all, I sha'n't 
be sorry.  They interest me.  They're remarkable letters."  And 
Vyse, without observation, returned to his writings. 
</p><p>The spring, that year, was delicious to Betton.  His college 
professor continued to address him tersely but cogently at fixed 
intervals, and twice a week eight serried pages came from Florida.  
There were other letters, too; he had the solace of feeling that at 
last "Abundance" was making its way, was reaching the people who, 
as Vyse said, read slowly because they read intelligently.  But 
welcome as were all these proofs of his restored authority they 
were but the background of his happiness.  His life revolved for 
the moment about the personality of his two chief correspondents.  
The professor's letters satisfied his craving for intellectual 
recognition, and the satisfaction he felt in them proved how 
completely he had lost faith in himself.  He blushed to think that 
his opinion of his work had been swayed by the shallow judgments of 
a public whose taste he despised.  Was it possible that he had 
allowed himself to think less well of "Abundance" because it was 
not to the taste of the average novel-reader?  Such false humility 
was less excusable than the crudest appetite for praise: it was 
ridiculous to try to do conscientious work if one's self-esteem 
were at the mercy of popular judgments.  All this the professor's 
letters delicately and indirectly conveyed to Betton, with the 
result that the author of "Abundance" began to recognize in it the 
ripest flower of his genius. 
</p><p>But if the professor understood his book, the girl in Florida 
understood <hi rend="italic"> him;</hi> and Betton was fully alive to the superior 
qualities of discernment which this process implied.  For his 
lovely correspondent his novel was but the starting-point, the 
pretext of her discourse: he himself was her real object, and he 
had the delicious sense, as their exchange of thoughts proceeded, 
that she was interested in "Abundance" because of its author, 
rather than in the author because of his book.  Of course she laid 
stress on the fact that his ideas were the object of her 
contemplation; but Betton's agreeable person had permitted him some 
insight into the incorrigible subjectiveness of female judgments, 
and he was pleasantly aware, from the lady's tone, that she guessed 
him to be neither old nor ridiculous.  And suddenly he wrote to ask 
if he might see her. . . . 

</p><p>The answer was long in coming.  Betton fumed at the delay, 
watched, wondered, fretted; then he received the one word 
"Impossible." 
</p><p>He wrote back more urgently, and awaited the reply with 
increasing eagerness.  A certain shyness had kept him from once 
more modifying the instructions regarding his mail, and Strett 
still carried the letters directly to Vyse.  The hour when he knew 
they were passing under the latter's eyes was now becoming 
intolerable to Betton, and it was a profound relief when the 
secretary, suddenly advised of his father's illness, asked 
permission to absent himself for a fortnight. 
</p><p>Vyse departed just after Betton had despatched to Florida his 
second missive of entreaty, and for ten days he tasted the furtive 
joy of a first perusal of his letters. <pb n="418"/>  The answer from 
Florida was not among them; but Betton said to himself "She's 
thinking it over," and delay, in that light, seemed favourable.  So 
charming, in fact, was this phase of sentimental suspense that he 
felt a start of resentment when a telegram apprised him one morning 
that Vyse would return to his post that day. 
</p><p>Betton had slept later than usual, and, springing out of bed 
with the telegram in his hand, he learned from the clock that his 
secretary was due in half an hour.  He reflected that the morning's 
mail must long since be in; and, too impatient to wait for its 
appearance with his breakfast-tray, he threw on a dressing-gown and 
went to the library.  There lay the letters, half a dozen of them: 
but his eye flew to one envelope, and as he tore it open a warm 
wave rocked his heart. 
</p><p>The letter was dated a few days after its writer must have 
received his own: it had all the qualities of grace and insight to 
which his unknown friend had accustomed him, but it contained no 
allusion, however indirect, to the special purport of his appeal.  
Even a vanity less ingenious than Betton's might have read in the 
lady's silence one of the most familiar motions of consent; but the 
smile provoked by this inference faded as he turned to his other 
letters.  For the uppermost bore the superscription "Dead Letter 
Office," and the document that fell from it was his own last letter 
from Florida. 
</p><p>Betton studied the ironic "Unknown" for an appreciable space 
of time; then he broke into a laugh.  He had suddenly recalled 
Vyse's similar experience with "Hester Macklin," and the light he 
was able to throw on that obscure episode was searching enough to 
penetrate all the dark corners of his own adventure.  He felt a 
rush of heat to the ears; catching sight of himself in the glass, 
he saw a red ridiculous congested countenance, and dropped into a 
chair to hide it between flushed fists.  He was roused by the 
opening of the door, and Vyse appeared on the threshold. 
</p><p>"Oh, I beg pardon&mdash;you're ill?" said the secretary. 
</p><p>Betton's only answer was an inarticulate murmur of derision; 
then he pushed forward the letter with the imprint of the Dead 
Letter Office. 
</p><p>"Look at that," he jeered. 
</p><p>Vyse peered at the envelope, and turned it over slowly in his 
hands.  Betton's eyes, fixed on him, saw his face decompose like a 
substance touched by some powerful acid.  He clung to the envelope 
as if to gain time. 
</p><p>"It's from the young lady you've been writing to at Swazee 
Springs?" he asked at length. 
</p><p>"It's from the young lady I've been writing to at Swazee 
Springs." 
</p><p>"Well&mdash;I suppose she's gone away," continued Vyse, rebuilding 
his countenance rapidly. 
</p><p>"Yes; and in a community numbering perhaps a hundred and 
seventy-five souls, including the dogs and chickens, the local 
post-office is so ignorant of her movements that my letter has to 
be sent to the Dead Letter Office." 
</p><p>Vyse meditated on this; then he laughed in turn.  "After all, 
the same thing happened to me&mdash;with 'Hester Macklin,' I mean," he 
recalled sheepishly. 
</p><p>"Just so," said Betton, bringing down his clenched fist on the 
table.  <hi rend="italic">" Just so</hi>," he repeated, in italics. 
</p><p>He caught his secretary's glance, and held it with his own for 
a moment.  Then he dropped it as, in pity, one releases something 
scared and squirming. 
</p><p>"The very day my letter was returned from Swazee Springs she 
wrote me this from there," he said, holding up the last Florida 
missive. 
</p><p>"Ha!  That's funny," said Vyse, with a damp forehead. 
</p><p>"Yes, it's funny; it's funny," said Betton.  He leaned back, 
his hands in his pockets, staring up at the ceiling, and noticing 
a crack in the cornice.  Vyse, at the corner of the writing-table, 
waited. 
</p><p>"Shall I get to work?" he began, after a silence measurable by 
minutes.  Betton's gaze descended from the cornice. 
</p><p>"I've got your seat, haven't I?" he said, rising and moving 
away from the table. 
</p><p>Vyse, with a quick gleam of relief, slipped into the vacant 
chair, and began to stir about vaguely among the papers. 
</p><p>"How's your father?" Betton asked from the hearth. 
</p><p>"Oh, better&mdash;better, thank you.  He'll pull out of it." 
</p><p>"But you had a sharp scare for a day or two?" 
</p><p>"Yes&mdash;it was touch and go when I got there." <pb n="419"/>  
</p><p>Another pause, while Vyse began to classify the letters. 
</p><p>"And I suppose," Betton continued in a steady tone, "your 
anxiety made you forget your usual precautions&mdash;whatever they 
were&mdash;about this Florida correspondence, and before you'd had time 
to prevent it the Swazee post-office blundered?" 
</p><p>Vyse lifted his head with a quick movement.  "What do you 
mean?" he asked, pushing his chair back. 
</p><p>"I mean that you saw I couldn't live without flattery, and 
that you've been ladling it out to me to earn your keep." 
</p><p>Vyse sat motionless and shrunken, digging the blotting-pad 
with his pen.  "What on earth are you driving at?" he repeated. 
</p><p>"Though why the deuce," Betton continued in the same steady 
tone, "you should need to do this kind of work when you've got such 
faculties at your service&mdash;those letters were magnificent, my dear 
fellow!  Why in the world don't you write novels, instead of 
writing to other people about them?" 
</p><p>Vyse straightened himself with an effort.  "What are you 
talking about, Betton?  Why the devil do you think <hi rend="italic"> I</hi> wrote 
those letters?" 
</p><p>Betton held back his answer, with a brooding face.  "Because 
I wrote 'Hester Macklin's'&mdash;to myself!" 
</p><p>Vyse sat stock-still, without the least outcry of wonder.  
"Well&mdash;?" he finally said, in a low tone. 
</p><p>"And because you found me out (you see, you can't even feign 
surprise!)&mdash;because you saw through it at a glance, knew at once 
that the letters were faked.  And when you'd foolishly put me on my 
guard by pointing out to me that they were a clumsy forgery, and 
had then suddenly guessed that <hi rend="italic">I</hi> was the forger, you drew the 
natural inference that I had to have popular approval, or at least 
had to make <hi rend="italic">you</hi> think I had it.  You saw that, to me, the worst 
thing about the failure of the book was having <hi rend="italic">you</hi> know it was 
a failure.  And so you applied your superior&mdash;your immeasurably 
superior&mdash;abilities to carrying on the humbug, and deceiving me as 
I'd tried to deceive you.  And you did it so successfully that I 
don't see why the devil you haven't made your fortune writing 
novels!" 
</p><p>Vyse remained silent, his head slightly bent under the 
mounting tide of Betton's denunciation. 
</p><p>"The way you differentiated your people&mdash;characterised them&mdash; 
avoided my stupid mistake of making the women's letters too short 
and logical, of letting my different correspondents use the same 
expressions: the amount of ingenuity and art you wasted on it!  I 
swear, Vyse, I'm sorry that damned post-office went back on you," 
Betton went on, piling up the waves of his irony. 
</p><p>But at this height they suddenly paused, drew back on 
themselves, and began to recede before the spectacle of Vyse's pale 
distress.  Something warm and emotional in Betton's nature&mdash;a 
lurking kindliness, perhaps, for any one who tried to soothe and 
smooth his writhing ego&mdash;softened his eye as it rested on the 
drooping figure of his secretary. 
</p><p>"Look here, Vyse&mdash;I'm not sorry&mdash;not altogether sorry this has 
happened!"  He moved slowly across the room, and laid a friendly 
palm on Vyse's shoulder.  "In a queer illogical way it evens up 
things, as it were.  I did you a shabby turn once, years ago&mdash;oh, 
out of sheer carelessness, of course&mdash;about that novel of yours I 
promised to give to Apthorn.  If I <hi rend="italic">had</hi> given it, it might not 
have made any difference&mdash;I'm not sure it wasn't too good for 
success&mdash;but anyhow, I dare say you thought my personal influence 
might have helped you, might at least have got you a quicker 
hearing.  Perhaps you thought it was because the thing <hi rend="italic">was</hi> so 
good that I kept it back, that I felt some nasty jealousy of your 
superiority.  I swear to you it wasn't that&mdash;I clean forgot it.  
And one day when I came home it was gone: you'd sent and taken it.  
And I've always thought since you might have owed me a grudge&mdash;and 
not unjustly; so this . . . this business of the letters . . . the 
sympathy you've shown . . . for I suppose it <hi rend="italic">is</hi> sympathy . . . 
?" 
</p><p>Vyse startled and checked him by a queer crackling laugh. 
</p><p>"It's <hi rend="italic">not</hi> sympathy?" broke in Betton, the moisture drying 
out of his voice.  He withdrew his hand from Vyse's shoulder.  
"What is it, then?  The joy of uncovering my nakedness?  An eye for 
an eye?  Is it <hi rend="italic">that?"</hi> 
</p><p>Vyse rose from his seat, and with a mechanical gesture swept 
into a heap all the letters he had sorted. 
</p><p>"I'm stone broke, and wanted to keep my job&mdash;that's what it 
is," he said wearily . . . 
</p> 
 
</div2> 
</div1> 
</body> 
</text> 
</TEI.2> 
