<?xml version="1.0"?>

<?dlps id="WhaFath"?>
<?dlps page-images="none" figure-images="no"?>
<?dlps transcription="other"?>

<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/tei-p4/tei2.dtd" [
<!ENTITY % POSTKB "INCLUDE">
<!ENTITY % TEI.extensions.ent SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.ent">
<!ENTITY % TEI.extensions.dtd SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.dtd">
<!ENTITY % ISOnum SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/charent/iso-num.ent"> %ISOnum;
<!ENTITY % ISOpub SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/charent/iso-pub.ent"> %ISOpub;

]>

<TEI.2 id="WhaFath"> 
<teiHeader type="migrated" creator="Etext">
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title type="main">His Father's Son</title>
<title type="sort">his fathers son</title>
<author>Wharton, Edith, 1862-1937</author>
<respStmt>
<resp>Creation of machine-readable version:</resp>
<name>Judy Boss</name>
</respStmt>
<respStmt>
<resp>Conversion to TEI-conformant markup:</resp>
<name>University of Virginia Library Electronic Text Center</name>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt> 
<extent>ca. <num type="kilobytes">41</num> kilobytes</extent> 
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>University of Virginia Library</publisher>
<pubPlace>Charlottesville, Virginia</pubPlace>
<idno type="ETC">WhaFath</idno> 
<date value="1995">1995</date>
<availability status="public">
<p n="copyright">Copyright &copy; 1995 by the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia</p>
<p n="access">Publicly accessible</p>
</availability>
<idno type="uva-pid">uva-lib:476492</idno>
</publicationStmt>
<seriesStmt>
<title>University of Virginia Library, Text collection</title>
<idno type="uva-set">UVA-LIB-Text</idno>
</seriesStmt> 
<sourceDesc>
<biblFull>
<titleStmt>
<title type="main">His Father's Son</title>
<title type="sort">his fathers son</title>
<author>Wharton, Edith</author>
</titleStmt> 
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>Scribner's Magazine</publisher>
<date value="1909-06">June 1909</date>
</publicationStmt> 
<notesStmt>
<note>
<p>Vol. 45</p>
</note>
</notesStmt>
</biblFull>
</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc> 
<encodingDesc>
<projectDesc>
<p>Prepared for the University of Virginia Library Electronic Text Center</p>
</projectDesc> 
<editorialDecl>
<p>All quotation marks retained as data</p> 
<p>Verification made against printed text</p> 
<p id="ETC">Keywords in the header are a local Electronic Text Center scheme  
to aid in establishing analytical groupings</p>
</editorialDecl> 
<refsDecl>
<p>ID elements are given for each page element and are composed of the text's 
unique cryptogram and the given page number, as in SpeFQue1 for page one of  
Spenser's Faerie Queene.</p>
</refsDecl>
</encodingDesc> 
<profileDesc>
<creation>
<date value="1909">1909</date>
</creation> 
<langUsage>
<language id="eng" usage="main">English</language>
</langUsage> 
<textClass>
<keywords>
<term>fiction</term>
<term>prose</term>
</keywords>
</textClass>
</profileDesc> 
<revisionDesc>
<change>
<date value="1995-01">January 1995</date> 
<respStmt>
<resp>corrector</resp>
<name>David Seaman and Kelly Tetterton</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Header and basic TEI SGML encoding added</item>
</change> 
<change>
<date value="2005-07">July 2005</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>Corrector</resp>
<name>Margaret Konkol</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Converted SGML to XML and fixed tagging.</item>
</change>
<change>
<date value="2007-09">September 2007</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>Migration</resp>
<name>Ethan Gruber, University of Virginia Library</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Converted XML markup from TEI Lite to uva-dl-tei (TEI P4 with local customizations).</item>
</change>
<change>
<date value="2008-01">January 2008</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>Migration</resp>
<name>Greg Murray, University of Virginia Library</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Programmatically updated TEI header markup (but not header content) for minimal compliance with current QA requirements.</item>
</change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader> 



<text id="d1">  
<body id="d2"> 
<div1 type="story" id="d3"> 
<head> 
                   <hi rend="italic"> TALES OF MEN</hi> 
<lb/> 
Wharton, Edith.  "His Father's Son."   
<lb/> 
<hi rend="italic"> Scribner's Magazine</hi> 45  
(June 1909): 657-665. 
</head> 
<pb n="657"/>  
<div2 type="section" n="1" id="d4"> 
<head> 
                        I 
</head> 
<p> 
AFTER his wife's death Mason Grew took the momentous step of 
selling out his business and moving from Wingfield, Connecticut, to 
Brooklyn. 
</p><p>For years he had secretly nursed the hope of such a change, 
but had never dared to suggest it to Mrs. Grew, a woman of 
immutable habits.  Mr. Grew himself was attached to Wingfield, 
where he had grown up, prospered, and become what the local press 
described as "prominent."  He was attached to his ugly brick house 
with sandstone trimmings and a cast-iron area-railing neatly sanded 
to match; to the similar row of houses across the street, the 
"trolley" wires forming a kind of aerial pathway between, and the 
sprawling vista closed by the steeple of the church which he and 
his wife had always attended, and where their only child had been 
baptized. 
</p><p>It was hard to snap all these threads of association, visual 
and sentimental; yet still harder, now that he was alone, to live 
so far from his boy.  Ronald Grew was practising law in New York, 
and there was no more chance of returning to live at Wingfield than 
of a river's flowing inland from the sea.  Therefore to be near him 
his father must move; and it was characteristic of Mr. Grew, and of 
the situation generally, that the translation, when it took place, 
was to Brooklyn, and not to New York. 
</p><p>"Why you bury yourself in that hole I can't think," had been 
Ronald's comment; and Mr. Grew simply replied that rents were lower 
in Brooklyn, and that he had heard of a house that would suit him.  
In reality he had said to himself&mdash;being the only recipient of his 
own confidences&mdash;that if he went to New York he might be on the 
boy's mind; whereas, if he lived in Brooklyn, Ronald would always 
have a good excuse for not popping over to see him every other day.  
The sociological isolation of Brooklyn, combined with its 
geographical nearness, presented in fact the precise conditions for 
Mr. Grew's case.  He wanted to be near enough to New York to go 
there often, to feel under his feet the same pavement that Ronald 
trod, to sit now and then in the same theatres, and find on his 
breakfast-table the journals which, with increasing frequency, 
inserted Ronald's name in the sacred bounds of the society column.  
It had always been a trial to Mr. Grew to have to wait twenty-four 
hours to read that "among those present was Mr. Ronald Grew."  Now 
he had it with his coffee, and left it on the breakfast-table to 
the perusal of a "hired girl" cosmopolitan enough to do it justice.  
In such ways Brooklyn attested the advantages of its propinquity to 
New York, while remaining, as regards Ronald's duty to his father, 
as remote and inaccessible as Wingfield. 
</p><p>It was not that Ronald shirked his filial obligations, but 
rather because of his heavy sense of them, that Mr. Grew so 
persistently sought to minimize and lighten them.  It was he who 
insisted, to Ronald, on the immense difficulty of getting from New 
York to Brooklyn. 
</p><p>"Any way you look at it, it makes a big hole in the day; and 
there's not much use in the ragged rim left.  You say you're dining 
out next Sunday?  Then I forbid you to come over here for lunch.  
Do you understand me, sir?  You disobey at the risk of your 
father's malediction!  Where did you say you were dining?  With the 
Waltham Bankshires again?  Why, that's the second time in three 
weeks, ain't it?  Big blow-out, I suppose?  Gold plate and 
orchids&mdash;opera singers in afterward?  Well, you'd be in a nice box 
if there was a fog on the river, and you got hung up half-way over.  
That'd be a handsome return for the attention Mrs. Bankshire has 
shown you&mdash;singling out a whipper-snapper like you twice in three 
weeks!  (What's the daughter's name&mdash;Daisy?)  No, <hi rend="italic"> sir</hi>&mdash;don't 
you come fooling round here next Sunday, or I'll set the dogs on 
you.  And you wouldn't find me in anyhow, come to think of it.  I'm 
lunching out myself, as it happens&mdash;yes sir, <hi rend="italic"> lunching out</hi>.  Is 
there anything especially comic in <pb n="658"/>  my lunching out?  I 
don't often do it, you say?  Well, that's no reason why I never 
should.  Who with?  Why, with&mdash;with old Dr. Bleaker: Dr. Eliphalet 
Bleaker.  No, you wouldn't know about him&mdash;he's only an old friend 
of your mother's and mine." 
</p><p>Gradually Ronald's insistence became less difficult to 
overcome.  With his customary sweetness and tact (as Mr. Grew put 
it) he began to "take the hint," to give in to "the old 
gentleman's" growing desire for solitude. 
</p><p>"I'm set in my ways, Ronny, that's about the size of it; I 
like to go tick-ticking along like a clock.  I always did.  And 
when you come bouncing in I never feel sure there's enough for 
dinner&mdash;or that I haven't sent Maria out for the evening.  And I 
don't want the neighbors to see me opening my own door to my son.  
That's the kind of cringing snob I am.  Don't give me away, will 
you?  I want 'em to think I keep four or five powdered flunkeys in 
the hall day and night&mdash;same as the lobby of one of those Fifth 
Avenue hotels.  And if you pop over when you're not expected, how 
am I going to keep up the bluff?" 
</p><p>Ronald yielded after the proper amount of resistance&mdash;his 
intuitive sense, in every social transaction, of the proper amount 
of force to be expended, was one of the qualities his father most 
admired in him.  Mr. Grew's perceptions in this line were probably 
more acute than his son suspected.  The souls of short thick-set 
men, with chubby features, mutton-chop whiskers, and pale eyes 
peering between folds of fat like almond kernels in half-split 
shells&mdash;souls thus encased do not reveal themselves to the casual 
scrutiny as delicate emotional instruments.  But in spite of the 
dense disguise in which he walked Mr. Grew vibrated exquisitely in 
response to every imaginative appeal; and his son Ronald was 
perpetually stimulating and feeding his imagination. 
</p><p>Ronald in fact constituted his father's one escape from the 
impenetrable element of mediocrity which had always hemmed him in.  
To a man so enamoured of beauty, and so little qualified to add to 
its sum total, it was a wonderful privilege to have bestowed on the 
world such a being.  Ronald's resemblance to Mr. Grew's early 
conception of what he himself would have liked to look might have 
put new life into the discredited theory of pre-natal influences.  
At any rate, if the young man owed his beauty, his distinction and 
his winning manner to the dreams of one of his parents, it was 
certainly to those of Mr. Grew, who, while outwardly devoting his 
life to the manufacture and dissemination of Grew's Secure 
Suspender Buckle, moved in an enchanted inward world peopled with 
all the figures of romance.  In this high company Mr. Grew cut as 
brilliant a figure as any of its noble phantoms; and to see his 
vision of himself suddenly projected on the outer world in the 
shape of a brilliant popular conquering son, seemed, in retrospect, 
to give to that image a belated objective reality.  There were even 
moments when, forgetting his physiognomy, Mr. Grew said to himself 
that if he'd had "half a chance" he might have done as well as 
Ronald; but this only fortified his resolve that Ronald should do 
infinitely better. 
</p><p>Ronald's ability to do well almost equalled his gift of 
looking well.  Mr. Grew constantly affirmed to himself that the boy 
was "not a genius"; but, barring this slight deficiency, he was 
almost everything that a parent could wish.  Even at Harvard he had 
managed to be several desirable things at once&mdash;writing poetry in 
the college magazine, playing delightfully "by ear," acquitting 
himself honorably in his studies, and yet holding his own in the 
fashionable sporting set that formed, as it were, the gateway of 
the temple of Society.  Mr. Grew's idealism did not preclude the 
frank desire that his son should pass through that gateway; but the 
wish was not prompted by material considerations.  It was Mr. 
Grew's notion that, in the rough and hurrying current of a new 
civilization, the little pools of leisure and enjoyment must 
nurture delicate growths, material graces as well as moral 
refinements, likely to be uprooted and swept away by the rush of 
the main torrent.  He based his theory on the fact that he had 
liked the few "society" people he had met&mdash;had found their manners 
simpler, their voices more agreeable, their views more consonant 
with his own, than those of the leading citizens of Wingfield.  But 
then he had met very few. 
</p><p>Ronald's sympathies needed no urging in the same direction.  
He took naturally, dauntlessly, to all the high and exceptional 
things about which his father's imagina-<pb n="659"/> tion had so long 
sheepishly and ineffectually hovered&mdash;from the start he <hi rend="italic"> was</hi> 
what Mr. Grew had dreamed of being.  And so precise, so detailed, 
was Mr. Grew's vision of his own imaginary career, that as Ronald 
grew up, and began to travel in a widening orbit, his father had an 
almost uncanny sense of the extent to which that career was 
enacting itself before him.  At Harvard, Ronald had done exactly 
what the hypothetical Mason Grew would have done, had not his 
actual self, at the same age, been working his way up in old 
Slagden's button factory&mdash;the institution which was later to 
acquire fame, and even notoriety, as the birthplace of Grew's 
Secure Suspender Buckle.  Afterward, at a period when the actual 
Grew had passed from the factory to the bookkeeper's desk, his 
invisible double had been reading law at Columbia&mdash;precisely again 
what Ronald did!  But it was when the young man left the paths laid 
out for him by the parental hand, and cast himself boldly on the 
world, that his adventures began to bear the most astonishing 
resemblance to those of the unrealized Mason Grew.  It was in New 
York that the scene of this hypothetical being's first exploits had 
always been laid; and it was in New York that Ronald was to achieve 
his first triumph.  There was nothing small or timid about Mr. 
Grew's imagination; it had never stopped at anything between 
Wingfield and the metropolis.  And the real Ronald had the same 
cosmic vision as his parent.  He brushed aside with a contemptuous 
laugh his mother's tearful entreaty that he should stay at 
Wingfield and continue the dynasty of the Grew Suspender Buckle.  
Mr. Grew knew that in reality Ronald winced at the Buckle, loathed 
it, blushed for his connection with it.  Yet it was the Buckle that 
had seen him through Groton, Harvard and the Law School, and had 
permitted him to enter the office of a distinguished corporation 
lawyer, instead of being enslaved to some sordid business with 
quick returns.  The Buckle had been Ronald's fairy godmother&mdash;yet 
his father did not blame him for abhorring and disowning it.  Mr. 
Grew himself often bitterly regretted having bestowed his own name 
on the instrument of his material success, though, at the time, his 
doing so had been the natural expression of his romanticism.  When 
he invented the Buckle, and took out his patent, he and his wife 
both felt that to bestow their name on it was like naming a battle-ship or a peak of the Andes. 
</p><p>Mrs. Grew had never learned to know better; but Mr. Grew had 
discovered his error before Ronald was out of school.  He read it 
first in a black eye of his boy's.  Ronald's symmetry had been 
marred by the insolent fist of a fourth former whom he had 
chastised for alluding to his father as "Old Buckles;" and when Mr. 
Grew heard the epithet he understood in a flash that the Buckle was 
a thing to blush for.  It was too late then to dissociate his name 
from it, or to efface from the hoardings of the entire continent 
the picture of two gentlemen, one contorting himself in the abject 
effort to repair a broken brace, while the careless ease of the 
other's attitude proclaimed his trust in the Secure Suspender 
Buckle.  These records were indelible, but Ronald could at least be 
spared all direct connection with them; and from that day Mr. Grew 
resolved that the boy should not return to Wingfield. 
</p><p>"You'll see," he had said to Mrs. Grew, "he'll take right hold 
in New York.  Ronald's got my knack for taking hold," he added, 
throwing out his chest. 
</p><p>"But the way you took hold was in business," objected Mrs. 
Grew, who was large and literal. 
</p><p>Mr. Grew's chest collapsed, and he became suddenly conscious 
of his comic face in its rim of sandy whiskers.  "That's not the 
only way," he said, with a touch of wistfulness which escaped his 
wife's analysis. 
</p><p>"Well, of course you could have written beautifully," she 
rejoined with admiring eyes. 
</p><p><hi rend="italic">" Written?</hi>  Me!"  Mr. Grew became sardonic. 
</p><p>"Why, those letters&mdash;weren't <hi rend="italic"> they</hi> beautiful, I'd like to 
know?" 
</p><p>The couple exchanged a glance, innocently allusive and amused 
on the wife's part, and charged with a sudden tragic significance 
on the husband's. 
</p><p>"Well, I've got to be going along to the office now," he 
merely said, dragging himself out of his rocking-chair. 

</p><p>This had happened while Ronald was still at school; and now 
Mrs. Grew slept in the Wingfield cemetery, under a life-size theo-<pb n="660"/> logical virtue of her own choosing, and Mr. Grew's 
prognostications as to Ronald's ability to "take right hold" in New 
York were being more and more brilliantly fulfilled. 
</p> 
</div2> 
<div2 type="section" n="2" id="d5"> 
<head> 
                        II 
</head> 

<p>RONALD obeyed his father's injunction not to come to luncheon 
on the day of the Bankshires' dinner; but in the middle of the 
following week Mr. Grew was surprised by a telegram from his son. 
</p><p>"Want to see you important matter.  Expect me to-morrow 
afternoon." 
</p><p>Mr. Grew received the telegram after breakfast.  To peruse it 
he had lifted his eye from a paragraph of the morning paper 
describing a fancy-dress dinner which had taken place the night 
before at the Hamilton Gliddens' for the house-warming of their new 
Fifth Avenue palace. 
</p><p>"Among the couples who afterward danced in the Poets' 
Quadrille were Miss Daisy Bankshire, looking more than usually 
lovely as Laura, and Mr. Ronald Grew as the young Petrarch." 
</p><p>Petrarch and Laura!  Well&mdash;if <hi rend="italic"> anything</hi> meant anything, Mr. 
Grew supposed he knew what that meant.  For weeks past he had 
noticed how constantly the names of the young people appeared 
together in the society notes he so insatiably devoured.  Even the 
soulless reporter was getting into the habit of coupling them in 
his lists.  And this Laura and Petrarch business was almost an 
announcement. . . 
</p><p>Mr. Grew dropped the telegram, wiped his eye-glasses, and re-read the paragraph.  "Miss Daisy Bankshire . . . more than usually 
lovely. . ."  Yes; she <hi rend="italic"> was</hi> lovely.  He had often seen her 
photograph in the papers&mdash;seen her represented in every conceivable 
attitude of the mundane game: fondling her prize bull-dog, taking 
a fence on her thoroughbred, dancing a <hi rend="italic"> gavotte</hi>, all patches and 
plumes, or fingering a guitar, all tulle and lilies; and once he 
had caught a glimpse of her at the theatre.  Hearing that Ronald 
was going to a fashionable first-night with the Bankshires, Mr. 
Grew had for once overcome his repugnance to following his son's 
movements, and had secured for himself, under the shadow of the 
balcony, a stall whence he could observe the Bankshire box without 
fear of detection.  Ronald had never known of his father's presence 
at the play; and for three blessed hours Mr. Grew had watched his 
boy's handsome dark head bent above the dense fair hair and white 
averted shoulder that were all he could catch of Miss Bankshire's 
beauties. 
</p><p>He recalled the vision now; and with it came, as usual, its 
ghostly double: the vision of his young self bending above such a 
white shoulder and such shining hair.  Needless to say that the 
real Mason Grew had never found himself in so enviable a situation.  
The late Mrs. Grew had no more resembled Miss Daisy Bankshire than 
he had looked like the happy victorious Ronald.  And the mystery 
was that from their dull faces, their dull endearments, the miracle 
of Ronald should have sprung.  It was almost&mdash;fantastically&mdash;as if 
the boy had been a changeling, child of a Latmian night, whom the 
divine companion of Mr. Grew's early reveries had secretly laid in 
the cradle of the Wingfield bedroom while Mr. And Mrs. Grew slept 
the deep sleep of conjugal indifference. 
</p><p>The young Mason Grew had not at first accepted this astral 
episode as the complete cancelling of his claims on romance.  He 
too had grasped at the high-hung glory; and, with his fatal 
tendency to reach too far when he reached at all, had singled out 
the prettiest girl in Wingfield.  When he recalled his stammered 
confession of love his face still tingled under her cool bright 
stare.  The wonder of his audacity had struck her dumb; and when 
she recovered her voice it was to fling a taunt at him. 
</p><p>"Don't be too discouraged, you know&mdash;have you ever thought of 
trying Addie Wicks?" 
</p><p>All Wingfield would have understood the gibe: Addie Wicks was 
the dullest girl in town.  And a year later he had married Addie 
Wicks. . . 

</p><p>He looked up from the perusal of Ronald's telegram with this 
memory in his mind.  Now at last his dream was coming true!  His 
boy would taste of the joys that had mocked his thwarted youth and 
his dull gray middle-age.  And it was fitting that they should be 
realized in Ronald's destiny.  Ronald was made to take happiness 
boldly by the hand and lead it home like a bridegroom.  He had the 
carriage, the confidence, the high faith in his fortune, that  
<pb n="661"/>  compel the wilful stars.  And, thanks to the Buckle, he would 
have the exceptional setting, the background of material elegance, 
that became his conquering person.  Since Mr. Grew had retired from 
business his investments had prospered, and he had been saving up 
his income for just such a contingency.  His own wants were few: he 
had transferred the Wingfield furniture to Brooklyn, and his 
sitting-room was a replica of that in which the long years of his 
married life had been spent.  Even the florid carpet on which 
Ronald's tottering footsteps had been taken was carefully matched 
when it became too threadbare.  And on the marble centre-table, 
with its chenille-fringed cover and bunch of dyed pampas grass, lay 
the illustrated Longfellow and the copy of Ingersoll's lectures 
which represented literature to Mr. Grew when he had led home his 
bride.  In the light of Ronald's romance, Mr. Grew found himself 
re-living, with a strange tremor of mingled pain and tenderness, 
all the poor prosaic incidents of his own personal history.  
Curiously enough, with this new splendor on them they began to emit 
a small faint ray of their own.  His wife's armchair, in its usual 
place by the fire, recalled her placid unperceiving presence, 
seated opposite to him during the long drowsy years; and he felt 
her kindness, her equanimity, where formerly he had only ached at 
her obtuseness.  And from the chair he glanced up at the large 
discolored photograph on the wall above, with a brittle brown 
wreath suspended on a corner of the frame.  The photograph 
represented a young man with a poetic necktie and untrammelled 
hair, leaning negligently against a Gothic chair-back, a roll of 
music in his hand; and beneath was scrawled a bar of Chopin, with 
the words: <hi rend="italic">" Adieu, Adele</hi>." 
</p><p>The portrait was that of the great pianist, Fortune 
Dolbrowski; and its presence on the wall of Mr. Grew's sitting-room 
commemorated the only exquisite hour of his life save that of 
Ronald's birth.  It was some time before the latter memorable 
event, a few months only after Mr. Grew's marriage, that he had 
taken his wife to New York to hear the great Dolbrowski.  Their 
evening had been magically beautiful, and even Addie, roused from 
her habitual inexpressiveness, had quivered into a momentary 
semblance of life.  "I never&mdash;I never&mdash;" she gasped out helplessly 
when they had regained their hotel bedroom, and sat staring back 
entranced at the evening's evocations.  Her large immovable face 
was pink and tremulous, and she sat with her hands on her knees, 
forgetting to roll up her bonnet-strings and prepare her curl-papers. 
</p><p>"I'd like to <hi rend="italic"> write</hi> him just how I felt&mdash;I wisht I knew 
how!" she burst out suddenly in a final effervescence of emotion. 
</p><p>Her husband lifted his head and looked at her. 
</p><p>"Would you?  I feel that way too," he said with a sheepish 
laugh.  And they continued to stare at each other shyly through a 
transfiguring mist of sound. 
</p><p>Mr. Grew recalled the scene as he gazed up at the pianist's 
faded photograph.  "Well, I owe her that anyhow&mdash;poor Addie!" he 
said, with a smile at the inconsequences of fate.  With Ronald's 
telegram in his hand he was in a mood to count his mercies. 
</p> 
</div2> 
<div2 type="section" n="3" id="d6"> 
<head>                           III 
</head> 

<p>"A CLEAR twenty-five thousand a year: that's what you can tell 
'em with my compliments," said Mr. Grew, glancing complacently 
across the centre-table at his boy's charming face. 
</p><p>It struck him that Ronald's gift for looking his part in life 
had never so romantically expressed itself.  Other young men, at 
such a moment, would have been red, damp, tight about the collar; 
but Ronald's cheek was only a shade paler, and the contrast made 
his dark eyes more expressive. 
</p><p>"A clear twenty-five thousand; yes, sir&mdash;that's what I always 
meant you to have." 
</p><p>Mr. Grew leaned back, his hands thrust carelessly in his 
pockets, as though to divert attention from the agitation of his 
features.  He had often pictured himself rolling out that phrase to 
Ronald, and now that it was actually on his lips he could not 
control their tremor. 
</p><p>Ronald listened in silence, lifting a nervous hand to his 
slight dark moustache, as though he, too, wished to hide some 
involuntary betrayal of emotion.  At first Mr. Grew took his 
silence for an expression of gratified surprise; but as it 
prolonged itself it became less easy to interpret. 
</p><p>"I&mdash;see here, my boy; did you expect more?  Isn't it enough?"  
Mr. Grew <pb n="662"/>  cleared his throat.  "Do <hi rend="italic"> they</hi> expect more?' he 
asked nervously.  He was hardly able to face the pain of inflicting 
a disappointment on Ronald at the very moment when he had counted 
on putting the final touch to his felicity. 
</p><p>Ronald moved uneasily in his chair and his eyes wandered 
upward to the laurel-wreathed photograph of the pianist above his 
father's head. 
</p><p><hi rend="italic">" Is</hi> it that, Ronald?  Speak out, my boy.  We'll see, we'll 
look round&mdash;I'll manage somehow." 
</p><p>"No, no," the young man interrupted, abruptly raising his hand 
as though to silence his father. 
</p><p>Mr. Grew recovered his cheerfulness.  "Well, what's the matter 
than, if <hi rend="italic"> she's</hi> willing?" 
</p><p>Ronald shifted his position again, and finally rose from his 
seat. 
</p><p>"Father&mdash;I&mdash;there's something I've got to tell you.  I can't 
take your money." 
</p><p>Mr. Grew sat speechless a moment, staring blankly at his son; 
then he emitted a puzzled laugh.  "My money?  What are you talking 
about?  What's this about my money?  Why, it ain't <hi rend="italic"> mine</hi>, Ronny; 
it's all yours&mdash;every cent of it!" he cried. 
</p><p>The young man met his tender look with a gaze of tragic 
rejection. 
</p><p>"No, no, it's not mine&mdash;not even in the sense you mean.  Not 
in any sense.  Can't you understand my feeling so?" 
</p><p>"Feeling so?  I don't know how you're feeling.  I don't know 
what you're talking about.  Are you too proud to touch any money 
you haven't earned?  Is that what you're trying to tell me?" 
</p><p>"No.  It's not that.  You must know&mdash;" 
</p><p>Mr. Grew flushed to the rim of his bristling whiskers.  "Know?  
Know <hi rend="italic"> what?</hi>  Can't you speak?" 
</p><p>Ronald hesitated, and the two men faced each other for a long 
strained moment, during which Mr. Grew's congested countenance grew 
gradually pale again. 
</p><p>"What's the meaning of this?  Is it because you've done 
something . . . something you're ashamed of . . . ashamed to tell 
me?" he suddenly gasped out; and walking around the table he laid 
his hand on his son's shoulder.  "There's nothing you can't tell 
me, my boy." 
</p><p>"It's not that.  Why do you make it so hard for me?" Ronald 
broke out with passion.  "You must have known this was sure to 
happen sooner or later." 
</p><p>"Happen?  What was sure to hap&mdash;?"  Mr. Grew's question 
wavered on his lip and passed into a tremulous laugh.  "Is it 
something <hi rend="italic"> I've</hi> done that you don't approve of?  Is it&mdash;is it 
<hi rend="italic"> 
the Buckle</hi> you're ashamed of, Ronald Grew?" 
</p><p>Ronald laughed too, impatiently.  "The Buckle?  No, I'm not 
ashamed of the Buckle; not any more than you are," he returned with 
a sudden bright flush.  "But I'm ashamed of all I owe to it&mdash;all I 
owe to you&mdash;when&mdash;when&mdash;"  He broke off and took a few distracted 
steps across the room.  "You might make this easier for me," he 
protested, turning back to his father. 
</p><p>"Make what easier?  I know less and less what you're driving 
at," Mr. Grew groaned. 
</p><p>Ronald's walk had once more brought him beneath the photograph 
on the wall.  He lifted his head for a moment and looked at it; 
then he looked again at Mr. Grew. 
</p><p>"Do you suppose I haven't always known?" 
</p><p>"Known&mdash;?" 
</p><p>"Even before you gave me those letters&mdash;after my mother's 
death&mdash;even before that, I suspected.  I don't know how it began . 
. . perhaps from little things you let drop . . . you and she . . 
. and resemblances that I couldn't help seeing . . . in myself . . 
.  How on earth could you suppose I shouldn't guess?  I always 
thought you gave me the letters as a way of telling me&mdash;" 
</p><p>Mr. Grew rose slowly from his chair.  "The letters?  
Dolbrowski's letters?" 
</p><p>Ronald nodded with white lips.  "You must remember giving them 
to me the day after the funeral." 
</p><p>Mr. Grew nodded back.  "Of course.  I wanted you to have 
everything your mother valued." 
</p><p>"Well&mdash;how could I help knowing after that?" 
</p><p>"Knowing <hi rend="italic"> what?"</hi>  Mr. Grew stood staring helplessly at his 
son.  Suddenly his look caught at a clue that seemed to confront it 
with a deeper bewilderment.  "You thought&mdash;you thought those 
letters . . . Dolbrowski's letters . . . you thought they meant . 
. ." 
</p><p>"Oh, it wasn't only the letters.  There were so many other 
signs.  My love of <pb n="663"/>  music&mdash;my&mdash;all my feelings about life . 
. . and art. . .  And when you gave me the letters I thought you 
must mean me to know." 
</p><p>Mr. Grew had grown quiet.  His lips were firm, and his small 
eyes looked out steadily from their creased lids. 
</p><p>"To know that you were Fortune Dolbrowski's son?" 
</p><p>Ronald made a mute sign of assent. 
</p><p>"I see.  And what did you mean to do?" 
</p><p>"I meant to wait till I could earn my living, and then repay 
you . . . as far as I can ever repay you. . .  But now that there's 
a chance of my marrying . . . and your generosity overwhelms me . 
. . I'm obliged to speak." 
</p><p>"I see," said Mr. Grew again.  He let himself down into his 
chair, looking steadily and not unkindly at the young man.  "Sit 
down, Ronald.  Let's talk." 
</p><p>Ronald made a protesting movement.  "Is anything to be gained 
by it?  You can't change me&mdash;change what I feel.  The reading of 
those letters transformed my whole life&mdash;I was a boy till then: 
they made a man of me.  From that moment I understood myself."  He 
paused, and then looked up at Mr. Grew's face.  "Don't imagine I 
don't appreciate your kindness&mdash;your extraordinary generosity.  But 
I can't go through life in disguise.  And I want you to know that 
I have not won Daisy under false pretences&mdash;" 
</p><p>Mr. Grew started up with the first expletive Ronald had ever 
heard on his lips. 
</p><p>"You damned young fool, you, you haven't <hi rend="italic"> told</hi> her&mdash;?" 
</p><p>Ronald raised his head quickly.  "Oh, you don't know her, sir!  
She thinks no worse of me for knowing my secret.  She is above and 
beyond all such conventional prejudices.  She's <hi rend="italic"> proud</hi> of my 
parentage&mdash;" he straightened his slim young shoulders&mdash;"as I'm 
proud of it . . . yes, sir, proud of it. . ." 
</p><p>Mr. Grew sank back into his seat with a dry laugh.  "Well, you 
ought to be.  You come of good stock.  And you're father's son, 
every inch of you!"  He laughed again, as though the humor of the 
situation grew on him with its closer contemplation. 
</p><p>"Yes, I've always felt that," Ronald murmured, flushing. 
</p><p>"Your father's son, and no mistake."  Mr. Grew leaned forward.  
"You're the son of as big a fool as yourself.  And here he sits, 
Ronald Grew." 
</p><p>The young man's flush deepened to crimson; but Mr. Grew 
checked his reply with a decisive gesture.  "Here he sits, with all 
your young nonsense still alive in him.  Don't you see the 
likeness?  If you don't, I'll tell you the story of those letters." 
</p><p>Ronald stared.  "What do you mean?  Don't they tell their own 
story?" 
</p><p>"I supposed they did when I gave them to you; but you've given 
it a twist that needs straightening out."  Mr. Grew squared his 
elbows on the table, and looked at the young man across the gift-books and the dyed pampas grass.  "I wrote all the letters that 
Dolbrowski answered." 
</p><p>Ronald gave back his look in frowning perplexity.  "You wrote 
them?  I don't understand.  His letters are all addressed to my 
mother." 
</p><p>"Yes.  And he thought he was corresponding with her." 
</p><p>"But my mother&mdash;what did she think?" 
</p><p>Mr. Grew hesitated, puckering his thick lids.  "Well, I guess 
she kinder thought it was a joke.  Your mother didn't think about 
things much." 
</p><p>Ronald continued to bend a puzzled frown on the question.  "I 
don't understand," he reiterated. 
</p><p>Mr. Grew cleared his throat with a nervous laugh.  "Well, I 
don't know as you ever will&mdash;<hi rend="italic"> quite</hi>.  But this is the way it 
came about.  I had a toughish time of it when I was young.  Oh, I 
don't mean so much the fight I had to put up to make my way&mdash;there 
was always plenty of fight in me.  But inside of myself it was 
kinder lonesome.  And the outside didn't attract callers."  He 
laughed again, with an apologetic gesture toward his broad blinking 
face.  "When I went round with the other young fellows I was always 
the forlorn hope&mdash;the one that had to eat the drumsticks and dance 
with the left-overs.  As sure as there was a blighter at a picnic 
I had to swing her, and feed her, and drive her home.  And all the 
time I was mad after all the things you've got&mdash;poetry and music 
and all the joy-forever business.  So there were the pair of us&mdash;my 
face and my imagination&mdash;chained together, and fighting, and hating 
each other like poison. 
</p><p>"Then your mother came along and took pity on me.  It sets up 
a gawky fellow to <pb n="664"/>  find a girl who ain't ashamed to be seen 
walking with him Sundays.  And I was grateful to your mother, and 
we got along first-rate.  Only I couldn't say things to her&mdash;and 
she couldn't answer.  Well&mdash;one day, a few months after we were 
married, Dolbrowski came to New York, and the whole place went wild 
about him.  I'd never heard any good music, but I'd always had an 
inkling of what it must be like, though I couldn't tell you to this 
day how I knew.  Well, your mother read about him in the papers 
too, and she thought it'd be the swagger thing to go to New York 
and hear him play&mdash;so we went. . .  I'll never forget that evening.  
Your mother wasn't easily stirred up&mdash;she never seemed to need to 
let off steam.  But that night she seemed to understand the way I 
felt.  And when we got back to the hotel she said suddenly: 'I'd 
like to tell him how I feel.  I'd like to sit right down and write 
to him.' 
</p><p>"'Would you?' I said.  'So would I.' 
</p><p>"There was paper and pens there before us, and I pulled a 
sheet toward me, and began to write.  'Is this what you'd like to 
say to him?' I asked her when the letter was done.  And she got 
pink and said: 'I don't understand it, but it's lovely.'  And she 
copied it out and signed her name to it, and sent it." 
</p><p>Mr. Grew paused, and Ronald sat silent, with lowered eyes. 
</p><p>That's how it began; and that's where I thought it would end.  
But it didn't, because Dolbrowski answered.  His first letter was 
dated January 10, 1872.  I guess you'll find I'm correct.  Well, I 
went back to hear him again, and I wrote him after the performance, 
and he answered again.  And after that we kept it up for six 
months.  Your mother always copied the letters and signed them.  
She seemed to think it was a kinder joke, and she was proud of his 
answering my letters.  But she never went back to New York to hear 
him, though I saved up enough to give her the treat again.  She was 
too lazy, and she let me go without her.  I heard him three times 
in New York; and in the spring he came to Wingfield and played once 
at the Academy.  Your mother was sick and couldn't go; so I went 
alone.  After the performance I meant to get one of the directors 
to take me in to see him; but when the time came, I just went back 
home and wrote to him instead.  And the month after, before he went 
back to Europe, he sent your mother a last little note, and that 
picture hanging up there. . ." 
</p><p>Mr. Grew paused again, and both men lifted their eyes to the 
photograph. 
</p><p>"Is that all?" Ronald slowly asked. 
</p><p>"That's all&mdash;every bit of it," said Mr. Grew. 
</p><p>"And my mother&mdash;my mother never even spoke to Dolbrowski?" 
</p><p>"Never.  She never even saw him but that once in New York at 
his concert." 
</p><p>"The blood crept again to Ronald's face.  "Are you sure of 
that, sir?" he asked in a trembling voice. 
</p><p>"Sure as I am that I'm sitting here.  Why, she was too lazy to 
look at his letters after the first novelty wore off.  She copied 
the answers just to humor me&mdash;but she always said she couldn't 
understand what we wrote." 
</p><p>"But how could you go on with such a correspondence?  It's 
incredible!" 
</p><p>Mr. Grew looked at his son thoughtfully.  "I suppose it is, to 
you.  You've only had to put out your hand and get the things I was 
starving for&mdash;music, and good talk, and ideas.  Those letters gave 
me all that.  You've read them, and you know that Dolbrowski was 
not only a great musician but a great man.  There was nothing 
beautiful he didn't see, nothing fine he didn't feel.  For six 
months I breathed his air, and I've lived on it ever since.  Do you 
begin to understand a little now?" 
</p><p>"Yes&mdash;a little.  But why write in my mother's name?  Why make 
it a sentimental correspondence?" 
</p><p>Mr. Grew reddened to his bald temples.  "Why, I tell you it 
began that way, as a kinder joke.  And when I saw that the first 
letter pleased and interested him, I was afraid to tell him&mdash;<hi rend="italic"> I 
couldn't</hi> tell him.  Do you suppose he'd gone on writing if he'd 
ever seen me, Ronny?" 
</p><p>Ronald suddenly looked at him with new eyes.  "But he must 
have thought your letters very beautiful&mdash;to go on as he did," he 
broke out. 
</p><p>"Well&mdash;I did my best," said Mr. Grew modestly. 
</p><p>Ronald pursued his idea.  "Where <hi rend="italic"> are</hi> all your letters, I 
wonder?  Weren't they returned to you at his death?" 
</p><p>Mr. Grew laughed.  "Lord, no.  I guess he had trunks and 
trunks full of better ones. <pb n="665"/>  I guess Queens and Empresses 
wrote to him." 
</p><p>"I should have liked to see your letters," the young man 
insisted. 
</p><p>"Well, they weren't bad," said Mr. Grew drily.  "But I'll tell 
you one thing, Ronny," he added suddenly.  Ronald raised his head 
with a quick glance, and Mr. Grew continued: "I'll tell you where 
the best of those letters is&mdash;it's in <hi rend="italic"> you</hi>.  If it hadn't been 
for that one look at life I couldn't have made you what you are.  
Oh, I know you've done a good deal of your own making&mdash;but I've 
been there behind you all the time.  And you'll never know the work 
I've spared you and the time I've saved you.  Fortune Dolbrowski 
helped me do that.  I never saw things in little again after I'd 
looked at 'em with him.  And I tried to give you the big view from 
the stars. . .  So that's what became of my letters." 
</p><p>Mr. Grew paused, and for a long time Ronald sat motionless, 
his elbows on the table, his face dropped on his hands. 
</p><p>Suddenly Mr. Grew's touch fell on his shoulder. 
</p><p>"Look at here, Ronald Grew&mdash;do you want me to tell you how 
you're feeling at this minute?  Just a mite let down, after all, at 
the idea that you ain't the romantic figure you'd got to think 
yourself. . .  Well, that's natural enough, too; but I'll tell you 
what it proves.  It proves you're my son right enough, if any more 
proof was needed.  For it's just the kind of fool nonsense I used 
to feel at your age&mdash;and if there's anybody here to laugh at it's 
myself, and not you.  And you can laugh at me just as much as you 
like. . ." 
</p> 
 
</div2> 
</div1> 
</body> 
</text> 
</TEI.2> 
