<?xml version="1.0"?>

<?dlps id="WhaGood"?>
<?dlps page-images="none" figure-images="no"?>
<?dlps transcription="other"?>

<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/tei-p4/tei2.dtd" [
<!ENTITY % POSTKB "INCLUDE">
<!ENTITY % TEI.extensions.ent SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.ent">
<!ENTITY % TEI.extensions.dtd SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.dtd">
<!ENTITY % ISOnum SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/charent/iso-num.ent"> %ISOnum;
<!ENTITY % ISOpub SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/charent/iso-pub.ent"> %ISOpub;

]>

<TEI.2 id="WhaGood"> 
<teiHeader type="migrated" creator="Etext">
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title type="main">That Good May Come</title>
<title type="sort">that good may come</title>
<author>Wharton, Edith, 1862-1937</author>
<respStmt>
<resp>Creation of machine-readable version:</resp>
<name>Judy Boss</name>
</respStmt>
<respStmt>
<resp>Conversion to TEI-conformant markup:</resp>
<name>University of Virginia Library Electronic Text Center</name>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt> 
<extent>ca. <num type="kilobytes">57</num> kilobytes</extent> 
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>University of Virginia Library</publisher>
<pubPlace>Charlottesville, Virginia</pubPlace>
<idno type="ETC">WhaGood</idno> 
<date value="1995">1995</date>
<availability status="public">
<p n="copyright">Copyright &copy; 1995 by the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia</p>
<p n="access">Publicly accessible</p>
</availability>
<idno type="uva-pid">uva-lib:476494</idno>
</publicationStmt>
<seriesStmt>
<title>University of Virginia Library, Text collection</title>
<idno type="uva-set">UVA-LIB-Text</idno>
</seriesStmt> 
<sourceDesc>
<biblFull>
<titleStmt>
<title type="main">That Good May Come</title>
<title type="sort">that good may come</title>
<author>Wharton, Edith</author>
</titleStmt> 
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>Scribner's Magazine</publisher>
<date value="1894-05">May 1894</date>
</publicationStmt> 
<notesStmt>
<note>
<p>Vol. 15</p>
</note>
</notesStmt>
</biblFull>
</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc> 
<encodingDesc>
<projectDesc>
<p>Prepared for the University of Virginia Library Electronic Text Center</p>
</projectDesc> 
<editorialDecl>
<p>All quotation marks retained as data</p> 
<p>Verification made against printed text</p> 
<p id="ETC">Keywords in the header are a local Electronic Text Center scheme  
to aid in establishing analytical groupings</p>
</editorialDecl> 
<refsDecl>
<p>ID elements are given for each page element and are composed of the text's 
unique cryptogram and the given page number, as in SpeFQue1 for page one of  
Spenser's Faerie Queene.</p>
</refsDecl>
</encodingDesc> 
<profileDesc>
<creation>
<date value="1894">1894</date>
</creation> 
<langUsage>
<language id="eng" usage="main">English</language>
</langUsage> 
<textClass>
<keywords>
<term>fiction</term>
<term>prose</term>
<term>verse</term>
</keywords>
</textClass>
</profileDesc> 
<revisionDesc>
<change>
<date value="1995-01">January 1995</date> 
<respStmt>
<resp>corrector</resp>
<name>David Seaman and Kelly Tetterton</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Header and basic TEI SGML encoding added</item>
</change> 
<change>
<date value="2005-07">July 2005</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>Corrector</resp>
<name>Margaret Konkol</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Converted SGML to XML and fixed tagging.</item>
</change>
<change>
<date value="2007-09">September 2007</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>Migration</resp>
<name>Ethan Gruber, University of Virginia Library</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Converted XML markup from TEI Lite to uva-dl-tei (TEI P4 with local customizations).</item>
</change>
<change>
<date value="2008-01">January 2008</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>Migration</resp>
<name>Greg Murray, University of Virginia Library</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Programmatically updated TEI header markup (but not header content) for minimal compliance with current QA requirements.</item>
</change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader> 
<text id="d1">  
<body id="d2"> 
<div1 type="story" id="d3"> 
<head> 
Wharton, Edith.  "That Good May Come."   
<lb/> 
<hi rend="italic"> Scribner's Magazine</hi> 15 (May 1894): 629-642. 
</head> 
<pb n="629"/>  

<p>"OH, it's the same old story," said Birkton, impatiently.  
"They've all come home to roost, as usual." 
</p><p>He glanced at a heap of type-written pages which lay on the 
shabby desk at his elbow; then, pushing back his chair, he began to 
stride up and down the length of the little bedroom in which he and 
Helfenridge sat. 
</p><p>"What magazines have you tried?" 
</p><p>"All the good ones&mdash;every one.  Nobody wants poetry nowadays.  
One of the editors told me the other day that it 'was going out.'" 
</p><p>Helfenridge picked up the sheet which lay nearest him and 
began to read, half to himself, half aloud, with a warmth of 
undertoned emphasis which made the lines glow. 
</p><p>Neither of the men was far beyond twenty-five.  Birkton, the 
younger of the two, had the musing, irresolute profile of the 
dreamer of dreams; while his friend, stouter, squarer, of more 
clayey make, was nevertheless too much like him to prove a useful 
counterpoise. 
</p><p>"I always liked 'The Old Odysseus,'" Helfenridge murmured.  
"There's something tremendously suggestive in that fancy of yours, 
that tradition has misrepresented the real feelings of all the 
great heroes and heroines; or rather, has only handed down to us 
the official statement of their sentiments, as an epitaph records 
the obligatory virtues which the defunct ought to have had, if he 
hadn't.  That theory, now, that Odysseus never really forgot Circe; 
and that Esther was in love with Haman, and decoyed him to the 
banquet with Ahasuerus just for the sake of once having him near 
her and hearing him speak; and that Dante, perhaps, if he could 
have been brought to book, would have had to confess for caring a 
great deal more for the <hi rend="italic"> pietosa donna</hi> of the window than for 
the mummified memory of a long-dead Beatrice&mdash;well, you know, it 
tallies wonderfully with the inconsequences and surprises that one 
is always discovering under the superficial fitnesses of life." 
</p><p>"Ah," said Birkton, "I meant to get a cycle of poems out of 
that idea&mdash;but what's the use, when I can't even get the first one 
into print?" 
</p><p>"You've tried sending 'The Old Odysseus'?" 
</p><p>Birkton nodded. 
</p><p>"To 'Scribner's' and 'The Century'?" 
</p><p>"And all the rest." 
</p><p>"Queer!" protested Helfenridge.  "If I were an editor&mdash;now 
this, for instance, is so fine:</p> 
<lg type="verse"> 
<l><hi rend="italic"> "'Circe, Circe, the sharp anguish of that last</hi></l> 
<l>        long speechless night</l> 
<l>     With the flame of tears unfallen scorches still</l> 
<l>        mine aching sight;</l> 
<l>     Still I feel the thunderous blackness of the hot</l> 
<l>        sky overhead,</l> 
<l>     While we two with close-locked fingers through</l> 
<l>        thy pillared porches strayed,</l> 
<l>     And athwart the sullen darkness, from the</l> 
<l>        shadow-muffled shore,</l> 
<l>     Heard aghast the savage summons of the sea's</l> 
<l>        incoming roar,</l> 
<l>     Shouting like a voice from Ilium, wailing like</l> 
<l>        a voice from home,</l> 
<l>     Shrieking through the pillared porches, Up,</l> 
<l>        Odysseus, wake and come!'</l> 
</lg> 
<p>"Devil take it, why isn't there an audience for that sort of 
thing?  And this line too&mdash;</p> 
<lg type="verse"> 
<l><hi rend="italic"> "'Where Persephone remembers the Trinacrian</hi></l> 
<l>        buds and bees&mdash;</l> <pb n="630"/>  
</lg> 
<p>what a light, allegretto movement it has, following on all that 
gloom and horror!  Ah&mdash;and here's that delicious little nocturne 
from 'The New and the Old.'</p> 
<lg type="verse"> 
<l>     <hi rend="italic"> "'Before the yellow dawn is up,</hi></l> 
 <l>            With pomp of shield and shaft,</l> 
<l>          Drink we of night's fast ebbing cup</l> 
<l>             One last delicious draught.</l></lg> 
<lg type="verse"> 
<l>         'The shadowy wine of night is sweet,</l> 
<l>             With subtle, slumberous fumes</l> 
<l>          Pressed by the Hours' melodious feet</l> 
<l>             From bloodless elder-blooms.'</l></lg> 

<p>"There&mdash;isn't that just like a little bacchanalian scene on a 
Greek gem?" 
</p><p>"Oh, don't go on," said Birkton sharply, "I'm sick of them." 
</p><p>"Don't say that," Helfenridge rebuked him.  "It's like 
disowning one's own children.  But if they say that mythology and 
classicism and <hi rend="italic"> plastik</hi> are played out&mdash;if they want Manet in 
place of David, or Cazin instead of Claude&mdash;why don't they like 
'Boulterby Ridge,' with its grim mystery intensified by a setting 
of such modern realism?  What lines there are in that!</p> 
<lg type="verse"> 
<l><hi rend="italic"> "'It was dark on Boulterby Ridge, with an ulti-</hi></l> 
<l>        mate darkness like death,</l> 
<l>     And the weak wind flagged and gasped like</l> 
<l>       a sick man straining for breath,</l> 
<l>     And one star's ineffectual flicker shot pale</l> 
<l>        through a gap in the gloom,</l> 
<l>     As faint as the taper that struggles with night</l> 
<l>        in the sick man's room.'</l> 
</lg> 
<p>"There's something about that beginning that makes me feel 
quietly cold from head to foot.  And how charming the description 
of the girl is:</p> 
<lg type="verse"> 
<l><hi rend="italic"> "'She walked with a springing step, as if to some</hi></l> 
 <l>       inner tune,</l> 
<l>     And her cheeks had the lucent pink of maple-</l> 
<l>        wings in June.'</l></lg>

<p>"There's Millet and nature for you!  And then when he meets 
her ghost on Boulterby Ridge&mdash; </p>
<lg type="verse"> 
<l><hi rend="italic"> "'White in the palpable black as a lily moored</hi></l> 
<l>        on a moat'&mdash;</l></lg>
<p>
what a contrast, eh?  And the deadly hopeless chill of the last 
line, too&mdash;</p> 
<lg type="verse"> 
<l><hi rend="italic"> "'For the grave is deeper than grief, and longer</hi></l> 
<l>        than life is death.'</l></lg>

<p>"By Jove, I don't see how that could be improved!" 
</p><p>"Neither do I," said Birkton, bitterly, "more's the pity." 
</p><p>"And what comes next?  Ah, that strange sonnet on the Cinque 
Cento.  Did you ever carry out your scheme of writing a series of 
sonnets embodying all the great epochs of art?" 
</p><p>"No," said Birkton, indifferently. 
</p><p>"It seems a pity, after such a fine beginning.  Now just 
listen to this&mdash;listen to it as if it had been written by somebody 
else:</p> 
<lg type="verse"> 
<l><hi rend="italic"> "'Strange hour of art's august ascendency</hi></l> 
<l>     When Sin and Beauty, the old lovers, met</l> 
<l>     In a new paradise, still sword-beset</l> 
<l>     With monkish terrors, but wherein the tree</l> 
<l>     Of knowledge held its golden apples free</l> 
<l>     To lips unstayed by hell's familiar threat;</l> 
<l>     And men, grown mad upon the fruit they</l> 
<l>        ate,</l> 
<l>     Dreamed a wild dream of lust and liberty;</l> 
<l>     Strange hour, when the dead gods arose in</l> 
<l>        Rome</l> 
<l>     From altars where the mass was sacrificed,</l> 
<l>     When Phryne flaunted on the tiaraed tomb</l> 
<l>     Of him who dearly sold the grace unpriced,</l> 
<l>     And, twixt old shames and infamies to come,</l> 
<l>     Cellini in his prison talked with Christ!'</l></lg> 

<p>"There now, don't you call that a very happy definition of the 
most magical moment the world has ever known?" 
</p><p>"Don't," said Birkton, with an impatient gesture.  "You're 
very good, old man, but don't go on." 
</p><p>Helfenridge, with a sigh, replaced the loose sheets on the 
desk. 
</p><p>"Well," he repeated, "I can't understand it.  But the tide's 
got to turn, Maurice&mdash;it's got to.  Don't forget that." 
</p><p>Birkton laughed drearily. 
</p><p>"Haven't you had a single opening&mdash;not one since I saw you?" 
</p><p>"Not one; at least nothing to speak of," said Birkton, 
reddening.  "I've had one offer, but what do you suppose it was?  
Do you remember that idiotic squib that I wrote the other day about 
Mrs. Tolquitt's being seen alone with Dick Blason at Koster &amp; 
Bial's?  The thing I read that night in Bradley's rooms after 
supper?" 
</p><p>Helfenridge nodded. 
</p><p>"Well, I'm sorry I read it now.  Somebody must have betrayed 
me (of course, though no names are mentioned, <pb n="631"/>  they all knew 
who was meant), for who should turn up yesterday but Baker Buley, 
the editor of the <hi rend="italic"> Social Kite</hi>, with an offer of a hundred and 
fifty dollars for my poem." 
</p><p>"You didn't, Maurice&mdash;?" 
</p><p>"Hang you, Helfenridge, what do you take me for?  I told him 
to go to the devil." 
</p><p>There was a long pause, during which Helfenridge relit his 
pipe.  Then he said, "But the book reviews in the <hi rend="italic"> Symbolic</hi> keep 
you going, don't they?" 
</p><p>"After a fashion," said Birkton, with a shrug.  "Luckily my 
mother has had a tremendous lot of visiting-lists to make up 
lately, and she has written the invitations for half the balls that 
have been given this winter, so that between us we manage to keep 
Annette and ourselves alive; but God knows what would happen if one 
of us fell ill." 
</p><p>"Something else will happen before that.  You'll be offered a 
hundred and fifty dollars for one of <hi rend="italic"> those</hi>," said Helfenridge, 
pointing to the pile of verses. 
</p><p>"I wish you were an editor!" Birkton retorted. 
</p><p>Helfenridge rose, picking up his battered gray hat, and 
slipping his pipe into his pocket.  "I'm not an editor and I'm no 
good at all," he said, mournfully. 
</p><p>"Don't say that, old man.  It's been the saving of me to be 
believed in by somebody." 
</p><p>Their hands met closely, and with a quick nod and inarticulate 
grunt Helfenridge turned from the room. 
</p><p>Maurice, left alone, dropped the smile which he had assumed to 
speed his friend, and sank into the nearest chair.  His eyes, the 
sensitive eyes of the seer whom Beauty has anointed with her 
mysterious unguent, travelled painfully about the little room.  Not 
a detail of it but was stamped upon his mind with a morbid 
accuracy&mdash;the yellowish-brown paper which had peeled off here and 
there, revealing the discolored plaster beneath; the ink-stained 
desk at which all his poems had been written; the rickety wash-stand of ash, with a strip of marbled oil-cloth nailed over it, and 
a cracked pitcher and basin; the gas-stove in which a low flame 
glimmered, the blurred looking-glass, and the book-case which held 
his thirty or forty worn volumes; yet he never took note of his 
sordid surroundings without a fresh movement of disgust. 
</p><p>"And this is our best room," he muttered to himself. 
</p><p>His mother and sister slept in the next room, which opened on 
an air-shaft in the centre of the house, and beyond that was the 
kitchen, drawing its ventilation from the same shaft, and sending 
its smells with corresponding facility into the room occupied by 
the two women. 
</p><p>The apartment in which they lived, by courtesy called a flat, 
was in reality a thinly disguised tenement in one of those ignoble 
quarters of New York where the shabby has lapsed into the degraded.  
They had moved there a year earlier, leaving reluctantly, under 
pressure of a diminished purse, the pleasant little flat up-town, 
with its three bedrooms and sunny parlor, which had been their 
former home.  Maurice winced when he remembered that he had made 
the change imperative by resigning his clerkship in a wholesale 
warehouse in order to give more leisure to the writing of the 
literary criticisms with which he supplied the <hi rend="italic"> Symbolic Weekly 
Review</hi>.  His mother had approved, had even urged his course; but 
in the unsparing light of poverty it showed as less inevitable than 
he had imagined.  And then, somehow, the great novel, which he had 
planned to write as soon as he should be released from his clerical 
task, was still in embryo.  He had time and to spare, but his pen 
persisted in turning to sonnets, and only the opening chapters of 
the romance had been summarily blocked out.  All this was not very 
satisfactory, and Maurice was glad to be called from the 
contemplation of facts so unamiable by the sound of his mother's 
voice in the adjoining room. 
</p><p>"Maurice, dear, has your friend gone?" Mrs. Birkton asked, 
advancing timidly across the threshold.  She had the step and 
gesture of one who has spent her best energies in a vain endeavor 
to propitiate fate, and her small, pale face was like a palimpsest 
on which the record of suffering had been so deeply written that 
its original lines were concealed beyond recovery. <pb n="632"/>  
</p><p>"If you are not writing, Maurice," she continued, "I might 
come and finish Mrs. Rushingham's list and save the gas for an hour 
longer.  The light is so good at your window." 
</p><p>"Come," said Maurice, sweeping the poems into his desk and 
pushing a chair forward for his mother. 
</p><p>Mrs. Birkton, as she seated herself and opened her neat blank-book, glanced up almost furtively into her son's face. 
</p><p>"No news, dear?" she asked, in a low tone. 
</p><p>"None," said Maurice, briefly.  "I tried the editor of the <hi rend="italic"> 
Inter Oceanic</hi> when I was out just now, and he likes The Old 
Odysseus and Boulterby Ridge very much, but they aren't exactly 
suited to his purpose.  That's their formula, you know." 
</p><p>Mrs. Birkton dipped her fine steel pen into the inkstand, and 
began to write, in a delicate copperplate hand: 
</p><p><hi rend="italic"> Mrs. Albert Lowbridge, 14 East Seventy-fifth Street.</hi> 
</p><p>Mrs. Charles M. McManus, 910 Fifth Avenue. 
</p><p>The Misses McManus, 910 Fifth Avenue. 
</p><p>Mr. &amp; Mrs. Hugh Lovermore, 30 East Ninety-Sixth Street. 
</p><p>She wrote on in silence, but Maurice, who had seated himself 
near her, saw a glimmer of tears on her thin lashes as her head 
moved mechanically to and fro with the motion of the pen. 
</p><p>"Well," he said, trying for a more cheerful note, <hi rend="italic">" your</hi> 
literary productions are always in demand, at all events.  Mrs. 
Stapleton's ball ought to bring you in a very tidy little sum.  
Some one told me the other day that she was going to send out two 
thousand invitations." 
</p><p>"Oh, Maurice&mdash;the Stapleton ball!  Haven't you heard?" 
</p><p>"What about it?" 
</p><p>"Mr. Seymour Carbridge, Mrs. Stapleton's uncle, died 
yesterday, and the ball is given up." 
</p><p>Maurice rose from his seat with a movement of dismay. 
</p><p>"The stars in their courses fight against us!" he exclaimed.  
"I'm afraid this will make a great difference to you, won't it, 
mother?" 
</p><p>"It does make a difference," she assented, writing on 
uninterruptedly.  "You see I was to have rewritten her whole 
visiting-list, besides doing the invitations to the ball.  And Lent 
comes so early this year." 
</p><p>Maurice was silent, and for some twenty minutes Mrs. Birkton's 
pen continued to move steadily forward over the ruled sheets of the 
visiting-book.  The short January afternoon was fast darkening into 
a snowy twilight, and Maurice presently stretched out his hand 
toward the match-box which lay on the desk. 
</p><p>"Oh, Maurice, don't light the gas yet.  I can see quite well, 
and you had better keep the stove going a little longer.  It's so 
cold." 
</p><p>"Why not have both?" 
</p><p>"You extravagant boy!  When it gets really dark I shall take 
my writing into the kitchen, but meanwhile it is so much pleasanter 
here; and I don't believe Annette has lit the kitchen stove yet.  
I haven't heard her come in." 
</p><p>"Where has she been this afternoon?" 
</p><p>"At her confirmation class.  Father Thurifer holds a class 
every afternoon this week in the chantry.  You know Annette is to 
be confirmed next Sunday." 
</p><p>"Is she?  No&mdash;I had forgotten." 
</p><p>"But she must have come in by this time," Mrs. Birkton 
continued, with a glance at the darkening window.  "Go and see, 
dear, will you?" 
</p><p>Maurice obediently stepped out into the narrow passage-way 
which led from his bedroom to the kitchen.  The kitchen door was 
shut, and as he opened it he came abruptly upon the figure of a 
young girl, seated in an attitude of tragic self-abandonment at the 
deal table in the middle of the room.  She had evidently just come 
in, for her shabby hat and jacket and two or three devotional-looking little volumes lay on a chair at her side.  Her arms were 
flung out across the table, with her face hidden between, so that 
the bluish glimmer of the gas-jet overhead, vaguely outlining her 
figure, seemed to concentrate all its light upon the mass of her 
wheat-colored braids.  At the sound of the opening door she sprang 
up sud-<pb n="633"/> denly, turning upon Maurice a small disordered face, 
with red lids and struggling mouth.  She was evidently not more 
than fifteen years old and her undeveloped figure and little round 
face, in its setting of pale hair, presented that curious mixture 
of maturity and childishness often seen in girls of her age who 
have been carefully watched over at home, yet inevitably exposed to 
the grim diurnal spectacle of poverty and degradation. 
</p><p>"Annette!" Maurice said, catching the hand with which she 
tried to hide her face. 
</p><p>"Oh, Maurice, don't&mdash;don't please!" she entreated, "I wasn't 
crying&mdash;I wasn't!  I was only a little tired; and it was so cold 
walking home from church." 
</p><p>"If you are cold, why haven't you lit the stove?" he asked, 
giving her time to regain her composure. 
</p><p>"I will&mdash;I was going to." 
</p><p>"Carry your things to your room, and I'll light it for you." 
</p><p>"As he spoke his eye fell on the slim little volumes at her 
side, and he picked up one, which was emblazoned with a cross, 
surmounted by the title: "Passion Flowers." 
</p><p>"And so you are going to be confirmed very soon, Annette?" he 
asked, his glance wandering over the wide-margined pages with their 
reiterated invocations in delicate italics: 

</p><p><hi rend="italic"> O Jesu Christ!  Eternal sweetness of them 
that love Thee,</hi> 
</p><p>O Jesu, Paradise of delights and very glory of 
the Angels, 
</p><p>O Jesu, mirror of everlasting love, 
</p><p>O King most lovely, and Loving One most dear, 
impress I pray Thee, O Lord Jesus, all Thy 
wounds upon my heart! 

</p><p>Annette's face was smoothed into instant serenity.  "Next 
Sunday&mdash;just think, Maurice, only three days more to wait!  It will 
be Sexagesima Sunday, you know." 
</p><p>"Will it?  And are you glad to be confirmed?" 
</p><p>"Oh, Maurice!  I have waited so long&mdash;some girls are confirmed 
at thirteen." 
</p><p>"Are they?  And why did you have to wait?" 
</p><p>"Because Father Thurifer thought it best," she answered, 
humbly.  "You see I am very young for my age, and very stupid in 
some ways.  He was afraid that I might not understand all the holy 
mysteries." 
</p><p>"And do you now?" 
</p><p>"Oh, yes&mdash;as well as a girl can presume to.  At least Father 
Thurifer says so." 
</p><p>"That is very nice," said Maurice.  "Now run away and I'll 
light the fire.  Mother will be coming soon to sit here." 
</p><p>He went back to his bedroom, where Mrs. Birkton's pen, in the 
thickening obscurity, still travelled unremittingly over the smooth 
pages. 
</p><p>"Mother, what's the matter with Annette?  When I went into the 
kitchen I found her crying." 
</p><p>Mrs. Birkton pushed her work aside with a vexed exclamation. 
</p><p>"Poor child!" she said.  "After all, Maurice, she is only a 
child; one can't be too hard on her." 
</p><p>"Hard on her?  But why?  What's the matter?" 
</p><p>"You see," continued Mrs. Birkton, who invariably put her 
apologies before her explanations, "she would never have allowed 
herself to think of it if we hadn't been so sure of the Stapleton 
ball." 
</p><p>"To think of what?" 
</p><p>"Her white dress, Maurice, her confirmation dress.  At the 
Church of the Precious Blood all the girls are confirmed in white 
muslin dresses, with tulle veils and <hi rend="italic"> moire</hi> sashes.  Father 
Thurifer makes a point of it." 
</p><p>"And you promised Annette such a dress?" 
</p><p>"I thought I might, dear, when Mrs. Stapleton decided to give 
her ball.  You see there is a very large class of candidates for 
confirmation, and I knew it would be very trying for Annette to be 
the only one not dressed in white&mdash;and at such a solemn time, too.  
But now, of course, she will have to give it up." 
</p><p>"Yes," said Maurice, absently.  He stood with his hands in his 
pockets, his unseeing eyes fixed upon the yellow gleam of the gas-stove, which was now the only point of light in the room. <pb n="634"/>  
</p><p>"And that is what Annette is crying about?" he asked at 
length. 
</p><p>"Poor child," murmured his mother, deprecatingly; "it is such 
a solemn moment, Maurice." 
</p><p>"Yes, yes&mdash;I know.  That's just it.  That's why I don't 
understand&mdash;Annette is a very religious girl, isn't she?" 
</p><p>"Father Thurifer tells me that he has never seen a more 
religious nature.  He said that it was as natural to her to believe 
as to breathe.  Isn't that such a beautiful expression?" 
</p><p>"And yet&mdash;yet&mdash;at such a solemn moment, as you say, it is the 
color of her dress that is uppermost in her mind?" 
</p><p>"Oh, Maurice, don't you see that it is just because she has so 
much devotional feeling, poor child, that she suffers at the 
thought of not appearing worthily at such a time?" 
</p><p>"As if Mrs. Stapleton should ask me to lead the cotillion at 
her ball when my dress coat is in pawn?" 
</p><p>"Maurice!" said his mother. 
</p><p>"I beg your pardon, mother; I didn't mean that; forgive me.  
But it all seems so queer&mdash;I don't understand." 
</p><p>"I wish you went oftener to church, Maurice," said Mrs. 
Birkton, sadly. 
</p><p>"I wish I understood Annette better," he returned in a musing 
tone. 
</p><p>"Annette is a very good girl," said Mrs. Birkton, gathering up 
her pen and papers.  "After the first shock is over she will bear 
her disappointment bravely; but don't tell her that I have spoken 
to you about it, for she would never forgive me." 
</p><p>"Poor little thing," Maurice sighed, as his mother groped her 
way to the door. 
</p><p>He sat still in the darkness after she had left, companioned 
by the dismal brood of his disappointments, until half an hour 
later Annette's knock told him that their slender supper was ready. 
</p><p>When he re-entered the kitchen his sister's face had grown as 
smooth and serene as that of some young seraph of Van Eyck's.  She 
had tied a white apron over her dress and was busy carrying the hot 
toast and fried eggs from the stove to the table, which had 
meanwhile been covered with a white cloth and neatly set for the 
evening meal. 
</p><p>Maurice sat down between her and his mother, listening in 
silence to their talk, which fell like the trickle of a cool stream 
upon his aching nerves.  They were speaking as usual of church 
matters, in which the daughter took an eager and precocious, the 
mother a somewhat ex-official interest; it seemed to Maurice as 
though Mrs. Birkton, who had resigned herself to getting on without 
so many things, had even surrendered her direct share in the scheme 
of redemption, or rather tacitly passed it on to her child.  But 
what more especially struck him was the force of will displayed in 
Annette's demeanor.  Her disappointment, which he felt to be very 
real, was impenetrably masked behind a mien of gay activity; and 
Maurice, knowing his own facile tendency to be swayed by the 
emotion of the moment, marvelled at the child's self-control. 
</p><p>The next morning he went out earlier than usual.  As he opened 
the hall-door he turned back and called to his mother, who was 
washing the breakfast dishes in the kitchen: 
</p><p>"Mother, if Helfenridge comes you can say that you don't know 
when I shall be back.  Say that I may not be in all day." 
</p><p>"Very well, dear," she replied, with some surprise; but her 
son's face forbade questioning, and she went on silently with her 
work. 
</p><p>Maurice, as it happened, returned in time for their one 
o'clock dinner.  His mother thought that he looked pale and 
spiritless, and feared that he had endured another defeat at the 
hands of some unenlightened editor. 
</p><p>"Has Helfenridge been here?" he inquired. 
</p><p>"Yes," Mrs. Birkton answered.  "He stopped on his way down 
town just after you had gone out.  He was very sorry not to find 
you, and said that he would come again to-morrow evening." 
</p><p>"Has Annette got back from school?" Maurice asked, 
irrelevantly. 
</p><p>"I think I hear her step now," Mrs. Birkton replied, and at 
the same moment the kitchen-door opened, admitting the young girl, 
whose small face was touched with a frosty pink by the cold.  
<pb n="635"/>  
</p><p>As she entered Maurice went up to her, extending something in 
his hand with an awkward gesture. 
</p><p>"Look here&mdash;will that buy you a white dress like the rest of 
the girls?" he said, abruptly. 
</p><p>Annette grew red and then pale; her lips parted, but she made 
no motion to take the roll of bills which he held out to her. 
</p><p>"Maurice!" his mother gasped.  "Have they accepted something?  
What is it?  What is it to appear in?" 
</p><p>Her small features, flattened into life-long submission to 
failure, seemed almost convulsed by the unwonted expression of a 
less negative emotion. 
</p><p>Maurice made no answer; he was still looking at Annette. 
</p><p>"Why don't you take it, Annette?" he said, a tinge of 
impatience in his voice. 
</p><p>"Annette!  Annette! why do you stand there?  Can't you speak?  
Why don't you thank your brother?" Mrs. Birkton cried, in a storm 
of exultation. 
</p><p>Annette held out her hand, but as she took the bills her face 
again grew crimson. 
</p><p>"Maurice, how did you know about the dress?  Mother, you 
promised not to tell him!"  Then, glancing at the roll of money, 
"But what have you given me, Maurice?  A hundred dollars&mdash;a hundred 
and fifty dollars?  Mother, what does he mean?" 
</p><p>"Maurice!" Mrs. Birkton almost shrieked. 
</p><p>"Well," said Maurice with a laugh, "isn't it enough to buy 
your dress?" 
</p><p>Annette stood, trembling, between sobs and laughter; but her 
mother's tears overflowed. 
</p><p>"Oh, my boy, my son, I'm so happy!  I knew it would come.  I 
knew it must&mdash;Mr. Helfenridge said so only this morning.  But I 
didn't dream it would be so soon!"  She lifted her poor, joy-distorted face to his averted kiss.  "Oh, it's too beautiful, 
Maurice, it's too beautiful!  But you haven't told us yet which 
poem it is." 
</p><p>Maurice turned sharply away, his hand on the door. 
</p><p>"Not yet&mdash;not now.  I've forgotten something.  I'm going out," 
he stammered. 
</p><p>"Why, Maurice!  Without your dinner?  You're not well, my 
son!" 
</p><p>"Nonsense, mother.  I shall be back presently.  Annette, keep 
some dinner for me." 
</p><p>"But, Maurice," the girl cried, springing forward, "you 
mustn't leave all this money with me." 
</p><p>"I've told you it's yours," he said, with a violence which 
made the women's startled eyes meet. 
</p><p>"Why, Maurice, you must be joking!  A hundred and fifty 
dollars?  I oughtn't to keep a penny of it, with all the things 
that you and mother need." 
</p><p>"Nonsense, keep it all.  If it's too much for your dress, 
mother can take the rest for herself.  I don't want it.  But mind 
you spend it all on yourselves; don't use any of it for the 
household.  And remember I won't touch a penny of it." 
</p><p>"But, Maurice," said Mrs. Birkton, "the dress won't cost 
twenty dollars." 
</p><p>"So much the worse," he retorted; and the door shut on him 
with a crash that was conclusive. 
</p><p>Helfenridge, whose work (he was a clerk in the same 
establishment which had been the scene of Maurice's brief 
commercial experience) often delayed him down town long after his 
dinner-hour, did not reach his friend's house until eight o'clock 
on the following evening.  As he started on his long ascent of the 
steep tenement-stairs some one ran against him on the first 
landing, and he drew back in surprise, recognizing Maurice in the 
flare of the gas-jet against the whitewashed wall. 
</p><p>"Hullo, Maurice!  Didn't Mrs. Birkton tell you that I was 
coming this evening?" 
</p><p>"I&mdash;yes&mdash;the fact is, I was just going out," Birkton said, 
confusedly. 
</p><p>Helfenridge glanced at him, marking his evasive eye. 
</p><p>"Oh, very well.  If you're going out I'll try again." 
</p><p>"No&mdash;no.  You'd better come up after all.  I'd rather see you 
now.  I've got something to say to you." 
</p><p>"Are you sure?" said Helfenridge.  "I'd rather not be taken on 
sufferance." 
</p><p>"I want to see you," Birkton repeated, with sudden force; and 
the two men climbed the stairs together in silence. <pb n="636"/>  
</p><p>"Come this way," said Maurice, leading Helfenridge into his 
bedroom. 
</p><p>He put a match to the gas-burner, and another to the stove, 
and pushed his only easy-chair forward within the radius of the 
dry, yellow heat, while Helfenridge threw aside his hat and 
overcoat, which were fringed with frozen snow. 
</p><p>"You don't look well, Maurice," he said, taking the seat 
proffered by his friend. 
</p><p>"It's because I'm new at it, I suppose," the other returned, 
dryly. 
</p><p>"New at what?  What do you mean?" 
</p><p>"Wait a minute," said Maurice; "I want to show you something 
first." 
</p><p>He opened the door as he spoke, and Helfenridge heard him walk 
along the narrow passage-way to the kitchen; then came the opening 
of another door, which launched a confusion of soft, gay tones upon 
the intervening obscurity.  "Oh, no, no," Helfenridge heard a young 
voice half laughingly protest; then an older tone interposed, 
gently urgent, mingled with an odd unfamiliar laugh from Maurice; 
lastly the door of the bedroom was suddenly thrown wide, and 
Maurice reappeared, pushing before him his sister, clad from head 
to foot in white muslin, her flat, childish waist defined by a wide 
white sash, even her little feet shod in immaculate ivory kid. 
</p><p>Above all this whiteness her flushed face emerged like a pink 
crocus from a snow-drift; her lips were parted in tremulous, 
inarticulate apologies, but no explanatory word reached 
Helfenridge. 
</p><p>"Why, Miss Annette, how lovely!" he exclaimed at random, 
questioning Maurice with his eyes. 
</p><p>"There&mdash;doesn't she look nice?" the brother asked, retaining 
his grasp of her white shoulders.  "That's her confirmation dress, 
if you please!  She's going to be confirmed next Sunday at the 
Church of the Precious Blood, and you've got to be there to see 
it." 
</p><p>"Oh, Maurice," murmured Annette. 
</p><p>"Of course I shall be there," said Helfenridge, warmly.  "But 
what a beautiful dress!  Are all confirmation dresses as beautiful 
as that?" 
</p><p>"Oh, no, Mr. Helfenridge; but Maurice&mdash;" 
</p><p>"Father Thurifer likes all the girls in the class to be 
dressed like that," Maurice quickly interposed.  "And now run off 
before your finery gets tumbled," he added, pushing her out of the 
room with a smile which softened the abruptness of the gesture. 
</p><p>He shut the door and the two men stood looking at each other. 
</p><p>"She's lovely," said Helfenridge, gently. 
</p><p>"Poor little girl," said Maurice.  "Isn't it a pretty fancy to 
dress them all in white?" 
</p><p>"Yes&mdash;I suppose it's a High Church idea?" 
</p><p>"I suppose so.  I never knew anything about it until the other 
day&mdash;until two days ago, in fact.  Then I found that Father 
Thurifer had requested all the girls who are to be confirmed to 
dress in white muslin; and we hadn't a penny between us to buy her 
a dress with." 
</p><p>"Yes?" said Helfenridge, tentatively. 
</p><p>"Annette's a very good little girl, you know&mdash;immensely 
religious.  Father Thurifer says he never saw a more religious 
nature.  And it nearly killed her not to have a white dress&mdash;not to 
appear worthy of the day.  She regards it as the most solemn day of 
her life.  Can you understand how she must have felt?  I couldn't 
at first, but I think I do now.  After all, she's only a child." 
</p><p>"I understand," said Helfenridge. 
</p><p>"Well, neither my mother nor I had a copper left.  There was 
no way of getting the dress&mdash;and it seemed to me she had to have 
it." 
</p><p>"Yes?" 
</p><p>"I said the other day that I didn't know what would happen if 
one of us fell ill; but in a way it would have been simpler than 
this.  Annette, now&mdash;if Annette had been ill we could have sent her 
to the hospital.  My mother is too sensible to have any prejudice 
against hospitals.  But this is different&mdash;there was no other way 
of getting the dress; and it had to be got somehow.  I don't 
believe her wedding-dress will seem half so important to her&mdash; 
there's so little perspective at fifteen." <pb n="637"/>  
</p><p>"Well?" said Helfenridge after a pause. 
</p><p>"Well, so I&mdash;good God, Helfenridge, won't you understand?" 
</p><p>Both men were silent; Helfenridge sat with his hands clenched 
on the arms of his chair. 
</p><p>Suddenly he said, as if in a flash of remembrance: "You sent 
that thing to Baker Buley&mdash;the thing about Mrs. Tolquitt?" 
</p><p>"Yes," said Maurice. 
</p><p>A long pause followed, in which the thoughts of the two men 
cried aloud to each other. 
</p><p>At length Maurice exclaimed, "I wish you'd speak out&mdash;say what 
you think." 
</p><p>"I don't know," said Helfenridge, in a low tone. 
</p><p>"You don't know?  You mean you don't know what to say?" 
</p><p>"What to think." 
</p><p>"What to think of a man who's sold his soul?" 
</p><p>"I'm not sure if you have.  It seems to me that I'm not sure 
of anything," Helfenridge said. 
</p><p>"I am&mdash;I'm sure that Annette had to have her dress," said 
Maurice, with a defiant laugh. 
</p><p>"When does it come out?" 
</p><p>"It's out already&mdash;it came out this morning.  It's all over 
town by this time." 
</p><p>"Do they know?" asked Helfenridge, suddenly. 
</p><p>"My mother and Annette?  God forbid.  Do you suppose they 
would have touched the money?" 
</p><p>"How did you account to them for having it?" 
</p><p>"I told them that was my secret&mdash;that they shouldn't know for 
the present.  Of course the&mdash;the thing in the <hi rend="italic"> Kite</hi> is not 
signed; and later, if one of my poems ever finds its way into 
print, they'll think it's that&mdash;but they'll have to wait." 
</p><p>Helfenridge rose.  "I must be going," he said. 
</p><p>"Why do you go?  Because you're afraid to tell me what you 
think?  You may say what you please&mdash;it can't make any difference.  
Annette had to have the dress.  I've been trying to avoid you for 
two days because I was afraid to tell you, but now I'd rather talk 
about it&mdash;that is if you care to have anything more to do with me.  
Because, after all, I'm no better than a blackguard now, you know&mdash; 
there's no getting around that fact.  You've a perfect right to cut 
me." 
</p><p>Helfenridge was mechanically pulling on his overcoat. 
</p><p>"At what time does the confirmation take place?" he asked.  
"Tell Miss Annette that I shall certainly be there." 

</p><p>On the ensuing Sunday morning, punctually at half-past ten 
o'clock, a closed carriage from the nearest livery-stable drew up 
before the house occupied by the Birktons.  It was snowing hard, 
and Annette's spotless draperies and flowing veil were concealed 
under an old cloak of her mother's as, sheltered by Maurice's 
umbrella, she stepped across the sidewalk, clasping her prayer-book 
in one tremulous, white-gloved hand.  Mrs. Birkton followed, her 
shabby bonnet refurbished with fresh velvet strings, and a glow of 
excitement on her small effaced features.  She and her son placed 
themselves on the front seat, leaving Annette to expand her crisp 
robe over the width of the opposite cushions; and the carriage 
rolled off heavily through the deepening snow. 
</p><p>All three sat silent during their slow, noiseless drive.  
Maurice was looking out of the window, so that the women saw only 
his uncommunicative profile.  Mrs. Birkton sat wiping away the 
tears from her flushed face.  They were pleasant tears, and she let 
them roll gently down her cheeks before she dried them.  As for 
Annette, her face was pale, with the candid pallor of an intense 
but scarce-comprehended emotion.  She sat bolt upright, in a kind 
of pre-Raphaelite rigidity which accorded with the primitive 
inexpressiveness of her rapt young features and the shadowless 
chalk-like mass of her dress and veil. 
</p><p>At length the carriage paused behind a train of others; and 
after some moments of delay, which seemed to lend a preparatory 
solemnity to their approach, Maurice, in the wake of his mother and 
sister, passed from the <pb n="638"/>  snowy crudeness of the outer world 
into the rich and complex atmosphere of the Church of the Precious 
Blood. 
</p><p>The raw, sunless daylight, mellowed by the jewelled opacity of 
stained-glass windows, fell with a caressing brilliance across the 
aisles, streaking the clustered shafts with heraldic emblazonments 
of gules and azure and leaving the intervening spaces swathed in a 
velvety dusk.  On the altar, with its embroidered hanging, the 
candle-flames hovered like yellow moths over the white lilies 
rigidly disposed in tall silver vases; while in their midst, 
relieved against the sculptured intricacies of the reredos of 
grayish stone, rose the outstretched arms of the great golden 
crucifix. 
</p><p>The church was already crowded; but a ribbon, latitudinally 
dividing the central aisle, indicated that the foremost rows of 
chairs (there were no pews in the Church of the Precious Blood) had 
been reserved for the candidates for confirmation and their 
relations.  Thither Maurice followed his mother and Annette, 
passing through a dove-like subsidence of feathery white and a 
double row of innocent young faces to the seats assigned to them by 
the verger.  Glancing about as he moved up the aisle he had caught 
a glimpse of Helfenridge seated far back, with his head against a 
pillar; and the sight lent him some momentary comfort. 
</p><p>Maurice cast down his eyes while Mrs. Birkton and Annette 
knelt to pray; and when he looked up the long white procession of 
choristers, preceded by the crucifer, was winding toward the 
chancel, while the first notes of the hymn 

</p><p><hi rend="italic"> How bright these glorious spirits shine!</hi> 
</p><p>   Whence all their white array? 

leapt jubilantly out of the expectant hush. 
</p><p>Maurice, observing his sister, saw the gravity of her vague 
young profile intensified to awe as the procession swept past their 
seats, closed by the sumptuous grouping of the ample-sleeved bishop 
with his attendant clergy in their embroidered vestments, and seen 
through the mauve mist of drifting incense fumes.  To him it was 
like fingering the leaves of a missal in some Umbrian sacristy, 
speculating idly, as he looked, upon the meaning of the delicate 
miniatures, wherein serene-visaged personages, saintly or seraphic, 
enacted their mysterious drama in a setting of fanciful white 
architecture or against a blue background starred with gold.  But 
to Annette, he perceived, it was something real, as real as 
physical birth or death.  Through the symbolic phantasmagoria, 
which she perhaps understood still less than he, ran a thread of 
actuality, linking her timid being to the occult significance of 
the whole splendid scene; and Maurice saw her tremble with the 
sense of that august alliance.  Perhaps, after all, he reflected, 
it was the white dress which formed the actual point of contact.  
At least he was glad to think that it made her a part of the 
pageant, a conscious factor in the gorgeous sacrifice of praise and 
prayer. 
</p><p>As he mused thus his unquiet eyes again began to wander; and 
suddenly they fell upon a lady who sat near by with a little girl 
in white muslin at her side.  The lady's face was very familiar to 
him, though he had never before seen it composed into its present 
expression of devotional repose.  It was a pretty face, crowned by 
abrupt waves of reddish hair just dashed here and there with a 
streak of gray, and lit by an insinuating, agate-colored glance; 
but the sight of it burned Maurice's eyeballs like vitriol, for it 
was the face of Mrs. Tolquitt. 
</p><p>He had never seen her thus before, with sober lips and 
modestly meditative lids; nor had he ever seen the small, solemn 
replica of herself now seated beside her in billows of clear white 
muslin.  The sight was an intolerable rebuke, and he would have 
given the world to hear her familiar laugh rattle derisively 
through the high quietude of the aisles.  As he gazed she turned 
her head, fixing upon him an absent look which gradually melted 
into a subdued smile of recognition.  Then she made a slight 
sideward motion of her eyes, which plainly said, "This is my little 
girl." <pb n="639"/>  
</p><p>Maurice noticed that she showed no surprise at seeing him 
there; she seemed to consider his presence as much a matter of 
course as her own, and with a shudder he said to himself, "Good 
heavens, perhaps she thinks I have come to see her daughter 
confirmed!" 
</p><p>The service rolled on, with its bursts of music and interludes 
of prayer, its mystical moving of brilliant figures and flitting of 
lights about the altar; and at length Maurice was aware of a pause, 
followed by a stirring of the white dovecote in whose midst he sat.  
He saw Mrs. Birkton glance tearfully at Annette.  The girl's lips 
and eyelids were trembling, and for a moment she seemed unable to 
move.  At length she looked up, fixing her eyes on the golden 
crucifix above the altar; then, as if hypnotized by the sight, she 
rose and glided into the aisle, mingling with the fluctuant mass of 
white-veiled figures which had begun to move slowly toward the 
apse. 
</p><p>Presently they were all kneeling together on the chancel step, 
settling their dresses with the quick motions of a flock of birds; 
and above them, whitely hovering, Maurice saw the pontifical head 
and voluminous sleeves of the bishop.  Annette knelt so that he 
could just see her between the intervening piers; but Mrs. 
Tolquitt's daughter was hidden from him, lost in the impersonal 
array of white veils and bowed heads. 
</p><p>The organ murmured a soft accompaniment above which rose the 
monotonous cadence of the episcopal supplication, "Defend, O Lord, 
this thy child. . . .  Defend, O Lord, this thy child . . ." 
reiterated like an incantation, as the invoking hands passed slowly 
down the line of motionless young heads. 
</p><p>Maurice saw the hands sway above Annette's pale braids, which 
shone like winter sunshine through her veil; then they moved on, 
and his eyes turned involuntarily to Mrs. Tolquitt.  But she did 
not see him now; she was crying, not daintily, for the gallery, but 
in genuine self-surrender, her shoulders shaking, her handkerchief 
pressed against her face. 
</p><p>There came over Maurice an uncontrollable longing to escape; 
the smoke of the incense and the strong fragrance of the lilies 
sickened him, and Mrs. Tolquitt's sobs seemed to be choking in his 
own throat. 
</p><p>At length the white line about the chancel swayed, broke, and 
dissolved itself; the choir burst into another victorious hymn, and 
the little veiled figures came fluttering back to their seats.  In 
the ensuing disturbance, Maurice rose with a quick whisper to his 
mother&mdash;"Let me pass&mdash;I'm going out.  I can't stand the incense"&mdash; 
and while Mrs. Birkton made way for him, startled and disappointed, 
his glance fell for a moment on Annette's illuminated face, as she 
moved toward her seat with fixed eyes and folded hands.  Her whole 
gaze was bent upon the inner vision; she did not even see him as he 
brushed her dress in passing out. 
</p><p>It was like a new birth to get out into the snow again, and 
Maurice, after a sharp breath or two, stepped forth rapidly against 
the wind, courting the tingle of the barbed flakes upon his face. 
</p><p>He did not go home until late that evening, and when he 
entered the kitchen, he was met by the festal spectacle of the 
supper-table adorned with a cluster of white lilies and a delicate 
array of fruit and angel-cake.  Annette, in her habitual dress of 
dark stuff, looked more familiar and less supernal than before, and 
though her face still shone, it now seemed to Maurice that he could 
discern the mingling of a gratified childish vanity with the 
mystical emotions of the morning. 
</p><p>"I'm so glad you have come, dear," Mrs. Birkton exclaimed, her 
countenance still dewy with a pleasant agitation.  "Annette, is the 
chicken ready?  We have a broiled chicken for you, Maurice, dear, 
and a little mayonnaise of tomatoes." 
</p><p>As she spoke her eye turned toward the supper-table, dumbly 
challenging his praise. 
</p><p>"How nice it looks," he murmured, obediently. 
</p><p>"It is all owing to you, dear," his mother replied.  "We asked 
Mr. Helfenridge to come to supper, too; we thought you would like 
to have him." <pb n="640"/>  
</p><p>"Is he coming?" Maurice asked, abruptly. 
</p><p>"No, he couldn't unfortunately.  He said he had promised to go 
to his sister's." 
</p><p>They sat down, Annette mutely radiant at the head of the 
table, with her mother and Maurice at the sides; but to the dismay 
of the two women Maurice refused to partake of the delicacies which 
they had prepared.  He had a headache, he said; but he sat watching 
them eat, in spite of his mother's entreaties that he should go and 
lie down in his own room. 
</p><p>When supper was over, however, he rose and bade them good-night; Annette's kiss was mingled with an inarticulate whisper of 
gratitude, but he pushed her gently aside, and the women heard him 
cross the passage-way and shut himself into his own room. 
</p><p>In a few moments, however, he was aroused by a timorous knock, 
which he recognized as his mother's. 
</p><p>"Come in," he called, and Mrs. Birkton stepped apologetically 
across the threshold. 
</p><p>"Maurice, is your head very bad?" 
</p><p>"No, no&mdash;it's not bad at all.  I only want to be quiet." 
</p><p>"I know, dear, and I'm very sorry to disturb you.  But here is 
the rest of this money&mdash;I can't keep it, you know, Maurice.  
Annette's dress and shoes and veil, and the carriage and supper, 
and the new strings for my bonnet, only cost twenty-seven dollars 
and a half, and I can't possibly keep the rest unless you will let 
me use it for the household expenses, as usual." 
</p><p>Maurice sprang up, white to the lips. 
</p><p>"For God's sake, mother, understand me.  I don't want the 
money&mdash;I won't touch it.  I can provide plenty for the household; 
I haven't let you starve yet.  And this is Annette's; yours and 
hers.  If you won't spend it for yourself let Annette put it in the 
savings-bank; or let her throw it into the street; I don't care 
what becomes of it&mdash;but don't speak to me of it again.  I'm sick to 
death of hearing about it!" 
</p><p>Mrs. Birkton shrank back, trembling at his unwonted tone.  She 
was afraid that he was going to be really ill, and her one thought 
was to withdraw without increasing his agitation. 
</p><p>"Very well, dear&mdash;just as you please," she said, 
deprecatingly.  "It was foolish of me to trouble you.  Don't think 
of it again, but go to bed and try to sleep.  I ought not to have 
disturbed you." 
</p><p>And she slipped back into the passage-way, stealthily closing 
the door. 
</p><p>Maurice had no thought of going to bed.  He sank into his arm-chair, which he had pushed close to the gas-stove, and sat staring 
at the hard yellow brilliance of the polished radiator. 
</p><p>Helfenridge had gone to see Annette confirmed, but he had not 
been willing to come to supper; and Maurice knew him too well not 
to penetrate the shallow excuse which had satisfied Mrs. Birkton.  
Well, Helfenridge was right; no man can handle pitch without being 
defiled.  And once a man's hand is soiled, why should his friends 
care to touch it? 
</p><p>After all, no cheap condonation of Helfenridge's would have 
helped Maurice now; rather did he feel a tonic force in his 
friend's disapproval.  It showed Helfenridge to be the better and 
stronger man; and there was a kind of dispassionate consolation in 
that.  If one had to fail it was better that the other should hold 
fast than be dragged down with him; and Helfenridge had always been 
the firmer-footed of the two. 
</p><p>So Maurice mused, letting the desolate hours travel on 
unregarded; till suddenly his vigil was disturbed by a knock, sharp 
and resolute this time, which made him start to his feet. 
</p><p>"Helfenridge!" he exclaimed, and there on the threshold stood 
his friend. 
</p><p>Maurice, on seeing him enter, had felt an involuntary thrill 
of relief, as though he were regaining his moral footing, but the 
illusion was transient and left him to sink back into profounder 
depths of self-accusal. 
</p><p>"I thought you weren't coming.  You would have been quite 
right not to come," he said, without asking his friend to sit down. 
</p><p>"I didn't mean to come," Helfenridge answered, taking off his 
coat.  "Your mother asked me to supper, but I refused.  I couldn't 
see my way clear at first&mdash;even in church that little white <pb n="641"/>  
seraph didn't seem to justify it for a moment; but I have been 
thinking hard all day&mdash;and now I've come." 
</p><p>He held out his hand, but Maurice made no motion to take it. 
</p><p>"It's no use," he said, heavily.  "No amount of thinking will 
make it right.  What's that in the Bible about doing evil that good 
may come?  That's what I've done.  I've done evil that good might 
come&mdash;but it hasn't come&mdash;it can't.  The fellow in the Bible was 
right.  You think Annette's dress was white?  I tell you it was 
black&mdash;black as pitch." 
</p><p>"No, no," said Helfenridge, taking the chair which Maurice had 
not offered him.  "The whole business is horribly mixed up, like 
most human affairs, but there's a germ of right in it somewhere, 
and the best thing we can do now is to nurse that and get it to 
flower." 
</p><p>"To flower?&mdash;bah&mdash;a poison-ivy&mdash;" 
</p><p>"Some poisons are valuable medicines," said Helfenridge. 
</p><p>"Oh, stop&mdash;drop that inane metaphor.  I tell you there's no 
excuse for what I did; and what's worse there's no reparation.  I'd 
give myself up, I'd go and proclaim the whole thing&mdash;but what good 
would that do?  Smother everybody in mud&mdash;Annette, and my mother, 
and that poor woman!  Helfenridge&mdash;" 
</p><p>"Well?" 
</p><p>"That woman&mdash;Mrs. Tolquitt&mdash;was in church with her little 
girl, who was confirmed.  Think of it, will you!  Her little girl 
was confirmed with Annette!  And they sat next to us&mdash;only a few 
seats off.  Helfenridge, I never knew she had a little girl." 
</p><p>"I don't suppose we any of us know much about anybody else," 
said Helfenridge. 
</p><p>"And there she sat crying&mdash;crying, I tell you.  Just such 
tears as my mother's&mdash;glad and proud and sorry all at once!" 
</p><p>"Yes, I saw her." 
</p><p>"You saw her&mdash;and you're here now?" 
</p><p>"I'm here, Maurice, because I know what you're suffering." 
</p><p>They were both silent, Helfenridge seated with bowed head, 
Birkton stirring uneasily about the room with the thwarted 
movements of a caged animal. 
</p><p>At length he flung himself down in the chair in front of his 
desk and hid his face against his arms.  Helfenridge heard his 
sobs. 
</p><p>It seemed a long time before either of them spoke; but finally 
Helfenridge rose and touched his friend's shoulder. 
</p><p>"My eyes are clearer than yours just now," he said, "and I 
shouldn't be here if I didn't see a way out of it." 
</p><p>"A way out of it?" 
</p><p>"Yes, only it's no empirical remedy: <hi rend="italic"> geschehen ist 
geschehen</hi>.  But you spoke just now of the biblical axiom that good 
can't come out of evil; well, no generalization of that sort is 
final.  It seems to me, on the contrary, that this good <hi rend="italic"> can</hi> 
come out of evil; that having done evil once it may become 
impossible to do it again.  One ill act may become the strongest 
rampart one can build against further ill-doing.  It divides 
things, it classifies them.  It may be the means of lifting one 
forever out of the region of quibbles and compromises and moral 
subtleties, in which we who are curious in emotions are apt to 
loiter till we get a shaking up of some sort.  It's horrible to 
make a stepping-stone out of a poor woman's anguish and 
humiliation; but the anguish and humiliation can't be prevented 
now; and who knows? in the occult economy of things they may be of 
some use to her if they help somebody else." 
</p><p>Maurice flung off his hand with a passionate gesture.  
"Quibbles and compromises and moral subtleties!  What else is your 
reasoning made up of, I should like to know?  It's nothing but the 
basest Liguorianism.  The plain fact is that I'm a damned 
blackguard, not fit to look decent people in the face again." 
</p><p>His head sank once more upon his outstretched arms, and 
Helfenridge drew back. 
</p><p>"Shall I go then, Maurice?" 
</p><p>"Yes, go; it's worse when you're here." 
</p><p>Helfenridge for a few moments stood irresolute, as if waiting 
for his friend to recall him; but Maurice still sat without moving, 
bowed beneath the immensity of his shame. <pb n="642"/>  
</p><p>"Well, I'm going," Helfenridge reluctantly declared. 
</p><p>Maurice made no reply; his shoulders still shook, although his 
grief had grown noiseless. 
</p><p>"Remember, Maurice," his friend conjured him, "that whatever 
you do your mother and sister mustn't find out about this business.  
That's your first duty now, to hide the whole thing from them." 
</p><p>Still there came no answer.  Helfenridge turned to the door 
and slowly opened it, glancing back as he did so at Maurice's 
downcast head; then he stepped out into the passage-way.  But as 
the door closed behind him a new impulse, uncontrollable in its 
suddenness, made him turn back abruptly and re-enter the room. 
</p><p>"Look here, Maurice, listen to me," he exclaimed.  "I didn't 
mean to tell you&mdash;but, hang it all, there's no use in your taking 
it like this.  Blason was waiting for Mrs. Tolquitt outside the 
church, and I saw them drive away together in her brougham, with 
the little girl between them." 
</p> 
 
</div1> 
</body> 
</text> 
</TEI.2> 
