<?xml version="1.0"?>

<?dlps id="WhaLett"?>
<?dlps page-images="none" figure-images="no"?>
<?dlps transcription="other"?>

<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/tei-p4/tei2.dtd" [
<!ENTITY % POSTKB "INCLUDE">
<!ENTITY % TEI.extensions.ent SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.ent">
<!ENTITY % TEI.extensions.dtd SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.dtd">
<!ENTITY % ISOnum SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/charent/iso-num.ent"> %ISOnum;
<!ENTITY % ISOpub SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/charent/iso-pub.ent"> %ISOpub;
]>

<TEI.2 id="WhaLett"> 
<teiHeader type="migrated" creator="Etext">
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title type="main">The Letter</title>
<title type="sort">letter</title>
<author>Wharton, Edith, 1862-1937</author>
<respStmt>
<resp>Creation of machine-readable version:</resp> 
<name>Judy Boss</name> 
<resp>Conversion to TEI.2-conformant markup:</resp>  
<name>University of Virginia Library Electronic Text Center</name>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt> 
<extent>ca. <num type="kilobytes">40</num> kilobytes</extent> 
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>University of Virginia Library</publisher>
<pubPlace>Charlottesville, Virginia</pubPlace> 
<idno type="ETC">WhaLett</idno> 
<date value="1995">1995</date>
<availability status="public">
<p n="copyright">Copyright &copy; 1995 by the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia</p>
<p n="access">Publicly accessible</p>
</availability>
<idno type="uva-pid">uva-lib:476500</idno>
</publicationStmt>
<seriesStmt>
<title>University of Virginia Library, Text collection</title>
<idno type="uva-set">UVA-LIB-Text</idno>
</seriesStmt> 
<sourceDesc>
<biblFull>
<titleStmt>
<title type="main">The Letter</title>
<title type="sort">letter</title>
<author>Edith Wharton</author>
</titleStmt> 
<editionStmt>
<p>1st Edition</p>
</editionStmt> 
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>Harper's Monthly</publisher> 
<pubPlace>New York</pubPlace> 
<date value="1904">1904</date>
</publicationStmt> 
</biblFull>
</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc> 
<encodingDesc>
<projectDesc>
<p>Prepared for the University of Virginia Library ElectronicText Center</p>
</projectDesc> 
<editorialDecl>
<p>All quotation marks retained as data</p> 
<p>Verification made against printed text.</p> 
<p>All unambiguous end-of-line hyphens have been removed, and the 
trailing part of a word has been joined to the precedingline.</p> 
<p id="ETC">Keywords in the header are a local Electronic Text Center scheme  
to aid in establishing analytical groupings</p>
</editorialDecl> 
<refsDecl>
<p>ID elements are given for each page element and are composed of the text's 
unique cryptogram and the given page number, as in AusEmma1 for page one of  
Jane Austen's Emma.</p>
</refsDecl>
</encodingDesc> 
<profileDesc>
<creation>
<date value="1904">1904</date>
</creation> 
<langUsage>
<language id="eng" usage="main">English</language>
</langUsage> 
<textClass>
<keywords>
<term>fiction</term>
<term>prose</term> 
<term>Women Writers</term>
</keywords>
</textClass>
</profileDesc> 
<revisionDesc>
<change>
<date value="1995-05">May 1995</date> 
<respStmt>
<resp>corrector</resp> 
<name>Kelly Moulton</name>
</respStmt>
<item>TEI tagging</item>
</change> 
<change>
<date value="2005-07">July 2005</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>Corrector</resp>
<name>Margaret Konkol</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Converted SGML to XML and fixed tagging.</item>
</change>
<change>
<date value="2007-09">September 2007</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>Migration</resp>
<name>Ethan Gruber, University of Virginia Library</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Converted XML markup from TEI Lite to uva-dl-tei (TEI P4 with local customizations).</item>
</change>
<change>
<date value="2008-01">January 2008</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>Migration</resp>
<name>Greg Murray, University of Virginia Library</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Programmatically updated TEI header markup (but not header content) for minimal compliance with current QA requirements.</item>
</change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader> 
<text id="d1">  
<body id="d2">
<div1 type="section" n="1" id="d3"> 
<head type="divisional">Wharton, Edith.  "The Letter." <lb/>  
<hi rend="italic"> Harper's Monthly</hi> 108 (April 1904): 781-89.</head> 

<head type="main">I</head> 
<pb n="781"/>  
 
<p>COLONEL ALINGDON died in Florence in 1890.</p> 
<p>For many years he had lived withdrawn from the world in which 
he had once played so active and even turbulent a part.  The study 
of Tuscan art was his only pursuit, and it was to help him in the 
classification of his notes and documents that I was first called 
to his villa.  Colonel Alingdon had then the look of a very old 
man, though his age can hardly have exceeded seventy.  He was 
small 
and bent, with a finely wrinkled face which still wore the tan of 
youthful exposure.  But for this dusky redness it would have been 
hard to reconstruct from the shrunken recluse, with his low 
fastidious voice and carefully tended hands, an image of that 
young 
knight of adventure whose sword had been at the service of every 
uprising which stirred the uneasy soil of Italy in the first half 
of the nineteenth century.</p><p> 
     Though I was more of a proficient in Colonel Alingdon's 
later 
than his earlier pursuits, the thought of his soldiering days was 
always coming between me and the pacific work of his old age.  As 
we sat collating papers and comparing photographs, I had the 
feeling that this dry and quiet old man had seen even stranger 
things than people said: that he knew more of the inner history 
of 
Europe than half the diplomatists of his day.</p><p> 
     I was not alone in this conviction; and the friend who had 
engaged me for Colonel Alingdon had appended to his instructions 
the injunction to "get him to talk."  But this was what no one 
could do.  Colonel Alingdon was ready to discuss by the hour the 
date of a Giottesque triptych, or the attribution of a disputed 
master; but on the history of his early life he was habitually 
silent.</p><p> 
     It was perhaps because I recognized this silence and 
respected 
it that it afterward came to be broken for me.  Or it was perhaps 
merely because, as the failure of Colonel Alingdon's sight cut 
him 
off from his work, he felt the natural inclination of age to 
revert 
from the empty present to the crowded past.  For one cause or 
another he <hi rend="italic"> did</hi> talk to me in the last year of his life; 
and I 
felt myself mingled, to an extent inconceivable to the mere 
reader 
of history, with the passionate scenes of the Italian struggle 
for 
liberty.  Colonel Alingdon had been mixed with it in all its 
phases: he had known the last Carbonari and the Young Italy of 
Mazzini; he had been in Perugia when the mercenaries of a liberal 
Pope slaughtered women and children in the streets; he had been 
in 
Sicily with the Thousand, and in Milan during the <hi rend="italic"> Cinque 
Giornate</hi>.</p><p> 
     "They say the Italians didn't know how to fight," he said 
one 
day, musingly&mdash;"that the French had to come down and do their 
work 
for them.  People forget how long it was since they had had any 
fighting to do.  But they hadn't forgotten how to suffer and hold 
their tongues; how to die and take their secrets with them.  The 
Italian war of independence was really carried on underground: it 
was one of those awful silent struggles which are so much more 
terrible than the roar of a battle.  It's a deuced sight easier 
to 
charge with your regiment than to lie rotting in an Austrian 
prison 
and know that if you give up the name of a friend or two you can 
go 
back scot-free to your wife and children.  And thousands and 
thousands of Italians had the choice given them&mdash;and hardly one 
went back."</p><p> 
     He sat silent, his meditative fingertips laid together, his 
eyes fixed on the past which was the now only thing clearly 
visible 
to them.</p><p> 
     "And the women?" I said.  "Were they as brave as the 
men?"</p><p> 
     I had not spoken quite at random.  I <pb n="782"/>  had 
always heard 
that there had been as much of love as of war in Colonel 
Alingdon's 
early career, and I hoped that my question might give a personal 
turn to his reminiscences.</p><p> 
     "The women?" he repeated.  "They were braver&mdash;for they had 
more to bear and less to do.  Italy could never have been saved 
without them."</p><p> 
     His eye had kindled and I detected in it the reflection of 
some vivid memory.  It was then that I asked him what was the 
bravest thing he had ever known of a woman's doing.</p><p> 
     The question was such a vague one that I hardly knew why I 
had 
put it, but to my surprise he answered almost at once, as though 
I 
had touched on a subject of frequent meditation.</p><p> 
     "The bravest thing I ever saw done by a woman," he said, 
"was 
brought about by an act of my own&mdash;and one of which I am not 
particularly proud.  For that reason I have never spoken of it 
before&mdash;there was a time when I didn't even care to think of it&mdash; 
but all that is past now.  She died years ago, and so did the 
Jack 
Alingdon she knew, and in telling you the story I am no more than 
the mouthpiece of an old tradition which some ancestor might have 
handed down to me."</p><p> 
     He leaned back, his clear blind gaze fixed smilingly on me, 
and I had the feeling that, in groping through the labyrinth of 
his 
young adventures, I had come unawares upon their central point. 
 
</p> 
</div1> 
 
<div1 type="section" n="2" id="d4"> 
<head>II</head> 
<p>(COLONEL ALINGDON'S STORY)</p> 
<p> 
     When I was in Milan in 'forty-seven an unlucky thing 
happened 
to me.</p><p> 
     I had been sent there to look over the ground by some of my 
Italian friends in England.  As an English officer I had no 
difficulty in getting into Milanese society, for England had for 
years been the refuge of the Italian fugitives, and I was known 
to 
be working in their interests.  It was just the kind of job I 
liked, and I never enjoyed life more than I did in those days.  
There was a great deal going on&mdash;good music, balls and theatres.  
Milan kept up her gayety to the last.  The English were shocked 
by 
the <hi rend="italic"> insouciance</hi> of a race who could dance under the very 
nose 
of the usurper; but those who understood the situation knew that 
Milan was playing Brutus, and playing it uncommonly well.</p><p> 
     I was in the thick of it all&mdash;it was just the atmosphere to 
suit a young fellow of nine-and-twenty, with a healthy passion 
for 
waltzing and fighting.  But, as I said, an unlucky thing happened 
to me.  I was fool enough to fall in love with Donna Candida 
Falco.  
You have heard of her, of course: you know the share she had in 
the 
great work.  In a different way she was what the terrible 
Princess 
Belgioioso had been to an earlier generation.  But Donna Candida 
was not terrible.  She was quiet, discreet and charming.  When I 
knew her she was a widow of thirty, her husband, Andrea Falco, 
having died ten years previously, soon after their marriage.  The 
marriage had been notoriously unhappy, and his death was a 
release 
to Donna Candida.  Her family were of Modena, but they had come 
to 
live in Milan soon after the execution of Ciro Menotti and his 
companions.  You remember the details of that business?  The Duke 
of Modena, one of the most adroit villains in Europe, had been 
bitten with the hope of uniting the Italian states under his 
rule.  
It was a vision of Italian liberation&mdash;of a sort.  A few madmen 
were dazzled by it, and Ciro Menotti was one of them.  You know 
the 
end.  The Duke of Modena, who had counted on Louis Philippe's 
backing, found that that astute sovereign had betrayed him to 
Austria.  Instantly, he saw that his first business was to get 
rid 
of the conspirators he had created.  There was nothing easier 
than 
for a Hapsburg Este to turn on a friend.  Ciro Menotti had staked 
his life for the Duke&mdash;and the Duke took it.  You may remember 
that, on the night when seven hundred men and a cannon attacked 
Menotti's house, the Duke was seen looking on at the slaughter 
from 
an arcade across the square.</p><p> 
     Well, among the lesser fry taken that night was a lad of 
eighteen, Emilio Verna, who was the only brother of Donna 
Candida.  
The Verna family was one of the most respected in Modena.  It 
consisted, at that time, of the mother, Countess Verna, of young 
Emilio and his sister.  Count Verna had been in  
<pb n="783"/>  
Spielberg 
in the twenties.  He had never recovered from his sufferings 
there, 
and died in exile, without seeing his wife and children again.  
Countess Verna had been an ardent patriot in her youth, but the 
failure of the first attempts against Austria had discouraged 
her.  
She thought that in losing her husband she had sacrificed enough 
for her country, and her one idea was to keep Emilio on good 
terms 
with the government.  But the Verna blood was not tractable, and 
his father's death was not likely to make Emilio a good subject 
of 
the Estes.  Not that he had as yet taken any active share in the 
work of the conspirators: he simply hadn't had time.  At his 
trial 
there was nothing to show that he had been in Menotti's 
confidence; 
but he had been seen once or twice coming out of what the ducal 
police called "suspicious" houses, and in his desk were found 
some 
verses to Italy.  That was enough to hang a man in Modena, and 
Emilio Verna was hanged.</p><p> 
     The Countess never recovered from the blow.  The 
circumstances 
of her son's death were too abominable, to unendurable.  If he 
had 
risked his life in the conspiracy, she might have been reconciled 
to his losing it.  But he was a mere child, who had sat at home, 
chafing but powerless, while his seniors plotted and fought.  He 
had been sacrificed to the Duke's insane fear, to his savage 
greed 
for victims, and the Countess Verna was not to be 
consoled.</p><p> 
     As soon as possible, the mother and daughter left Modena for 
Milan.  There they lived in seclusion till Candida's marriage.  
During her girlhood she had had to accept her mother's view of 
life: to shut herself up in the tomb in which the poor woman 
brooded over her martyrs.  But that was not the girl's way of 
honoring the dead.  At the moment when the first shot was fired 
on 
Menotti's house she had been reading Petrarch's Ode to the Lords 
of 
Italy, and the lines 
</p><p> 
                    <hi rend="italic"> l'antico valor 
     Ne Vitalici cor non e ancor morto</hi> 
 
had lodged like a bullet in her brain.  From the day of her 
marriage she began to take a share in the silent work which was 
going on throughout Italy.  Milan was at that time the centre of 
the movement, and Candida Falco threw herself into it with all 
the 
passion which her unhappy marriage left unsatisfied.  At first 
she 
had to act with great reserve, for her husband was a prudent man, 
who did not care to have his habits disturbed by political 
complications; but after his death there was nothing to restrain 
her, except the exquisite tact which enabled her to work night 
and 
day in the Italian cause without giving the Austrian authorities 
a 
pretext for interference.</p><p> 
     When I first knew Donna Candida, her mother was still 
living: 
a tragic woman, prematurely bowed, like an image of death in the 
background of the daughter's brilliant life.  The Countess, since 
her son's death, had become a patriot again, though in a narrower 
sense than Candida.  The mother's first thought was that her dead 
must be avenged, the daughter's that Italy must be saved; but 
from 
different motives they worked for the same end.  Candida felt for 
the Countess that protecting tenderness with which Italian 
children 
so often regard their parents, a feeling heightened by the 
reverence which the mother's sufferings inspired.  Countess 
Verna, 
as the wife and mother of martyrs, had done what Candida longed 
to 
do: she had given her utmost to Italy.  There must have been 
moments when the self-absorption of her grief chilled her 
daughter's ardent spirit; but Candida revered in her mother the 
image of their afflicted country.</p><p> 
     "It was too terrible," she said, speaking of what the 
Countess 
had suffered after Emilio's death.  "All the circumstances were 
too 
unmerciful.  It seemed as if God had turned His face from my 
mother; as if she had been singled out to suffer more than any of 
the others.  All the other families received some message or 
token 
of farewell from the prisoners.  One of them bribed the gaoler to 
carry a letter&mdash;another sent a lock of hair by the chaplain.  But 
Emilio made no sign, sent no word.  My mother felt as though he 
had 
turned his back on us.  She used to sit for hours, saying again 
and 
again, 'Why was he the only one to forget his mother?'  I tried 
to 
comfort her, but it was useless: she had suffered too much.  Now 
I 
never reason with her; I listen, and let her ease her poor heart. 
<pb n="784"/>  Do you know, she still asks me sometimes if I 
think he may 
have left a letter&mdash;if there is no way of finding out if he left 
one?  She forgets that I have tried again and again: that I have 
sent bribes and messages to the gaoler, the chaplain, to every 
one 
who came near him.  The answer is always the same&mdash;no one has 
ever 
heard of a letter.  I suppose the poor boy was stunned, and did 
not 
think of writing.  Who knows what was passing through his poor 
bewildered brain?  But it would have been a great help to my 
mother 
to have a word from him.  If I had known how to imitate his 
writing 
I should have forged a letter."</p><p> 
     I knew enough of the Italians to understand how her boy's 
silence must have aggravated the Countess's grief.  Precious as a 
message from a dying son would be to any mother, such signs of 
tenderness have to the Italians a peculiar significance.  The 
Latin 
race is rhetorical: it possesses the gift of death-bed eloquence, 
the knack of saying the effective thing on momentous occasions.  
The letters which the Italian patriots sent home from their 
prisons 
or from the scaffold are not the halting farewells that anguish 
would have wrung from a less expressive race: they are veritable 
"compositions," saved from affectation only by the fact that 
fluency and sonority are a part of the Latin inheritance.  Such 
letters, passed from hand to hand among the bereaved families, 
were 
not only a comfort to the survivors but an incentive to fresh 
sacrifices.  They were the "seed of the martyrs" with which Italy 
was being sown; and I knew what it meant to the Countess Verna to 
have no such treasure in her bosom, to sit silent while other 
mothers quoted their sons' last words.</p><p> 
     I said just now that it was an unlucky day for me when I 
fell 
in love with Donna Candida; and no doubt you have guessed the 
reason.  She was in love with some one else.  It was the old 
situation of Heine's song.  That other loved another&mdash;loved 
Italy, 
and with an undivided passion.  His name was Fernando Briga, and 
at 
that time he was one of the foremost liberals in Italy.  He came 
of 
a middle-class Modenese family.  His father was a doctor, a 
prudent 
man, engrossed in his profession and unwilling to compromise it 
by 
meddling in politics.  His irreproachable attitude won the 
confidence of the government, and the Duke conferred on him the 
sinister office of physician to the prisons of Modena.  It was 
this 
Briga who attended Emilio Falco, and several of the other 
prisoners 
who were executed at the same time.</p><p> 
     Under shelter of his father's loyalty young Fernando 
conspired 
in safety.  He was studying medicine, and every one supposed him 
to 
be absorbed in his work; but as a matter of fact he was fast 
ripening into one of Mazzini's ablest lieutenants.  His career 
belongs to history, so I need not enlarge on it here.  In 1847 he 
was in Milan, and had become one of the leading figures in the 
liberal group which was working for a coalition with Piedmont.  
Like all the ablest men of his day, he had cast off Mazziniism 
and 
pinned his faith to the house of Savoy.  The Austrian government 
had an eye on him, but he had inherited his father's prudence, 
though he used it for nobler ends, and his discretion enabled him 
to do far more for the cause than a dozen enthusiasts could have 
accomplished.  No one understood this better than Donna Candida.  
She had a share of his caution, and he trusted her with secrets 
which he would not have confided to many men.  Her drawing-room 
was 
the centre of the Piedmontese party, yet so clever was she in 
averting suspicion that more than one hunted conspirator hid in 
her 
house, and was helped across the Alps by her agents.</p><p> 
     Briga relied on her as he did on no one else; but he did not 
love her, and she knew it.  Still, she was young, she was 
handsome, 
and he loved no one else: how could she give up hoping?  From her 
intimate friends she made no secret of her feelings: Italian 
women 
are not reticent in such matters, and Donna Candida was proud of 
loving a hero.  You will see at once that I had no chance; but if 
she could not give up hope, neither could I.  Perhaps in her 
desire 
to secure my services for the cause she may have shown herself 
overkind; or perhaps I was still young enough to set down to my 
own 
charms a success due to quite different causes.  At any rate, I 
persuaded myself that if I could manage to do <pb n="785"/>  
something 
conspicuous for Italy I might yet make her care for me.  With 
such 
an incentive you will not wonder that I worked hard; but though 
Donna Candida was full of gratitude she continued to adore my 
rival.</p><p> 
     One day we had a hot scene.  I began, I believe, by 
reproaching her with having led me on; and when she defended 
herself, I retaliated by taunting her with Briga's indifference.  
She grew pale at that, and said it was enough to love a hero, 
even 
without hope of return; and as she said it she herself looked so 
heroic, so radiant, so unattainably the woman I wanted, that a 
sneer may have escaped me:&mdash;was she so sure then that Briga was a 
hero?  I remember her proud silence and our wretched parting.  I 
went away feeling that at last I had really lost her; and the 
thought made me savage and vindictive.</p><p> 
     Soon after, as it happened, came the <hi rend="italic"> Five Days</hi>, and 
Milan 
was free.  I caught a distant glimpse of Donna Candida in the 
hospital to which I was carried after the fight; but my wound was 
a slight one and in twenty-four hours I was about again on 
crutches.  I hoped she might send for me, but she did not, and I 
was too sulky to make the first advance.  A day or two later I 
heard there had been a commotion in Modena, and not being in 
fighting trim I got leave to go over there with one or two men 
whom 
the Modenese liberals had called in to help them.  When we 
arrived 
the precious Duke had been swept out and a provisional government 
set up.  One of my companions, who was a Modenese, was made a 
member, and knowing that I wanted something to do, he 
commissioned 
me to look up some papers in the ducal archives.  It was 
fascinating work, for in the pursuit of my documents I uncovered 
the hidden springs of his late Highness's paternal 
administration.  
The principal papers relative to the civil and criminal 
administration of Modena have since been published, and the world 
knows how that estimable sovereign cared for the material and 
spiritual welfare of his subjects.</p><p> 
     Well&mdash;in the course of my search, I came across a file of 
old 
papers marked: "Taken from political prisoners.  A.D. 1831."  It 
was the year of Menotti's conspiracy, and everything connected 
with 
that date was thrilling.  I loosened the band and ran over the 
letters.  Suddenly I came across one which was docketed: "Given 
by 
Doctor Briga's son to the warder of His Highness's prisons."  <hi rend="italic"> 
Doctor Briga's son?</hi>  That could be no other than Fernando: I 
knew 
he was an only child.  But how came such a paper into his hands, 
and how had it passed from them into those of the Duke's warder?  
My own hands shook as I opened the letter&mdash;I felt the man 
suddenly 
in my power.</p><p> 
     Then I began to read.  "My adored mother, even in this 
lowest 
circle of hell all hearts are not closed to pity, and I have been 
given the hope that these last words of farewell may reach you. . 
. ."  My eyes ran on over pages of plaintive rhetoric.  "Embrace 
for me my adored Candida . . . let her never forget the cause for 
which her father and brother perished . . . let her keep alive in 
her breast the thought of Spielberg and Reggio.  Do not grieve 
that 
I die so young . . . though not with those heroes in deed I was 
with them in spirit, and am worthy to be enrolled in the sacred 
phalanx . . ." and so on.  Before I reached the signature I knew 
the letter was from Emilio Verna.</p><p> 
     I put it in my pocket, finished my work and started 
immediately for Milan.  I didn't quite know what I meant to 
do&mdash;my 
head was in a whirl.  I saw at once what must have happened.  
Fernando Briga, then a lad of fifteen or sixteen, had attended 
his 
father in prison during Emilio Verna's last hours, and the 
latter, 
perhaps aware of the lad's liberal sympathies, had found an 
opportunity of giving him the letter.  But why had Briga given it 
up to the warder?  That was the puzzling question.  The docket 
said: <hi rend="italic">" Given by</hi> Doctor Briga's son"&mdash;but it might mean 
"taken 
from."  Fernando might have been seen to receive the letter and 
might have been searched on leaving the prison.  But that would 
not 
account for his silence afterward.  How was it that, if he knew 
of 
the letter, he had never told Emilio's family of it?  There was 
only one explanation.  If the letter had been taken from him by 
force he would have had no reason for concealing its existence; 
and 
his silence was <pb n="786"/>  clear proof that he had given 
it up 
voluntarily, no doubt in the hope of standing well with the 
authorities.  But then he was a traitor and a coward; the patriot 
of 'forty-eight had begun life as an informer!  But does innate 
character ever change so radically that the lad who has committed 
a base act at fifteen may grow up into an honorable man?  A good 
man may be corrupted by life, but can the years turn a born sneak 
into a hero?</p><p> 
     You may fancy how I answered my own questions. . . .  If 
Briga 
had been false and cowardly then, was he not sure to be false and 
cowardly still?  In those days there were traitors under every 
coat, and more than one brave fellow had been sold to the police 
by 
his best friend. . . .  You will say that Briga's record was 
unblemished, that he had exposed himself to danger too 
frequently, 
had stood by his friends too steadfastly, to permit of a rational 
doubt of his good faith.  So reason might have told me in a 
calmer 
moment, but she was not allowed to make herself heard just then.  
I was young, I was angry, I chose to think I had been unfairly 
treated, and perhaps at my rival's instigation.  It was not 
unlikely that Briga knew of my love for Donna Candida, and had 
encouraged her to use it in the good cause.  Was she not always 
at 
his bidding?  My blood boiled at the thought, and reaching Milan 
in 
a rage I went straight to Donna Candida.</p><p> 
     I had measured the exact force of the blow I was going to 
deal.  The triumph of the liberals in Modena had revived public 
interest in the unsuccessful struggle of their predecessors, the 
men who, sixteen years earlier, had paid for the same attempt 
with 
their lives.  The victors of 'forty-eight wished to honor the 
vanquished of 'thirty-two.  All the families exiled by the ducal 
government were hastening back to recover possession of their 
confiscated property and of the graves of their dead.  Already it 
had been decided to raise a monument to Menotti and his 
companions.  
There were to be speeches, garlands, a public holiday: the thrill 
of the commemoration would run through Europe.  You see what it 
would have meant to the poor Countess to appear on the scene with 
her boy's letter in her hand; and you see also what the 
memorandum 
on the back of the letter would have meant to Donna Candida.  
Poor 
Emilio's farewell would be published in all the journals of 
Europe: 
the finding of the letter would be on every one's lips.  And how 
conceal those fatal words on the back?  At the moment, it seemed 
to 
me that fortune could not have given me a handsomer chance of 
destroying my rival than in letting me find the letter which he 
stood convicted of having suppressed.</p><p> 
     My sentiment was perhaps not a strictly honorable one; yet 
what could I do but give the letter to Donna Candida?  To keep it 
back was out of the question; and with the best will in the world 
I could not have erased Briga's name from the back.  The mistake 
I 
made was in thinking it lucky that the paper had fallen into my 
hands.</p><p> 
     Donna Candida was alone when I entered.  We had parted in 
anger, but she held out her hand with a smile of pardon, and 
asked 
what news I brought from Modena.  The smile exasperated me: I 
felt 
as though she were trying to get me into her power again.</p><p> 
     "I bring you a letter from your brother," I said, and handed 
it to her.  I had purposely turned the superscription downward, 
so 
that she should not see it.</p><p> 
     She uttered an incredulous cry and tore the letter open.  A 
light struck up from it into her face as she read&mdash;a radiance 
that 
smote me to the soul.  For a moment I longed to snatch the paper 
from her and efface the name on the back.  It hurt me to think 
how 
short-lived her happiness must be.</p><p> 
     Then she did a fatal thing.  She came up to me, caught my 
two 
hands and kissed them.  "Oh, thank you&mdash;bless you a thousand 
times!  
He died thinking of us&mdash;he died loving Italy!"</p><p> 
     I put her from me gently: it was not the kiss I wanted, and 
the touch of her lips hardened me.</p><p> 
     She shone on me through her happy tears.  "What happiness&mdash; 
what consolation you have brought my poor mother!  This will take 
the bitterness from her grief.  And that it should come to her 
now!  
Do you know, she had a presentiment of it?  When we heard of the 
Duke's flight her first word was: 'Now  
<pb n="787"/>  we may 
find Emilio's 
letter.'  At heart she was always sure that he had written&mdash;I 
suppose some blessed instinct told her so."  She dropped her face 
on her hands, and I saw her tears fall on the wretched 
letter.</p><p> 
     In a moment she looked up again, with eyes that blessed and 
trusted me.  "Tell me where you found it," she said.</p><p> 
     I told her.</p><p> 
     "Oh, the savages!  They took it from him&mdash;"</p><p> 
     My opportunity had come.  "No," I said, "it appears they did 
<hi rend="italic"> not</hi> take it from him."</p><p> 
     "Then how&mdash;"</p><p> 
     I waited a moment.  "The letter," I said, looking full at 
her, 
"was given up to the warder of the prison by the son of Doctor 
Briga."</p><p> 
     She stared, repeating the words slowly.  "The son of Doctor 
Briga?  But that is&mdash;Fernando," she said.</p><p> 
     "I have always understood," I replied, "that your friend was 
an only son."</p><p> 
     I had expected an outcry of horror; if she had uttered it I 
could have forgiven her anything.  But I heard, instead, an 
incredulous exclamation: my statement was really too 
preposterous!  
I saw that her mind had flashed back to our last talk, and that 
she 
charged me with something too nearly true to be endurable.</p><p> 
     "My brother's letter?  Given to the prison warder by 
Fernando 
Briga?  My dear Captain Alingdon&mdash;on what authority do you expect 
me to believe such a tale?"</p><p> 
     Her incredulity had in it an evident implication of bad 
faith, 
and I was stung to a quick reply.</p><p> 
     "If you will turn over the letter you will see."</p><p> 
     She continued to gaze at me a moment: then she obeyed.  I 
don't think I ever admired her more than I did then.  As she read 
the name a tremor crossed her face; and that was all.  Her mind 
must have reached out instantly to the farthest consequences of 
the 
discovery, but the long habit of self-command enabled her to 
steady 
her muscles at once.  If I had not been on the alert I should 
have 
seen no hint of emotion.</p><p> 
     For a while she looked fixedly at the back of the letter; 
then 
she raised her eyes to mine.</p><p> 
     "Can you tell me who wrote this?" she asked.</p><p> 
     Her composure irritated me.  She had rallied all her forces 
to 
Briga's defence, and I felt as though my triumph were slipping 
from 
me.</p><p> 
     "Probably one of the clerks of the archives," I answered.  
"It 
is written in the same hand as all the other memoranda relating 
to 
the political prisoners of that year."</p><p> 
     "But it is a lie!" she exclaimed.  "He was never admitted to 
the prisons."</p><p> 
     "Are you sure?"</p><p> 
     "How should he have been?"</p><p> 
     "He might have gone as his father's assistant."</p><p> 
     "But if he had seen my poor brother he would have told me 
long 
ago."</p><p> 
     "Not if he had really given up this letter," I 
retorted.</p><p> 
     I supposed her quick intelligence had seized this from the 
first; but I saw now that it came to her as a shock.  She stood 
motionless, clenching the letter in her hands, and I could guess 
the rapid travel of her thoughts.</p><p> 
     Suddenly she came up to me.  "Colonel Alingdon," she said, 
"you have been a good friend of mine, though I think you have not 
liked me lately.  But whether you like me or not, I know you will 
not deceive me.  On your honor, do you think this memorandum may 
have been written later than the letter?"</p><p> 
     I hesitated.  If she had cried out once against Briga I 
should 
have wished myself out of the business; but she was too sure of 
him.</p><p> 
     "On my honor," I said, "I think it hardly possible.  The ink 
has faded to the same degree."</p><p> 
     She made a rapid comparison and folded the letter with a 
gesture of assent.</p><p> 
     "It may have been written by an enemy," I went on, wishing 
to 
clear myself of any appearance of malice.</p><p> 
     She shook her head.  "He was barely fifteen&mdash;and his father 
was on the side of the government.  Besides, this would have 
served 
him with the government, and the liberals would never have known 
of 
it."</p><p> 
     This was unanswerable&mdash;and still not a word of revolt 
against 
the man whose condemnation she was pronouncing!</p><p> 
     "Then&mdash;" I said with a vague gesture.  
<pb n="788"/>  
</p><p> 
     She caught me up.  "Then&mdash;?"</p><p> 
     "You have answered my objections," I returned.</p><p> 
     "Your objections?"</p><p> 
     "To thinking that Signor Briga could have begun his career 
as 
a patriot by betraying a friend."</p><p> 
     I had brought her to the test at last, but my eyes shrank 
from 
her face as I spoke.  There was a dead silence, which I broke by 
adding lamely: "But no doubt Signor Briga could explain."</p><p> 
     She lifted her head, and I saw that my triumph was to be 
short.  She stood erect, a few paces from me, resting her hand on 
a table, but not for support.</p><p> 
     "Of course he can explain," she said; "do you suppose I ever 
doubted it?  But&mdash;" she paused a moment, fronting me nobly&mdash;"he 
need not, for I understand it all now."</p><p> 
     "Ah," I murmured with a last flicker of irony.</p><p> 
     "I understand," she repeated.  It was she, now, who sought 
my 
eyes and held them.  "It is quite simple&mdash;he could not have done 
otherwise."</p><p> 
     This was a little too oracular to be received with 
equanimity.  
I suppose I smiled.</p><p> 
     "He could not have done otherwise," she repeated with 
tranquil 
emphasis.  "He merely did what is every Italian's duty&mdash;he put 
Italy before himself and his friends."  She waited a moment, and 
then went on with growing passion: "Surely you must see what I 
mean?  He was evidently in the prison with his father at the time 
of my poor brother's death.  Emilio perhaps guessed that he was a 
friend&mdash;or perhaps appealed to him because he was young and 
looked 
kind.  But don't you see how dangerous it would have been for 
Briga 
to bring this letter to us, or even to hide it in his father's 
house?  It is true that he was not yet suspected of liberalism, 
but 
he was already connected with Young Italy, and it is just because 
he managed to keep himself so free of suspicion that he was able 
to 
do such good work for the cause."  She paused, and then went on 
with a firmer voice.  "You don't know the danger we all lived in. 
 
The government spies were everywhere.  The laws were set aside as 
the Duke pleased&mdash;was not Emilio hanged for having an ode to 
Italy 
in his desk?  After Menotti's conspiracy the Duke grew mad with 
fear&mdash;he was haunted by the dread of assassination.  The police, 
to 
prove their zeal, had to trump up false charges and arrest 
innocent 
persons&mdash;you remember the case of poor Ricci?  Incriminating 
papers 
were smuggled into people's houses&mdash;they were condemned to death 
on 
the paid evidence of brigands and galley-slaves.  The families of 
the revolutionists were under the closest observation and were 
shunned by all who wished to stand well with the government.  If 
Briga had been seen going into our house he would at once have 
been 
suspected.  If he had hidden Emilio's letter at home, its 
discovery 
might have ruined his family as well as himself.  It was his duty 
to consider all these things.  In those days no man could serve 
two 
masters, and he had to choose between endangering the cause and 
failing to serve a friend.  He chose the latter&mdash;and he was 
right."</p><p> 
     I stood listening, fascinated by the rapidity and skill with 
which she had built up the hypothesis of Briga's defence.  But 
before she ended a strange thing happened&mdash;her argument had 
convinced me.  It seemed to me quite likely that Briga had in 
fact 
been actuated by the motives she suggested.</p><p> 
     I suppose she read the admission in my face, for hers lit up 
victoriously.</p><p> 
     "You see?" she exclaimed.  "Ah, it takes one brave man to 
understand another."</p><p> 
     Perhaps I winced a little at being thus coupled with her 
hero; 
at any rate, some last impulse of resistance made me say: "I 
should 
be quite convinced, if Briga had only spoken of the letter 
afterward.  If brave people understand each other, I cannot see 
why 
he should have been afraid of telling you the truth."</p><p> 
     She colored deeply, and perhaps not quite 
resentfully.</p><p> 
     "You are right," she said; "he need not have been afraid.  
But 
he does not know me as I know him.  I was useful to Italy, and he 
may have feared to risk my friendship."</p><p> 
     "You are the most generous woman I ever knew!" I 
exclaimed.</p><p> 
     She looked at me intently.  "You also are generous," she 
said.</p><p> 
     I stiffened instantly, suspecting a 
pur-<pb n="789"/> pose behind her 
praise.  "I have given you small proof of it!" I said.</p><p> 
     She seemed surprised.  "In bringing me this letter?  What 
else 
could you do?"  She sighed deeply.  "You can give me proof enough 
now."</p><p> 
     She had dropped into a chair, and I saw that we had reached 
the most difficult point in our interview.</p><p> 
     "Captain Alingdon," she said, "does any one else know of 
this 
letter?"</p><p> 
     "No.  I was alone in the archives when I found it."</p><p> 
     "And you spoke of it to no one?"</p><p> 
     "To no one."</p><p> 
     "Then no one must know."</p><p> 
     I bowed.  "It is for you to decide."</p><p> 
     She paused.  "Not even my mother," she continued, with a 
painful blush.</p><p> 
     I looked at her in amazement.  "Not even&mdash;?"</p><p> 
     She shook her head sadly.  "You think me a cruel daughter?  
Well&mdash;<hi rend="italic"> he</hi> was a cruel friend.  What he did was done for 
Italy: 
shall I allow myself to be surpassed?"</p><p> 
     I felt a pang of commiseration for the mother.  "But you 
will 
at least tell the Countess&mdash;"</p><p> 
     Her eyes filled with tears.  "My poor mother&mdash;don't make it 
more difficult for me!"</p><p> 
     "But I don't understand&mdash;"</p><p> 
     "Don't you see that she might find it impossible to forgive 
him?  She has suffered so much!  And I can't risk that&mdash;for in 
her 
anger she might speak.  And even if she forgave him, she might be 
tempted to show the letter.  Don't you see that, even now, a word 
of this might ruin him?  I will trust his fate to no one.  If 
Italy 
needed him then she needs him far more to-day."</p><p> 
     She stood before me magnificently, in the splendor of her 
great refusal; then she turned to the writing-table at which she 
had been seated when I came in.  Her sealing-taper was still 
alight, and she held her brother's letter to the flame.</p><p> 
     I watched her in silence while it burned; but one more 
question rose to my lips.</p><p> 
     "You will tell <hi rend="italic"> him</hi>, then, what you have done for 
him?" I 
cried.</p><p> 
     And at that the heroine turned woman, melted and pressed 
unhappy hands in mine.</p><p> 
     "Don't you see that I can never tell him what I do for him?  
That is my gift to Italy," she said. 
</p> 
 
 
</div1> 
</body> 
</text> 
</TEI.2> 
