<?xml version="1.0"?>

<?dlps id="WhaLamp"?>
<?dlps page-images="none" figure-images="no"?>
<?dlps transcription="other"?>

<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/tei-p4/tei2.dtd" [
<!ENTITY % POSTKB "INCLUDE">
<!ENTITY % TEI.extensions.ent SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.ent">
<!ENTITY % TEI.extensions.dtd SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.dtd">
<!ENTITY % ISOnum SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/charent/iso-num.ent"> %ISOnum;
<!ENTITY % ISOpub SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/charent/iso-pub.ent"> %ISOpub;

]>

<TEI.2 id="WhaLamp"> 
<teiHeader type="migrated" creator="Etext">
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title type="main">The Lamp of Psyche</title>
<title type="sort">lamp of psyche</title>
<author>Wharton, Edith, 1862-1937</author>
<respStmt>
<resp>Creation of machine-readable version:</resp>
<name>Judy Boss</name>
</respStmt>
<respStmt>
<resp>Conversion to TEI-conformant markup:</resp>
<name>University of Virginia Library Electronic Text Center</name>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt> 
<extent>ca. <num type="kilobytes">46</num> kilobytes</extent> 
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>University of Virginia Library</publisher>
<pubPlace>Charlottesville, Virginia</pubPlace>
<idno type="ETC">WhaLamp</idno> 
<date value="1995">1995</date>
<availability status="public">
<p n="copyright">Copyright &copy; 1995 by the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia</p>
<p n="access">Publicly accessible</p>
</availability>
<idno type="uva-pid">uva-lib:476498</idno>
</publicationStmt>
<seriesStmt>
<title>University of Virginia Library, Text collection</title>
<idno type="uva-set">UVA-LIB-Text</idno>
</seriesStmt> 
<sourceDesc>
<biblFull>
<titleStmt>
<title type="main">The Lamp of Psyche</title>
<title type="sort">lamp of psyche</title>
<author>Wharton, Edith</author>
</titleStmt> 
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>Scribner's Magazine</publisher>
<pubPlace>New York</pubPlace> 
<date value="1895">1895</date>
</publicationStmt> 
<notesStmt>
<note>
<p>Volume 18</p>
</note>
</notesStmt>
</biblFull>
</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc> 
<encodingDesc>
<projectDesc>
<p>Prepared for the University of Virginia Library Electronic Text Center</p>
</projectDesc> 
<editorialDecl>
<p>All quotation marks retained as data</p> 
<p>Verification made against printed text</p> 
<p id="ETC">Keywords in the header are a local Electronic Text Center scheme  
to aid in establishing analytical groupings</p>
</editorialDecl> 
<refsDecl>
<p>ID elements are given for each page element and are composed of the text's 
unique cryptogram and the given page number, as in SpeFQue1 for page one of  
Spenser's Faerie Queene.</p>
</refsDecl>
</encodingDesc> 
<profileDesc>
<creation>
<date value="1895">1895</date>
</creation> 
<langUsage>
<language id="eng" usage="main">English</language>
</langUsage> 
<textClass>
<keywords>
<term>fiction</term>
<term>prose</term>
</keywords>
</textClass>
</profileDesc> 
<revisionDesc>
<change>
<date value="1995">1995</date> 
<respStmt>
<resp>corrector</resp>
<name>David Seaman</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Header and basic TEI SGML encoding added.</item>
</change> 
<change>
<date value="2005-07">July 2005</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>Corrector</resp>
<name>Margaret Konkol</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Converted SGML to XML and fixed tagging.</item>
</change>
<change>
<date value="2007-09">September 2007</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>Migration</resp>
<name>Ethan Gruber, University of Virginia Library</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Converted XML markup from TEI Lite to uva-dl-tei (TEI P4 with local customizations).</item>
</change>
<change>
<date value="2008-01">January 2008</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>Migration</resp>
<name>Greg Murray, University of Virginia Library</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Programmatically updated TEI header markup (but not header content) for minimal compliance with current QA requirements.</item>
</change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader> 
<text id="d1">  
<body id="d2"> 
<div1 type="story" id="d3"> 
<head> 
Wharton, Edith.  "The Lamp of Psyche."<lb/> 
  <hi rend="italic"> Scribner's Magazine</hi> 18 (Oct. 1895): 418-28. </head>

<pb n="418"/>  

<div2 type="section" n="1" id="d4"> 
<head>                            I 
</head>
<p> 
DELIA CORBETT was too happy; her happiness frightened her.  Not on 
theological grounds, however; she was sure that people had a right 
to be happy; but she was equally sure that it was a right seldom 
recognized by destiny.  And her happiness almost touched the 
confines of pain &mdash; it bordered on that sharp ecstasy which she had 
known, through one sleepless night after another, when what had now 
become a reality had haunted her as an unattainable longing. 
</p><p>Delia Corbett was not in the habit of using what the French 
call <hi rend="italic"> gros mots</hi> in the rendering of her own emotions; she took 
herself, as a rule, rather flippantly, with a dash of contemptuous 
pity.  But she felt that she had now entered upon a phase of 
existence wherein it became her to pay herself an almost 
reverential regard.  Love had set his golden crown upon her 
forehead, and the awe of the office allotted to her subdued her 
doubting heart.  To her had been given the one portion denied to 
all other women on earth, the immense, the unapproachable privilege 
of becoming Laurence Corbett's wife. 
</p><p>Here she burst out laughing at the sound of her own thoughts, 
and rising from her seat walked across the drawing-room and looked 
at herself in the mirror above the mantel-piece.  She was past 
thirty and had never been very pretty; but she knew herself to be 
capable of loving her husband better and pleasing him longer than 
any other woman in the world.  She was not afraid of rivals; he and 
she had seen each other's souls. 
</p><p>She turned away, smiling carelessly at her insignificant 
reflection, and went back to her arm-chair near the balcony.  The 
room in which she sat was very beautiful; it pleased Corbett to 
make all his surroundings beautiful.  It was the drawing-room of 
his hotel in Paris, and the balcony near which his wife sat 
overlooked a small bosky garden framed in ivied walls, with a 
mouldering terra-cotta statue in the centre of its cup-shaped lawn.  
They had now been married some two months, and, after travelling 
for several weeks, had both desired to return to Paris; Corbett 
because he was really happier there than elsewhere, Delia because 
she passionately longed to enter as a wife the house where she had 
so often come and gone as a guest.  How she used to find herself 
dreaming in the midst of one of Corbett's delightful dinners (to 
which she and her husband were continually being summoned) of a day 
when she might sit at the same table, but facing its master, a day 
when no carriage should wait to whirl her away from the brightly 
lit porte-cochere, and when, after the guests had gone, he and she 
should be left alone in his library, and she might sit down beside 
him and put her hand in his!  The high-minded reader may infer from 
this that I am presenting him, in the person of Delia Corbett, with 
a heroine whom he would not like his wife to meet; but how many of 
us could face each other in the calm consciousness of moral 
rectitude if our inmost desire were not hidden under a convenient 
garb of lawful observance? 
</p><p>Delia Corbett, as Delia Benson, had been a very good wife to 
her first husband; some people (Corbett among them) had even 
thought her laxly tolerant of "poor Benson's" weaknesses.  But then 
she knew her own; and it is admitted that nothing goes so far 
toward making us blink the foibles of others as the wish to have 
them extend a like mercy to ourselves.  Not that Delia's foibles 
were of a tangible nature; they belonged to the order which escapes 
analysis by the coarse process of our social standards.  Perhaps 
their very immateriality, the consciousness that she could never be 
brought to book <pb n="419"/>  for them before any human tribunal, made 
her the more restive under their weight; for she was of a nature to 
prefer buying her happiness to stealing it.  But her rising 
scruples were perpetually being allayed by some fresh indiscretion 
of Benson's, to which she submitted with an undeviating amiability 
which flung her into the opposite extreme of wondering if she 
didn't really influence him to do wrong &mdash; if she mightn't help him 
to do better.  All these psychological subtleties exerted, however, 
no influence over her conduct which, since the day of her marriage, 
had been a model of delicate circumspection.  It was only necessary 
to look at Benson to see that the most eager reformer could have 
done little to improve him.  In the first place he must have 
encountered the initial difficulty, most disheartening to 
reformers, of making his neophyte distinguish between right and 
wrong.  Undoubtedly it was within the measure even of Benson's 
primitive perceptions to recognize that some actions were 
permissible and others were not; but his sole means of classifying 
them was to try both, and then deny having committed those of which 
his wife disapproved.  Delia had once owned a poodle who greatly 
desired to sleep on a white fur rug which she destined to other 
uses.  She and the poodle disagreed on the subject, and the later, 
though submitting to her authority (when reinforced by a whip), 
could never be made to see the justice of her demand, and 
consequently (as the rug frequently revealed) never missed an 
opportunity of evading it when her back was turned.  Her husband 
often reminded her of the poodle, and, not having a whip or its 
moral equivalent to control him with, she had long since resigned 
herself to seeing him smudge the whiteness of her early illusions.  
The worst of it was that her resignation was such a cheap virtue.  
She had to be perpetually rousing herself to a sense of Benson's 
enormities; through the ever-lengthening perspective of her 
indifference they looked as small as the details of a landscape 
seen through the wrong end of a telescope.  Now and then she tried 
to remind herself that she had married him for love; but she was 
well aware that the sentiment she had once entertained for him had 
nothing in common with the state of mind which the words now 
represented to her; and this naturally diminished the force of the 
argument.  She had married him at nineteen, because he had 
beautiful blue eyes and always wore a gardenia in his coat; really, 
as far as she could remember, these considerations had been the 
determining factors in her choice.  Delia as a child (her parents 
were since dead) had been a much-indulged daughter, with a liberal 
allowance of pocket-money, and permission to spend it unquestioned 
and unadvised.  Subsequently, she used sometimes to look, in a 
critical humor, at the various articles which she had purchased in 
her teens; futile chains and lockets, valueless china knick-knacks, 
and poor engravings of sentimental pictures.  These, as a 
chastisement to her taste, she religiously preserved; and they 
often made her think of Benson.  No one, she could not but reflect, 
would have blamed her if, with the acquirement of a fuller 
discrimination, she had thrown them all out of the window and 
replaced them by some object of permanent merit; but she was 
expected not only to keep Benson for life, but to conceal the fact 
that her taste had long since discarded him. 
</p><p>It could hardly be expected that a woman who reasoned so 
dispassionately about her mistakes should attempt to deceive 
herself about her preferences.  Corbett personified all those finer 
amenities of mind and manners which may convert the mere act of 
being into a beneficent career; to Delia he seemed the most 
admirable man she had ever met, and she would have thought it 
disloyal to her best aspirations not to admire him.  But she did 
not attempt to palliate her warmer feeling under the mask of a 
plausible esteem; she knew that she loved him, and scorned to 
disavow that also.  So well, however, did she keep her secret that 
Corbett himself never suspected it, until her husband's death freed 
her from the obligation of concealment.  Then, indeed, she gloried 
in its confession; and after two years of widowhood, and more than 
<pb n="420"/>  two months of marriage, she was still under the spell of 
that moment of exquisite avowal. 
</p><p>She was reliving it now, as she often did in the rare hours 
which separated her from her husband; when presently she heard his 
step on the stairs, and started up with the blush of eighteen.  As 
she walked across the room to meet him she asked herself perversely 
(she was given to such obliqueness of self-scrutiny) if to a 
dispassionate eye he would appear as complete, as supremely well-equipped as she beheld him, or if she walked in a cloud of 
delusion, dense as the god-concealing mist of Homer.  But whenever 
she put this question to herself, Corbett's appearance instantly 
relegated it to the limbo of solved enigmas; he was so obviously 
admirable that she wondered that people didn't stop her in the 
street to attest her good fortune. 
</p><p>As he came forward now, this renewal of satisfaction was so 
strong in her that she felt an impulse to seize him and assure 
herself of his reality; he was so perilously like the phantasms of 
joy which had mocked her dissatisfied past.  But his coat-sleeve 
was convincingly tangible; and, pinching it, she felt the muscles 
beneath. 
</p><p>"What &mdash; all alone?" he said, smiling back her welcome. 
</p><p>"No, I wasn't &mdash; I was with you!" she exclaimed; then fearing to 
appear fatuous, added, with a slight shrug, "Don't be alarmed &mdash; it 
won't last." 
</p><p>"That's what frightens me," he answered, gravely. 
</p><p>"Precisely," she laughed; "and I shall take good care not to 
reassure you!" 
</p><p>They stood face to face for a moment, reading in each other's 
eyes the completeness of their communion; then he broke the silence 
by saying, "By the way, I'd forgotten; here's a letter for you." 
</p><p>She took it unregardingly, her eyes still deep in his; but as 
her glance turned to the envelope she uttered a note of pleasure. 
</p><p>"Oh, how nice &mdash; it's from your only rival!" 
</p><p>"Your Aunt Mary?" 
</p><p>She nodded.  "I haven't heard from her in a month &mdash; and I'm 
afraid I haven't written to her either.  You don't know how many 
beneficent intentions of mine you divert from their proper 
channels." 
</p><p>"But your Aunt Mary has had you all your life &mdash; I've only had 
you two months," he objected. 
</p><p>Delia was still contemplating the letter with a smile.  "Dear 
thing!" she murmured.  "I wonder when I shall see her?" 
</p><p>"Write and ask her to come and spend the winter with us." 
</p><p>"What &mdash; and leave Boston, and her kindergartens, and associated 
charities, and symphony concerts, and debating clubs?  You don't 
know Aunt Mary!" 
</p><p>"No, I don't.  It seems so incongruous that you should adore 
such a bundle of pedantries." 
</p><p>"I forgive that, because you've never seen her.  How I wish 
you could!" 
</p><p>He stood looking down at her with the all-promising smile of 
the happy lover.  "Well, if she won't come to us we'll go to her." 
</p><p>"Laurence &mdash; and leave this!" 
</p><p>"It will keep &mdash; we'll come back to it.  My dear girl, don't 
beam so; you make me feel as if you hadn't been happy until now." 
</p><p>"No &mdash; but it's your thinking of it!" 
</p><p>"I'll do more than think; I'll act; I'll take you to Boston to 
see your Aunt Mary." 
</p><p>"Oh, Laurence, you'd hate doing it." 
</p><p>"Not doing it together." 
</p><p>She laid her hand for a moment on his.  "What a difference 
that does make in things!" she said, as she broke the seal of the 
letter. 
</p><p>"Well, I'll leave you to commune with Aunt Mary.  When you've 
done, come and find me in the library." 
</p><p>Delia sat down joyfully to the perusal of her letter, but as 
her eye travelled over the closely written pages her gratified 
expression turned to one of growing concern; and presently, 
thrusting it back into the envelope, she followed her husband to 
the library.  It was a charming room and singularly indicative, to 
her fancy, of its occupant's character; the expanse of harmonious 
bindings, the fruity bloom of Renaissance bronzes, and the 
imprisoned sunlight <pb n="421"/>  of two or three old pictures fitly 
epitomizing the delicate ramifications of her husband's taste.  But 
now her glance lingered less appreciatively than usual on the warm 
tones and fine lines which formed so expressive a background for 
Corbett's fastidious figure. 
</p><p>"Aunt Mary has been ill &mdash; I'm afraid she's been seriously ill," 
she announced as he rose to receive her.  "She fell in coming down-stairs from one of her tenement-house inspections, and it brought 
on water on the knee.  She's been laid up ever since &mdash; some three or 
four weeks now.  I'm afraid it's rather bad at her age; and I don't 
know how she will resign herself to keeping quiet." 
</p><p>"I'm very sorry," said Corbett, sympathetically; "but water on 
the knee isn't dangerous, you know." 
</p><p>"No &mdash; but the doctor says she mustn't go out for weeks and 
weeks; and that will drive her mad.  She'll think the universe has 
come to a standstill." 
</p><p>"She'll find it hasn't," suggested Corbett, with a smile which 
took the edge from his comment. 
</p><p>"Ah, but such discoveries hurt &mdash; especially if one makes them 
late in life!" 
</p><p>Corbett stood looking affectionately at his wife. 
</p><p>"How long is it," he asked, "since you have seen your Aunt 
Mary?" 
</p><p>"I think it must be two years.  Yes, just two years; you know 
I went home on business after &mdash; "  She stopped; they never alluded 
to her first marriage. 
</p><p>Corbett took her hand.  "Well," he declared, glancing rather 
wistfully at the Paris Bordone above the mantel-piece, "we'll sail 
next month and pay her a little visit." 
</p> 
</div2> 
<div2 type="section" n="2" id="d5"> 
<head>                           II 

</head> 
<p>CORBETT was really making an immense concession in going to 
America at that season; he disliked the prospect at all times, but 
just as his hotel in Paris had reopened its luxurious arms to him 
for the winter, the thought of departure was peculiarly 
distasteful.  Delia knew it, and winced under the enormity of the 
sacrifice which he had imposed upon himself; but he bore the burden 
so lightly, and so smilingly derided her impulse to magnify the 
heroism of his conduct, that she gradually yielded to the 
undisturbed enjoyment of her anticipations.  She was really very 
glad to be returning to Boston as Corbett's wife; her occasional 
appearances there as Mrs. Benson had been so eminently 
unsatisfactory to herself and her relatives that she naturally 
desired to efface them by so triumphal a re-entry.  She had passed 
so great a part of her own life in Europe that she viewed with a 
secret leniency Corbett's indifference to his native land; but 
though she did not mind his not caring for his country she was 
intensely anxious that his country should care for him.  He was a 
New Yorker, and entirely unknown, save by name, to her little 
circle of friends and relatives in Boston; but she reflected, with 
tranquil satisfaction, that, if he were cosmopolitan enough for 
Fifth Avenue, he was also cultured enough for Beacon Street.  She 
was not so confident of his being altruistic enough for Aunt Mary; 
but Aunt Mary's appreciations covered so wide a range that there 
seemed small doubt of his coming under the head of one of her 
manifold enthusiasms. 
</p><p>Altogether Delia's anticipations grew steadily rosier with the 
approach to Sandy Hook; and to her confident eye the Statue of 
Liberty, as they passed under it in the red brilliance of a winter 
sunrise, seemed to look down upon Corbett with her Aunt Mary's most 
approving smile. 
</p><p>Delia's Aunt Mary &mdash; known from the Back Bay to the South End as 
Mrs. Mason Hayne &mdash; had been the chief formative influence of her 
niece's youth.  Delia, after the death of her parents, had even 
spent two years under Mrs. Hayne's roof, in direct contact with all 
her apostolic ardors, her inflammatory zeal for righteousness in 
everything from baking-powder to municipal government; and though 
the girl never felt any inclination to interpret her aunt's 
influence in action, it was potent in modifying her judgment of 
herself and others.  Her parents had been in-<pb n="422"/> curably 
frivolous, Mrs. Hayne was incurably serious, and Delia, by some 
unconscious powers of selection, tended to frivolity of conduct, 
corrected by seriousness of thought.  She would have shrunk from 
the life of unadorned activity, the unsmiling pursuit of Purposes 
with a capital letter, to which Mrs. Hayne's energies were 
dedicated; but it lent relief to her enjoyment of the purposeless 
to measure her own conduct by her aunt's utilitarian standards.  
This curious sympathy with aims so at variance with her own ideals 
would hardly have been possible to Delia had Mrs. Hayne been a 
narrow enthusiast without visual range beyond the blinders of her 
own vocation; it was the consciousness that her aunt's perceptions 
included even such obvious inutility as hers which made her so 
tolerant of her aunt's usefulness.  All this she had tried, on the 
way across the Atlantic, to put vividly before Corbett; but she was 
conscious of a vague inability on his part to adjust his conception 
of Mrs. Hayne to his wife's view of her; and Delia could only count 
on her aunt's abounding personality to correct the one-sidedness of 
his impression. 
</p><p>Mrs. Hayne lived in a wide brick house on Mount Vernon Street, 
which had belonged to her parents and grandparents, and from which 
she had never thought of moving.  Thither, on the evening of their 
arrival in Boston, the Corbetts were driven from the Providence 
Station.  Mrs. Hayne had written to her niece that Cyrus would meet 
them with a "hack;" Cyrus was a sable factotum designated in Mrs. 
Hayne's vocabulary as a "chore-man."  When the train entered the 
station he was, in fact, conspicuous on the platform, his smile 
shining like an open piano, while he proclaimed with abundant 
gesture the proximity of "de hack," and Delia, descending from the 
train into his dusky embrace, found herself guiltily wishing that 
he could have been omitted from the function of their arrival.  She 
could not help wondering what her husband's valet would think of 
him.  The valet was to be lodged at a hotel: Corbett himself had 
suggested that his presence might disturb the routine of Mrs. 
Hayne's household, a view in which Delia had eagerly acquiesced.  
There was, however, no possibility of dissembling Cyrus, and under 
the valet's depreciatory eye the Corbetts suffered him to precede 
them to the livery-stable landau, with blue shades and a 
confidentially disposed driver, which awaited them outside the 
station. 
</p><p>During the drive to Mount Vernon Street Delia was silent; but 
as they approached her aunt's swell-fronted domicile she said, 
hurriedly, "You won't like the house." 
</p><p>Corbett laughed.  "It's the inmate I've come to see," he 
commented. 
</p><p>"Oh, I'm not afraid of her," Delia almost too confidently 
rejoined. 
</p><p>The parlor-maid who admitted them to the hall (a discouraging 
hall, with a large-patterned oil-cloth and buff walls stencilled 
with a Greek border) informed them that Mrs. Hayne was above; and 
ascending to the next floor they found her genial figure, supported 
on crutches, awaiting them at the drawing-room door.  Mrs. Hayne 
was a tall, stoutish woman, whose bland expanse of feature was 
accentuated by a pair of gray eyes of such surpassing penetration 
that Delia often accused her of answering people's thoughts before 
they had finished thinking them.  These eyes, through the close 
fold of Delia's embrace, pierced instantly to Corbett, and never 
had that accomplished gentleman been more conscious of being called 
upon to present his credentials.  But there was no reservation in 
the uncritical warmth of Mrs. Hayne's welcome, and it was obvious 
that she was unaffectedly happy in their coming. 
</p><p>She led them into the drawing-room, still clinging to Delia, 
and Corbett, as he followed, understood why his wife had said that 
he would not like the house.  One saw at a glance that Mrs. Hayne 
had never had time to think of her house or her dress.  Both were 
scrupulously neat, but her gown might have been an unaltered one of 
her mother's, and her drawing-room wore the same appearance of 
contented archaism.  There was a sufficient number of arm-chairs, 
and the tables (mostly marble-topped) were redeemed from monotony 
by their freight of books; <pb n="423"/>  but it had not occurred to Mrs. 
Hayne to substitute logs for hard coal in her fireplace, nor to 
replace by more personal works of art the smoky expanses of canvas 
"after" Raphael and Murillo which lurched heavily forward from the 
walls.  She had even preserved the knotty antimacassars on her 
high-backed armchairs, and Corbett, who was growing bald, 
resignedly reflected that during his stay in Mount Vernon Street he 
should not be able to indulge in any lounging. 
</p> 
</div2> 
<div2 type="section" n="3" id="d6"> 
<head> 
                        III 
</head> 
<p>DELIA held back for three days the question which burned her 
lip; then, following her husband upstairs after an evening during 
which Mrs. Hayne had proved herself especially comprehensive (even 
questioning Corbett upon the tendencies of modern French art), she 
let escape the imminent "Well?" 
</p><p>"She's charming," Corbett returned, with the fine smile which 
always seemed like a delicate criticism. 
</p><p>"Really?" 
</p><p>"Really, Delia.  Do you think me so narrow that I can't value 
such a character as your aunt's simply because it's cast in 
different lines from mine?  I once told you that she must be a 
bundle of pedantries, and you prophesied that my first sight of her 
would correct that impression.  You were right; she's a bundle of 
extraordinary vitalities.  I never saw a woman more thoroughly 
alive; and that's the great secret of living &mdash; to be thoroughly 
alive." 
</p><p>"I knew it; I knew it!" his wife exclaimed.  "Two such people 
couldn't help liking each other." 
</p><p>"Oh, I should think she might very well help liking me." 
</p><p>"She doesn't; she admires you immensely; but why?" 
</p><p>"Well, I don't precisely fit into any of her ideals, and the 
worst part of having ideals is that the people who don't fit into 
them have to be discarded." 
</p><p>"Aunt Mary doesn't discard anybody," Delia interpolated. 
</p><p>"Her heart may not, but I fancy her judgment does." 
</p><p>"But she doesn't exactly fit into any of your ideals, and yet 
you like her," his wife persisted. 
</p><p>"I haven't any ideals," Corbett lightly responded.  <hi rend="italic"> "Je 
prends mon bien ou je le trouve;</hi> and I find a great deal in your 
Aunt Mary." 
</p><p>Delia did not ask Mrs. Hayne what she thought of her husband; 
she was sure that, in due time, her aunt would deliver her verdict; 
it was impossible for her to leave any one unclassified.  Perhaps, 
too, there was a latent cowardice in Delia's reticence; an 
unacknowledged dread lest Mrs. Hayne should range Corbett among the 
intermediate types. 
</p><p>After a day or two of mutual inspection and adjustment the 
three lives under Mrs. Hayne's roof lapsed into their separate 
routines.  Mrs. Hayne once more set in motion the complicated 
machinery of her own existence (rendered more intricate by the 
accident of her lameness), and Corbett and his wife began to dine 
out and return the visits of their friends.  There were, however, 
some hours which Corbett devoted to the club or to the 
frequentation of the public libraries, and these Delia gave to her 
aunt, driving with Mrs. Hayne from one committee meeting to 
another, writing business letters at her dictation, or reading 
aloud to her the reports of the various philanthropic, educational, 
or political institutions in which she was interested.  She had 
been conscious on her arrival of a certain aloofness from her 
aunt's militant activities; but within a week she was swept back 
into the strong current of Mrs. Hayne's existence.  It was like 
stepping from a gondola to an ocean steamer; at first she was dazed 
by the throb of the screw and the rush of the parting waters, but 
gradually she felt herself infected by the exhilaration of getting 
to a fixed place in the shortest possible time.  She could make 
sufficient allowance for the versatility of her moods to know that, 
a few weeks after her return to Paris, all that seemed most 
strenuous in Mrs. Hayne's occupations would fade to unreality; but 
that did not defend her from the strong spell of the moment.  In 
its light her own life seemed vacuous, her husband's aims trivial 
as the subtleties <pb n="424"/>  of Chinese ivory carving; and she 
wondered if he walked in the same revealing flash. 
</p><p>Some three weeks after the arrival of the Corbetts in Mount 
Vernon Street it became manifest that Mrs. Hayne had overtaxed her 
strength and must return for an undetermined period to her lounge.  
The life of restricted activity to which this necessity condemned 
her left her an occasional hour of leisure when there seemed no 
more letters to be dictated, no more reports to be read; and 
Corbett, always sure to do the right thing, was at hand to speed 
such unoccupied moments with the ready charm of his talk. 
</p><p>One day when, after sitting with her for some time, he 
departed to the club, Mrs. Hayne, turning to Delia, who came in to 
replace him, said, emphatically, "My dear, he's delightful." 
</p><p>"Oh, Aunt Mary, so are you!" burst gratefully from Mrs. 
Corbett. 
</p><p>Mrs. Hayne smiled.  "Have you suspended your judgment of me 
until now?" she asked. 
</p><p>"No; but your liking each other seems to complete you both." 
</p><p>"Really, Delia, your husband couldn't have put that more 
gracefully.  But sit down and tell me about him." 
</p><p>"Tell you about him?" repeated Delia, thinking of the 
voluminous letters in which she had enumerated to Mrs. Hayne the 
sum of her husband's merits. 
</p><p>"Yes," Mrs. Hayne continued, cutting, as she talked, the pages 
of a report on state lunatic asylums; "for instance, you've never 
told me why so charming an American has condemned America to the 
hard fate of being obliged to get on without him." 
</p><p>"You and he will never agree on that point, Aunt Mary," said 
Mrs. Corbett, coloring. 
</p><p>"Never mind; I rather like listening to reasons that I know 
beforehand I'm bound to disagree with; it saves so much mental 
effort.  And besides, how can you tell?  I'm very uncertain." 
</p><p>"You are very broad-minded, but you'll never understand his 
just having drifted into it.  Any definite reason would seem to you 
better than that." 
</p><p>"Ah &mdash; he drifted into it?" 
</p><p>"Well, yes.  You know his sister, who married the Comte de 
Vitrey and went to live in Paris, was very unhappy after her 
marriage; and when Laurence's mother died there was no one left to 
look after her; and so Laurence went abroad in order to be near 
her.  After a few years Monsieur de Vitrey died too; but by that 
time Laurence didn't care to come back." 
</p><p>"Well," said Mrs. Hayne, "I see nothing so shocking in that.  
Your husband can gratify his tastes much more easily in Europe than 
in America; and, after all, that is what we're all secretly 
striving to do.  I'm sure if there were more lunatic asylums and 
poor-houses and hospitals in Europe than there are here I should be 
very much inclined to go and live there myself." 
</p><p>Delia laughed.  "I knew you would like Laurence," she said, 
with a wisdom bred of the event. 
</p><p>"Of course I like him; he's a liberal education.  It's very 
interesting to study the determining motives in such a man's 
career.  How old is your husband, Delia?" 
</p><p>"Laurence is fifty-two." 
</p><p>"And when did he go abroad to look after his sister?" 
</p><p>"Let me see &mdash; when he was about twenty-eight; it was in 1867, 
I think." 
</p><p>"And before that he had lived in America?" 
</p><p>"Yes, the greater part of the time." 
</p><p>"Then of course he was in the war?" Mrs. Hayne continued, 
laying down her pamphlet.  "You've never told me about that.  Did 
he see any active service?" 
</p><p>As she spoke Delia grew pale; for a moment she sat looking 
blankly at her aunt. 
</p><p>"I don't think he was in the war at all," she said at length, 
in a low tone. 
</p><p>Mrs. Hayne stared at her.  "Oh, you must be mistaken," she 
said, decidedly.  "Why shouldn't he have been in the war?  What 
else could he have been doing?" 
</p><p>Mrs. Corbett was silent.  All the men of her family, all the 
men of her friends' families, had fought in the war; Mrs. Hayne's 
husband had been killed at Bull Run, and one of Delia's cousins at 
Gettysburg.  Ever since she could re-<pb n="425"/> member it had been 
regarded as a matter of course by those about her that every man of 
her husband's generation who was neither lame, halt, nor blind 
should have fought in the war.  Husbands had left their wives, 
fathers their children, young men their sweethearts, in answer to 
that summons; and those who had been deaf to it she had never heard 
designated by any name but one. 
</p><p>But all that had happened long ago; for years it had ceased to 
be a part of her consciousness.  She had forgotten about the war; 
about her uncle who fell at Bull Run, and her cousin who was killed 
at Gettysburg.  Now, of a sudden, it all came back to her, and she 
asked herself the question which her aunt had just put to her &mdash; why 
had her husband not been in the war?  What else could he have been 
doing? 
</p><p>But the very word, as she repeated it, struck her as 
incongruous; Corbett was a man who never did anything.  His 
elaborate intellectual processes bore no flower of result; he 
simply <hi rend="italic"> was</hi> &mdash; but had she not hitherto found that sufficient?  
She rose from her seat, turning away from Mrs. Hayne. 
</p><p>"I really don't know," she said, coldly.  "I never asked him." 
</p></div2> 
<div2 type="section" n="4" id="d7"><head>IV</head> 
<p>TWO weeks later the Corbetts returned to Europe.  Corbett had 
really been charmed with his visit, and had in fact shown a marked 
inclination to outstay the date originally fixed for their 
departure.  But Delia was firm; she did not wish to remain in 
Boston.  She acknowledged that she was sorry to leave her Aunt 
Mary; but she wanted to get home. 
</p><p>"You turncoat!" Corbett said, laughing.  "Two months ago you 
reserved that sacred designation for Boston." 
</p><p>"One can't tell where it is until one tries," she answered, 
vaguely. 
</p><p>"You mean that you don't want to come back and live in 
Boston?" 
</p><p>"Oh, no &mdash; no!" 
</p><p>"Very well.  But pray take note of the fact that I'm very 
sorry to leave.  Under your Aunt Mary's tutelage I'm becoming a 
passionate patriot." 
</p><p>Delia turned away in silence.  She was counting the moments 
which led to their departure.  She longed with an unreasoning 
intensity to get away from it all; from the dreary house in Mount 
Vernon Street, with its stencilled hall and hideous drawing-room, 
its monotonous food served in unappetizing profusion; from the 
rarefied atmosphere of philanthropy and reform which she had once 
found so invigorating; and most of all from the reproval of her 
aunt's altruistic activities.  The recollection of her husband's 
delightful house in Paris, so framed for a noble leisure, seemed to 
mock the aesthetic barrenness of Mrs. Hayne's environment.  Delia 
thought tenderly of the mellow bindings, the deep-piled rugs, the 
pictures, bronzes, and tapestries; of the "first nights" at the 
Francais, the eagerly discussed <hi rend="italic"> conferences</hi> on art or 
literature, the dreaming hours in galleries and museums, and all 
the delicate enjoyments of the life to which she was returning.  It 
would be like passing from a hospital-ward to a flower-filled 
drawing-room; how could her husband linger on the threshold? 
</p><p>Corbett, who observed her attentively, noticed that a change 
had come over her during the last two weeks of their stay in Mount 
Vernon Street.  He wondered uneasily if she were capricious; a man 
who has formed his own habits upon principles of the finest 
selection does not care to think that he has married a capricious 
woman.  Then he reflected that the love of Paris is an insidious 
disease, breaking out when its victim least looks for it, and 
concluded that Delia was suffering from some such unexpected 
attack. 
</p><p>Delia certainly was suffering.  Ever since Mrs. Hayne had 
asked her that innocent question &mdash; "Why shouldn't your husband have 
been in the war?" &mdash; she had been repeating it to herself day and 
night with the monotonous iteration of a monomaniac.  Whenever 
Corbett came into the room, with that air of giving the simplest 
act its due value which made episodes of his entrances she was 
tempted to cry out to him &mdash; "Why weren't you in the war?"  When she 
heard him, at a dinner, point one of his polished epigrams, or 
smilingly demolish the syllogism of an an-<pb n="426"/> tagonist, her 
pride in his achievement was chilled by the question &mdash; "Why wasn't 
he in the war?"  When she saw him, in the street, give a coin to a 
crossing-sweeper, or lift his hat ceremoniously to one of Mrs. 
Hayne's maid-servants (he was always considerate of poor people and 
servants) her approval winced under the reminder &mdash; "Why wasn't he in 
the war?"  And when they were alone together, all through the spell 
of his talk and the exquisite pervasion of his presence ran the 
embittering undercurrent, "Why wasn't he in the war?" 
</p><p>At times she hated herself for the thought; it seemed a 
disloyalty to life's best gift.  After all, what did it matter now?  
The war was over and forgotten; it was what the newspapers call "a 
dead issue."  And why should any act of her husband's youth affect 
their present happiness together?  Whatever he might once have 
been, he was perfect now; admirable in every relation of life; 
kind, generous, upright; a loyal friend, an accomplished gentleman, 
and, above all, the man she loved.  Yes &mdash; but why had he not been in 
the war?  And so began again the reiterant torment of the question.  
It rose up and lay down with her; it watched with her through 
sleepless nights, and followed her into the street; it mocked her 
from the eyes of strangers, and she dreaded lest her husband should 
read it in her own.  In her saner moments she told herself that she 
was under the influence of a passing mood, which would vanish at 
the contact of her wonted life in Paris.  She had become over-strung in the high air of Mrs. Hayne's moral enthusiasms; all she 
needed was to descend again to regions of more temperate virtue.  
This thought increased her impatience to be gone; and the days 
seemed interminable which divided her from departure. 
</p><p>The return to Paris, however, did not yield the hoped-for 
alleviation.  The question was still with her, clamoring for a 
reply, and reinforced, with separation, by the increasing fear of 
her aunt's unspoken verdict.  That shrewd woman had never again 
alluded to the subject of her brief colloquy with Delia; up to the 
moment of his farewell she had been unreservedly cordial to 
Corbett; but she was not the woman to palter with her convictions. 
</p><p>Delia knew what she must think; she knew what name, in the old 
days, Corbett would have gone by in her aunt's uncompromising 
circle. 
</p><p>Then came a flash of resistance &mdash; the heart's instinct of self-preservation.  After all, what did she herself know of her 
husband's reasons for not being in the war?  What right had she to 
set down to cowardice a course which might have been enforced by 
necessity, or dictated by unimpeachable motives?  Why should she 
not put to him the question which she was perpetually asking 
herself?  And not having done so, how dared she condemn him 
unheard? 
</p><p>A month or more passed in this torturing indecision.  Corbett 
had returned with fresh zest to his accustomed way of life, weaned, 
by his first glimpse of the Champs Elysees, from his factitious 
enthusiasm for Boston.  He and his wife entertained their friends 
delightfully, and frequented all the "first nights" and "private 
views" of the season, and Corbett continued to bring back knowing 
"bits" from the Hotel Drouot, and rare books from the quays; never 
had he appeared more cultivated, more decorative and enviable; 
people agreed that Delia Benson had been uncommonly clever to catch 
him. 
</p><p>One afternoon he returned later than usual from the club, and, 
finding his wife alone in the drawing-room, begged her for a cup of 
tea.  Delia reflected, in complying, that she had never seen him 
look better; his fifty-two years sat upon him like a finish which 
made youth appear crude, and his voice, as he recounted his 
afternoon's doings, had the intimate inflections reserved for her 
ear. 
</p><p>"By the way," he said presently, as he set down his tea-cup, 
"I had almost forgotten that I've brought you a present &mdash; something 
I picked up in a little shop in the Rue Bonaparte.  Oh, don't look 
too expectant; it's not a <hi rend="italic"> chef-d'oeuvre;</hi> on the contrary, it's 
about as bad as it can be.  But you'll see presently why I bought 
it." 
</p><p>As he spoke he drew a small flat parcel from the breast-pocket 
of his impec-<pb n="427"/> cable frock-coat and handed it to his wife. 
</p><p>Delia, loosening the paper which wrapped it, discovered within 
an oval frame studded with pearls and containing the crudely 
executed miniature of an unknown young man in the uniform of a 
United States cavalry officer.  She glanced inquiringly at Corbett. 
</p><p>"Turn it over," he said. 
</p><p>She did so, and on the back, beneath two unfamiliar initials, 
read the brief inscription: 
</p><p>"Fell at Chancellorsville, May 3, 1863." 
</p><p>The blood rushed to her face as she stood gazing at the words. 
</p><p>"You see now why I bought it?" Corbett continued.  "All the 
pieties of one's youth seemed to protest against leaving it in the 
clutches of a Jew pawnbroker in the Rue Bonaparte.  It's awfully 
bad, isn't it? &mdash; but some poor soul might be glad to think that it 
had passed again into the possession of fellow-countrymen."  He 
took it back from her, bending to examine it critically.  "What a 
daub!" he murmured.  "I wonder who he was?  Do you suppose that by 
taking a little trouble one might find out and restore it to his 
people?" 
</p><p>"I don't know &mdash; I dare say," she murmured, absently. 
</p><p>He looked up at the sound of her voice.  "What's the matter, 
Delia?  Don't you feel well?" he asked. 
</p><p>"Oh, yes.  I was only thinking" &mdash; she took the miniature from 
his hand.  "It was kind of you, Laurence, to buy this &mdash; it was like 
you." 
</p><p>"Thanks for the latter clause," he returned, smiling. 
</p><p>Delia stood staring at the vivid flesh-tints of the young man 
who had fallen at Chancellorsville. 
</p><p>"You weren't very strong at his age, were you, Laurence?  
Weren't you often ill?" she asked. 
</p><p>Corbett gave her a surprised glance.  "Not that I'm aware of," 
he said; "I had the measles at twelve, but since then I've been 
unromantically robust." 
</p><p>"And you &mdash; you were in America until you came abroad to be with 
your sister?" 
</p><p>"Yes &mdash; barring a trip of a few weeks in Europe." 
</p><p>Delia looked again at the miniature; then she fixed her eyes 
upon her husband's. 
</p><p>"Then why weren't you in the war?" she said. 
</p><p>Corbett answered her gaze for a moment; then his lids dropped, 
and he shifted his position slightly. 
</p><p>"Really," he said, with a smile, "I don't think I know." 
</p><p>They were the very words which she had used in answering her 
aunt. 
</p><p>"You don't know?" she repeated, the question leaping out like 
an electric shock.  "What do you mean when you say that you don't 
know?" 
</p><p>"Well &mdash; it all happened some time ago," he answered, still 
smiling, "and the truth is that I've completely forgotten the 
excellent reasons that I doubtless had at the time for remaining at 
home." 
</p><p>"Reasons for remaining at home?  But there were none; every 
man of your age went to the war; no one stayed at home who wasn't 
lame, or blind, or deaf, or ill, or &mdash; "  Her face blazed, her voice 
broke passionately. 
</p><p>Corbett looked at her with rising amazement. 
</p><p>"Or &mdash; ?" he said. 
</p><p>"Or a coward," she flashed out.  The miniature dropped from 
her hands, falling loudly on the polished floor. 
</p><p>The two confronted each other in silence; Corbett was very 
pale. 
</p><p>"I've told you," he said, at length, "that I was neither lame, 
deaf, blind, nor ill.  Your classification is so simple that it 
will be easy for you to draw your own conclusion." 
</p><p>And very quietly, with that admirable air which always put him 
in the right, he walked out of the room.  Delia, left alone, bent 
down and picked up the miniature; its protecting crystal had been 
broken by the fall.  She pressed it close to her and burst into 
tears. 
</p><p>An hour later, of course, she went to ask her husband's 
forgiveness.  As a woman of sense she could do no less; and her 
conduct had been so absurd that it was the more obviously 
pardonable.  Corbett, as he kissed her hand, assured her that he 
had known it was only nervousness; and after dinner, during which 
he made himself excep-<pb n="428"/> tionally agreeable, he proposed their 
ending the evening at the Palais Royal, where a new play was being 
given. 
</p><p>Delia had undoubtedly behaved like a fool, and was prepared to 
do meet penance for her folly by submitting to the gentle sarcasm 
of her husband's pardon; but when the episode was over, and she 
realized that she had asked her question and received her answer, 
she knew that she had passed a milestone in her existence.  Corbett 
was perfectly charming; it was inevitable that he should go on 
being charming to the end of the chapter.  It was equally 
inevitable that she should go on being in love with him; but her 
love had undergone a modification which the years were not to 
efface. 
</p><p>Formerly he had been to her like an unexplored country, full 
of bewitching surprises and recurrent revelations of wonder and 
beauty; now she had measured and mapped him, and knew beforehand 
the direction of every path she trod.  His answer to her question 
had given her the clue to the labyrinth; knowing what he had once 
done, it seemed quite simple to forecast his future conduct.  For 
that long-past action was still a part of his actual being; he had 
not outlived or disowned it; he had not even seen that it needed 
defending. 
</p><p>Her ideal of him was shivered like the crystal above the 
miniature of the warrior of Chancellorsville.  She had the crystal 
replaced by a piece of clear glass which (as the jeweller pointed 
out to her) cost much less and looked equally well; and for the 
passionate worship which she had paid her husband she substituted 
a tolerant affection which possessed precisely the same advantages. 
</p> 
 
</div2> 
</div1> 
</body> 
</text> 
</TEI.2> 
