<?xml version="1.0"?>

<?dlps id="WhaLege"?>
<?dlps page-images="none" figure-images="no"?>
<?dlps transcription="other"?>

<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/tei-p4/tei2.dtd" [
<!ENTITY % POSTKB "INCLUDE">
<!ENTITY % TEI.extensions.ent SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.ent">
<!ENTITY % TEI.extensions.dtd SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.dtd">
<!ENTITY % ISOnum SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/charent/iso-num.ent"> %ISOnum;
<!ENTITY % ISOpub SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/charent/iso-pub.ent"> %ISOpub;

]>

<TEI.2 id="WhaLege"> 
<teiHeader type="migrated" creator="Etext">
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title type="main">The Legend</title>
<title type="sort">legend</title>
<author>Wharton, Edith, 1862-1937</author>
<respStmt>
<resp>Creation of machine-readable version</resp>
<name>Judy Boss</name>
</respStmt>
<respStmt>
<resp>Conversion to TEI-conformant markup</resp>
<name>University of Virginia Library Electronic Text Center</name>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt> 
<extent>ca. <num type="kilobytes">66</num> kilobytes</extent> 
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>University of Virginia Library</publisher>
<pubPlace>Charlottesville, Virginia</pubPlace> 
<idno type="ETC">WhaLege</idno> 
<date value="1995">1995</date>
<availability status="public">
<p n="copyright">Copyright &copy; 1995 by the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia</p>
<p n="access">Publicly accessible</p>
</availability>
<idno type="uva-pid">uva-lib:476499</idno>
</publicationStmt>
<seriesStmt>
<title>University of Virginia Library, Text collection</title>
<idno type="uva-set">UVA-LIB-Text</idno>
</seriesStmt> 
<sourceDesc>
<biblFull>
<titleStmt>
<title type="main">The Legend</title>
<title type="sort">legend</title>
<author>Edith Wharton</author>
</titleStmt> 
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>Scribner's</publisher> 
<pubPlace>New York</pubPlace> 
<date value="1910">1910</date>
</publicationStmt> 
<seriesStmt>
<p>Scribner's Magazine</p>
</seriesStmt> 
<notesStmt>
<note>
<p>March 1910, pp. 278-291</p>
</note>
</notesStmt>
</biblFull>
</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc> 
<encodingDesc>
<projectDesc>
<p>Prepared for the University of Virginia Library Electronic Text Center</p>
</projectDesc> 
<editorialDecl>
<p>All quotation marks retained as data</p> 
<p id="ETC">Keywords in the header are a local Electronic Text Center scheme  
to aid in establishing analytical groupings</p>
</editorialDecl> 
<refsDecl>
<p>ID elements are given for each page element and are composed of the text's 
unique cryptogram and the given page number, as in SpeFQue1 for page one of  
Spenser's Faerie Queene.</p>
</refsDecl>
</encodingDesc> 
<profileDesc>
<creation>
<date value="1910-03">March 1910</date>
</creation> 
<langUsage>
<language id="eng" usage="main">English</language>
</langUsage> 
<textClass>
<keywords>
<term>fiction</term>
<term>prose</term>
</keywords>
</textClass>
</profileDesc> 
<revisionDesc>
<change>
<date value="1995-02">February 1995</date> 
<respStmt>
<resp>corrector</resp>
<name>Monique Dull, University of Virginia Electronic Text Center</name>
</respStmt>
<item>conversion to basic TEI-conformant markup</item>
</change> 
<change>
<date value="2005-07">July 2005</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>Corrector</resp>
<name>Margaret Konkol</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Converted SGML to XML and fixed tagging.</item>
</change>
<change>
<date value="2007-09">September 2007</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>Migration</resp>
<name>Ethan Gruber, University of Virginia Library</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Converted XML markup from TEI Lite to uva-dl-tei (TEI P4 with local customizations).</item>
</change>
<change>
<date value="2008-01">January 2008</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>Migration</resp>
<name>Greg Murray, University of Virginia Library</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Programmatically updated TEI header markup (but not header content) for minimal compliance with current QA requirements.</item>
</change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader> 
<text id="d1">  
<body id="d2"> 
<div1 type="story" id="d3"> 
<pb n="278"/>  
<head> 
<hi rend="italic">TALES OF MEN</hi> 
<lb/> 
THE LEGEND 
</head> 
<div2 type="chapter" n="1" id="d4"> 
<head>I</head> 
<p>ARTHUR BERNALD could never afterward recall just when the first 
conjecture flashed on him: oddly enough, there was no record of it 
in the agitated jottings of his diary.  But, as it seemed to him in 
retrospect, he had always felt that the queer man at the Wades' 
must be John Pellerin, if only for the negative reason that he 
couldn't imaginably be any one else.  It was impossible, in the 
confused pattern of the century's intellectual life, to fit the 
stranger in anywhere, save in the big gap which, some five and 
twenty years earlier, had been left by Pellerin's unaccountable 
disappearance; and conversely, such a man as the Wades' visitor 
couldn't have lived for sixty years without filling, somewhere in 
space, a nearly equivalent void. 
</p><p>At all events, it was certainly not to Doctor Wade or to his 
mother that Bernald owed the hint: the good unconscious Wades, one 
of whose chief charms in the young man's eyes was that they 
remained so robustly untainted by Pellerinism, in spite of the fact 
that Doctor Wade's younger brother, Howland, was among its most 
impudently flourishing high-priests. 
</p><p>The incident had begun by Bernald's running across Doctor 
Robert Wade one hot summer night at the University Club, and by 
Wade's saying, in the tone of unprofessional laxity which the 
shadowy stillness of the place invited: "I got hold of a queer fish 
at St. Martin's the other day &mdash; case of heat-prostration picked up 
in Central Park.  When we'd patched him up I found he had nowhere 
to go, and not a dollar in his pocket, and I sent him down to our 
place at Portchester to re-build." 
</p><p>The opening roused his hearer's attention.  Bob Wade had an 
odd unformulated sense of values that Bernald had learned to trust. 
</p><p>"What sort of chap?  Young or old?" 
</p><p>"Oh, every age &mdash; full of years, and yet with a lot left.  He 
called himself sixty on the books." 
</p><p>"Sixty's a good age for some kinds of living.  And age is of 
course purely subjective.  How has he used his sixty years?" 
</p><p>"Well &mdash; part of them in educating himself, apparently.  He's a 
scholar &mdash; humanities, languages, and so forth." 
</p><p>"Oh &mdash; decayed gentleman," Bernald murmured, disappointed. 
</p><p>"Decayed?  Not much!" cried the doctor with his accustomed 
literalness.  "I only mentioned that side of Winterman &mdash; his name's 
Winterman &mdash; because it was the side my mother noticed first.  I 
suppose women generally do.  But it's only a part &mdash; a small part.  
The man's the big thing." 
</p><p>"Really big?" 
</p><p>"Well &mdash; there again. . . .  When I took him down to the 
country, looking rather like a tramp from a 'Shelter,' with an 
untrimmed beard, and a suit of reach-me-downs he'd slept round the 
Park in for a week, I felt sure my mother'd carry the silver up to 
her room, and send for the gardener's dog to sleep in the hall the 
first night.  But she didn't." 
</p><p>"I see.  'Women and children love him.'  Oh, Wade!" Bernald 
groaned. 
</p><p>"Not a bit of it!  You're out again.  We don't love him, 
either of us.  But we <hi rend="italic">feel</hi> him &mdash; the air's charged with him.  
You'll see." 
</p><p>And Bernald agreed that he <hi rend="italic">would</hi> see, the following 
Sunday.  Wade's inarticulate attempts to characterize the stranger 
had struck his friend.  The human revelation had for Bernald a 
poignant and ever-renewed interest, which his trade, as the 
dramatic critic of a daily paper, had hitherto failed to 
discourage.  And he knew that Bob Wade, simple and undefiled by 
literature &mdash; Bernald's specific affliction &mdash; had a free and personal 
way of judging men, and the diviner's knack of reaching their 
hidden <pb n="279"/>  springs.  During the days that followed, the young 
doctor gave Bernald farther details about John Winterman: details 
not of fact &mdash; for in that respect his visitor's reticence was 
baffling &mdash; but of impression.  It appeared that Winterman, while 
lying insensible in the Park, had been robbed of the few dollars he 
possessed; and on leaving the hospital, still weak and half-blind, 
he had quite simply and unprotestingly accepted the Wades' offer to 
give him shelter till such time as he should be strong enough to go 
to work. 
</p><p>"But what's his work?" Bernald interjected.  "Hasn't he at 
least told you that?" 
</p><p>"Well, writing.  Some kind of writing."  Doctor Bob always 
became vague and clumsy when he approached the confines of 
literature.  "He means to take it up again as soon as his eyes get 
right." 
</p><p>Bernald groaned.  "Oh, Lord &mdash; that finishes him; and <hi rend="italic">me!</hi>  
He's looking for a publisher, of course &mdash; he wants a 'favourable 
notice.'  I won't come!" 
</p><p>"He hasn't written a line for twenty years." 
</p><p>"A line of <hi rend="italic">what?</hi>  What kind of literature can one keep 
corked up for twenty years?" 
</p><p>Wade surprised him.  "The real kind, I should say.  But I 
don't know Winterman's line," the doctor added.  "He speaks of the 
things he used to write merely as 'stuff that wouldn't sell.'  He 
has a wonderfully confidential way of <hi rend="italic">not</hi> telling one things.  
But he says he'll have to do something for his living as soon as 
his eyes are patched up, and that writing is the only trade he 
knows.  The queer thing is that he seems pretty sure of selling 
<hi rend="italic">now</hi>.  He even talked of buying the bungalow of us, with an acre or 
two about it." 
</p><p>"The bungalow?  What's that?" 
</p><p>"The studio down by the shore that we built for Howland when 
he thought he meant to paint."  (Howland Wade, as Bernald knew, had 
experienced various "calls.")  "Since he's taken to writing 
nobody's been near it.  I offered it to Winterman, and he camps 
there &mdash; cooks his meals, does his own house-keeping, and never comes 
up to the house except in the evenings, when he joins us on the 
verandah, in the dark, and smokes while my mother knits." 
</p><p>"A discreet visitor, eh?" 
</p><p>"More than he need be.  My mother actually wanted him to stay 
on in the house &mdash; in her pink chintz room.  Think of it!  But he 
says houses smother him.  I take it he's lived for years in the 
open." 
</p><p>"In the open where?" 
</p><p>"I can't make out, except that it was somewhere in the East.  
'East of everything &mdash; beyond the day-spring.  In places not on the 
map.'  That's the way he put it; and when I said: 'You've been an 
explorer, then?' he smiled in his beard, and answered: 'Yes; that's 
it &mdash; an explorer.'  Yet he doesn't strike me as a man of action: 
hasn't the hands or the eyes." 
</p><p>"What sort of hands and eyes has he?" 
</p><p>Wade reflected.  His range of observation was not large, but 
within its limits it was exact and could give an account of itself. 
</p><p>"He's worked a lot with his hands, but that's not what they 
were made for.  I should say they were extraordinarily delicate 
conductors of sensation.  And his eye &mdash; his eye too.  He hasn't used 
it to dominate people: he didn't care to.  He simply looks through 
'em all like windows.  Makes me feel like the fellows who think 
they're made of glass.  The mitigating circumstance is that he 
seems to see such a glorious landscape through me."  Wade grinned 
at the thought of serving such a purpose. 
</p><p>"I see.  I'll come on Sunday and be looked through!" Bernald 
cried. 
</p> 
</div2> 
<div2 type="chapter" n="2" id="d5"> 
<head>                                 
II 
</head> 
<p>BERNALD came on two successive Sundays; and the second time he 
lingered till the Tuesday. 
</p><p>"Here he comes!" Wade had said, the first evening, as the two 
young men, with Wade's mother sat in the sultry dusk, with the 
Virginian creeper drawing, between the verandah arches, its black 
arabesques against a moon-lined sky. 
</p><p>In the darkness Bernald heard a step on the gravel, and saw 
the red flit of a cigar through the shrubs.  Then a loosely-moving 
figure obscured the patch of sky between the creepers, and the red 
spark became the centre of a dim bearded face, in which Bernald 
discerned only a broad white gleam of forehead. 
</p><p>It was the young man's subsequent impression that Winterman 
had not spoken <pb n="280"/>  much that first evening; at any rate, 
Bernald himself remembered chiefly what the Wades had said.  And 
this was the more curious because he had come for the purpose of 
studying their visitor, and because there was nothing to divert him 
from that purpose in Wade's halting communications or his mother's 
artless comments.  He reflected afterward that there must have been 
a mysteriously fertilizing quality in the stranger's silence: it 
had brooded over their talk like a large moist cloud above a dry 
country. 
</p><p>Mrs. Wade, apparently apprehensive lest her son should have 
given Bernald an exaggerated notion of their visitor's importance, 
had hastened to qualify it before the latter appeared. 
</p><p>"He's not what you or Howland would call 
intellectual &mdash; "(Bernald writhed at the coupling of the names) &mdash; "not 
in the least <hi rend="italic">literary;</hi> though he told Bob he used to write.  I 
don't think, though, it could have been what Howland would call 
writing."  Mrs. Wade always mentioned her younger son with a 
reverential drop of the voice.  She viewed literature much as she 
did Providence, as an inscrutably mystery; and she spoke of Howland 
as a dedicated being, set apart to perform secret rites within the 
veil of the sanctuary. 
</p><p>"I shouldn't say he had a quick mind," she continued, 
reverting apologetically to Winterman.  "Sometimes he hardly seems 
to follow what we're saying.  But he's got such sound ideas &mdash; when 
he does speak he's never silly.  And clever people sometimes 
<hi rend="italic">are</hi>, don't you think so?"  Bernald groaned an unqualified assent.  
"And he's so capable.  The other day something went wrong with the 
kitchen range, just as I was expecting some friends of Bob's for 
dinner; and do you know, when Mr. Winterman heard we were in 
trouble, he came and took a look, and knew at once what to do?  I 
told him it was a dreadful pity he wasn't married!" 
 
</p><p>Close on midnight, when the session on the verandah ended, and 
the two young men were strolling down to the bungalow at 
Winterman's side, Bernald's mind reverted to the image of the 
fertilizing cloud.  There was something brooding, pregnant, in the 
silent presence beside him: he had, in place of any circumscribing 
impression of the individual, a large hovering sense of manifold 
latent meanings.  And he felt a distinct thrill of relief when, 
half-way down the lawn, Doctor Bob was checked by a voice that 
called him back to the telephone. 
</p><p>"Now I'll be with him alone!" thought Bernald, with a throb 
like a lover's. 
</p><p>In the low-ceilinged bungalow Winterman had to grope for the 
lamp on his desk, and as its light struck up into his face 
Bernald's sense of the rareness of his opportunity increased.  He 
couldn't have said why, for the face, with its ridged brows, its 
shabby greyish beard and blunt Socratic nose, made no direct appeal 
to the eye.  It seemed rather like a stage on which remarkable 
things might be enacted, like some shaggy moorland landscape 
dependent for form and expression on the clouds rolling over it, 
and the bursts of light between; and one of these flashed out in 
the smile with which Winterman, as if in answer to his companion's 
thought, said simply, as he turned to fill his pipe: "Now we'll 
talk." 
</p><p>So he'd known all along that they hadn't yet &mdash; and had guessed 
that, with Bernald, one might! 
</p><p>The young man's glow of pleasure was so intense that it left 
him for a moment unable to meet the challenge; and in that moment 
he felt the brush of something winged and summoning.  His spirit 
rose to it with a rush; but just as he felt himself poised between 
the ascending pinions, the door opened and Bob Wade plunged in. 
</p><p>"Too bad!  I'm so sorry!  It was from Howland, to say he can't 
come to-morrow after all."  The doctor panted out his news with 
honest grief. 
</p><p>"I tried my best to pull it off for you; and my brother 
<hi rend="italic">wants</hi> to come &mdash; he's keen to talk to you and see what he can do.  
But you see he's so tremendously in demand.  He'll try for another 
Sunday later on." 
</p><p>Winterman nodded with a whimsical gesture.  "Oh, he'll find me 
here.  I shall work my time out slowly."  He pointed to the 
scattered sheets on the kitchen table which formed his writing 
desk. 
</p><p>"Not slowly enough to suit us," Wade answered hospitably.  
"Only, if Howland could have come he might have given you a tip or 
two &mdash; put you on the right track &mdash; shown you how to get in touch with 
the public." 
</p><p>Winterman, his hands in his sagging <pb n="281"/>  pockets, lounged 
against the bare pine walls, twisting his pipe under his beard.  
"Does your brother enjoy the privilege of that contact?" he 
questioned gravely. 
</p><p>Wade stared a little.  "Oh, of course Howland's not what you'd 
call a <hi rend="italic">popular</hi> writer; he despises that kind of thing.  But 
whatever he says goes with &mdash; well, with the chaps that count; and 
every one tells me he's written <hi rend="italic">the</hi> book on Pellerin.  You must 
read it when you get back your eyes."  He paused, as if to let the 
name sink in, but Winterman drew at his pipe with a blank face.  
"You must have heard of Pellerin, I suppose?" the doctor continued.  
"I've never read a word of him myself: he's too big a proposition 
for <hi rend="italic">me</hi>.  But one can't escape the talk about him.  I have him 
crammed down my throat even in hospital.  The internes read him at 
the clinics.  He tumbles out of the nurses' pockets.  The patients 
keep him under their pillows.  Oh, with most of them, of course, 
it's just a craze, like the last new game or puzzle: they don't 
understand him in the least.  Howland says that even now, twenty-five years after his death, and with his books in everybody's 
hands, there are not twenty people who really understand Pellerin; 
and Howland ought to know, if anybody does.  He's &mdash; what's their 
great word? &mdash; <hi rend="italic">interpreted</hi> him.  You must get Howland to put you 
through a course of Pellerin." 
</p><p>And as the young men, having taken leave of Winterman, 
retraced their way across the lawn, Wade continued to develop the 
theme of his brother's accomplishments. 
</p><p>"I wish I <hi rend="italic">could</hi> get Howland to take an interest in 
Winterman: this is the third Sunday he's chucked us.  Of course he 
does get bored with people consulting him about their writings &mdash; but 
I believe if he could only talk to Winterman he'd see something in 
him, as we do.  And it would be such a god-send to the poor man to 
have some one to advise him about his work.  I'm going to make a 
desperate effort to get Howland here next Sunday." 
 
</p><p>It was then that Bernald vowed to himself that he would return 
the next Sunday at all costs.  He hardly knew whether he was 
prompted by the impulse to shield Winterman from Howland Wade's 
ineptitude, or by the desire to see the latter abandon himself to 
the full shamelessness of its display; but of one fact he was 
blissfully assured &mdash; and that was of the existence in Winterman of 
some quality which would provoke Howland to the amplest exercise of 
his fatuity.  "How he'll draw him &mdash; how he'll draw him!" Bernald 
chuckled, with a security the more unaccountable that his one 
glimpse of Winterman had shown the latter only as a passive subject 
for experimentation; and he felt himself avenged in advance for the 
injury of Howland Wade's existence. 
</p> 
</div2> 
<div2 type="chapter" n="3" id="d6"> 
<head> 
III 
</head> 
<p>THAT this hope was to be frustrated Bernald learned from 
Howland Wade's own lips, the day before the two young men were to 
meet at Portchester. 
</p><p>"I can't really, my dear fellow," the Interpreter lisped, 
passing a polished hand over the faded smoothness of his face.  
"Oh, an authentic engagement, I assure you: otherwise, to oblige 
old Bob I'd submit cheerfully to looking over his foundling's 
literature.  But I'm pledged this week to the Pellerin Society of 
Kenosha: I had a hand in founding it, and for two years now they've 
been patiently waiting for a word from me &mdash; the <hi rend="italic">Fiat Lux</hi>, so to 
speak.  You see it's a ministry, Bernald &mdash; I assure you, I look upon 
my calling quite religiously." 
</p><p>As Bernald listened, his disappointment gradually changed to 
relief.  Howland, on trial, always turned out to be too 
insufferable, and the pleasure of watching his antics was 
invariably lost in the impulse to put a sanguinary end to them. 
</p><p>"If he'd only keep his beastly pink hands off Pellerin," 
Bernald groaned, thinking of the thick manuscript condemned to 
perpetual incarceration in his own desk by the publication of 
Howland's "definitive" work on the great man.  One couldn't, 
<hi rend="italic"> after </hi> Howland Wade, expose one's self to the derision of writing 
about Pellerin: the eagerness with which Wade's book had been 
devoured proved, not that the public had enough appetite for 
another, but simply that, for a stomach so undiscriminating, 
anything better than Wade had given it would be too good.  And 
Bernald, in the confidence that his own work was open to this 
objection, had stoically locked it up.  Yet if he had resigned his 
exasperated intelligence to the fact that Wade's book existed, 

 <pb n="282"/> 

and was already passing into the immortality of 
perpetual republication, he could not, after repeated trials, 
adjust himself to the author's talk about Pellerin.  When Wade 
wrote of the great dead he was egregious, but in conversation he 
was familiar and fond.  It might have been supposed that one of the 
beauties of Pellerin's hidden life and mysterious taking off would 
have been to guard him from the fingering of anecdote; but 
biographers like Howland Wade were born to rise above such 
obstacles.  He might be vague or inaccurate in dealing with the few 
recorded events of his subject's life; but when he left fact for 
conjecture no one had a firmer footing.  Whole chapters in his 
volume were constructed in the conditional mood and packed with 
hypothetical detail; and in talk, by the very law of the process, 
hypothesis became affirmation, and he was ready to tell you 
confidentially the exact circumstances of Pellerin's death, and of 
the "distressing incident" leading up to it.  Bernald himself not 
only questioned the form under which this incident was shaping 
itself before posterity, but the mere radical fact of its 
occurrence: he had never been able to discover any break in the 
dense cloud enveloping Pellerin's later life and its mysterious 
termination.  He had gone away &mdash; that was all that any of them knew: 
he who had so little, at any time, been with them or of them; and 
his going had so slightly stirred the public consciousness that 
even the subsequent news of his death, laconically imparted from 
afar, had dropped unheeded into the universal scrap-basket, to be 
long afterward fished out, with all its details missing, when some 
enquiring spirit first became aware, by chance encounter with a 
two-penny volume in a London book-stall, not only that such a man 
as John Pellerin had died, but that he had ever lived, or written. 
</p><p>It need hardly be noted that Howland Wade had not been the 
pioneer in question: his had been the wiser part of swelling the 
chorus when it rose, and gradually drowning the other voices by his 
own insistent note.  He had pitched the note so screamingly, and 
held it so long, that he was now the accepted authority on 
Pellerin, not only in the land which had given birth to his genius 
but in the Europe which had first acclaimed it; and it was the 
central point of pain in Bernald's sense of the situation that a 
man who had so yearned for silence as Pellerin should have his 
grave piped over by such a voice as Wade's. 
</p><p>Bernald's talk with the Interpreter had revived this ache to 
the momentary exclusion of other sensations; and he was still sore 
with it when, the next afternoon, he arrived at Portchester for his 
second Sunday with the Wades. 
</p><p>At the station he had the surprise of seeing Winterman's face 
on the platform, and of hearing from him that Doctor Bob had been 
called away to assist at an operation in a distant town. 
</p><p>"Mrs. Wade wanted to put you off, but I believe the message 
came too late; so she sent me down to break the news to you," said 
Winterman, holding out his hand. 
</p><p>Perhaps because they were the first conventional words that 
Bernald had heard him speak, the young man was struck by the relief 
his intonation gave them. 
</p><p>"She wanted to send a carriage," Winterman added, "but I told 
her we'd walk back through the woods."  He looked at Bernald with 
a sudden kindness that flushed the young man with pleasure. 
</p><p>"Are you strong enough?  It's not too far?" 
</p><p>"Oh, no.  I'm pulling myself together.  Getting back to work 
is the slowest part of the business: not on account of my eyes &mdash; I 
can use them now, though not for reading; but some of the links 
between things are missing.  It's a kind of broken spectrum . . . 
here, that boy will look after your bag." 
</p><p>The walk through the woods remained in Bernald's memory as an 
enchanted hour.  He used the word literally, as descriptive of the 
way in which Winterman's contact changed the face of things, or 
perhaps restored them to their primitive meanings.  And the scene 
they traversed &mdash; one of those little untended woods that still, in 
America, fringe the tawdry skirts of civilization &mdash; acquired, as a 
background to Winterman, the hush of a spot aware of transcendent 
visitings.  Did he talk, or did he make Bernald talk?  The young 
man never knew.  He recalled only a sense of lightness and 
liberation, as if the hard walls of individuality had melted, and 
he were merged in the poet's deeper interfusion, yet without losing 
the least sharp edge of self.  This general impression resolved 
itself afterward into the <pb n="283"/>  sense of Winterman's wide 
elemental range.  His thought encircled things like the horizon at 
sea.  He didn't, as it happened, touch on lofty themes &mdash; Bernald was 
gleefully aware that, to Howland Wade, their talk would hardly have 
been Talk at all &mdash; but Winterman's mind, applied to lowly topics, 
was like a powerful lens that brought out microscopic delicacies 
and differences. 
</p><p>The lack of Sunday trains kept Doctor Bob for two days on the 
scene of his surgical duties, and during those two days Bernald 
seized every moment of communion with his friend's guest.  
Winterman, as Wade had said, was reticent as to his personal 
affairs, or rather as to the practical and material conditions to 
which the term is generally applied.  But it was evident that, in 
Winterman's case, the usual classification must be reversed, and 
that the discussion of ideas carried one much farther into his 
intimacy than any specific acquaintance with the incidents of his 
life. 
</p><p>"That's exactly what Howland Wade and his tribe have never 
understood about Pellerin: that it's much less important to know 
how, or even why, he disapp &mdash; " 
</p><p>Bernald pulled himself up with a jerk, and turned to look full 
at his companion.  It was late on the Monday evening, and the two 
men, after an hour's chat on the verandah to the tune of Mrs. 
Wade's knitting-needles, had bidden their hostess good-night and 
strolled back to the bungalow together. 
</p><p>"Come and have a pipe before you turn in," Winterman had said; 
and they had sat on together till midnight, with the door of the 
bungalow open on a heaving moonlit bay, and summer insects bumping 
against the chimney of the lamp.  Winterman had just bent down to 
re-fill his pipe from the jar on the table, and Bernald, jerking 
about to catch him in the yellow circle of lamplight, sat 
speechless, staring at a fact that seemed suddenly to have 
substituted itself for Winterman's face, or rather to have taken on 
its features. 
</p><p>"No, they never saw that Pellerin's ideas <hi rend="italic">were</hi> Pellerin. 
. . ."  He continued to stare at Winterman.  "Just as this man's 
ideas are &mdash; why, <hi rend="italic">are</hi> Pellerin!" 
</p><p>The thought uttered itself in a kind of inner shout, and 
Bernald started upright with the violent impact of his conclusion.  
Again and again in the last forty-eight hours he had exclaimed to 
himself: "This is as good as Pellerin."  Why hadn't he said till 
now: "This <hi rend="italic">is</hi> Pellerin"? . . .  Surprising as the answer was, 
he had no choice but to take it.  He hadn't said so simply because 
Winterman was <hi rend="italic">better than Pellerin</hi> &mdash; that there was so much more 
of him, so to speak.  Yes; but &mdash; it came to Bernald in a flash &mdash;  
wouldn't there by this time have been any amount more of Pellerin? 
. . .  The young man felt actually dizzy with the thought.  That 
was it &mdash; there was the solution of the haunting problem!  This man 
was Pellerin, and more than Pellerin!  It was so fantastic and yet 
so unanswerable that he burst into a sudden startled laugh. 
</p><p>Winterman, at the same moment, brought his palm down with a 
sudden crash on the pile of manuscript covering the desk. 
</p><p>"What's the matter?" Bernald gasped. 
</p><p>"My match wasn't out.  In another minute the destruction of 
the library of Alexandria would have been a trifle compared to what 
you'd have seen."  Winterman, with his large deep laugh, shook out 
the smouldering sheets.  "And I should have been a pensioner on 
Doctor Bob the Lord knows how much longer!" 
</p><p>Bernald pulled himself together.  "You've really got going 
again?  The thing's actually getting into shape?" 
</p><p>"This particular thing <hi rend="italic">is</hi> in shape.  I drove at it hard 
all last week, thinking our friend's brother would be down on 
Sunday, and might look it over." 
</p><p>Bernald had to repress the tendency to another wild laugh. 
</p><p>"Howland &mdash; you meant to show <hi rend="italic">Howland</hi> what you've done?" 
</p><p>Winterman, looming against the moonlight, slowly turned a 
dusky shaggy head toward him. 
</p><p>"Isn't it a good thing to do?" 
</p><p>Bernald wavered, torn between loyalty to his friends and the 
grotesqueness of answering in the affirmative.  After all, it was 
none of his business to furnish Winterman with an estimate of 
Howland Wade. 
</p><p>"Well, you see, you've never told me what your line <hi rend="italic">is</hi>," 
he answered, temporizing. 
</p><p>"No, because nobody's ever told <hi rend="italic">me</hi>.  It's exactly what I 
want to find out," said the other genially. 
</p><p>"And you expect Wade &mdash; ?" <pb n="284"/>  
</p><p>"Why, I gathered from our good Doctor that it's his trade.  
Doesn't he explain &mdash; interpret?" 
</p><p>"In his own domain &mdash; which is Pellerinism." 
</p><p>Winterman gazed out musingly upon the moon-touched dusk of 
waters.  "And what <hi rend="italic">is</hi> Pellerinism?" he asked. 
</p><p>Bernald sprang to his feet with a cry.  "Ah, I don't know &mdash; but 
you're Pellerin!" 
</p><p>They stood for a minute facing each other, among the uncertain 
swaying shadows of the room, with the sea breathing through it as 
something immense and inarticulate breathed through young Bernald's 
thoughts; then Winterman threw up his arms with a humorous gesture. 
</p><p>"Don't shoot!" he said. 
</p> 
</div2> 
<div2 type="chapter" n="4" id="d7"> 
<head>                                 
IV 
</head> 
<p>DAWN found them there, and the risen sun laid its beams on the 
rough floor of the bungalow, before either of the men was conscious 
of the passage of time.  Bernald, vaguely trying to define his own 
state in retrospect, could only phrase it: "I floated . . . 
floated. . . ." 
</p><p>The gist of fact at the core of the extraordinary experience 
was simply that John Pellerin, twenty-five years earlier, had 
voluntarily disappeared, causing the rumour of his death to be 
reported to an inattentive world; and that now he had come back to 
see what that world had made of him. 
</p><p>"You'll hardly believe it of me; I hardly believe it of 
myself; but I went away in a rage of disappointment, of wounded 
pride &mdash; no, vanity!  I don't know which cut deepest &mdash; the sneers or 
the silence &mdash; but between them, there wasn't an inch of me that 
wasn't raw.  I had just the one thing in me: the message, the cry, 
the revelation.  But nobody saw and nobody listened.  Nobody wanted 
what I had to give.  I was like a poor devil of a tramp looking for 
shelter on a bitter night, in a town with every door bolted and all 
the windows dark.  And suddenly I felt that the easiest thing would 
be to lie down and go to sleep in the snow.  Perhaps I'd a vague 
notion that if they found me there at daylight, frozen stiff, the 
pathetic spectacle might produce a reaction, a feeling of remorse. 
. . .  So I took care to be found!  Well, a good many thousand 
people die every day on the face of the globe; and I soon 
discovered that I was simply one of the thousands; and when I made 
that discovery I really died &mdash; and stayed dead a year or two. . . .  
When I came to life again I was off on the under side of the world, 
in regions unaware of what we know as 'the public.'  Have you any 
notion how it shifts the point of view to wake under new 
constellations?  I advise any who's been in love with a woman under 
Cassiopeia to go and think about her under the Southern Cross. . . 
.  It's the only way to tell the pivotal truths from the others. . 
. .  I didn't believe in my theory any less &mdash; there was my triumph 
and my vindication!  It held out, resisted, measured itself with 
the stars.  But I didn't care a snap of my finger whether anybody 
else believed in it, or even knew it had been formulated.  It 
escaped out of my books &mdash; my poor still-born books &mdash; like Psyche from 
the chrysalis and soared away into the blue, and lived there.  I 
knew then how it frees an idea to be ignored; how apprehension 
circumscribes and deforms it. . . .  Once I'd learned that, it was 
easy enough to turn to and shift for myself.  I was sure now that 
my idea would live: the good ones are self-supporting.  I had to learn to be so; and I tried my hand at a 
number of things . . . adventurous, menial, commercial. . . .  It's 
not a bad thing for a man to have to live his life &mdash; and we nearly 
all manage to dodge it.  Our first round with the Sphinx may strike 
something out of us &mdash; a book or a picture or a symphony; and we're 
amazed at our feat, and go on letting that first work breed others, 
as some animal forms reproduce each other without renewed 
fertilization.  So there we are, committed to our first guess at 
the riddle; and our works look as like as successive impressions of 
the same plate, each with the lines a little fainter; whereas they 
ought to be &mdash; if we touch earth between times &mdash; as different from 
each other as those other creatures &mdash; jellyfish, aren't they, of a 
kind? &mdash; where successive generations produce new forms, and it takes 
a zoologist to see the hidden likeness. . . . 
</p><p>"Well, I proved my first guess, off there in the wilds, and it 
lived, and grew, and took care of itself.  And I said 'Some day it 
will make itself heard; but by that time my atoms will have waltzed 
into a new pattern.' <pb n="285"/>  Then, in Cashmere one day, I met a 
fellow in a caravan, with a dog-eared book in his pocket.  He said 
he never stirred without it &mdash; wanted to know where I'd been, never 
to have heard of it.  It was <hi rend="italic">my guess</hi> &mdash; in its twentieth 
edition! . . .  The globe spun round at that, and all of a sudden 
I was under the old stars.  That's the way it happens when the 
ballast of vanity shifts!  I'd lived a third of a life out there, 
unconscious of human opinion &mdash; because I supposed it was unconscious 
of <hi rend="italic">me</hi>.  But now &mdash; now!  Oh, it was different.  I wanted to know 
what they said. . . .  Not exactly that, either: I wanted to know 
<hi rend="italic">what I'd made them say</hi>.  There's a difference. . . .  And here 
I am," said John Pellerin, with a pull at his pipe. 
</p><p>So much Bernald retained of his companion's actual narrative; 
the rest was swept away under the tide of wonder that rose and 
submerged him as Pellerin &mdash; at some indefinitely later stage of 
their talk &mdash; picked up his manuscript and began to read.  Bernald 
sat opposite, his elbows propped on the table, his eyes fixed on 
the swaying waters outside, from which the moon gradually faded, 
leaving them to make a denser blackness in the night.  As Pellerin 
read, this density of blackness &mdash; which never for a moment seemed 
inert or unalive &mdash; was attenuated by imperceptible degrees, till a 
greyish pallour replaced it; then the pallour breathed and 
brightened, and suddenly dawn was on the sea. 
</p><p>Something of the same nature went on in the young man's mind 
while he watched and listened.  He was conscious of a gradually 
withdrawing light, of an interval of obscurity full of the stir of 
invisible forces, and then of the victorious flush of day.  And as 
the light rose, he saw how far he had travelled and what wonders 
the night had prepared.  Pellerin had been right in saying that his 
first idea had survived, had borne the test of time; but he had 
given his hearer no hint of the extent to which it had been 
enlarged and modified, of the fresh implications it now unfolded.  
In a brief flash of retrospection Bernald saw the earlier books 
dwindle and fall into their place as mere precursors of this fuller 
revelation; then, with a leap of helpless rage, he pictured Howland 
Wade's pink hands on the new treasure, and his prophetic feet upon 
the lecture platform. 
</p> 
</div2> 
<div2 type="chapter" n="5" id="d8">                                  
<head> 
V 
</head> 
<p>"IT won't do &mdash; oh, he let him down as gently as possible; but 
it appears it simply won't do." 
</p><p>Doctor Bob imparted the ineluctable fact to Bernald while the 
two men, accidentally meeting at their club a few nights later, sat 
together over the dinner they had immediately agreed to consume in 
company. 
</p><p>Bernald had left Portchester the morning after his strange 
discovery, and he and Bob Wade had not seen each other since.  And 
now Bernald, moved by an irresistible instinct of postponement, had 
waited for his companion to bring up Winterman's name, and had even 
executed several conversational diversions in the hope of delaying 
its mention.  For how could one talk of Winterman with the thought 
of Pellerin swelling one's breast? 
</p><p>"Yes; the very day Howland got back from Kenosha I brought the 
manuscript to town, and got him to read it.  And yesterday evening 
I nailed him, and dragged an answer out of him." 
</p><p>"Then Howland hasn't seen Winterman yet?" 
</p><p>"No.  He said: 'Before you let him loose on me I'll go over 
the stuff, and see if it's at all worth while.'" 
</p><p>Bernald drew a freer breath.  "And he found it wasn't?" 
</p><p>"Between ourselves, he found it was of no account at all.  
Queer, isn't it, when the <hi rend="italic">man</hi> . . . but of course literature's 
another proposition.  Howland says it's one of the cases where an 
idea might seem original and striking if one didn't happen to be 
able to trace its descent.  And this is straight out of bosh &mdash; by 
Pellerin. . . .  Yes: Pellerin.  It seems that everything in the 
article that isn't pure nonsense is just Pellerinism.  Howland 
thinks poor Winterman must have been tremendously struck by 
Pellerin's writings, and have lived too much out of the world to 
know that they've become the text-books of modern thought.  
Otherwise, of course, he'd have taken more trouble to disguise his 
plagiarisms." 
</p><p>"I see," Bernald mused.  "Yet you say there <hi rend="italic">is</hi> an original 
element?" 
</p><p>"Yes; but unluckily it's no good." 
</p><p>"It's not &mdash; conceivably &mdash; in any sense a development of 
Pellerin's idea: a logical step farther?" <pb n="286"/>  
</p><p><hi rend="italic">"Logical?</hi>  Howland says it's twaddle at white heat." 
</p><p>Bernald sat silent, divided between the fierce satisfaction of 
seeing the Interpreter rush upon his fate, and the despair of 
knowing that the state of mind he represented was indestructible.  
Then both emotions were swept away on a wave of pure joy, as he 
reflected that now, at last, Howland Wade had given him back John 
Pellerin. 
</p><p>The possession was one he did not mean to part with lightly; 
and the dread of its being torn from him constrained him to 
extraordinary precautions. 
</p><p>"You've told Winterman, I suppose?  How did he take it?" 
</p><p>"Why, unexpectedly, as he does most things.  You can never 
tell which way he'll jump.  I thought he'd take a high tone, or 
else laugh it off; but he did neither.  He seemed awfully cast 
down.  I wished myself well out of the job when I saw how cut up he 
was."  Bernald thrilled at the words.  Pellerin had shared his 
pang, then &mdash; the "old woe of the world" at the perpetuity of human 
dulness! 
</p><p>"But what did he say to the charge of plagiarism &mdash; if you made 
it?" 
</p><p>"Oh, I told him straight out what Howland said.  I thought it 
fairer.  And his answer to that was the rummest part of all." 
</p><p>"What was it?" Bernald questioned, with a tremor. 
</p><p>"He said: 'That's queer, for I've never read Pellerin.'" 
</p><p>Bernald drew a deep breath of ecstasy.  "Well &mdash; and I suppose 
you believed him?" 
</p><p>"I believed him, because I know him.  But the public won't &mdash;  
the critics won't.  And if it's a pure coincidence it's just as bad 
for him as if it were a straight steal &mdash; isn't it?" 
</p><p>Bernald sighed his acquiescence. 
</p><p>"It bothers me awfully," Wade continued, knitting his kindly 
brows, "because I could see what a blow it was to him.  He's got to 
earn his living, and I don't suppose he knows how to do anything 
else.  At his age it's hard to start fresh.  I put that to 
Howland &mdash; asked him if there wasn't a chance he might do better if 
he only had a little encouragement.  I can't help feeling he's got 
the essential thing in him.  But of course I'm no judge when it 
comes to books.  And Howland says it would be cruel to give him any 
hope."  Wade paused, turned his wineglass about under a meditative 
stare, and then leaned across the table toward Bernald.  "Look 
here &mdash; do you know what I've proposed to Winterman?  That he should 
come to town with me to-morrow and go in the evening to hear 
Howland lecture to the Uplift Club.  They're to meet at Mrs. 
Beecher Bain's, and Howland is to repeat the lecture that he gave 
the other day before the Pellerin Society at Kenosha.  It will give 
Winterman a chance to get some notion of what Pellerin <hi rend="italic">was:</hi> 
he'll get it much straighter from Howland than if he tried to 
plough through Pellerin's books.  And then afterward &mdash; as if 
accidentally &mdash; I thought I might bring him and Howland together.  If 
Howland could only see him and hear him talk, there's no knowing 
what might come of it.  He couldn't help feeling the man's force, 
as we do; and he might give him a pointer &mdash; tell him what line to 
take.  Anyhow, it would please Winterman, and take the edge off his 
disappointment.  I saw that as soon as I proposed it." 
 
</p><p>"Some one who's never heard of Pellerin?" 
</p><p>Mrs. Beecher Bain, large, smiling, diffuse, reached out 
parenthetically from the incoming throng on her threshold to waylay 
Bernald with the question as he was about to move past her in the 
wake of his companion. 
</p><p>"Oh, keep straight on, Mr. Winterman!" she interrupted herself 
to call after the latter.  "Into the back drawing-room, please!  
And remember, you're to sit next to me &mdash; in the corner on the left, 
close under the platform." 
</p><p>She renewed her interrogative clutch on Bernald's sleeve.  
"Most curious!  Doctor Wade has been telling me all about him &mdash; how 
remarkable you all think him.  And it's actually true that he's 
never heard of Pellerin?  Of course as soon as Doctor Wade told me 
<hi rend="italic">that</hi>, I said 'Bring him!'  It will be so extraordinarily 
interesting to watch the first impression. &mdash; Yes, do follow him, 
dear Mr. Bernald, and be sure that you and he secure the seats next 
to me.  Of course Alice Fosdick insists on being with us.  She was 
wild with excitement when I told her she was to meet some one who'd 
never heard of Pellerin!" 
</p><p>On the indulgent lips of Mrs. Beecher Bain conjecture speedily 
passed into affirmation; 
<pb n="287"/> 
and as Bernald's companion, broad 
and shaggy in his visibly new evening clothes, moved down the 
length of the crowded rooms, he was already, to the ladies drawing 
aside their skirts to let him pass, the interesting Huron of the 
fable. 
</p><p>How far he was aware of the character ascribed to him it was 
impossible for Bernald to discover.  He was as unconscious as a 
tree or a cloud, and his observer had never known any one so alive 
to human contacts and yet so secure from them.  But the scene was 
playing such a lively tune on Bernald's own sensibilities that for 
the moment he could not adjust himself to the probable effect it 
produced on his companion.  The young man, of late, had made but 
rare appearances in the group of which Mrs. Beecher Bain was one of 
the most indefatigable hostesses, and the Uplift Club the chief 
medium of expression.  To a critic, obliged by his trade to 
cultivate convictions, it was the essence of luxury to leave them 
at home in his hours of ease; and Bernald gave his preference to 
circles in which less finality of judgment prevailed, and it was 
consequently less embarrassing to be caught without an opinion. 
</p><p>But in his fresher days he had known the spell of the Uplift 
Club and the thrill of moving among the Emancipated; and he felt an 
odd sense of rejuvenation as he looked at the rows of faces packed 
about the embowered platform from which Howland Wade was presently 
to hand down the eternal verities.  Many of these countenances 
belonged to the old days, when the gospel of Pellerin was unknown, 
and it required considerable intellectual courage to avow one's 
acceptance of the very doctrines he had since demolished.  The 
latter moral revolution seemed to have been accepted as 
submissively as a change in hair-dressing; and it even struck 
Bernald that, in the case of many of the assembled ladies, their 
convictions were rather newer than their clothes. 
</p><p>One of the most interesting examples of this facility of 
adaptation was actually, in the person of Miss Alice Fosdick, 
brushing his elbow with exotic amulets, and enveloping him in 
Arabian odours, as she leaned forward to murmur her sympathetic 
sense of the situation.  Miss Fosdick, who was one of the most 
advanced exponents of Pellerinism, had large eyes and a plaintive 
mouth, and Bernald had always fancied that she might have been 
pretty if she had not been perpetually explaining things. 
</p><p>"Yes, I know &mdash; Isabella Bain told me all about him.  (He can't 
hear us, can he?)  And I wonder if you realize how remarkably 
interesting it is that we should have such an opportunity <hi rend="italic">now</hi> &mdash;  
I mean the opportunity to see the impression of Pellerinism on a 
perfectly fresh mind.  (You must introduce him as soon as the 
lecture's over.)  I explained that to Isabella as soon as she 
showed me Doctor Wade's note.  Of course you see why, don't you?"  
Bernald made a faint motion of acquiescence, which she instantly 
swept aside.  "At least I think I can <hi rend="italic">make you see why</hi>.  (If 
you're sure he can't hear?)  Why, it's just this &mdash; Pellerinism is in 
danger of becoming a truism.  Oh, it's an awful thing to say!  But 
then I'm not afraid of saying awful things!  I rather believe it's 
my mission.  What I mean is, that we're getting into the way of 
taking Pellerin for granted &mdash; as we do the air we breathe.  We don't 
sufficiently lead our <hi rend="italic">conscious life</hi> in him &mdash; we're gradually 
letting him become subliminal."  She swayed closer to the young 
man, and he saw that she was making a graceful attempt to throw her 
explanatory net over his companion, who, evading Mrs. Bain's 
hospitable signal, had cautiously wedged himself into a seat 
between Bernald and the wall. 
</p><p><hi rend="italic">"Did</hi> you hear what I was saying, Mr. Winterman?  (Yes, I 
know who you are, of course!)  Oh, well, I don't really mind if you 
did.  I was talking about you &mdash; about you and Pellerin.  I was 
explaining to Mr. Bernald that what we need at this very minute is 
a Pellerin revival; and we need some one like you &mdash; to whom his 
message comes as a wonderful new interpretation of life &mdash; to lead 
the revival, and rouse us out of our apathy. . . . 
</p><p>"You see," she went on winningly, "it's not only the big 
public that needs it (of course <hi rend="italic">their</hi> Pellerin isn't ours!)  
It's we, his disciples, his interpreters, who discovered him and 
gave him to the world &mdash; we, the Chosen People, the Custodians of the 
Sacred Books, as Howland Wade calls us &mdash; it's <hi rend="italic">we</hi>, who are in 
perpetual danger of sinking back into the old stagnant ideals, and 
practising the Seven Deadly Virtues; it's <hi rend="italic">we</hi> who need to count 
our mercies, and realize anew what he's done for us, and what we 
ought to do for him!  And it's for <pb n="288"/>  that reason that I urged 
Mr. Wade to speak here, in the very inner sanctuary of Pellerinism, 
exactly as he would speak to the uninitiated &mdash; to repeat, simply, 
his Kenosha lecture, 'What Pellerinism means'; and we ought all, I 
think, to listen to him with the hearts of little children &mdash; just as 
<hi rend="italic">you</hi> will, Mr. Winterman &mdash; as if he were telling us new things, 
and we &mdash; " 
</p><p>"Alice, <hi rend="italic">dear</hi> &mdash; " Mrs. Bain murmured with a deprecating 
gesture; and Howland Wade, emerging between the palms, took the 
centre of the platform. 
</p><p>A pang of commiseration shot through Bernald as he saw him 
there, so innocent and so exposed.  His plump pulpy body, which 
made his evening dress fall into intimate and wrapper-like folds, 
was like a wide surface spread to the shafts of irony; and the mild 
ripples of his voice seemed to enlarge the vulnerable area as he 
leaned forward, poised on confidential finger-tips, to say 
persuasively: "Let me try to tell you what Pellerinism means." 
</p><p>Bernald moved restlessly in his seat.  He had the obscure 
sense of being a party to something not wholly honourable.  He 
ought not to have come; he ought not to have let his companion 
come.  Yet how could he have done otherwise?  John Pellerin's 
secret was his own.  As long as he chose to remain John Winterman 
it was no one's business to gainsay him; and Bernald's scruples 
were really justifiable only in respect of his own presence on the 
scene.  But even in this connection he ceased to feel them as soon 
as Howland Wade began to speak. 
</p> 
</div2> 
<div2 type="chapter" n="6" id="d9"> 
<head> 
VI 
</head> 
<p>IT had been arranged that Pellerin, after the meeting of the 
Uplift Club, should join Bernald at his rooms and spend the night 
there, instead of returning to Portchester.  The plan had been 
eagerly elaborated by the young man, but he had been unprepared for 
the alacrity with which his wonderful friend accepted it.  He was 
beginning to see that it was a part of Pellerin's wonderfulness to 
fall in, quite simply and naturally, with any arrangements made for 
his convenience, or tending to promote the convenience of others.  
Bernald felt that his extreme docility in such matters was 
proportioned to the force of resistance which, for nearly half a 
life-time, had kept him, with his back to the wall, fighting alone 
against the powers of darkness.  In such a scale of values how 
little the small daily alternatives must weigh! 
</p><p>At the close of Howland Wade's discourse, Bernald, charged 
with his prodigious secret, had felt the need to escape for an 
instant from the liberated rush of talk.  The interest of watching 
Pellerin was so perilously great that the watcher felt it might, at 
any moment, betray him.  He lingered in the crowded drawing-room 
long enough to see his friend enclosed in a mounting tide, above 
which Mrs. Beecher Bain and Miss Fosdick actively waved their 
conversational tridents; then he took refuge, at the back of the 
house, in a small dim library where, in his younger days, he had 
discussed personal immortality and the problem of consciousness 
with beautiful girls whose names he could not remember. 
</p><p>In this retreat he surprised Mr. Beecher Bain, a quiet man 
with a mild brow, who was smoking a surreptitious cigar over the 
last number of the <hi rend="italic">Strand</hi>.  Mr. Bain, at Bernald's approach, 
dissembled the <hi rend="italic">Strand</hi> under a copy of the <hi rend="italic">Hibbert Journal</hi>, 
but tendered his cigar-case with the remark that stocks were heavy 
again; and Bernald blissfully abandoned himself to this unexpected 
contact with reality. 
</p><p>On his return to the drawing-room he found that the tide had 
set toward the supper-table, and when it finally carried him 
thither it was to land him in the welcoming arms of Bob Wade. 
</p><p>"Hullo, old man!  Where have you been all this time? &mdash;  
Winterman?  Oh, <hi rend="italic">he's</hi> talking to Howland: yes, I managed it 
finally.  I believe Mrs. Bain has steered them into the library, so 
that they shan't be disturbed.  I gave her an idea of the 
situation, and she was awfully kind.  We'd better leave them alone, 
don't you think?  I'm trying to get a croquette for Miss Fosdick." 
</p><p>Bernald's secret leapt in his bosom, and he devoted himself to 
the task of distributing sandwiches and champagne while his pulses 
danced to the tune of the cosmic laughter.  The vision of Pellerin 
and his Interpreter, face to face at last, had a Cyclopean grandeur 
that dwarfed all other comedy.  "And I shall hear of it presently; 
in an hour or two he'll be telling me about it.  And that hour will 
be all mine &mdash; mine and his!"  The dizziness of the thought made it 
<pb n="289"/>  difficult for Bernald to preserve the balance of the 
supper-plates he was distributing.  Life had for him at that moment 
the completeness which seems to defy disintegration. 
</p><p>The throng in the dining-room was thickening, and Bernald's 
efforts as purveyor were interrupted by frequent appeals, from 
ladies who had reached repleteness, that he should sit down a 
moment and tell them all about his interesting friend.  Winterman's 
fame, trumpeted abroad by Miss Fosdick, had reached the four 
corners of the Uplift Club, and Bernald found himself fabricating 
<hi rend="italic">de toutes pieces</hi> a Winterman legend which should in some degree 
respond to the Club's demand for the human document.  When at 
length he had acquitted himself of this obligation, and was free to 
work his way back through the lessening groups into the drawing-room, he was at last rewarded by a glimpse of his friend, who, 
still densely encompassed, towered in the centre of the room in all 
his sovran ugliness. 
</p><p>Their eyes met across the crowd; but Bernald gathered only 
perplexity from the encounter.  What were Pellerin's eyes saying to 
him?  What orders, what confidences, what indefinable apprehension 
did their long look impart?  The young man was still trying to 
decipher their complex message when he felt a tap on the arm, and 
turned to encounter the rueful gaze of Bob Wade, whose meaning lay 
clearly enough on the surface of his good blue stare. 
</p><p>"Well, it won't work &mdash; it won't work," the doctor groaned. 
</p><p>"What won't?" 
</p><p>"I mean with Howland.  Winterman won't.  Howland doesn't take 
to him.  Says he's crude &mdash; frightfully crude.  And you know how 
Howland hates crudeness." 
</p><p>"Oh, I know," Bernald exulted.  It was the word he had waited 
for &mdash; he saw it now!  Once more he was lost in wonder at Howland's 
miraculous faculty for always, as the naturalists said, being true 
to type. 
</p><p>"So I'm afraid it's all up with his chance of writing.  At 
least <hi rend="italic">I</hi> can do no more," said Wade, discouraged. 
</p><p>Bernald pressed him for farther details.  "Does Winterman seem 
to mind much?  Did you hear his version?" 
</p><p>"His version?" 
</p><p>"I mean what he said to Howland." 
</p><p>"Why no.  What the deuce was there for him to say?" 
</p><p>"What indeed?  I think I'll take him home," said Bernald 
gaily. 
</p><p>He turned away to join the circle from which, a few minutes 
before, Pellerin's eyes had vainly and enigmatically signalled to 
him; but the circle had dispersed, and Pellerin himself was not in 
sight. 
</p><p>Bernald, looking about him, saw that during his brief aside 
with Wade the party had passed into the final phase of dissolution.  
People still delayed, in diminishing groups, but the current had 
set toward the doors, and every moment or two it bore away a few 
more lingerers.  Bernald, from his post, commanded the clearing 
perspective of the two drawing-rooms, and a rapid survey of their 
length sufficed to assure him that Pellerin was not in either.  
Taking leave of Wade, the young man made his way back to the 
drawing-room, where only a few hardened feasters remained, and then 
passed on to the library which had been the scene of the late 
momentous colloquy.  But the library too was empty, and drifting 
back uncertainly to the inner drawing-room Bernald found Mrs. 
Beecher Bain domestically putting out the wax candles on the 
mantel-piece. 
</p><p>"Dear Mr. Bernald!  Do sit down and have a little chat.  What 
a wonderful privilege it has been!  I don't know when I've had such 
an intense impression." 
</p><p>She made way for him, hospitably, in a corner of the sofa to 
which she had sunk; and he echoed her vaguely: "You <hi rend="italic">were</hi> 
impressed, then?" 
</p><p>"I can't express to you how it affected me!  As Alice said, it 
was a resurrection &mdash; it was as if John Pellerin were actually here 
in the room with us!" 
</p><p>Bernald turned on her with a half-audible gasp.  "You felt 
that, dear Mrs. Bain?" 
</p><p>"We all felt it &mdash; every one of us!  I don't wonder the Greeks &mdash;  
it <hi rend="italic">was</hi> the Greeks? &mdash; regarded eloquence as a supernatural power.  
As Alice says, when one looked at Howland Wade one understood what 
they meant by the Afflatus." 
</p><p>Bernald rose and held out his hand.  "Oh, I see &mdash; it was 
Howland who made you feel as if Pellerin were in the room?  And he 
made Miss Fosdick feel so too?" 
</p><p>"Why, of course.  But why are you rushing off?" <pb n="290"/>  
</p><p>"Because I must hunt up my friend, who's not used to such late 
hours." 
</p><p>"Your friend?"  Mrs. Bain had to collect her thoughts.  "Oh, 
Mr. Winterman, you mean?  But he's gone already." 
</p><p>"Gone?" Bernald exclaimed, with an odd twinge of foreboding.  
Remembering Pellerin's signal across the crowd, he reproached 
himself for not having answered it more promptly.  Yet it was 
certainly strange that his friend should have left the house 
without him. 
</p><p>"Are you quite sure?" he asked, with a startled glance at the 
clock. 
</p><p>"Oh, perfectly.  He went half an hour ago.  But you needn't 
hurry home on his account, for Alice Fosdick carried him off with 
her.  I saw them leave together." 
</p><p>"Carried him off?  She took him home with her, you mean?" 
</p><p>"Yes.  You know what strange hours she keeps.  She told me she 
was going to give him a Welsh rabbit, and explain Pellerinism to 
him." 
</p><p>"Oh, <hi rend="italic">if</hi> she's going to explain &mdash; " Bernald murmured.  But 
his amazement at the news struggled with a confused impatience to 
reach his rooms in time to be there for his friend's arrival.  
There could be no stranger spectacle beneath the stars than that of 
John Pellerin carried off by Miss Fosdick, and listening, in the 
small hours, to her elucidation of his doctrines; but Bernald knew 
enough of his sex to be aware that such an experiment may present 
a less humorous side to its subject than to an impartial observer.  
Even the Uplift Club and its connotations might benefit by the 
attraction of the unknown; and it was conceivable that to a 
traveller from Mesopotamia Miss Fosdick might present elements of 
interest which she had lost for the frequenters of Fifth Avenue.  
There was, at any rate, no denying that the affair had become 
unexpectedly complex, and that its farther development promised to 
be rich in comedy. 
</p><p>In the charmed contemplation of these possibilities Bernald 
sat over his fire, listening for Pellerin's ring.  He had arranged 
his modest quarters with the reverent care of a celebrant awaiting 
the descent of his deity.  He guessed Pellerin to be unconscious of 
visual detail, but sensitive to the happy blending of sensuous 
impressions: to the intimate spell of lamplight on books, and of a 
deep chair placed where one could watch the fire.  The chair was 
there, and Bernald, facing it across the hearth, already saw it 
filled by Pellerin's lounging figure.  The autumn dawn came late, 
and even now they had before them the promise of some untroubled 
hours.  Bernald, sitting there alone in the warm stillness of his 
room, and in the profounder hush of his expectancy, was conscious 
of gathering up all his sensibilities and perceptions into one 
exquisitely-adjusted instrument of notation.  Until now he had 
tasted Pellerin's society only in unpremeditated snatches, and had 
always left him with a sense, on his own part, of waste and 
shortcoming.  Now, in the lull of this dedicated hour, he felt that 
he should miss nothing, and forget nothing, of the initiation that 
awaited him.  And catching sight of Pellerin's pipe, he rose and 
laid it carefully on a table by the arm-chair. 
 
</p><p>"No.  I've never had any news of him," Bernald heard himself 
repeating.  He spoke in a low tone, and with the automatic 
utterance that alone made it possible to say the words. 
</p><p>They were addressed to Miss Fosdick, into whose neighbourhood 
chance had thrown him at a dinner, a year or so later than their 
encounter at the Uplift Club.  Hitherto he had successfully, and 
intentionally, avoided Miss Fosdick, not from any animosity toward 
that unconscious instrument of fate, but from an intense reluctance 
to pronounce the words which he knew he should have to speak if 
they met. 
</p><p>Now, as it turned out, his chief surprise was that she should 
wait so long to make him speak them.  All through the dinner she 
had swept him along on a rapid current of talk which showed no 
tendency to linger or turn back upon the past.  At first he 
ascribed her reserve to a sense of delicacy with which he 
reproached himself for not having previously credited her; then he 
saw that she had been carried so far beyond the point at which they 
had last faced each other, that it was by the merest hazard of 
associated ideas that she was now finally borne back to it.  For it 
appeared that the very next evening, at Mrs. Beecher Bain's, a 
Hindu Mahatma was to lecture to the Uplift Club on the Limits of 
the Subliminal; and it was owing to no less a person than Howland 
Wade that this exceptional privilege had been obtained. <pb n="291"/>  
</p><p>"Of course Howland's known all over the world as the 
interpreter of Pellerinism, and the Aga Gautch, who had absolutely 
declined to speak anywhere in public, wrote to Isabella that he 
could not refuse anything that Mr. Wade asked.  Did you know that 
Howland's lecture, 'What Pellerinism Means,' has been translated 
into twenty-two languages, and gone into a fifth edition in 
Icelandic?  Why, that reminds me," Miss Fosdick broke off &mdash; "I've 
never heard what became of your queer friend &mdash; what was his name? &mdash;  
whom you and Bob Wade accused me of spiriting away after that very 
lecture.  And I've never seen <hi rend="italic">you</hi> since you rushed into the 
house the next morning, and dragged me out of bed to know what I'd 
done with him!" 
</p><p>With a sharp effort Bernald gathered himself together to have 
it out.  "Well, what <hi rend="italic">did</hi> you do with him?" he retorted. 
</p><p>She laughed her appreciation of his humour.  "Just what I told 
you, of course.  I said good-bye to him on Isabella's door-step." 
</p><p>Bernald looked at her.  "It's really true, then, that he 
didn't go home with you?" 
</p><p>She bantered back: "Have you suspected me, all this time, of 
hiding his remains in the cellar?"  And with a droop of her fine 
lids she added: "I wish he <hi rend="italic">had</hi> come home with me, for he was 
rather interesting, and there were things I think I could have 
explained to him." 
</p><p>Bernald helped himself to a nectarine, and Miss Fosdick 
continued on a note of amused curiosity: "So you've really never 
had any news of him since that night?" 
</p><p>"No &mdash; I've never had any news of him." 
</p><p>"Not the least little message?" 
</p><p>"Not the least little message." 
</p><p>"Or a rumour or report of any kind?" 
</p><p>"Or a rumour or report of any kind." 
</p><p>Miss Fosdick's interest seemed to be revived by the 
strangeness of the case.  "It's rather creepy, isn't it?  What <hi rend="italic">could</hi>  
have happened?  You don't suppose he could have been waylaid 
and murdered?" she asked with brightening eyes. 
</p><p>Bernald shook his head serenely.  "No.  I'm sure he's safe &mdash;  
quite safe." 
</p><p>"But if you're sure, you must know something." 
</p><p>"No.  I know nothing," he repeated. 
</p><p>She scanned him incredulously.  "But what's your theory &mdash; for 
you must have a theory?  What in the world can have become of him?" 
</p><p>Bernald returned her look and hesitated.  "Do you happen to 
remember the last thing he said to you &mdash; the very last, on the door-step, when he left you?" 
</p><p>"The last thing?"  She poised her fork above the peach on her 
plate.  "I don't think he said anything.  Oh, yes &mdash; when I reminded 
him that he'd solemnly promised to come back with me and have a 
little talk he said he couldn't because he was going home." 
</p><p>"Well, then, I suppose," said Bernald, "he went home." 
</p><p>She glanced at him as if suspecting a trap.  "Dear me, how 
flat!  I always inclined to a mysterious murder.  But of course you 
know more of him than you say." 
</p><p>She began to cut her peach, but paused above a lifted bit to 
ask, with a renewal of animation in her expressive eyes: "By the 
way, had you heard that Howland Wade has been gradually getting 
farther and farther away from Pellerinism?  It seems he's begun to 
feel that there's a Positivist element in it which is narrowing to 
any one who has gone at all deeply into the Wisdom of the East.  He 
was intensely interesting about it the other day, and of course I 
<hi rend="italic">do</hi> see what he feels. . . .  Oh, it's too long to tell you now; 
but if you could manage to come in to tea some afternoon soon &mdash; any 
day but Wednesday &mdash; I should so like to explain &mdash; " 
</p> 
 
</div2> 
</div1> 
</body> 
</text> 
</TEI.2> 
