<?xml version="1.0"?>

<?dlps id="WhaOgri"?>
<?dlps page-images="none" figure-images="no"?>
<?dlps transcription="other"?>

<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/tei-p4/tei2.dtd" [
<!ENTITY % POSTKB "INCLUDE">
<!ENTITY % TEI.extensions.ent SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.ent">
<!ENTITY % TEI.extensions.dtd SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.dtd">
<!ENTITY % ISOnum SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/charent/iso-num.ent"> %ISOnum;
<!ENTITY % ISOpub SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/charent/iso-pub.ent"> %ISOpub;

]>

 
<TEI.2 id="WhaOgri"> 
<teiHeader type="migrated" creator="Etext">
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title type="main">Ogrin the Hermit</title>
<title type="sort">ogrin the hermit</title>
<author>Wharton, Edith, 1862-1937</author>
<respStmt>
<resp>Creation of machine-readable version:</resp> 
<name>Judy Boss</name> 
<resp>Conversion to TEI.2-conformant markup:</resp>  
<name>University of Virginia Library Electronic Text Center</name>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt> 
<extent>ca. <num type="kilobytes">13</num> kilobytes</extent> 
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>University of Virginia Library</publisher>
<pubPlace>Charlottesville, Virginia</pubPlace> 
<idno type="ETC">WhaOgri</idno> 
<date value="1996">1996</date>
<availability status="public">
<p n="copyright">Copyright &copy; 1996 by the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia</p>
<p n="access">Publicly accessible</p>
</availability>
<idno type="uva-pid">uva-lib:476505</idno>
</publicationStmt>
<seriesStmt>
<title>University of Virginia Library, Text collection</title>
<idno type="uva-set">UVA-LIB-Text</idno>
</seriesStmt> 
<sourceDesc>
<biblFull>
<titleStmt>
<title type="main">Ogrin the Hermit</title>
<title level="j">Atlantic Monthly</title>
<title type="sort">ogrin the hermit</title>
<author>Edith Wharton</author>
</titleStmt> 
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>Atlantic Monthly Co.</publisher> 
<pubPlace>Boston</pubPlace> 
<date value="1909">1909</date>
</publicationStmt> 
<seriesStmt>
<p>104</p>
</seriesStmt> 
<notesStmt>
<note>
<p>Wharton, Edith.  "Ogrin the Hermit."  <hi rend="italic">Atlantic Monthly</hi> 104 (1909): 844-848.</p>
</note>
</notesStmt>
</biblFull>
</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc> 
<encodingDesc>
<projectDesc>
<p>Prepared for the University of Virginia Library Electronic Text Center</p>
</projectDesc> 
<editorialDecl>
<p>All quotation marks retained as data</p> 
<p>All unambiguous end-of-line hyphens have been removed, and the 
trailing part of a word has been joined to the preceding line.</p> 
<p id="ETC">Keywords in the header are a local Electronic Text Center scheme  
to aid in establishing analytical groupings</p>
</editorialDecl> 
<refsDecl>
<p>ID elements are given for each page element and are composed of the text's 
unique cryptogram and the given page number, as in AusEmma1 for page one of  
Jane Austen's Emma.</p>
</refsDecl> 
</encodingDesc> 
<profileDesc>
<creation>
<date value="1909">1909</date>
</creation> 
<langUsage>
<language id="eng" usage="main">English</language>
</langUsage> 
<textClass>
<keywords>
<term>fiction</term>
<term>poetry</term> 
<term>Women Writers</term>
</keywords> 
</textClass>
</profileDesc> 
<revisionDesc>
<change>
<date value="1996-03">March 1996</date> 
<respStmt>
<resp>corrector</resp> 
<name>Jamie L Spriggs, Electronic Text Center, University of Virginia</name>
</respStmt> 
<item>Added header; Tagged with TEI.2-compatible SGML; Parsed against  
local "teilite" dtd.</item>
</change> 
<change>
<date value="2005-07">July 2005</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>Corrector</resp>
<name>Margaret Konkol</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Converted SGML to XML and fixed tagging.</item>
</change>
<change>
<date value="2007-09">September 2007</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>Migration</resp>
<name>Ethan Gruber, University of Virginia Library</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Converted XML markup from TEI Lite to uva-dl-tei (TEI P4 with local customizations).</item>
</change>
<change>
<date value="2008-01">January 2008</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>Migration</resp>
<name>Greg Murray, University of Virginia Library</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Programmatically updated TEI header markup (but not header content) for minimal compliance with current QA requirements.</item>
</change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader> 
 
<text id="d1">  
 
  
<front id="d2"> 
<titlePage id="d3"> 
	<pb/>
<docTitle><titlePart type="main"> 
                         OGRIN THE HERMIT 
</titlePart></docTitle> 
<byline> 
                         BY <docAuthor>EDITH WHARTON</docAuthor> 
</byline> 
<epigraph> 
<p> 
Vous qui nous jugez, savez-vous quel boivre nous avons bu sur la mer? 
</p> 
</epigraph> 
</titlePage> 
</front> 
 
<body id="d4"> 
<div1 type="poem" id="d5"> <pb n="844"/>
<lg type="head"> 
<l><hi rend="italic"> Ogrin the Hermit in old age set forth</hi></l> 
<l><hi rend="italic">This tale to them that sought him in the extreme</hi></l> 
<l><hi rend="italic">Ancient grey wood where he and silence housed:</hi></l> 
</lg> 
<lg type="stanza"> 
<l>Long years ago, when yet my sight was keen,</l> 
<l>My hearing knew the word of wind in bough,</l> 
<l>And all the low fore-runners of the storm,</l> 
<l>There reached me, where I sat beneath my thatch,</l> 
<l>A crash as of tracked quarry in the brake,</l> 
<l>And storm-flecked, fugitive, with straining breasts</l> 
<l>And backward eyes and hands inseparable,</l> 
<l>Tristan and Iseult, swooning at my feet,</l> 
<l>Sought hiding from their hunters.  Here they lay.</l> 
</lg><lg type="stanza"> 
<l>For pity of their great extremity,</l> 
<l>Their sin abhorring, yet not them with it,</l> 
<l>I nourished, hid, and suffered them to build</l> 
<l>Their branched hut in sight of this grey cross,</l> 
<l>That haply, falling on their guilty sleep,</l> 
<l>Its shadow should part them like the blade of God,</l> 
<l>And they should shudder at each other's eyes.</l> 
</lg><lg type="stanza"> 
<l>So dwelt they in this solitude with me,</l> 
<l>And daily, Tristan forth upon the chase,</l> 
<l>The tender Iseult sought my door and heard</l> 
<l>The words of holiness.  Abashed she heard,</l> 
<l>Like one in wisdom nurtured from a child,</l> 
<l>Yet in whose ears an alien language dwells</l> 
<l>Of some far country whence the traveller brings</l> 
<l>Magical treasure, and still images</l> 
<l>Of gods forgotten, and the scent of groves</l> 
<l>That sleep by painted rivers.  As I have seen</l> 
<l>Oft-times returning pilgrims with the spell <pb n="845"/> </l> 
<l>Of these lost lands upon their lids, she moved</l> 
<l>Among familiar truths, accustomed sights,</l> 
<l>As she to them were strange, not they to her.</l> 
<l>And often, reasoning with her, have I felt</l> 
<l>Some ancient lore was in her, dimly drawn</l> 
<l>>From springs of life beyond the four-fold stream</l> 
<l>That makes a silver pale to Paradise;</l> 
<l>For she was calm as some forsaken god</l> 
<l>Who knows not that his power is passed from him,</l> 
<l>But sees with tranced eyes rich pilgrim-trains</l> 
<l>In sands the desert blows about his feet.</l> 
</lg><lg type="stanza"> 
<l>Abhorring first, I heard her; yet her speech</l> 
<l>Warred not with pity, or the contrite heart,</l> 
<l>Or hatred of things evil: rather seemed</l> 
<l>The utterance of some world where these are not,</l> 
<l>And the heart lives in heathen innocence</l> 
<l>With earth's innocuous creatures.  For she said:</l> 
<l>"Love is not, as the shallow adage goes,</l> 
<l>A witch's filter, brewed to trick the blood.</l> 
<l>The cup we drank of on the flying deck</l> 
<l>Was the blue vault of air, the round world's lip,</l> 
<l>Brimmed with life's hydromel, and pressed to ours</l> 
<l>By myriad hands of wind and sun and sea.</l> 
<l>For these are all the cup-bearers of youth,</l> 
<l>That bend above it at the board of life,</l> 
<l>Solicitous accomplices: there's not</l> 
<l>A leaf on bough, a foam-flash on the wave,</l> 
<l>So brief and glancing but it serves them too;</l> 
<l>No scent the pale rose spends upon the night,</l> 
<l>Nor sky-lark's rapture trusted to the blue,</l> 
<l>But these, from the remotest tides of air</l> 
<l>Brought in mysterious salvage, breathe and sing</l> 
<l>In lovers' lips and eyes; and two that drink</l> 
<l>Thus onely of the strange commingled cup</l> 
<l>Of mortal fortune shall into their blood</l> 
<l>Take magic gifts.  Upon each others' hearts</l> 
<l>They shall surprise the heart-beat of the world,</l> 
<l>And feel a sense of life in things inert;</l> 
<l>For as love's touch upon the yielded body</l> 
<l>Is a diviner's wand, and where it falls <pb n="846"/> </l> 
<l>A hidden treasure trembles: so their eyes,</l> 
<l>Falling upon the world of clod and brute,</l> 
<l>And cold hearts plotting evil, shall discern</l> 
<l>The inextinguishable flame of life</l> 
<l>That girdles the remotest frame of things</l> 
<l>With influences older than the stars."</l> 
</lg><lg type="stanza"> 
<l>So spake Iseult; and thus her passion found</l> 
<l>Far-flying words, like birds against the sunset</l> 
<l>That look on lands we see not.  Yet I know</l> 
<l>It was not any argument she found,</l> 
<l>But that she was, the colour that life took</l> 
<l>About her, that thus reasoned in her stead,</l> 
<l>Making her like a lifted lantern borne</l> 
<l>Through midnight thickets, where the flitting ray</l> 
<l>Momently from inscrutable darkness draws</l> 
<l>A myriad-veined branch, and its shy nest</l> 
<l>Quivering with startled life: so moved Iseult.</l> 
<l>And all about her this deep solitude</l> 
<l>Stirred with responsive motions.  Oft I knelt</l> 
<l>In night-long vigil while the lovers slept</l> 
<l>Under their outlawed thatch, and with long prayers</l> 
<l>Sought to disarm the indignant heavens; but lo,</l> 
<l>Thus kneeling in the intertidal hour</l> 
<l>'Twixt dark and dawning, have mine eyes beheld</l> 
<l>How the old gods that hide in these hoar woods,</l> 
<l>And were to me but shapings of the air,</l> 
<l>And flit and murmur of the breathing trees,</l> 
<l>Or slant of moon on pools&mdash;how these stole forth,</l> 
<l>Grown living presences, yet not of bale,</l> 
<l>But innocent-eyed as fawns that come to drink,</l> 
<l>Thronging the threshold where the lovers lay,</l> 
<l>In service of the great god housed within</l> 
<l>Who hides in his breast, beneath his mighty plumes,</l> 
<l>The purposes and penalties of life.</l> 
<l>Or in yet deeper hours, when all was still,</l> 
<l>And the hushed air bowed over them alone,</l> 
<l>Such music of the heart as lovers hear,</l> 
<l>When close as lips lean, lean the thoughts between&mdash;</l> 
<l>When the cold world, no more a lonely orb</l> 
<l>Circling the unimagined track of Time, <pb n="847"/> </l> 
<l>Is like a beating heart within their hands,</l> 
<l>A numb bird that they warm, and feel its wings&mdash;</l> 
<l>Such music have I heard; and through the prayers</l> 
<l>Wherewith I sought to shackle their desires,</l> 
<l>And bring them humbled to the feet of God,</l> 
<l>Caught the loud quiring of the fruitful year,</l> 
<l>The leap of springs, the throb of loosened earth,</l> 
<l>And the sound of all the streams that seek the sea.</l> 
</lg><lg type="stanza"> 
<l>So fell it, that when pity moved their hearts,</l> 
<l>And those high lovers, one unto the end,</l> 
<l>Bowed to the sundering will, and each his way</l> 
<l>Went through a world that could not make them twain,</l> 
<l>Knowing that a great vision, passing by,</l> 
<l>Had swept mine eye-lids with its fringe of fire,</l> 
<l>I, with the wonder of it on my head,</l> 
<l>And with the silence of it in my heart,</l> 
<l>Forth to Tintagel went by secret ways,</l> 
<l>A long lone journey; and from them that loose</l> 
<l>Their spiced bales upon the wharves, and shake</l> 
<l>Strange silks to the sun, or covertly unbosom</l> 
<l>Rich hoard of pearls and amber, or let drip</l> 
<l>Through swarthy fingers links of sinuous gold,</l> 
<l>Chose their most delicate treasures.  Though I knew</l> 
<l>No touch more silken than this knotted gown,</l> 
<l>My hands, grown tender with the sense of her,</l> 
<l>Discerned the airiest tissues, light to cling</l> 
<l>As shower-loosed petals, veils like meadow-smoke,</l> 
<l>Fur soft as snow, amber like sun congealed,</l> 
<l>Pearls pink as may-buds in an orb of dew;</l> 
<l>And laden with these wonders, that to her</l> 
<l>Were natural as the vesture of a flower,</l> 
<l>Fared home to lay my booty at her feet.</l> 
</lg><lg type="stanza"> 
<l>And she, consenting, nor with useless words</l> 
<l>Proving my purpose, robed herself therein</l> 
<l>To meet her lawful lord; but while she thus</l> 
<l>Prisoned the wandering glory of her hair,</l> 
<l>Dimmed her bright breast with jewels, and subdued</l> 
<l>Her light to those dull splendours, well she knew</l> 
<l>The lord that I adorned her thus to meet <pb n="848"/> </l> 
<l>Was not Tintagel's shadowy King, but he,</l> 
<l>That other lord beneath whose plumy feet</l> 
<l>The currents of the seas of life run gold</l> 
<l>As from eternal sunrise; well she knew</l> 
<l>That when I laid my hands upon her head,</l> 
<l>Saying, "Fare forth forgiven," the words I spoke</l> 
<l>Were the breathings of his pity, who beholds</l> 
<l>How, swept on his inexorable wings</l> 
<l>Too far beyond the planetary fires</l> 
<l>On the last coasts of darkness, plunged too deep</l> 
<l>In light ineffable, the heart amazed</l> 
<l>Swoons of its glory, and dropping back to earth</l> 
<l>Craves the dim shelter of familiar sounds,</l> 
<l>The rain on the roof, the noise of flocks that pass,</l> 
<l>And the slow world waking to its daily round. . . .</l> 
</lg><lg type="stanza"> 
<l>And thus, as one who speeds a banished queen,</l> 
<l>I set her on my mule, and hung about</l> 
<l>With royal ornament she went her way;</l> 
<l>For meet it was that this great Queen should pass</l> 
<l>Crowned and forgiven from the face of Love.</l> 
</lg> 
 
</div1> 
</body> 
</text> 
</TEI.2> 
 
