<?xml version="1.0"?>

<?dlps id="WhaR1Fo"?>
<?dlps page-images="none" figure-images="no"?>
<?dlps transcription="other"?>

<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/tei-p4/tei2.dtd" [
<!ENTITY % POSTKB "INCLUDE">
<!ENTITY % TEI.extensions.ent SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.ent">
<!ENTITY % TEI.extensions.dtd SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.dtd">
<!ENTITY % ISOnum SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/charent/iso-num.ent"> %ISOnum;
<!ENTITY % ISOpub SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/charent/iso-pub.ent"> %ISOpub;
]>      
<TEI.2 id="WhaR1Fo">  
<teiHeader type="migrated" creator="Etext">
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title type="main">Mrs. Wharton's "The Fruit of the Tree" 
In: Seven Books of the Month.</title>
<title type="sort">mrs whartons the fruit of the tree in seven books of the month</title>
<author>Wharton review: Marsh, Edward Clark</author>
<respStmt>
<resp>Creation of machine-readable version:</resp>  
<name>Judy Boss</name>  
<resp>Conversion to TEI.2-conformant markup:</resp>   
<name>University of Virginia Library Electronic Text Center.</name>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt>  
<extent>ca. <num type="kilobytes">11</num> kilobytes</extent>  
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>University of Virginia Library</publisher>
<pubPlace>Charlottesville, Virginia</pubPlace>  
<idno type="ETC">WhaR1Fo</idno>  
<date value="1996">1996</date>
<availability status="public">
<p n="copyright">Copyright &copy; 1996 by the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia</p>
<p n="access">Publicly accessible</p>
</availability>
<idno type="uva-pid">uva-lib:476514</idno>
</publicationStmt>
<seriesStmt>
<title>University of Virginia Library, Text collection</title>
<idno type="uva-set">UVA-LIB-Text</idno>
</seriesStmt>  
<notesStmt>
<note>
<p>UVa ed. AP2.B78</p>
</note>
</notesStmt>  
<sourceDesc>
<biblFull>
<titleStmt>
<title type="main">Mrs. Wharton's "The Fruit of the Tree."</title>
<title level="j">Bookman</title>
<title type="sort">mrs whartons the fruit of the tree</title>
<author>Edward Clark Marsh</author>
</titleStmt>  
<editionStmt>
<p>1st Edition.</p>
</editionStmt>  
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>Dodd, Mead and Company</publisher>  
<pubPlace>New York, N. Y.</pubPlace>  
<date value="1907">1907</date>
</publicationStmt>  
<seriesStmt>
<p>
<hi rend="italic">Bookman</hi> 26 (Nov. 1907): 273-75.</p>
</seriesStmt>  
</biblFull>
</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc>  
<encodingDesc>
<projectDesc>
<p>Prepared for the University of Virginia Library Electronic Text  
Center.</p>
</projectDesc>  
<editorialDecl>
<p>All quotation marks retained as data.</p>  
<p>Spell-check and verification made  
against printed text using WordPerfect spell checker.</p>  
<p>All unambiguous end-of-line hyphens have been removed, and the  
trailing part of a word has been joined to the preceding line.</p>  
<p>The images exist as archived TIFF images, one or more JPEG versions  
for general use, and thumbnail GIFs.</p>  
<p id="ETC">Keywords in the header are a local Electronic Text Center scheme   
to aid in establishing analytical groupings.</p>
</editorialDecl>  
<refsDecl>
<p>ID elements are given for each page element and are composed of the text's  
unique cryptogram and the given page number, as in AusEmma1 for page one of   
Jane Austen's Emma.</p>
</refsDecl>
</encodingDesc>  
<profileDesc>
<creation>
<date value="1907">1907</date>
</creation>  
<langUsage>
<language id="eng" usage="main">English</language>
</langUsage>  
<textClass>
<keywords>
<term>non-fiction</term>
<term>prose</term>  
<term>Women Writers</term>
</keywords>
</textClass>
</profileDesc>  
<revisionDesc>
<change>
<date value="1996-03">March 1996</date>  
<respStmt>
<resp>corrector</resp>  
<name>Deirdre A. Johnson, Electronic Text Center, University of  
Virginia</name>
</respStmt>  
<item>Added header and basic TEI markup</item>
</change>  
<change>
<date value="2005-07">July 2005</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>Corrector</resp>
<name>Margaret Konkol</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Converted SGML to XML and fixed tagging.</item>
</change>
<change>
<date value="2007-09">September 2007</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>Migration</resp>
<name>Ethan Gruber, University of Virginia Library</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Converted XML markup from TEI Lite to uva-dl-tei (TEI P4 with local customizations).</item>
</change>
<change>
<date value="2008-01">January 2008</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>Migration</resp>
<name>Greg Murray, University of Virginia Library</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Programmatically updated TEI header markup (but not header content) for minimal compliance with current QA requirements.</item>
</change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>  
  
<text id="d1">  
<body id="d2">  
<div1 type="essay" id="d3"><pb n="273" id="WhaR1Fo273"/>  <head>MRS. WHARTON'S "THE FRUIT OF THE TREE"<ref target="n1">*</ref>  
  </head>
<note id="n1"><seg type="note-symbol">* </seg> <p>The Fruit of the Tree.  By Edith Wharton.  New York: Charles  
Scribner's Sons.</p></note>  
  
<p>It is one of the penalties of so striking a success as Mrs.  
Wharton achieved in <hi rend="italic">The House of Mirth</hi> that for a long time  
to come all her work must endure the comparative judgment.  The  
first question asked concerning <hi rend="italic">The Fruit of the Tree</hi> will  
pertain neither to its proper merits nor its formal classification.   
"Is it as good as <hi rend="italic">The House of Mirth?"</hi>&mdash;that is the query  
that must be met at the outset, unless it is anticipated by the no  
less pressing interrogation, "Will it be as popular as <hi rend="italic">The House  
of Mirth?"</hi>  The implied distinction must be maintained.  Those  
shallow-pated readers who identify merit with popularity are not to  
be found in the intellectual circles to which Mrs. Wharton  
ministers.  Rather is her most numerous following among those who  
forgive the popularity for the sake of the merit.  But since the  
dual question is sure to be propounded, and the dilemma cannot be  
avoided by even the humblest commentator, I may at once lay a  
reckless hand on either horn by hazarding the opinion that  
<hi rend="italic">The</hi> <pb n="274" id="WhaR1Fo274"/> <hi rend="italic">Fruit of the Tree</hi>, though a better book  
than its predecessor, is not likely to provoke an equal amount of  
that heated and emotional public discussion which is the true sign  
of popularity.  
</p><p>And so enough of the grocer's quantitative method of weighing  
genius.  It is more gratifying to declare Mrs. Wharton's new book  
a novel that richly repays reading, without reference to intrusive  
comparisons.  To the reader of much fiction of the day, and even  
more perhaps to the craftsman, its craftsmanship must be a delight.   
It is not merely that the author knows how to write, though even  
this faculty, which ought to be taken for granted, is sufficiently  
rare.  She knows also how to manage and develop a story.  Her skill  
in this province of her art is all the more striking because her  
latest work is frankly disdainful of certain traditional precepts.   
It lacks unity.  Its point of view is not single.  It does not flow  
evenly, but leaps over years in a paragraph and halts for pages  
over a momentary incident.  It takes in different groups of  
personages whose relations are shifting and varied, and the main  
interest is more than once transferred from one character to  
another.  
</p><p>These facts might well excite the academic person who reads by  
rule.  But it should be remembered that Mrs. Wharton has  
established her right to ignore rules by first proving how  
faithfully she can observe them.  The perfectly direct development  
of Lily Bart's career, though it was empty of the dramatic element,  
was structurally an almost faultless narrative.  In <hi rend="italic">The Fruit of  
the Tree</hi> the problem is, if not actually bigger, at least  
vastly more complex&mdash;or, rather, there are two or three distinct  
though related problems dealt with.  It is not altogether  
discreditable to Mrs. Wharton that she has attempted a more  
difficult task, and the only valid test of her success or failure  
is the concrete one&mdash;the impression produced by an honest reading  
of the book.  The truth is that the structure of the story is for  
the most part managed with admirable skill.  The transitions are  
effected so easily that there is no jar, and the point of view  
throughout is large enough to allow for some variation without  
forcing a consciousness of the change.  Only the shifting of  
attention from one to another of the principal characters,  
resulting in a lessening of the grip of the story, must be recorded  
as a positive fault.  The stage is set in the beginning around the  
figure of John Amherst, at first a worker in the Westmore mills and  
eventually their virtual owner, and it is his relation to the mills  
that furnishes the semblance of a unifying interest.  But the  
personal problem springing from this relationship falls into  
abeyance for a time as the character of his first wife emerges into  
the light, and it drops nearly out of sight before the more  
poignant demand of the situation which develops toward the end  
around the woman who becomes his second wife.  Hers is the real  
drama, for which all that goes before is mere preparation.  And the  
preparation goes back too far, is too thorough; the length of the  
approach dwarfs the edifice.  
</p><p>But I have dwelt too long on purely formal considerations.   
Mrs. Wharton's highly polished style and mastery of her craft imply  
at least that the stuff she has put into her book is worthy of some  
attention.  But when one comes to examine the story itself and the  
ideas that lie back of it some very large questions obtrude  
themselves.  Here the backward view with its comparison is  
inevitable again.  No one who has followed this author's career  
attentively can have failed to note that <hi rend="italic">The House of Mirth</hi>  
betrayed a decided change of front; and the terms in which this  
change is characterised are likely to involve one's view of the  
whole province of fiction.  In her earlier work, and particularly  
in the best of it as contained in certain of her short stories,  
Mrs. Wharton showed herself the cultivator of a highly specialised  
field.  The problems with which she dealt were subtle ones, and her  
characters were tinged with the morbid excess of sensibility which  
seems to us to belong to modern life.  It was not for nothing that  
she was proclaimed the faithful disciple of Mr. Henry James.   
Perhaps the persistent attribution of this discipleship stung her  
to seek escape into a different field.  Whatever the reason, the  
marks of her former master's influence have almost wholly  
disappeared in her later <pb n="275" id="WhaR1Fo275"/> work; for her recent book,  
<hi rend="italic">Madame de Treymes</hi>, though reminiscent of Mr. James as to  
subject, is scarcely so as to treatment.  In <hi rend="italic">The Fruit of the  
Tree</hi> there is elaboration of plot, but little of the complexity  
that springs from the interaction of highly individualised  
characters.  The persons of the drama are indeed somewhat  
conventionalised into the guise of "types," and the situation into  
which they are finally plunged provokes a reference to literature  
rather than to life.  Ingeniously, plausibly as the climax is  
developed, it is possible to feel that it is a wonderfully clever  
invention, not an organic growth.  
</p><p>All this the contemner of popularity may explain by asserting  
that Mrs. Wharton's inspiration has dwindled as her technical  
mastery has increased.  On the other hand, it may be declared that  
she has sought a universal note in place of the limited appeal of  
her earlier work; and the advocate of this view can at least have  
the satisfaction of pointing triumphantly to the fact that she now  
has twenty readers where she formerly had one.  For the reader who  
is honestly in doubt as between these two extremes of opinion there  
is no course open but to fall back on the heartiest praise of Mrs.  
Wharton's fine and exceptional gift, and the liveliest curiosity as  
to what pleasure it may still have in store for us.</p>  
<signed>                              <hi rend="italic">Edward Clark Marsh.</hi></signed>  
  
</div1>  
</body>  
</text>  
</TEI.2>  
  
