<?xml version="1.0"?>

<?dlps id="WhaR2Co"?>
<?dlps page-images="none" figure-images="no"?>
<?dlps transcription="other"?>

<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/tei-p4/tei2.dtd" [
<!ENTITY % POSTKB "INCLUDE">
<!ENTITY % TEI.extensions.ent SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.ent">
<!ENTITY % TEI.extensions.dtd SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.dtd">
<!ENTITY % ISOnum SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/charent/iso-num.ent"> %ISOnum;
<!ENTITY % ISOpub SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/charent/iso-pub.ent"> %ISOpub;
]>
 
<TEI.2 id="WhaR2Co"> 
<teiHeader type="migrated" creator="Etext">
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title type="main">Mrs. Wharton's Manner</title>
<title type="sort">mrs whartons manner</title>
<author>Wharton review: Boynton, H. W.</author>
<respStmt>
<resp>Creation of machine-readable version:</resp> 
<name>Judy Boss</name> 
<resp>Conversion to TEI.2-conformant markup:</resp>  
<name>University of Virginia Library Electronic Text Center.</name>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt> 
<extent>ca. <num type="kilobytes">16</num> kilobytes</extent> 
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>University of Virginia Library</publisher>
<pubPlace>Charlottesville, Virginia</pubPlace> 
<idno type="ETC">WhaR2Co</idno> 
<date value="1996">1996</date>
<availability status="public">
<p n="copyright">Copyright &copy; 1996 by the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia</p>
<p n="access">Publicly accessible</p>
</availability>
<idno type="uva-pid">uva-lib:476520</idno>
</publicationStmt>
<seriesStmt>
<title>University of Virginia Library, Text collection</title>
<idno type="uva-set">UVA-LIB-Text</idno>
</seriesStmt> 
<sourceDesc>
<biblFull>
<titleStmt>
<title type="main">Mrs. Wharton's Manner</title>
<title level="j">Nation. A Weekly Journal Devoted to Politics, Literature, Science, Drama, Music, Art, and Finance.</title>
<title type="sort">mrs whartons manner</title>
<author>H. W. Boynton</author>
</titleStmt> 
<editionStmt>
<p>1st Edition.</p>
</editionStmt> 
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>New York Evening Post Company</publisher> 
<pubPlace>New York</pubPlace> 
<date value="1913">1913</date>
</publicationStmt> 
<seriesStmt>
<p>
<hi rend="italic">The Nation</hi> 97 (30 Oct. 1913): 404-05.</p>
</seriesStmt> 
<notesStmt>
<note>
<p>UVa ed. AP2.N2</p>
</note>
</notesStmt>
</biblFull>
</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc> 
<encodingDesc>
<projectDesc>
<p>Prepared for the University of Virginia Library Electronic Text Center.</p>
</projectDesc> 
<editorialDecl>
<p>All quotation marks retained as data.</p> 
<p>Spell-check and verification made 
against printed text using WordPerfect spell checker.</p> 
<p>All unambiguous end-of-line hyphens have been removed, and the 
trailing part of a word has been joined to the preceding line.</p> 
<p id="ETC">Keywords in the header are a local Electronic Text Center scheme  
to aid in establishing analytical groupings.</p>
</editorialDecl> 
<refsDecl>
<p>ID elements are given for each page element and are composed of the text's 
unique cryptogram and the given page number, as in AusEmma1 for page one of  
Jane Austen's Emma.</p>
</refsDecl> 
</encodingDesc> 
<profileDesc>
<creation>
<date value="1913">1913</date>
</creation> 
<langUsage>
<language id="eng" usage="main">English</language>
</langUsage> 
<textClass>
<keywords>
<term>non-fiction</term>
<term>prose</term> 
<term>Women Writers</term>
</keywords> 
</textClass>
</profileDesc> 
<revisionDesc>
<change>
<date value="1996-03">March 1996</date> 
<respStmt>
<resp>corrector</resp> 
<name>Deirdre A. Johnson, Electronic Text Center, University of Virginia</name>
</respStmt> 
<item>Added header and basic TEI markup</item>
</change>
<change>
<date value="2007-09">September 2007</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>Migration</resp>
<name>Ethan Gruber, University of Virginia Library</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Converted XML markup from TEI Lite to uva-dl-tei (TEI P4 with local customizations).</item>
</change>
<change>
<date value="2008-01">January 2008</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>Migration</resp>
<name>Greg Murray, University of Virginia Library</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Programmatically updated TEI header markup (but not header content) for minimal compliance with current QA requirements.</item>
</change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader> 
 
<text id="d1"> 
<body id="d2"> 
<div1 type="essay" id="d3"><pb n="404" id="WhaR2Co404"/>  
<head>           MRS. WHARTON'S MANNER.</head> 
 
<p>Mrs. Wharton's early successes as a writer of short stories 
were not the chance successes of a tyro. She had already served 
her apprenticeship, without making the public pay for the crude 
products of that trying phase of experience. She had learned what 
she wanted to do, and how to do it. She could take a situation or 
an episode involving two or three human figures, and wring the 
truth from it&mdash;the truth as she personally saw it. She could drive 
home her interpretation with witty phrase and epigram. She could 
make people &laquo;sit up,&raquo; without the use of vulgar stimulants. If 
there was one quality which pleased her audience more than her 
brilliancy, it was her breeding. A final zest was given to the 
enjoyment of her style by the sense that it was gentlemanlike.  
That sense was misleading, of course, for she has always been 
strongly feminine; but it is possible for a voice a trifle deeper 
than common, a gesture somewhat more frank, to enhance the charm of 
femininity by its hint of contradiction. 
</p><p>But beneath the suavity and self-possession of her manner 
there has always been a restless spirit, and the time passed soon 
when the exercise of wit and adroitness could soothe it. She had, 
besides, the resources of the study, and the riches of art.  
Turning from the short story to the novel, she called them to her 
aid. She ranged herself in that school of sophistication, of 
finesse, half-lights, and rich, dim accessories, which was then 
ascendant. She knew her Meredith, her James, her Howells, and the 
greater masters of France&mdash;Bourget, Stendhal, and the rest. She 
wished to address herself to no vulgar audience. The very titles 
of those earlier books, &laquo;The Greater Inclination,&raquo; &laquo;Crucial 
Instances,&raquo; &laquo;The Valley of Decision,&raquo; were a snub to the populace 
and a challenge to the fastidious. The populace does not deal in 
comparatives, <hi rend="italic">nuances</hi>, reservations, compunctions. 
</p><p>There lies, however, between the reading masses and the small 
choir of the elect, a surprising body of persons, chiefly feminine, 
who aspire to sophistication and connoisseurship. The aspiration, 
as applied to literature, was more fashionable ten years ago than 
now, perhaps. Certainly a good many readers who aspired in that 
way were attracted to Mrs. Wharton's earlier novels. To wander 
through the pages of &laquo;The Valley of Decision,&raquo; for example, was to 
breathe an atmosphere of polite and erudite adventure, in lands 
where life had become a finished thing long before American crudity 
began. It was not a very good story as a story; but the charm of 
its style, of its leisurely winding along paths of old-world 
glamour, was indubitable. There was something else&mdash;the occurrence 
here and there of an episode vivid and telling, the work not of the 
gentleman and scholar and agreeable cicerone, under whose guidance 
we seemed, for the most part, to be quietly progressing, but of 
Mrs. Wharton, the story-teller. 
</p><p>Looking back, from this remove, we suspect that those 
episodes, so incidentally and even negligently vouchsafed, were the 
most genuine part of the book: the rest, a brilliant <hi rend="italic">tour de 
force</hi>. Its very elegance, its langour, its abstention from 
display of wit or from excess of any sort, mark it as a feat. For 
Mrs. Wharton is not a gentleman or a reflective philosopher. She 
is a nervous, cultivated American woman, an extremely clever 
performer on one of the favorite instruments of the hour: a 
virtuoso, but in the popular sense of the word. And she has been 
too clever not to find her way instinctively to the larger audience 
which was ready for her. 
</p><p>With &laquo;The House of Mirth&raquo; she captured it. Here, almost in 
the flesh, was that society to which striving America looks up with 
delighted consternation. Here was a story of the &laquo;Four Hundred&raquo; 
written from the inside, a moving picture of high life. It could 
have been the work of no one but Mrs. Wharton, and yet was plainly 
the work of another than the Mrs. Wharton of &laquo;The Dilettante&raquo; or 
&laquo;The Valley of Decision.&raquo; Both her wit and her erudition were now 
under better control. She no longer sparkled for the sake of 
sparkling, or alluded for the sake of allusion. In fact, she must 
have had a pretty clear notion of the audience she was addressing 
and of its needs. 
</p><p>It was not an altogether different audience from her older 
one; but it was wider, more various. The novelist, like the 
playwright, must, if he expects to command a satisfactory hearing, 
appeal, in some sense, to the mass as an individual. What Mr. A. 
B. Walkley has said of the theatre audience applies, roughly, to 
what may be called the magazine audience. The element of physical 
contact and contagion is lacking; but the constituency of the news-stands does somehow pull together as one man. &laquo;A crowd,&raquo; Mr. 
Walkley says, &laquo;forms a new entity, with a mind and character of its 
own; it differs from the individuals composing it, just as our 
bodies are unlike the cells of which they are made up, or just as 
a chemical combination is unlike its separate ingredients.&raquo; 
</p><p>Before &laquo;The House of Mirth&raquo; Mrs. Wharton had not set herself 
seriously to the task of captivating the magazine audience. She 
had tickled its ears with her clever wisps of satire and badinage.  
She had gone over its head entirely with &laquo;The Valley of Decision,&raquo; 
and the books on Italy which followed. Now, at one stroke, she 
succeeded in rousing it to excited attention with the &laquo;House of 
Mirth.&raquo; Not that Mrs. Wharton abased herself to the magazine 
manner. Her style was as finished and urbane as ever. But at last 
its refinement was felt to be in keeping with the theme. Here, in 
elegant black and white, were the superior beings to whom democracy 
had hitherto been able to award only the humbler tributes of the 
society column and <hi rend="italic">Town Topics</hi>. 
</p><p>The tale of Lily Bart could have been justified only as lifted 
to the plane of tragedy. In Mrs. Wharton's hands, adroit as they 
are, it remained sordid and vulgar. Something might have been done 
with it in the way of uncompromising realism; so, at least, a 
negative force and meaning might have been given to it. But in 
attempting to employ the machinery of tragic romance, Mrs. Wharton 
attempted the impossible. Lily is not a tragic figure, but a 
feeble and paltry one. Such glamour as she has is the meretricious 
glamour of social position; and this is true of all her &laquo;set.&raquo; 
</p><p>Perhaps Mrs. Wharton felt the irony of Lily's fame. No doubt 
she was annoyed by the persistent attempts to give a local 
habitation and a name to each of her imaginary figures of New York.  
That was her penalty for not having made them also imaginative. At 
all events, in &laquo;Madame de Treymes&raquo; she withdrew to a safer and 
sounder field. Here, as in &laquo;Sanctuary,&raquo; she challenged the closest 
comparison with Miss Anne Douglas Sedgwick (who, then irreproachable,<pb n="405" id="WhaR2Co405"/> 
has since gained popularity with &laquo;Tante&raquo;). A 
delicate study of old-world life on a comparatively small scale, 
&laquo;Madame de Treymes&raquo; went its quiet way. But in &laquo;The Fruit of the 
Tree&raquo; Mrs. Wharton again made, to speak coarsely, a hit. It was 
not precisely the same kind of hit as that which she had scored in 
&laquo;The House of Mirth.&raquo; It lacked two elements of popular appeal 
which had counted in the earlier novel. It did not paint the 
society of our dreams&mdash;that of New York and environs&mdash;and it did 
not turn upon a problem of sex. But there was a problem&mdash;and it 
interested the public because it was a problem which everybody has 
attacked, however casually, and nobody has solved: is it right, 
under any circumstance, to put a human being &laquo;out of misery&raquo;?  
Unluckily, this is even less approachably a &laquo;well-made&raquo; novel than 
&laquo;The House of Mirth.&raquo; Its six hundred odd pages contain material 
for two distinct novels&mdash;or perhaps we should say for a dozen short 
stories. And, as in &laquo;The House of Mirth,&raquo; its material was 
presented with nothing more than cleverness&mdash;without the 
transforming touch of imagination. 
</p><p>In &laquo;The Custom of the 
Country,&raquo;<ref target="WhaR2Con2">*</ref>we are told, Mrs. Wharton has 
returned to the field of &laquo;The House of Mirth.&raquo; We do not find this 
to be literally true. The heroine of this story is not a Lily 
Bart, but an Undine Spragg, of Apex City, Arizona. We find her in 
New York, to be sure, bent upon breaking in among the best people.  
In fact, when we meet her she has been there two years, with her 
attendant parents, and has not yet broken in. But she is on the 
eve of it. In a Bohemian circle to which she has penetrated, she 
meets a fashionable portrait-painter, Claud Walsingham Popple, and 
is much impressed with his fine presence and manners. Through him 
she meets, and is not impressed by a real scion of the aristocracy, 
Ralph Marvell. He at once, without other excuse than her crude 
young beauty, falls in love with her; and as soon as she realizes 
that he is &laquo;the real thing,&raquo; she succumbs.</p> 
<p>Now, Undine Spragg is not a new type. We have met her 
recently in many novels&mdash;in Mr. Herrick's &laquo;One Woman's Story,&raquo; in 
Mr. Dreiser, in the recent &laquo;Joan Thursday&raquo; of Mr. Louis Joseph 
Vance; in fact, wherever among our novelists realism continues to 
rear its head. She is the daughter of the plain people, forging 
towards success and happiness in the fashionable sense of the 
terms. The thing that is hard to pardon in her is that she appears 
a caricature instead of a refinement of that type. Undine Spragg 
is as hard, as vulgar, as calculating, as selfish as any 
professional daughter of pleasure could be. That she is physically 
cold does not prevent her being twice divorced in pursuit of the 
main chance, and finally falling back upon her first husband, 
because he is not only a multi-millionaire, but the only person who 
understands her. They are unmistakably a pair. 
</p><p>There is nothing to attach the deeper sympathies of the reader 
to this person or to any other in the book. Paul Marvell, who dies 
by his own hand, is well out of it, and that is all we feel: with 
his elegance and sensitiveness, he shows the futility that besets 
most of Mrs. Wharton's finer-grained male Americans. The Count de 
Trezac, who succeeds him, is of similar type, except for the fact 
that &laquo;the custom of the country,&raquo; with him, makes the family of 
more importance than the wife, and so stiffens his backbone against 
her encroachments. Most of the other figures in the book are 
caricatured, from the masseuse and manicure artist, Mrs. Heeny, to 
the unspeakable Van Degen. 
</p><p>With all its amenity of manner, &laquo;The Custom of the Country&raquo; 
has a sharply satirical tone. The heroine is a mere monster of 
vulgarity; and Mrs. Wharton seems to feel a ruthless satisfaction 
in exposing her in all her enormity. The result is a defeat of 
what should have been the main purpose, to <hi rend="italic">interest</hi> us in 
the Spragg. A caricature does not remain interesting to the length 
of six hundred pages. And there is no use trying to convey on 
paper the charm of a physical beauty which has no backing in mind 
or character. The mood of satire seems to be growing upon Mrs. 
Wharton, a dubious sign in a writer who has passed a certain age.  
It is hard to feel that, clever and effective and varied as her 
work has been, and is, she has ever yet veritably &laquo;found herself&raquo;&mdash; 
the self of assured power which seemed to exist potentially in her 
first books. Ten years ago, a stranger asking an American who was 
the most distinguished of our novelists would very likely have 
heard the name of Mrs. Wharton. It is not altogether due to the 
fact that other (potential) giants have arisen among us, that the 
answer would now hardly be the same.</p> 
<signed>                    H. W. B.</signed> 
</div1> 
</body> 


<back id="d4">
<div1 type="notes" id="d5">
	<note id="WhaR2Con2"><seg type="note-symbol">*</seg><p><hi rend="italic"> The Custom of the Country</hi>. By Edith Wharton. New 
York: Charles Scribner's Sons.</p>
</note>
</div1></back> 

 

</text> 
</TEI.2> 
 
 
 
