<?xml version="1.0"?>

<?dlps id="WhaR1At"?>
<?dlps page-images="none" figure-images="no"?>
<?dlps transcription="other"?>

<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/tei-p4/tei2.dtd" [
<!ENTITY % POSTKB "INCLUDE">
<!ENTITY % TEI.extensions.ent SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.ent">
<!ENTITY % TEI.extensions.dtd SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.dtd">
<!ENTITY % ISOlat1 SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/charent/iso-lat1.ent"> %ISOlat1;
<!ENTITY % ISOnum SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/charent/iso-num.ent"> %ISOnum;
<!ENTITY % ISOpub SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/charent/iso-pub.ent"> %ISOpub;
]> 
<TEI.2 id="WhaR1At"> 
<teiHeader type="migrated" creator="Etext">
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title type="main">"Artemis to Actaeon," from "Some Springtime Verse."</title>
<title type="sort">artemis to actaeon, from some springtime verse</title>
<author>Wharton review: Hooker, Brian</author>
<respStmt>
<resp>Creation of machine-readable version:</resp> 
<name>Judy Boss</name> 
<resp>Conversion to TEI.2-conformant markup:</resp>  
<name>University of Virginia Library Electronic Text Center.</name>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt> 
<extent>ca. <num type="kilobytes">7</num> kilobytes</extent> 
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>University of Virginia Library</publisher>
<pubPlace>Charlottesville, Virginia</pubPlace> 
<idno type="ETC">WhaR1At</idno> 
<date value="1996">1996</date>
<availability status="public">
<p n="copyright">Copyright &copy; 1996 by the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia</p>
<p n="access">Publicly accessible</p>
</availability>
<idno type="uva-pid">uva-lib:476510</idno>
</publicationStmt>
<seriesStmt>
<title>University of Virginia Library, Text collection</title>
<idno type="uva-set">UVA-LIB-Text</idno>
</seriesStmt> 
<notesStmt>
<note>
<p>Text is a review which appeared in a larger article. Editorial comment by the creator of the electronic text appears in square brackets and explains an antecedent reference.</p>
</note> 
<note>
<p>UVa ed. AP2.B78</p>
</note>
</notesStmt> 
<sourceDesc>
<biblFull>
<titleStmt>
<title type="main">Review: "Artemis to Act&aelig;on," in "Some Springtime Verse."</title>
<title level="j">Bookman</title>
<title type="sort">review artemis to actaeon, in some springtime verse</title>
<author>Brian Hooker</author>
</titleStmt> 
<editionStmt>
<p>1st Edition.</p>
</editionStmt> 
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>Dodd, Mead and Company</publisher> 
<pubPlace>New York</pubPlace> 
<date value="1909">1909</date>
</publicationStmt> 
<seriesStmt>
<p>
<hi rend="italic">Bookman</hi> 29 (June 1909): 367-68.</p>
</seriesStmt> 
</biblFull>
</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc> 
<encodingDesc>
<projectDesc>
<p>Prepared for the University of Virginia Library Electronic Text 
Center.</p>
</projectDesc> 
<editorialDecl>
<p>All quotation marks retained as data.</p> 
<p>Spell-check and verification made 
against printed text using WordPerfect spell checker.</p> 
<p>All unambiguous end-of-line hyphens have been removed, and the 
trailing part of a word has been joined to the preceding line.</p> 
<p id="ETC">Keywords in the header are a local Electronic Text Center scheme  
to aid in establishing analytical groupings.</p>
</editorialDecl> 
<refsDecl>
<p>ID elements are given for each page element and are composed of the text's 
unique cryptogram and the given page number, as in AusEmma1 for page one of  
Jane Austen's Emma.</p>
</refsDecl>
</encodingDesc> 
<profileDesc>
<creation>
<date value="1909">1909</date>
</creation> 
<langUsage>
<language id="eng" usage="main">English</language>
</langUsage> 
<textClass>
<keywords>
<term>non-fiction</term>
<term>prose</term> 
<term>Women Writers</term>
</keywords> 
</textClass>
</profileDesc> 
<revisionDesc>
<change>
<date value="1996-03">March 1996</date> 
<respStmt>
<resp>corrector</resp> 
<name>Deirdre A. Johnson, Electronic Text Center, University of 
Virginia</name>
</respStmt> 
<item>Added header and basic TEI markup</item>
</change> 
<change>
<date value="2005-07">July 2005</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>Corrector</resp>
<name>Margaret Konkol</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Converted SGML to XML and fixed tagging.</item>
</change>
<change>
<date value="2007-09">September 2007</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>Migration</resp>
<name>Ethan Gruber, University of Virginia Library</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Converted XML markup from TEI Lite to uva-dl-tei (TEI P4 with local customizations).</item>
</change>
<change>
<date value="2008-01">January 2008</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>Migration</resp>
<name>Greg Murray, University of Virginia Library</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Programmatically updated TEI header markup (but not header content) for minimal compliance with current QA requirements.</item>
</change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader> 
 
<text id="d1"> 
<body id="d2"> 

<div1 type="essay" id="d3"><pb n="367" id="WhaR1At367"/>  

<p>The title-poem of Mrs. Wharton's <hi rend="italic">Artemis to Actaeon</hi> 
takes a very different but equally modern view of the same goddess 
[as Mr. Hewlett's].  Her Artemis slays Actaeon not in anger, but in 
grace, recognising in him who dared to look upon her a soul too 
great for the little uses of the world, worthy of that immortality 
which is death.  Now, there are two ways of handling mythological 
material: one may simply retell the old stories vividly, for the 
sheer beauty that is in them; or one may seek out some latent 
meaning, some new idea whereof the myth will form a fitting 
incarnation.  The trouble with these present examples of the second 
method is that they do violence to the spirit of the myth.  The 
vigorous and original mentality which has done so much for Mrs. 
Wharton as a novelist stands somewhat in her light as a poet.  It 
is not that a poem can be too intellectual, but that it must not be 
more intellectual than emotional; and Mrs. Wharton's thought 
sometimes absorbs her feeling and leaves her language dry. 
<q><lg type="stanza"> 
<l>  Orpheus the Harper, coming to the gate</l> 
<l>  Where the implacable dim warder sate,</l> 
<l>  Besought for parley with a shade within,</l> 
<l>  Dearer to him than life itself had been,</l> 
<l>  Sweeter than sunlight on Illyrian sea . . .</l> 
</lg></q> 
Compare with this the opening of Mr. Stephen Phillips's "Christ in 
Hades": 
<q><lg type="stanza"> 
<l>  Keen as a blinded man at dawn awake</l> 
<l>  Smells in the dark the cold odor of earth&mdash;</l> 
<l>  Eastward he turns his eyes, and over him</l> 
<l>  A dreadful freshness exquisitely breathes&mdash;</l> 
</lg></q> 
This is the magic; the other is only well written; thought, not 
felt.  But the most of Mrs. Wharton's book is far better.  It is a 
delight to follow the steady and sonorous lines of her blank verse 
and to note how thoroughly she has assimilated the craftsmanship of 
her models.  Tennyson and Mr. Phillips have given her style, 
Browning has taught her monologue and Rossetti sonnet-form; yet 
there is not an imitative line in her book.  She has made her 
learning her own; and there is far more personality in her poems 
than in Mr. Hewlett's.  "Margaret of Cortona" is perhaps the best 
of them.  In her girlhood a man took Margaret out of the slums, 
made her a woman and wise.  He dying, she took the veil, and in 
time became a saint; and the poem is her confession. 
<q><lg type="stanza"> 
<l>Judge Thou alone between this priest and me;</l> 
<l>Nay, rather, Lord, between my past and present,</l> 
<l>Thy Margaret and that other's&mdash;whose she is</l> 
<l>By right of salvage&mdash;and whose call should follow</l> 
<l>Thine?  Silent still&mdash;  Or his who stooped to her,</l><pb n="368" id="WhaR1At368"/> 
<l>And drew her to Thee by the bands of love?</l> 
<l>Not Thine?  Then his?</l> 
<l>          Ah, Christ&mdash;the thorn-crowned Head</l> 
<l>Bends . . . bends again . . . down on your knees, Fra Paolo!</l> 
<l>If his, then Thine!</l> 
<l>          Kneel, priest, for this is heaven . . .</l> 
</lg></q> 
Mrs. Wharton is at her best in the dramatic monologue, both because 
of her power of characterisation and because blank verse is her 
readiest medium.  Rhyme often troubles her; and some of her 
sonnets, though well versified, are abstract and confused in 
expression.  She was not born a poet; but this volume shows well 
how high in poetry a thoroughly cultured prose artist may attain.  
It is a noble and worthy piece of work, of which at least no living 
poet need be ashamed. 
</p> 
 
</div1> 
</body> 
</text> 
</TEI.2> 
 
