<?xml version="1.0"?>

<?dlps id="WhaR1Vo"?>
<?dlps page-images="none" figure-images="no"?>
<?dlps transcription="other"?>

<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/tei-p4/tei2.dtd" [
<!ENTITY % POSTKB "INCLUDE">
<!ENTITY % TEI.extensions.ent SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.ent">
<!ENTITY % TEI.extensions.dtd SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.dtd">
<!ENTITY % ISOnum SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/charent/iso-num.ent"> %ISOnum;
<!ENTITY % ISOpub SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/charent/iso-pub.ent"> %ISOpub;
]>

<TEI.2 id="WhaR1Vo"> 
<teiHeader type="migrated" creator="Etext">
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title type="main">Mrs. Wharton's "The Valley of Decision."</title>
<title type="sort">mrs whartons the valley of decision</title>
<author>Wharton review: Cooper, Frederic Taber</author>
<respStmt>
<resp>Creation of machine-readable version:</resp> 
<name>Judy Boss</name> 
<resp>Conversion to TEI.2-conformant markup:</resp>  
<name>University of Virginia Library Electronic Text Center.</name>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt> 
<extent>ca. <num type="kilobytes">19</num> kilobytes</extent> 
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>University of Virginia Library</publisher>
<pubPlace>Charlottesville, Virginia</pubPlace> 
<idno type="ETC">WhaR1Vo</idno> 
<date value="1996">1996</date>
<availability status="public">
<p n="copyright">Copyright &copy; 1996 by the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia</p>
<p n="access">Publicly accessible</p>
</availability>
<idno type="uva-pid">uva-lib:476519</idno>
</publicationStmt>
<seriesStmt>
<title>University of Virginia Library, Text collection</title>
<idno type="uva-set">UVA-LIB-Text</idno>
</seriesStmt> 
<notesStmt>
<note>
<p>This electronic text has been excerpted from a longer article.</p>
</note>
</notesStmt> 
<sourceDesc>
<biblFull>
<titleStmt>
<title type="main">Mrs. Wharton's "The Valley of Decision", 
in: Nine Books of Some Importance</title>
<title type="sort">mrs whartons the valley of decision , in nine books of some importance</title>
<author>Frederic Taber Cooper</author>
</titleStmt> 
<editionStmt>
<p>1st Edition.</p>
</editionStmt> 
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>Dodd, Mead &amp; Company</publisher> 
<pubPlace>New York, N. Y.</pubPlace> 
<date value="1902">1902</date>
</publicationStmt> 
<seriesStmt>
<p>
<hi rend="italic">Bookman</hi> 15 (April 1902): 173-75.</p>
</seriesStmt> 
<notesStmt>
<note>
<p>UVa ed. AP2.B78</p>
</note>
</notesStmt>
</biblFull>
</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc> 
<encodingDesc>
<projectDesc>
<p>Prepared for the University of Virginia Library Electronic Text Center.</p>
</projectDesc> 
<editorialDecl>
<p>All quotation marks retained as data.</p> 
<p>Spell-check and verification made 
against printed text using WordPerfect spell checker.</p> 
<p>All unambiguous end-of-line hyphens have been removed, and the 
trailing part of a word has been joined to the preceding line.</p> 
<p id="ETC">Keywords in the header are a local Electronic Text Center scheme  
to aid in establishing analytical groupings.</p>
</editorialDecl> 
<refsDecl>
<p>ID elements are given for each page element and are composed of the text's 
unique cryptogram and the given page number, as in AusEmma1 for page one of  
Jane Austen's Emma.</p>
</refsDecl> 
</encodingDesc> 
<profileDesc>
<creation>
<date value="1902">1902</date>
</creation> 
<langUsage>
<language id="eng" usage="main">English</language> 
<language id="fre">French</language>
<language id="it">Italian</language>
<language id="ger">German</language>
</langUsage> 
<textClass>
<keywords>
<term>non-fiction</term>
<term>prose</term> 
<term>Women Writers</term>
</keywords> 
</textClass>
</profileDesc> 
<revisionDesc>
<change>
<date value="1996-03">March 1996</date> 
<respStmt>
<resp>corrector</resp> 
<name>Deirdre A. Johnson, Electronic Text Center, University of Virginia</name>
</respStmt> 
<item>Added header and basic TEI markup</item>
</change> 
<change>
<date value="2005-07">July 2005</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>Corrector</resp>
<name>Margaret Konkol</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Converted SGML to XML and fixed tagging.</item>
</change>
<change>
<date value="2007-09">September 2007</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>Migration</resp>
<name>Ethan Gruber, University of Virginia Library</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Converted XML markup from TEI Lite to uva-dl-tei (TEI P4 with local customizations).</item>
</change>
<change>
<date value="2008-01">January 2008</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>Migration</resp>
<name>Greg Murray, University of Virginia Library</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Programmatically updated TEI header markup (but not header content) for minimal compliance with current QA requirements.</item>
</change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader> 
 
<text id="d1"> 
<body id="d2"> 
<div1 type="essay" id="d3"><pb n="173" id="WhaR1Vo173"/> <head>MRS. WHARTON'S &laquo;THE VALLEY OF DECISION.&raquo;</head>

<p><ref target="WhaR1Von1">*</ref></p> 
<p>There is a type of artistic temperament that seems to find a 
sensuous satisfaction in vast canvases and themes of epic 
magnitude. And since, in a certain sense, the novelist has a far 
wider canvas than the artist upon which to paint his picture, he 
runs a proportionately greater chance of overestimating his 
strength. He is not limited by any single hour or day or year; he 
is not bounded by the visible horizon; he may cover a whole epoch 
in the history of an individual or a family or a nation; or he may 
concentrate himself upon a single crucial moment in the life of a 
man or woman. The value of what he does depends not upon the 
breadth of the canvas, but upon the inherent truth of the 
perspective, the accuracy of the line and colour, the subtle and 
indefinable sense of proportion underlying the whole conception.  
Yet the temptation to strive for something big and broad and 
impressive, to paint humanity in the mass, to study not individual 
lives, but the complex development of a race, has led astray more 
than one of our promising younger writers. It is the sort of task 
which demands a long apprenticeship. Kipling embodied in 
<hi rend="italic">Kim</hi> the thoughtful deliberation of a dozen years. Zola was 
content to toil for more than twenty before he attempted to sum up 
the motley life of the French metropolis in a single volume, 
<hi rend="italic">Paris</hi>. Tolstoy waited almost to the end of his career 
before trying to epitomise all Russia in his <hi rend="italic">Resurrection</hi>, 
and even then, in spite of its acknowledged power, more than one 
critic questioned its right to the title of the novel. Yet it is 
just this sort of colossal task that the author of <hi rend="italic">The 
Touchstone</hi> serenely set herself in <hi rend="italic">The Valley of 
Decision;</hi> and the fact that the resulting novel is entitled to 
a modicum of honest and cordial praise is in itself a recognition 
of her versatility and her genius. 
</p><p>Mrs. Wharton was fortunate at the outset in her choice of a 
subject. She has attempted to sum up the life of Italy in the 
latter half of the eighteenth century, that crucial 
<foreign lang="it"><hi rend="italic">settecento</hi></foreign>, which has aptly been compared to the closing act 
of a tragedy. It was that period of fallacious calm following the 
war of the Austrian Succession, when beneath the surface all Italy 
was seething with undercurrents of discontent against the old 
established order of things; when &laquo;the little Italian courts were 
still dozing in fancied security under the wing of Bourbon and 
Hapsburg suzerains;&raquo; when clergy and nobles still clung tenaciously 
to their class privileges and united in their efforts to repress 
the spread of learning; when throngs of the ignorant and 
superstitious still crowded the highroads to the shrines of popular 
saints, and a small but growing number of enlightened spirits met 
in secret conclave to discuss forbidden new doctrines of philosophy 
and science. It is a vast subject, and one full of epic values&mdash;a 
subject which it is easy to imagine a Balzac or a Tolstoy treating 
in the bold, sweeping, impressionistic way that it demands. But it 
is not easy to imagine what an introspective writer, a Bourget, or 
a Henry James, could make of such a theme, and still less an avowed 
disciple of Mr. James, such as Mrs. Wharton has hitherto shown 
herself. That the resulting volume shows so much comparative 
excellence is a pleasant surprise. She has brought to her task a 
considerable amount of erudition. She is saturated to her finger-tips with the historical facts of the period&mdash;the motley and 
confusing tangle of petty dukedoms, the warring claims of Austria 
and of Spain. She has given us not merely a broad canvas but a 
moving panorama of the life of that restless time, presenting with 
a certain dramatic power the discontent of the masses; the petty 
intrigues of the Church and the aristocracy; the gilded uselessness 
of the typical fine lady with her <foreign lang="fre"><hi rend="italic">cavaliere servante</hi></foreign>, her 
pet monkey and her parrot; the brutal ignorance of the peasantry; 
the disorders and license of the Bohemian <pb n="174" id="WhaR1Vo174"/> world&mdash;all the 
various strata and sub-strata of the social life of the times. The 
book is less a novel than a sort of cultured 
<foreign lang="ger"><hi rend="italic">Sittengeschichte</hi></foreign> of the epoch, as minute, as conscientious 
and as comprehensive as a chapter from Gibbon's <hi rend="italic">Rome</hi>, yet 
lacking those little, vital, illuminating touches which help to 
make us see. Her most obvious fault seems to be her avoidance of 
the concrete and the specific. She delights in indulging in 
generalities. She leaves a mental impression of crowds and 
movement and the turmoil of hurrying, bustling human life; but when 
we search in our memory for further impressions, we find them misty 
and uncertain. The people, the scenes, the incidents, are often 
not necessarily Italian at all. She is seldom definite enough in 
her descriptions to be Much of the time we miss even the sunshine, 
the blue sky, that redolence of warmth and colour and superficial 
gayety which is the very essence of Italy&mdash;which fills every page 
of Stendahl's <foreign lang="fre"><hi rend="italic">Chartreuse de Parme</hi></foreign>, is woven into the woof 
and warp of <hi rend="italic">Romola</hi>, and goes far toward redeeming even the 
tawdry sensationalism of such a writer as Ouida. There are times 
when one cannot help feeling that Mrs. Wharton has something in 
common with her hero, who, she tells us, &laquo;had lived through twelve 
Italian summers without sense of the sun-steeped quality of an 
atmosphere that even in shade gives each object a golden salience.  
He was conscious of it now only as it suggested fingering a missal 
stiff with gold leaf and edged with a swarming diversity of buds 
and insects.&raquo; When she does pause to describe nature, it is 
usually from a purely aesthetic point of view, with the 
professional delight of an artist at a grouping of rocks, or trees, 
or hills which would make an effective picture&mdash;&laquo;a scene which 
Salvator might have painted;&raquo; or a bend in the road where &laquo;the 
roadside started into detail like the foreground of some minute 
Dutch painter.&raquo; And it is characteristic that these descriptions 
are always of the briefest character. It is only when she becomes 
interested in some matter of aesthetic or philosophic interest that 
Mrs. Wharton becomes verbose. It is worth while to quote, even at 
some length, a characteristic passage of this latter type, for 
which such passages constitute a formidable proportion of the pages 
of these two volumes&mdash;pages which are apt to remain unread, if not 
uncut, by a large number of readers, both those who read frankly 
for amusement, and those who look upon the novel as a serious and 
important human document:</p> 

<p>In the semi-Parisian capital, where French architects designed 
the king's pleasure-houses and the nobility imported their boudoir-panelings from Paris and their damask hangings from Lyons, 
Benedetto Alfieri represented the old classic tradition, the 
tradition of the &laquo;grand manner,&raquo; which had held its own through all 
later variations of taste, running parallel with the 
<foreign lang="it"><hi rend="italic">barocchismo</hi></foreign>of the seventeenth century and the effeminate 
caprices of the rococo period. He had lived much in Rome, in the 
company of men like Winckelmann and Maffei, in that society where 
the revival of classical research was being forwarded by the 
liberality of princes and cardinals and by the indefatigable zeal 
of the scholars in their pay. From this centre of aesthetic 
reaction Alfieri had returned to the Gallicised Turin, with its 
preference for the graceful and ingenious rather than for the 
large, the noble, the restrained; bringing to bear on the taste of 
his native city the influence of a view raised but perhaps narrowed 
by close study of the past; the view of a generation of architects 
in whom archaeological curiosity had stifled the artistic instinct, 
and who, instead of assimilating the spirit of the past like their 
great predecessors, were engrossed in a sterile restoration of the 
letter.</p> 

<p>Considered in its aspect of a novel, a story of human 
interest, the shortcomings of <hi rend="italic">The Valley of Decision</hi> are 
somewhat more intangible, yet none the less they make themselves 
felt. The characters are clearly and conscientiously drawn, the 
drama in which they play a part deals with vital questions of life 
and liberty and human happiness; and yet they leave us cold; they 
fail for the most part to touch the keynote of responsive sympathy.  
The explanation is somewhat hard to find; it lies, in part, at 
least, in the author's obvious willingness to subordinate her 
characters to the exposition of her main theme, the picture of 
Italy as a whole. With this end in view it must be granted that 
her plot is cleverly chosen. She has conceived a petty dukedom, 
Pianura, in the north of Italy, owing allegiance to Charles 
Ferdinand on the one hand, and attached by marriage to the house of 
Hapsburg on the other. The hero, Odo Valsecca, is of the Old 
Order, heir-presumptive to the throne of Pianura, and kept from the 
succession only by a sickly cousin and the latter's dying child.  
In his <pb n="175" id="WhaR1Vo175"/> character Odo represents the conflicting tendencies 
of the times. He is in sympathy with the new ideas of progress and 
liberty, and has brief flashes of energy and enthusiasm. But they 
soon burn themselves out, for he is fundamentally lethargic and 
indifferent, inheriting the fatal taint of his house. The heroine, 
Fulvia Vivaldi, represents the new order. She is the daughter of 
a professor of philosophy, who pays by exile the penalty for his 
temerity in following up the forbidden learning. Under Fulvia's 
influence Odo becomes an enthusiastic disciple of the new 
philosophy, and he is on the point of sacrificing all his prospects 
and accompanying her to France, when the death of his cousin 
unexpectedly makes him Duke of Pianura. To both of them his duty 
is plain. He must accept the burden, and devote his life to giving 
the people that liberty to which they are entitled. For Fulvia 
there are two alternatives. She may continue her way alone to 
Paris, or she may remain at Pianura in a capacity which she will 
not accept.</p> 
 
<p>&laquo;The Regent's mistress?&raquo; she said slowly. &laquo;The key to the 
treasury, the back-door to preferment, the secret trafficker in 
titles and appointments? That is what I should stand for&mdash;and it 
is not to such services that you must even appear to owe your 
power. I will not say that I have my own work to do; for the 
dearest service I could perform would be to help you in yours. But 
to do this I must stand aside. To be near you, I must go from you.  
To love you, I must give you up.&raquo;</p>  
<p>So Odo returns alone to Pianura and in course of time marries 
his cousin's widow, of the House of Hapsburg, with whom he might 
eventually have been fairly happy. But three years later Fulvia 
changes her mind, comes back to him, and accepts the very 
conditions which she previously found such excellent reasons for 
refusing. No doubt, had Mrs. Wharton chosen, she might have given 
us a luminous picture of the mental transition through which her 
heroine passed during these three years of self-inflicted exile.  
But she has not chosen to do so, and the result is an impression of 
inconsistency, a feeling that the Fulvia who went away and the 
Fulvia who returned are not one and the same person. Apparently, 
the only real necessity for her return was to pave the way for an 
effective and tragic ending. Fulvia spurs Odo on to give the 
people the liberal constitution for which they are not yet ready, 
and in the midst of the resulting riots receives in her heart the 
shot intended for her lover. 
</p><p>This, in hasty outline, is the plot of <hi rend="italic">The Valley of 
Decision</hi>, and, frankly speaking, it is the least essential and 
least interesting aspect of the book. What really do count are her 
vivid pictures of life, the human interest of brief but crucial 
moments, her wonderful intuition in analysing complex emotions&mdash;in 
short, the same qualities which to a greater degree stamped the 
appearance of her earliest volume as a literary event. In taking 
up these volumes for a second time, one is apt to turn back to one 
of just a few brief scenes luminous with comprehensions&mdash;such a 
passage as this, for instance, describing an incident in Odo's 
youth, when, as a boy of twelve, on his way to Turin, his lot fell 
in for a single night with a company of strolling players:</p> 

<p>The pretty girl who had pillowed Odo's slumbers now knelt by 
his bed and laughingly drew on his stockings. She was a slim, 
brown morsel, not much above his age, with a glance that flitted 
like a bird, and round shoulders slipping out of her kerchief. A 
wave of shyness bathed Odo to the forehead as their eyes met; he 
hung his head stupidly and turned away when she fetched the comb to 
dress his hair. 
</p><p>His toilet completed, she called out to the abate to go below 
and see that the cavaliere's chocolate was ready; and as the door 
closed she turned and kissed Odo on the lips. 
</p><p>&laquo;Oh, how red you are!&raquo; she cried, laughingly. &laquo;Is that the 
first kiss you've ever had? Then you'll remember me when you're 
Duke of Pianura&mdash;Mirandolina of Chioggia, the first girl you ever 
kissed!&raquo; She was pulling his collar straight while she talked, so 
that he could not get away from her. &laquo;You will remember me, won't 
you?&raquo; she persisted. &laquo;I shall be a great actress by that time, and 
you'll appoint me<foreign lang="it"><hi rend="italic">prima amorosa</hi></foreign>to the ducal theatre of 
Pianura, and throw me a diamond bracelet from your Highness's box 
and make all the court ladies ready to poison me for rage!&raquo; She 
released his collar and drooped away from him. &laquo;Ah, no; I shall be 
a poor strolling player and you a great prince,&raquo; she sighed, &laquo;and 
you'll never, never think of me again; but I shall always remember 
that I was the first girl you ever kissed!&raquo; 
</p><p>She hung back in a dazzle of tears, looking so bright and 
tender that Odo's bashfulness melted like a spring frost. 
</p><p>&laquo;I shall never be duke,&raquo; he cried, &laquo;and I shall never forget 
you!&raquo; And with that he turned and kissed her boldly and then 
bolted down the stairs like a hare. And all that day he scorched 
and froze with the thought that perhaps she had been laughing at 
him.</p> 
<signed>             <hi rend="italic">Frederic Taber Cooper.</hi></signed> 
 
</div1> 
</body> 
<back id="d4">
<div1 type="notes" id="d5">

<note id="WhaR1Von1"><seg type="note-symbol">*The</seg> <p>Valley of Decision. By Edith Wharton. New York: Charles 
Scribner's Sons. $1.50.</p></note>

</div1>
</back> 
</text> 
</TEI.2> 
 
