<?xml version="1.0"?>

<?dlps id="WhaReco"?>
<?dlps page-images="none" figure-images="no"?>
<?dlps transcription="other"?>

<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/tei-p4/tei2.dtd" [
<!ENTITY % POSTKB "INCLUDE">
<!ENTITY % TEI.extensions.ent SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.ent">
<!ENTITY % TEI.extensions.dtd SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.dtd">
<!ENTITY % ISOnum SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/charent/iso-num.ent"> %ISOnum;
<!ENTITY % ISOpub SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/charent/iso-pub.ent"> %ISOpub;
]> 
 
<TEI.2 id="WhaReco"> 
<teiHeader type="migrated" creator="Etext">
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title type="main">The Recovery</title>
<title type="sort">recovery</title>
<author>Wharton, Edith, 1862-1937</author>
<respStmt>
<resp>Creation of machine-readable version:</resp> 
<name>Judy Boss</name> 
<resp>Conversion to TEI.2-conformant markup:</resp>  
<name>University of Virginia Library Electronic Text Center</name>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt> 
<extent>ca. <num type="kilobytes">47</num> kilobytes</extent> 
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>University of Virginia Library</publisher>
<pubPlace>Charlottesville, Virginia</pubPlace> 
<idno type="ETC">WhaReco</idno> 
<date value="1995">1995</date>
<availability status="public">
<p n="copyright">Copyright &copy; 1995 by the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia</p>
<p n="access">Publicly accessible</p>
</availability>
<idno type="uva-pid">uva-lib:476524</idno>
</publicationStmt>
<seriesStmt>
<title>University of Virginia Library, Text collection</title>
<idno type="uva-set">UVA-LIB-Text</idno>
</seriesStmt> 
<sourceDesc>
<biblFull>
<titleStmt>
<title type="main">The Recovery</title>
<title type="sort">recovery</title>
<author>Edith Wharton</author>
</titleStmt> 
<editionStmt>
<p>1st Edition</p>
</editionStmt> 
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>Harper's Monthly</publisher> 
<pubPlace>New York</pubPlace> 
<date value="1901">1901</date>
</publicationStmt> 
</biblFull>
</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc> 
<encodingDesc>
<projectDesc>
<p>Prepared for the University of Virginia Library Electronic 
Text Center</p>
</projectDesc> 
<editorialDecl>
<p>All quotation marks retained as data</p> 
<p>Verification made against printed text.</p> 
<p>All unambiguous end-of-line hyphens have been removed, and the 
trailing part of a word has been joined to the preceding line.</p> 
<p id="ETC">Keywords in the header are a local Electronic Text 
Center scheme to aid in establishing analytical groupings</p>
</editorialDecl> 
<refsDecl>
<p>ID elements are given for each page element and are composed of the text's  
unique cryptogram and the given page number, as in AusEmma1 for page one of  
Jane Austen's Emma.</p>
</refsDecl> 
</encodingDesc> 
<profileDesc>
<creation>
<date value="1901">1901</date>
</creation> 
<langUsage>
<language id="eng" usage="main">English</language>
</langUsage> 
<textClass>
<keywords>
<term>fiction</term>
<term>prose</term> 
<term>Women Writers</term>
</keywords>
</textClass>
</profileDesc> 
<revisionDesc>
<change>
<date value="1995-04">April 1995</date> 
<respStmt>
<resp>corrector</resp> 
<name>Kelly Moulton</name>
</respStmt>
<item>TEI tagging</item>
</change> 
<change>
<date value="2005-07">July 2005</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>Corrector</resp>
<name>Margaret Konkol</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Converted SGML to XML and fixed tagging.</item>
</change>
<change>
<date value="2007-09">September 2007</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>Migration</resp>
<name>Ethan Gruber, University of Virginia Library</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Converted XML markup from TEI Lite to uva-dl-tei (TEI P4 with local customizations).</item>
</change>
<change>
<date value="2008-01">January 2008</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>Migration</resp>
<name>Greg Murray, University of Virginia Library</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Programmatically updated TEI header markup (but not header content) for minimal compliance with current QA requirements.</item>
</change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader> 
<text id="d1">  
<body id="d2"> 
<div1 type="section" n="1" id="d3"> 
<head>Wharton, Edith.  "The Recovery."<lb/>   
<hi rend="italic"> Harper's Monthly</hi> 102 (Feb. 1901): 468-477.<lb/> 
                                I</head> 
<pb n="468"/>  
 
<p>TO the visiting stranger Hillbridge's first question was, 
"Have you 
seen Keniston's things?"</p><p> 
     Keniston took precedence of the Colonial State House, the 
Gilbert Stuart Washington, and the Ethnological Museum; nay, he 
ran 
neck and neck with the President of the University, a 
pre-historic 
relic who had known Emerson, and who was still sent about the 
country in cotton-wool to open educational institutions with a 
toothless oration on Brook Farm.</p><p> 
     Keniston was sent about the country too; he opened art 
exhibitions, laid the foundations of academies, and acted, in a 
general sense, as the spokesman and apologist of art.  Hillbridge 
was proud of him in his peripatetic character, but his fellow-townsmen let it be understood that to "know" Keniston one must 
come 
to Hillbridge.  Never was work more dependent for its effect on 
"atmosphere," on <hi rend="italic"> milieu</hi>.  Hillbridge was Keniston's <hi rend="italic"> 
milieu</hi>, 
and there was one lady, a devotee of his art, who went so far as 
to 
assert that once, at an exhibition in New York, she had passed a 
Keniston without recognizing it.  "It simply didn't want to be 
seen 
in such surroundings; it was hiding itself under an incognito," 
she 
declared.</p><p> 
     It was a source of special pride to Hillbridge that it 
contained all the artist's best works.  Strangers were told that 
Hillbridge had discovered him.  The discovery had come about in 
the 
simplest manner.  Professor Driffert, who had a reputation for 
"collecting," had one day hung a sketch on his drawing-room wall, 
and thereafter Mrs. Driffert's visitors (always a little flurried 
by the sense that it was the kind of house in which one might be 
suddenly called upon to distinguish between a dry-point and an 
etching, or between Raphael Mengs and Raphael Sanzio) were not 
infrequently subjected to the Professor's off-hand inquiry, "By-the-way, have you seen my Keniston?"  The visitors, perceptibly 
awed, would retreat to a critical distance and murmur the usual 
guarded generalities, while they tried to keep the name in mind 
long enough to look it up in the Encyclopaedia.  The name was not 
in the Encyclopaedia; but, as a compensating fact, it became 
known 
that the man himself was in Hillbridge.  Hillbridge, then, owned 
an 
artist whose celebrity it was the proper thing to take for 
granted!  
Some one else, emboldened by the thought, bought a Keniston; and 
the next year, on the occasion of the President's golden jubilee, 
the Faculty, by unanimous consent, presented him with a Keniston. 
 
Two years later there was a Keniston exhibition, to which the 
art-critics came from New York and Boston; and not long afterward a 
well-known Chicago collector vainly attempted to buy Professor 
Driffert's sketch, which the art journals cited as a rare example 
of the painter's first or silvery manner.  Thus there gradually 
grew up a small circle of connoisseurs known in artistic circles 
as 
men who collected Kenistons.</p><p> 
     Professor Wildmarsh, of the chair of Fine Arts and 
Archaeology, was the first critic to publish a detailed analysis 
of 
the master's methods and purpose.  The article was illustrated by 
engravings which (though they had cost the magazine a fortune) 
were 
declared by Professor Wildmarsh to give but an imperfect 
suggestion 
of the esoteric significance of the originals.  The Professor, 
with 
a tact that contrived to make each reader feel himself included 
among the exceptions, went on to say that Keniston's work would 
never appeal to any but exceptional natures; and he closed with 
the 
usual assertion that to apprehend the full meaning of the 
master's 
"message" it was necessary to see him in the surroundings of his 
own home at Hillbridge.</p><p> 
     Professor Wildmarsh's article was read <pb n="469"/>  
one spring 
afternoon by a young lady just speeding eastward on her first 
visit 
to Hillbridge, and already flushed with anticipation of the 
intellectual opportunities awaiting her.  In East Onondaigua, 
where 
she lived, Hillbridge was looked on as an Oxford.  Magazine 
writers, with the easy American use of the superlative, 
designated 
it as "the venerable Alma Mater," the "antique seat of learning," 
and Claudia Day had been brought up to regard it as the fountain-head of knowledge, and of that mental distinction which is so 
much 
rarer than knowledge.  An innate passion for all that was thus 
distinguished and exceptional made her revere Hillbridge as the 
native soil of those intellectual amenities that were of such 
difficult growth in the thin air of East Onondaigua.  At the 
first 
suggestion of a visit to Hillbridge&mdash;whither she went at the 
invitation of a girl-friend who (incredible apotheosis!) had 
married one of the University professors&mdash;Claudia's spirit 
dilated 
with the sense of new possibilities.  The vision of herself 
walking 
under the "historic elms" toward the Memorial Library, standing 
rapt before the Stuart Washington, or drinking in, from some 
obscure corner of an academic drawing-room, the President's 
reminiscences of the Concord group&mdash;this vividness of self-projection into the emotions awaiting her made her glad of any 
delay that prolonged so exquisite a moment.</p><p> 
     It was in this mood that she opened the article on Keniston. 
 
She knew about him, of course; she was wonderfully "well up," 
even 
for East Onondaigua.  She had read of him in the magazines; she 
had 
met, on a visit to New York, a man who collected Kenistons, and a 
photogravure of a Keniston, in an "artistic" frame, hung above 
her 
writing-table at home.  But Professor Wildmarsh's article made 
her 
feel how little she really knew of the master; and she trembled 
to 
think of the state of relative ignorance in which, but for the 
timely purchase of the magazine, she might have entered 
Hillbridge.  
She had, for instance, been densely unaware that Keniston had 
already had three "manners," and was showing symptoms of a 
fourth.  
She was equally ignorant of the fact that he had founded a school 
and "created a formula"; and she learned with a thrill that no 
one 
could hope to understand him who had not seen him in his studio 
at 
Hillbridge, surrounded by his own works.  "The man and the art 
interpret each other," their exponent declared; and Claudia Day, 
bending a brilliant eye on the future, wondered if she would ever 
be admitted to the privilege of that double initiation.</p><p> 
     Keniston to his other claims to distinction added that of 
being hard to know.  His friends always hastened to announce the 
fact to strangers&mdash;adding after a pause of suspense that they 
"would see what they could do."  Visitors in whose favor he was 
induced to make an exception were further warned that he never 
spoke unless he was interested&mdash;so that they mustn't mind if he 
remained silent.  It was under these reassuring conditions that, 
some ten days after her arrival at Hillbridge, Miss Day was 
introduced to the master's studio.  She found him a tall 
listless-looking man, who appeared middle-aged to her youth, and who stood 
before his own pictures with a vaguely interrogative gaze, 
leaving 
the task of their interpretation to the lady who had courageously 
contrived the visit.  The studio, to Claudia's surprise, was bare 
and shabby.  It formed a rambling addition to the small cheerless 
house in which the artist lived with his mother and a widowed 
sister.  For Claudia it added the last touch to his distinction 
to 
learn that he was poor, and that what he earned was devoted to 
the 
maintenance of the two limp women who formed a sort of neutral-tinted background to his impressive outline.  His pictures of 
course fetched high prices; but he worked slowly&mdash;"painfully," as 
his devotees preferred to phrase it&mdash;with frequent intervals of 
ill 
health and inactivity, and the circle of Keniston connoisseurs 
was 
still as small as it was distinguished.  The girl's fancy 
instantly 
hailed in him that favorite figure of imaginative youth, the 
artist 
who would rather starve than paint a pot-boiler.  It is known to 
comparatively few that the production of successful pot-boilers 
is 
an art in itself, and that such heroic abstentions as Keniston's 
are not always purely voluntary.</p><p> 
     On the occasion of her first visit the <pb n="470"/>  
artist said so 
little that Claudia was able to indulge to the full the harrowing 
sense of her inadequacy.  No wonder she had not been one of the 
few 
that he cared to talk to; every word she uttered must so 
obviously 
have diminished the inducement!  She had been cheap, trivial, 
conventional; at once gushing and inexpressive, eager and 
constrained.  She could feel him counting the minutes till the 
visit was over, and as the door finally closed on the scene of 
her 
discomfiture she almost shared the hope with which she 
confidently 
credited him&mdash;that they might never meet again. 
 
</p> 
</div1> 
<div1 type="section" n="2" id="d4"> 
<head> 
                                II</head> 
<p> 
     Mrs. Davant glanced reverentially about the studio.  "I have 
always said," she murmured, "that they ought to be seen in 
Europe."</p><p> 
     Mrs. Davant was young, credulous, and emotionally 
extravagant; 
she reminded Claudia of her earlier self&mdash;the self that, ten 
years 
before, had first set an awe-struck foot on that very 
threshold.</p><p> 
     "Not for <hi rend="italic"> his</hi> sake," Mrs. Davant continued, "but for 
Europe's."</p><p> 
     Claudia smiled.  She was glad that her husband's pictures 
were 
to be exhibited in Paris.  She concurred in Mrs. Davant's view of 
the importance of the event; but she thought her visitor's way of 
putting the case a little overcharged.  Ten years spent in an 
atmosphere of Keniston-worship had insensibly developed in 
Claudia 
a preference for moderation of speech.  She believed in her 
husband, of course; to believe in him, with an increasing 
abandonment and tenacity, had become one of the necessary laws of 
being; but she did not believe in his admirers.  Their faith in 
him 
was perhaps as genuine as her own; but it seemed to her less able 
to give an account of itself.  Some few of his appreciators 
doubtless measured him by their own standards; but it was 
difficult 
not to feel that in the Hillbridge circle, where rapture ran the 
highest, he was accepted on what was at best but an indirect 
valuation; and now and then she had a frightened doubt as to the 
independence of her own convictions.  That innate sense of 
relativity which even East Onondaigua had not been able to check 
in 
Claudia Day had been fostered in Mrs. Keniston by the artistic 
absolutism of Hillbridge, and she often wondered that her husband 
remained so uncritical of the quality of admiration accorded him. 
 
Her husband's uncritical attitude toward himself and his admirers 
had in fact been one of the surprises of her marriage.  That an 
artist should believe in his potential powers seemed to her at 
once 
the incentive and the pledge of excellence: she knew there was no 
future for a hesitating talent.  What perplexed her was 
Keniston's 
satisfaction in his achievement.  She had always imagined that 
the 
true artist must regard himself as the imperfect vehicle of the 
cosmic emotion&mdash;that beneath every difficulty overcome a new one 
lurked, the vision widening as the scope enlarged.  To be 
initiated 
into these creative struggles, to shed on the toiler's path the 
consolatory ray of faith and encouragement, had seemed the chief 
privilege of her marriage.  But there is something supererogatory 
in believing in a man obviously disposed to perform that service 
for himself; and Claudia's ardor gradually spent itself against 
the 
dense surface of her husband's complacency.  She could smile now 
at 
her ignorant vision of an intellectual communion which should 
admit 
her to the inmost precincts of his inspiration.  She had learned 
that the creative processes are seldom self-explanatory, and 
Keniston's inarticulateness no longer discouraged her; but she 
could not reconcile her sense of the continuity of all high 
effort 
to his unperturbed air of finishing each picture as though he had 
despatched a masterpiece to posterity.  In the first recoil from 
her disillusionment she even allowed herself to perceive that if 
he 
worked slowly it was not because he mistrusted his powers of 
expression, but because he had so little to express.</p><p> 
     "It's for Europe," Mrs. Davant vaguely repeated; and Claudia 
noticed that she was blushingly intent on tracing with the tip of 
her elaborate sunshade the pattern of the shabby carpet.</p><p> 
     "It will be a revelation to them," she went on, 
provisionally, 
as though Claudia had missed her cue and left an awkward interval 
to fill.</p><p> 
     Claudia had in fact a sudden sense of deficient intuition.  
She felt that her visitor had something to communicate which 
required, on her own part, an in-<pb n="471"/> telligent 
co-operation; but 
what it was her insight failed to suggest.  She was, in truth, a 
little tired of Mrs. Davant, who was Keniston's latest 
worshipper, 
who ordered pictures recklessly, who paid for them regally in 
advance, and whose gallery was, figuratively speaking, crowded 
with 
the artist's unpainted masterpieces.  Claudia's impatience was 
perhaps complicated by the uneasy sense that Mrs. Davant was too 
young, too rich, too inexperienced; that somehow she ought to be 
warned.  Warned of what?  That some of the pictures might never 
be 
painted?  Scarcely that, since Keniston, who was scrupulous in 
business transactions, might be trusted not to take any material 
advantage of such evidence of faith.  Claudia's impulse remained 
undefined.  She merely felt that she would have liked to help 
Mrs. 
Davant, and that she did not know how.</p><p> 
     "You'll be there to see them?" she asked, as her visitor 
lingered.</p><p> 
     "In Paris?"  Mrs. Davant's blush deepened.  "We must all be 
there together."</p><p> 
     Claudia smiled.  "My husband and I mean to go abroad some 
day&mdash;but I don't see any chance of it at present."</p><p> 
     "But he <hi rend="italic"> ought</hi> to go&mdash;you ought both to go this 
summer!" 
Mrs. Davant persisted.  "I know Professor Wildmarsh and Professor 
Driffert and all the other critics think that Mr. Keniston's 
never 
having been to Europe has given his work much of its wonderful 
individuality, its peculiar flavor and meaning&mdash;but now that his 
talent is formed, that he has full command of his means of 
expression" (Claudia recognized one of Professor Driffert's 
favorite formulas), "they all think he ought to see the work of 
the 
<hi rend="italic"> other</hi> great masters&mdash;that he ought to visit the home of 
his 
ancestors, as Professor Wildmarsh says!"  She stretched an 
impulsive hand to Claudia.  "You ought to let him go, Mrs. 
Keniston!"</p><p> 
     Claudia accepted the admonition with the philosophy of the 
wife who is used to being advised on the management of her 
husband.  
"I sha'n't interfere with him," she declared; and Mrs. Davant 
instantly caught her up with a sudden cry of, "Oh, it's too 
lovely 
of you to say that!"  With this exclamation she left Claudia to a 
silent renewal of wonder.</p><p> 
     A moment later Keniston entered; to a mind curious in 
combinations it might have occurred that he had met Mrs. Davant 
on 
the door-step.  In one sense he might, for all his wife cared, 
have 
met fifty Mrs. Davants on the door-step: it was long since 
Claudia 
had enjoyed the solace of resenting such coincidences.  Her only 
thought now was that her husband's first words might not 
improbably 
explain Mrs. Davant's last; and she waited for him to 
speak.</p><p> 
     He paused with his hands in his pockets before an unfinished 
picture on the easel; then, as his habit was, he began to stroll 
touristlike from canvas to canvas, standing before each in a 
musing 
ecstasy of contemplation that no readjustment of view ever seemed 
to disturb.  Her eye instinctively joined his in its inspection; 
it 
was the one point where their natures merged.  Thank God, there 
was 
no doubt about the pictures!  She was what she had always dreamed 
of being&mdash;the wife of a great artist.  Keniston dropped into an 
arm-chair and filled his pipe.  "How should you like to go to 
Europe?" he asked.</p><p> 
     His wife looked up quickly.  "When?"</p><p> 
     "Now&mdash;this spring, I mean."  He paused to light the pipe.  
"I 
should like to be over there while these things are being 
exhibited."</p><p> 
     Claudia was silent.</p><p> 
     "Well?" he repeated after a moment.</p><p> 
     "How can we afford it?" she asked.</p><p> 
     Keniston had always scrupulously fulfilled his duty to the 
mother and sister whom his marriage had dislodged; and Claudia, 
who 
had the atoning temperament which seeks to pay for every 
happiness 
by making it a source of fresh obligations, had from the outset 
accepted his ties with an exaggerated devotion.  Any disregard of 
such a claim would have vulgarized her most delicate pleasures; 
and 
her husband's sensitiveness to it in great measure extenuated the 
artistic obtuseness that often seemed to her like a failure of 
the 
moral sense.  His loyalty to the dull women who depended on him 
was, after all, compounded of finer tissues than any mere 
sensibility to ideal demands.</p><p> 
     "Oh, I don't see why we shouldn't," he rejoined.  "I think 
we 
might manage it." <pb n="472"/> </p><p> 
     "At Mrs. Davant's expense?" leaped from Claudia.  She could 
not tell why she had said it; some inner barrier seemed to have 
given way under a confused pressure of emotions.</p><p> 
     He looked up at her with frank surprise.  "Well, she <hi rend="italic"> 
has</hi> 
been very jolly about it&mdash;why not?  She has a tremendous feeling 
for art&mdash;the keenest I ever knew in a woman."  Claudia 
imperceptibly smiled.  "She wants me to let her pay in advance 
for 
the four panels she has ordered for the Memorial Library.  That 
would give us plenty of money for the trip, and my having the 
panels to do is another reason for my wanting to go abroad just 
now."</p><p> 
     "Another reason?"</p><p> 
     "Yes; I've never worked on such a big scale.  I want to see 
how those old chaps did the trick; I want to measure myself with 
the big fellows over there.  An artist ought to, once in his 
life."</p><p> 
     She gave him a wondering look.  The words implied a dawning 
sense of possible limitation; but his easy tone seemed to retract 
what they conceded.  What he really wanted was fresh food for his 
self-satisfaction: he was like an army that moves on after 
exhausting the resources of the country.</p><p> 
     Womanlike, she abandoned the general survey of the case for 
the consideration of a minor point.</p><p> 
     "Are you sure you can do that kind of thing?" she 
asked.</p><p> 
     "What kind of thing?"</p><p> 
     "The panels."</p><p> 
     He glanced at her indulgently: his self-confidence was too 
impenetrable to feel the pin-prick of such a doubt.</p><p> 
     "Immensely sure," he said, smiling.</p><p> 
     "And you don't mind taking so much money from her in 
advance?"</p><p> 
     He stared.  "Why should I?  She'll get it back&mdash;with 
interest!"  He laughed and drew at his pipe.  "It will be an 
uncommonly interesting experience.  I shouldn't wonder if it 
freshened me up a bit."</p><p> 
     She looked at him again.  This second hint of potential 
self-distrust struck her as the sign of a quickened sensibility.  What 
if, after all, he was beginning to be dissatisfied with his work? 
 
The thought filled her with a renovating sense of his 
sufficiency. 
 
</p> 
</div1> 
<div1 type="section" n="3" id="d5"> 
<head> 
                                III</head> 
<p> 
     They stopped in London to see the National Gallery.  It was 
thus that, in their inexperience, they had narrowly put it; but 
in 
reality every stone of the streets, every trick of the 
atmosphere, 
had its message of surprise for their virgin sensibilities.  The 
pictures were simply the summing up, the final interpretation, of 
the cumulative pressure of an unimagined world; and it seemed to 
Claudia that long before they reached the doors of the gallery 
she 
had some intuitive revelation of what awaited them within.</p><p> 
     They moved about from room to room without exchanging a 
word.  
The vast noiseless space seemed full of sound, like the roar of a 
distant multitude heard only by the inner ear.  Had their speech 
been articulate their language would have been incomprehensible; 
and even that far-off murmur of meaning pressed intolerably on 
Claudia's throbbing nerves.  Keniston took the onset without 
outward sign of disturbance.  Now and then he paused before a 
canvas, or prolonged from one of the benches his silent communion 
with some miracle of line or color; but he neither looked at his 
wife nor spoke to her.  He seemed to have forgotten her 
presence.</p><p> 
     Claudia was conscious of keeping a furtive watch on him; but 
the sum total of her impressions was negative.  She remembered 
thinking when she first met him that his face was rather 
expressionless; and he had the habit of self-engrossed 
silences.</p><p> 
     All that evening, at the hotel, they talked about London, 
and 
he surprised her by an acuteness of observation that she had 
sometimes inwardly accused him of lacking.  He seemed to have 
seen 
everything, to have examined, felt, compared, with nerves as 
finely 
adjusted as her own; but he said nothing of the pictures.  The 
next 
day they returned to the National Gallery, and he began to 
examine 
the paintings in detail, pointing out differences of technique, 
analyzing and criticising, but still without summing up his 
conclusions.  He seemed to have a sort of provincial dread of 
showing himself too much impressed.  Claudia's own sensations 
were 
too complex, too overwhelming, to be readily classified.  Lacking 
the <pb n="473"/>  craftsman's instinct to steady her, she 
felt herself 
carried off her feet by the rush of incoherent impressions.  One 
point she consciously avoided, and that was the comparison of her 
husband's work with what they were daily seeing.  Art, she 
inwardly 
argued, was too various, too complex, dependent on too many 
inter-relations of feeling and environment, to allow of its being 
judged 
by any provisional standard.  Even the subtleties of technique 
must 
be modified by the artist's changing purpose, as this in turn is 
acted on by influences of which he is himself unconscious.  How, 
then, was an unprepared imagination to distinguish between such 
varied reflections of the elusive vision?  She took refuge in a 
passionate exaggeration of her own ignorance and insufficiency. 
</p><p> 
     After a week in London they went to Paris.  The exhibition 
of 
Keniston's pictures had been opened a few days earlier; and as 
they 
drove through the streets on the way to the station an 
"impressionist" poster here and there invited them to the display 
of the American artist's work.  Mrs. Davant, who had been in 
Paris 
for the opening, had already written rapturously of the 
impression 
produced, enclosing commendatory notices from one or two papers.  
She reported that there had been a great crowd on the first day, 
and that the critics had been "immensely struck."</p><p> 
     The Kenistons arrived in the evening, and the next morning 
Claudia, as a matter of course, asked her husband at what time he 
meant to go and see the pictures.</p><p> 
     He looked up absently from his guide-book.</p><p> 
     "What pictures?"</p><p> 
     "Why&mdash;yours," she said, surprised.</p><p> 
     "Oh, they'll keep," he answered; adding, with a slightly 
embarrassed laugh, "We'll give the other chaps a show first."  
Presently he laid down his book and proposed that they should go 
to 
the Louvre.</p><p> 
     They spent the morning there, lunched at a restaurant near 
by, 
and returned to the gallery in the afternoon.  Keniston had 
passed 
from inarticulateness to an eager volubility.  It was clear that 
he 
was beginning to co-ordinate his impressions, to find his way 
about 
in a corner of the great imaginative universe.  He seemed 
extraordinarily ready to impart his discoveries; and Claudia was 
conscious that her ignorance served him as a convenient buffer 
against the terrific impact of new sensations.</p><p> 
     On the way home she asked when he meant to see Mrs. 
Davant.</p><p> 
     His answer surprised her.  "Does she know we're 
here?"</p><p> 
     "Not unless you've sent her word," said Claudia, with a 
touch 
of harmless irony.</p><p> 
     "That's all right, then," he returned simply.  "I want to 
wait 
and look about a day or two longer.  She'd want us to go sight-seeing with her; and I'd rather get my impressions alone."</p><p> 
     The next two days were hampered by the necessity of eluding 
Mrs. Davant.  Claudia, under different circumstances, would have 
scrupled to share in this somewhat shabby conspiracy; but she 
found 
herself in a state of suspended judgment, wherein her husband's 
treatment of Mrs. Davant became for the moment merely a clue to 
larger meanings.</p><p> 
     They had been four days in Paris when Claudia, returning one 
afternoon from a parenthetical excursion to the Rue de la Paix, 
was 
confronted on her threshold by the reproachful figure of their 
benefactress.  It was not to her, however, that Mrs. Davant's 
reproaches were addressed.  Keniston, it appeared, had borne the 
brunt of them; for he stood leaning against the mantel-piece of 
their modest <hi rend="italic"> salon</hi> in that attitude of convicted 
negligence 
when, if ever, a man is glad to take refuge behind his 
wife.</p><p> 
     Claudia had, however, no immediate intention of affording 
him 
such shelter.  She wanted to observe and wait.</p><p> 
     "He's too impossible!" cried Mrs. Davant, sweeping her at 
once 
into the central current of her grievance.</p><p> 
     Claudia looked from one to the other.</p><p> 
     "For not going to see you?"</p><p> 
     "For not going to see his pictures!" cried the other, 
nobly.</p><p> 
     Claudia colored, and Keniston shifted his position 
uneasily.</p><p> 
     "I can't make her understand," he said, turning to his 
wife.</p><p> 
     "I don't care about myself!" Mrs. Davant interjected.</p><p> 
     <hi rend="italic">" I</hi> do, then; it's the only thing I do care about," 
he 
hurriedly protested.  "I <pb n="474"/>  meant to go at 
once&mdash;to write&mdash; 
Claudia wanted to go, but I wouldn't let her."  He looked 
helplessly about the pleasant red-curtained room, which was 
rapidly 
burning itself into Claudia's consciousness as a visible 
extension 
of Mrs. Davant's claims.</p><p> 
     "I can't explain," he broke off.</p><p> 
     Mrs. Davant in turn addressed herself to Claudia.</p><p> 
     "People think it's so odd," she complained.  "So many of the 
artists here are anxious to meet him; they've all been so 
charming 
about the pictures; and several of our American friends have come 
over from London expressly for the exhibition.  I told every one 
that he would be here for the opening&mdash;there was a private view, 
you know&mdash;and they were so disappointed&mdash;they wanted to give him 
an 
ovation; and I didn't know what to say.  What <hi rend="italic"> am</hi> I to 
say?" she 
abruptly ended.</p><p> 
     "There's nothing to say," said Keniston.</p><p> 
     "But the exhibition closes the day after to-morrow."</p><p> 
     "Well, <hi rend="italic"> I</hi> sha'n't close&mdash;I shall be here," he 
declared with 
an effort at playfulness.  "If they want to see me&mdash;all these 
people you're kind enough to mention&mdash;won't there be other 
chances?"</p><p> 
     "But I wanted them to see you <hi rend="italic"> among</hi> your 
pictures&mdash;to hear 
you talk about them, explain them in that wonderful way.  I 
wanted 
you to interpret each other, as Professor Wildmarsh says!"</p><p> 
     "Oh, hang Professor Wildmarsh!" said Keniston, softening the 
commination with a smile.  "If my pictures are good for anything 
they oughtn't to need explaining."</p><p> 
     Mrs. Davant stared.  "But I thought that was what made them 
so 
interesting!" she exclaimed.</p><p> 
     Keniston looked down.  "Perhaps it was," he murmured.</p><p> 
     There was an awkward silence, which Claudia broke by saying, 
with a glance at her husband: "But if the exhibition is to remain 
open to-morrow, could we not meet you there?  And perhaps you 
could 
send word to some of our friends."</p><p> 
     Mrs. Davant brightened like a child whose broken toy is 
glued 
together.  "Oh, <hi rend="italic"> do</hi> make him!" she implored.  "I'll ask 
them to 
come in the afternoon&mdash;we'll make it into a little tea&mdash;a <hi rend="italic"> 
five 
o'clock</hi>.  I'll send word at once to everybody!"  She gathered 
up 
her beruffled boa and sunshade, settling her plumage like a 
reassured bird.  "It will be too lovely!" she ended in a self-consoling murmur.</p><p> 
     But in the doorway a new doubt assailed her.  "You won't 
fail 
me?" she said, turning plaintively to Keniston.  "You'll make him 
come, Mrs. Keniston?"</p><p> 
     "I'll bring him!" Claudia promised. 
 
</p> 
</div1> 
<div1 type="section" n="4" id="d6"> 
<head> 
                                IV</head> 
<p> 
     When, the next morning, she appeared equipped for their 
customary ramble, her husband surprised her by announcing that he 
meant to stay at home.</p><p> 
     "The fact is I'm rather surfeited," he said, smiling.  "I 
suppose my appetite isn't equal to such a plethora.  I think I'll 
write some letters and join you somewhere later."</p><p> 
     She detected the wish to be alone, and responded to it with 
her usual readiness.</p><p> 
     "I shall sink to my proper level and buy a bonnet, then," 
she 
said.  "I haven't had time to take the edge off that 
appetite."</p><p> 
     They agreed to meet at the Hotel Cluny at mid-day, and she 
set 
out alone with a vague sense of relief.  Neither she nor Keniston 
had made any direct reference to Mrs. Davant's visit; but its 
effect was implicit in their eagerness to avoid each 
other.</p><p> 
     Claudia accomplished some shopping in the spirit of 
perfunctoriness that robs even new bonnets of their bloom; and 
this 
business despatched, she turned aimlessly into the wide inviting 
brightness of the streets.  Never had she felt more isolated amid 
that ordered beauty which gives a social quality to the very 
stones 
and mortar of Paris.  All about her were evidences of an artistic 
sensibility pervading every form of life like the nervous 
structure 
of the huge frame&mdash;a sensibility so delicate, alert, and 
universal 
that it seemed to leave no room for obtuseness or error.  In such 
a medium the faculty of plastic expression must develop as 
unconsciously as any organ in its normal surroundings; to be 
"artistic" must cease to be an attitude and become a natural 
function.  To Claudia the significance of the whole vast 
revelation 
was centred in the light it shed on one tiny <pb n="475"/>  
spot of 
consciousness&mdash;the value of her husband's work.  There are 
moments 
when to the groping soul the world's accumulated experiences are 
but stepping-stones across a private difficulty.</p><p> 
     She stood hesitating on a street corner.  It was barely 
eleven, and she had an hour to spare before going to the Hotel 
Cluny.  She seemed to be letting her inclination float as it 
would 
on the cross-currents of suggestion emanating from the brilliant 
complex scene before her; but suddenly, in obedience to an 
impulse 
that she became aware of only in acting on it, she called a cab 
and 
drove to the gallery where her husband's pictures were 
exhibited.</p><p> 
     A magnificent official in gold braid sold her a ticket and 
pointed the way up the empty crimson-carpeted stairs.  His 
duplicate, on the upper landing, offered her a catalogue with an 
air of recognizing the futility of the offer; and a moment later 
she found herself in the long noiseless impressive room full of 
velvet-covered ottomans and exotic plants.  It was clear that the 
public ardor on which Mrs. Davant had expatiated had spent itself 
earlier in the week; for Claudia had this luxurious apartment to 
herself.  Something about its air of rich privacy, its diffusion 
of 
that sympathetic quality in other countries so conspicuously 
absent 
from the public show-room, seemed to emphasize its present 
emptiness.  It was as though the flowers, the carpet, the 
lounges, 
surrounded their visitor's solitary advance with the mute 
assurance 
that they had done all they could toward making the thing "go 
off," 
and that if they had failed it was simply for lack of efficient 
co-operation.  She stood still and looked about her.  The pictures 
struck her instantly as odd gaps in the general harmony: it was 
self-evident that they had not co-operated.  They had not been 
pushing, aggressive, discordant: they had merely effaced 
themselves.  She swept a startled eye from one familiar painting 
to 
another.  The canvases were all there&mdash;and the frames&mdash;but the 
miracle, the mirage of life and meaning, had vanished like some 
atmospheric illusion.  What was it that had happened?  And had it 
happened to <hi rend="italic"> her</hi> or to the pictures?  She tried to rally 
her 
frightened thoughts; to push or coax them into a semblance of 
resistance; but argument was swept off its feet by the huge rush 
of 
a single conviction&mdash;the conviction that the pictures were bad.  
There was no standing up against that: she felt herself 
submerged.</p><p> 
     The stealthy fear that had been following her all these days 
had her by the throat now.  The great vision of beauty through 
which she had been moving as one enchanted turned to a 
phantasmagoria of evil mocking shapes.  She hated the past; she 
hated its splendor, its power, its wicked magical vitality.  She 
dropped into a seat and continued to stare at the wall before 
her.  
Gradually, as she stared, there stole out to her from the dimmed 
humbled canvases a reminder of what she had once seen in them, a 
spectral appeal to her faith to call them back to life.  What 
proof 
had she that her present estimate of them was less subjective 
than 
the other?  The confused impressions of the last few days were 
hardly to be pleaded as a valid theory of art.  How, after all, 
did 
she know that the pictures were bad?  On what suddenly acquired 
technical standard had she thus decided the case against them?  
It 
seemed as though it were a standard outside of herself, as though 
some unheeded inner sense were gradually making her aware of the 
presence, in that empty room, of a critical intelligence that was 
giving out a subtle effluence of disapproval.  The fancy was so 
vivid that, to shake it off, she rose and began to move about 
again.  In the middle of the room stood a monumental divan 
surmounted by a <hi rend="italic"> massif</hi> of palms and azaleas.  As 
Claudia's 
muffled wanderings carried her around the angle of this seat, she 
saw that its farther side was occupied by the figure of a man, 
who 
sat with his hands resting on his stick and his head bowed upon 
them.  She gave a little cry and her husband rose and faced 
her.</p><p> 
     Instantly the live point of consciousness was shifted, and 
she 
became aware that the quality of the pictures no longer mattered. 
 
It was what <hi rend="italic"> he</hi> thought of them that counted: her life 
hung on 
that.</p><p> 
     They looked at each other a moment in silence; such 
concussions are not apt to flash into immediate speech.  At 
length 
he said simply, "I didn't know you were coming here." 
<pb n="476"/> </p><p> 
     She colored as though he had charged her with something 
underhand.</p><p> 
     "I didn't mean to," she stammered; "but I was too early for 
our appointment&mdash;"</p><p> 
     Her blundering words cast a revealing glare on the 
situation.  
Neither of them looked at the pictures; but to Claudia those 
unobtruding presences seemed suddenly to press upon them and 
force 
them apart.</p><p> 
     Keniston glanced at his watch.  "It's twelve o'clock," he 
said.  "Shall we go on?" 
 
</p> 
</div1> 
<div1 type="section" n="5" id="d7"> 
<head> 
                                 V</head> 
<p> 
     At the door he called a cab and put her in it; then, drawing 
out his watch again, he said, abruptly: "I believe I'll let you 
go 
alone.  I'll join you at the hotel in time for luncheon."  She 
wondered for a moment if he meant to return to the gallery; but, 
looking back as she drove off, she saw him walk rapidly away in 
the 
opposite direction.</p><p> 
     The cabman had carried hr half-way to the Hotel Cluny before 
she realized where she was going, and cried out to him to turn 
home.  There was an acute irony in this mechanical prolongation 
of 
the quest of beauty.  She had had enough of it, too much of it; 
her 
one longing was to escape, to hide herself away from its all-suffusing implacable light.</p><p> 
     At the hotel, alone in her room, a few tears came to soften 
her scared vision; but her mood was too tense to be eased by 
weeping.  Her whole being was centred in the longing to know what 
her husband thought.  Their short exchange of words had, after 
all, 
told her nothing.  She had guessed a faint resentment of her 
unexpected appearance; but that might merely imply a dawning 
sense, 
on his part, of being furtively watched and criticised.  She had 
sometimes wondered if he was never conscious of her observation; 
there were moments when it seemed to radiate from her in visible 
waves.  Perhaps, after all, he was aware of it, on his guard 
against it, as a lurking knife behind the thick curtain of his 
complacency; and to-day he must have caught the gleam of the 
blade.</p><p> 
     Claudia had not reached the age when pity is the first chord 
to vibrate in contact with any revelation of failure.  Her one 
hope 
had been that Keniston should be clear-eyed enough to face the 
truth.  Whatever it turned out to be, she wanted him to measure 
himself with it.  But as his image rose before her she felt a 
sudden half-maternal longing to thrust herself between him and 
disaster.  Her eagerness to see him tested by circumstances 
seemed 
now like a cruel scientific curiosity.  She saw in a flash of 
sympathy that he would need her most if he fell beneath his 
fate.</p><p> 
     He did not, after all, return for luncheon; and when she 
came 
up stairs from her solitary meal their <hi rend="italic"> salon</hi> was still 
untenanted.  She permitted herself no sensational fears; for she 
could not, at the height of apprehension, figure Keniston as 
yielding to any tragic impulse; but the lengthening hours brought 
an uneasiness that was fuel to her pity.  Suddenly she heard the 
clock strike five.  It was the hour at which they had promised to 
meet Mrs. Davant at the gallery&mdash;the hour of the "ovation."  
Claudia rose and went to the window, straining for a glimpse of 
her 
husband in the crowded street.  Could it be that he had forgotten 
her, had gone to the gallery without her?  Or had something 
happened&mdash;that veiled "something" which, for the last hour, had 
grimly hovered on the outskirts of her mind?</p><p> 
     She heard a hand on the door and Keniston entered.  As she 
turned to meet him her whole being was swept forward on a great 
wave of pity: she was so sure, now, that he must know.</p><p> 
     But he confronted her with a glance of preoccupied 
brightness; 
her first impression was that she had never seen him so vividly, 
so 
expressively pleased.  If he needed her, it was not to bind up 
his 
wounds.</p><p> 
     He gave her a smile which was clearly the lingering 
reflection 
of some inner light.  "I didn't mean to be so late," he said, 
tossing aside his hat and the little red volume that served as a 
clue to his explorations.  "I turned in to the Louvre for a 
minute 
after I left you this morning, and the place fairly swallowed me 
up&mdash;I couldn't get away from it.  I've been there ever since."  
He 
threw himself into a chair and glanced about for his pipe.</p><p> 
     "It takes time," he continued musingly, "to get at them, to 
make out what <pb n="477"/>  they're saying&mdash;the big 
fellows, I mean.  
They're not a communicative lot.  At first I couldn't make much 
out 
of their lingo&mdash;it was too different from mine!  But gradually, 
by 
picking up a hint here and there, and piecing them together, I've 
begun to understand; and to-day, by Jove, I got one or two of the 
old chaps by the throat and fairly turned them inside out&mdash;made 
them deliver up their last drop."  He lifted a brilliant eye to 
her.  "Lord, it was tremendous!" he declared.</p><p> 
     He had found his pipe and was musingly filling it.  Claudia 
waited in silence.</p><p> 
     "At first," he began again, "I was afraid their language was 
too hard for me&mdash;that I should never quite know what they were 
driving at; they seemed to cold-shoulder me, to be bent on 
shutting 
me out.  But I was bound I wouldn't be beaten, and now, 
to-day"&mdash;he 
paused a moment to strike a match&mdash;"when I went to look at those 
things of mine it all came over me in a flash.  By Jove! it was 
as 
if I'd made them all into a big bonfire to light up my 
road!"</p><p> 
     His wife was trembling with a kind of sacred terror.  She 
had 
been afraid to pray for light for him, and here he was joyfully 
casting his whole past upon the pyre!</p><p> 
     "Is there nothing left?" she faltered.</p><p> 
     "Nothing left?  There's everything!" he exulted.  "Why, here 
I am, not much over forty, and I've found out already&mdash;already!"  
He stood up and began to move excitedly about the room.  "My God! 
 
Suppose I'd never known!  Suppose I'd gone on painting things 
like 
that forever!  Why, I feel like those chaps at revivalist 
meetings 
when they get up and say they're saved!  Won't somebody please 
start a hymn?"</p><p> 
     Claudia, with a tremulous joy, was letting herself go on the 
strong current of his emotion; but it had not yet carried her 
beyond her depth, and suddenly she felt hard ground 
underfoot.</p><p> 
     "Mrs. Davant&mdash;" she exclaimed.</p><p> 
     He stared, as though suddenly recalled from a long 
distance.</p><p> 
     "Mrs. Davant?"</p><p> 
     "We were to have met her&mdash;this afternoon&mdash;now&mdash;"</p><p> 
     "At the gallery?  Oh, that's all right.  I put a stop to 
that; 
I went to see her after I left you; I explained it all to 
her."</p><p> 
     "All?"</p><p> 
     "I told her I was going to begin all over again."</p><p> 
     Claudia's heart gave a forward bound and then sank back 
hopelessly.</p><p> 
     "But the panels&mdash;?"</p><p> 
     "That's all right too.  I told her about the panels," he 
reassured her.</p><p> 
     "You told her&mdash;?"</p><p> 
     "That I can't paint them now.  She doesn't understand, of 
course; but she's the best little woman and she trusts 
me."</p><p> 
     She could have wept for joy at his exquisite obtuseness.  
"But 
that isn't all," she wailed.  "It doesn't matter how much you've 
explained to her.  It doesn't do away with the fact that we're 
living on those panels!"</p><p> 
     "Living on them?"</p><p> 
     "On the money that she paid you to paint them.  Isn't that 
what brought us here?  And&mdash;if you mean to do as you say&mdash;to 
begin 
all over again&mdash;how in the world are we ever to pay her 
back?"</p><p> 
     Her husband turned on her an inspired eye.</p><p> 
     "There's only one way that I know of," he imperturbably 
declared; "and that's to stay out here till I learn how to paint 
them." 
</p> 
 
 
</div1> 
</body> 
</text> 
</TEI.2> 
 
