<?xml version="1.0"?>

<?dlps id="WhaR2Ho"?>
<?dlps page-images="none" figure-images="no"?>
<?dlps transcription="other"?>

<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/tei-p4/tei2.dtd" [
<!ENTITY % POSTKB "INCLUDE">
<!ENTITY % TEI.extensions.ent SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.ent">
<!ENTITY % TEI.extensions.dtd SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.dtd">
<!ENTITY % ISOnum SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/charent/iso-num.ent"> %ISOnum;
<!ENTITY % ISOpub SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/charent/iso-pub.ent"> %ISOpub;
]> 
 
<TEI.2 id="WhaR2Ho"> 
<teiHeader type="migrated" creator="Etext">
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title type="main">Women and Business</title>
<title type="sort">women and business</title>
<author>Wharton review: Franklin, C. L.</author>
<respStmt>
<resp>Creation of machine-readable version:</resp> 
<name>Judy Boss</name> 
<resp>Conversion to TEI.2-conformant markup:</resp>  
<name>University of Virginia Library Electronic Text Center.</name>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt> 
<extent>ca. <num type="kilobytes">9</num> kilobytes</extent> 
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>University of Virginia Library</publisher>
<pubPlace>Charlottesville, Virginia</pubPlace> 
<idno type="ETC">WhaR2Ho</idno> 
<date value="1996">1996</date>
<availability status="public">
<p n="copyright">Copyright &copy; 1996 by the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia</p>
<p n="access">Publicly accessible</p>
</availability>
<idno type="uva-pid">uva-lib:476522</idno>
</publicationStmt>
<seriesStmt>
<title>University of Virginia Library, Text collection</title>
<idno type="uva-set">UVA-LIB-Text</idno>
</seriesStmt> 
<sourceDesc>
<biblFull>
<titleStmt>
<title type="main">Women and Business</title>
<title level="j">Bookman</title>
<title type="sort">women and business</title>
<author>C. L. Franklin</author>
</titleStmt> 
<editionStmt>
<p>1st Edition.</p>
</editionStmt> 
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>Dodd, Mead and Company</publisher> 
<pubPlace>New York</pubPlace> 
<date value="1907">1907</date>
</publicationStmt> 
<seriesStmt>
<p>
<hi rend="italic">Bookman</hi> 24 Nov. 1906): 249-50.</p>
</seriesStmt> 
<notesStmt>
<note>
<p>UVa ed. AP2.B78</p>
</note>
</notesStmt>
</biblFull>
</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc> 
<encodingDesc>
<projectDesc>
<p>Prepared for the University of Virginia Library Electronic Text 
Center.</p>
</projectDesc> 
<editorialDecl>
<p>All quotation marks retained as data.</p> 
<p>Spell-check and verification made 
against printed text using WordPerfect spell checker.</p> 
<p>All unambiguous end-of-line hyphens have been removed, and the 
trailing part of a word has been joined to the preceding line.</p> 
<p id="ETC">Keywords in the header are a local Electronic Text Center scheme  
to aid in establishing analytical groupings.</p>
</editorialDecl> 
<refsDecl>
<p>ID elements are given for each page element and are composed of the text's 
unique cryptogram and the given page number, as in AusEmma1 for page one of  
Jane Austen's Emma.</p>
</refsDecl> 
</encodingDesc> 
<profileDesc>
<creation>
<date value="1906">1906</date>
</creation> 
<langUsage>
<language id="eng" usage="main">English</language>
</langUsage> 
<textClass>
<keywords>
<term>non-fiction</term>
<term>prose</term> 
<term>Women Writers</term>
</keywords> 
</textClass>
</profileDesc> 
<revisionDesc>
<change>
<date value="1996-03">March 1996</date> 
<respStmt>
<resp>corrector</resp> 
<name>Deirdre A. Johnson, Electronic Text Center, University of Virginia</name>
</respStmt> 
<item>Added header and basic TEI markup</item>
</change> 
<change>
<date value="2005-07">July 2005</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>Corrector</resp>
<name>Margaret Konkol</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Converted SGML to XML and fixed tagging.</item>
</change>
<change>
<date value="2007-09">September 2007</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>Migration</resp>
<name>Ethan Gruber, University of Virginia Library</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Converted XML markup from TEI Lite to uva-dl-tei (TEI P4 with local customizations).</item>
</change>
<change>
<date value="2008-01">January 2008</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>Migration</resp>
<name>Greg Murray, University of Virginia Library</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Programmatically updated TEI header markup (but not header content) for minimal compliance with current QA requirements.</item>
</change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader> 
 
<text id="d1"> 
<body id="d2"> 
<div1 type="essay" id="d3"><pb n="249" id="WhaR2Ho249"/> <head>WOMEN AND BUSINESS</head> 

<opener> 
TO THE EDITORS OF THE BOOKMAN. 
<salute><hi rend="italic">Dear Sirs:</hi></salute></opener>

<p>Mrs. Wharton's <hi rend="italic">The House of Mirth</hi> is 
a splendid study of social conditions; but, as the reviewers have 
pointed out, it leaves us somewhat cold as to the fortunes of Lily 
Bart (very largely, I conceive, owing to the extreme unpleasantness 
of her name), and hence we shall not be shocking its readers too 
much if we discuss in cold blood certain financial matters which 
come up near the end of the book. 
</p><p>It will be remembered that Lily Bart's troubles are largely 
due to a phenomenal ignorance of money matters&mdash;so profound that 
she thinks that once a man is a member of the Stock Exchange he can 
take possession of the modest capital of any one of his 
acquaintances and with no trouble at all cause it to produce a 
delightfully large income. What I wish to call attention to here 
is that Lily Bart's creator (though, as an extremely successful 
author, if nothing more, she must have had wide financial 
experiences) is herself apparently less familiar with money matters 
than one might have a right to expect. 
</p><p>The day before her tragic end Lily Bart receives a cheque for 
ten thousand dollars as her share of her aunt's estate, and after 
a good deal of hesitation she 
<pb n="250" id="WhaR2Ho250"/> 
decides to use the greater 
part of this money in relieving herself of her indebtedness to her 
over-generous speculating friend. At the moment when this 
resolution was finally arrived at we are told that she &laquo;reached out 
suddenly, and drawing the cheque from her writing desk, enclosed it 
in an envelope, which she addressed to her bank. She then wrote 
out a cheque for Trenor, and placing it, without an accompanying 
word, in an envelope inscribed with his name, laid the two letters 
side by side on her desk.&raquo; Now, Lily Bart has here overlooked the 
fact that in order to make this a valid transaction it was 
necessary that the cheque should have been first endorsed to the 
bank; and as her creator does not call attention to this oversight, 
the inference is plain that to her also the situation had failed to 
present itself with sufficient vividness. 
</p><p>There is another element of the scene which goes to show 
financial inadvertence on the part of the writer. At this same 
time we are told that &laquo;a careful examination of her cheque-book, 
<hi rend="italic">and of the unpaid bills in her desk</hi>, showed that when the 
latter had been settled she would have barely enough,&raquo; etc. The 
next morning, after the tragic death of Lily Bart, it falls to 
Lawrence Selden to be the first to look through the contents of her 
desk. &laquo;He opened the cheque-book and saw that the very night 
before a cheque of ten thousand dollars . . . had been entered in 
it. . . . But turning another page or two, he discovered with 
astonishment that in spite of this recent accession of funds the 
balance had already declined to a few dollars. A rapid glance at 
the stubs of the last cheques, all of which bore the date of the 
previous day, showed that between four and five hundred dollars of 
the legacy had been spent in the settlement of bills, while the 
remaining thousands were comprehended in one cheque, made out at 
the same time to Charles Augustus Trenor.&raquo; We have just been told, 
also, that, &laquo;to his surprise, he found that all the bills were 
receipted; there was not an unpaid account among them.&raquo; Now, this 
happened at nine o'clock in the morning, and it must have been 
already very late in the preceding evening when the cheque for the 
ten thousand dollars, contained in a belated letter, had been 
delivered to Lily; for it was &laquo;long after seven o'clock&raquo; when she 
returned home, and since then she had dressed for dinner, dined, 
&laquo;examined systematically the contents of her drawers and cupboard,&raquo; 
drawn out her remaining fine dresses from a trunk, allowed them to 
revive recollections of happier days, and then &laquo;put them back one 
by one.&raquo; The question that troubles me here is this: How did these 
bills, unpaid late the night before, come to be receipted early the 
next morning? Through the simple writing of the cheques? The 
ordinary way of securing receipted bills is to enclose the bills 
with the cheques by which they are to be paid, and to receive them 
back receipted, at best by return of mail. Can it be that Lily 
Bart, in a moment of inadvertence, receipted her bills herself 
instead of sending them to her creditors for their signatures? 
</p><p>Most readers, I take it, must have thought that Lily Bart's 
ignorance of business matters, on the part of so astute a person, 
accustomed to shifting for herself from her earliest years, is much 
overdrawn in the book; but if her creator, one of the acutest minds 
of the time in the construction of a story and in the psychological 
development of a character, can make mistakes like these in the 
plainest of every-day business transactions, it is possible that 
the situation among women in general is worse than one had thought.  
Certain it is that fathers who do not see to it that their 
daughters are thoroughly trained in the proper conduct of ordinary 
matters of business are preparing for them the possibility&mdash;as in 
the case of Lily Bart&mdash;of ruined lives, or at least of a very 
dangerous helplessness.</p> 
<signed>            <hi rend="italic">C. L. Franklin.</hi></signed> 
 
</div1> 
</body> 
</text> 
</TEI.2> 
 
