<?xml version="1.0"?>

<?dlps id="WhaRemb"?>
<?dlps page-images="none" figure-images="no"?>
<?dlps transcription="other"?>

<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/tei-p4/tei2.dtd" [
<!ENTITY % POSTKB "INCLUDE">
<!ENTITY % TEI.extensions.ent SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.ent">
<!ENTITY % TEI.extensions.dtd SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.dtd">
<!ENTITY % ISOnum SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/charent/iso-num.ent"> %ISOnum;
<!ENTITY % ISOpub SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/charent/iso-pub.ent"> %ISOpub;
]>

<TEI.2 id="WhaRemb"> 
<teiHeader type="migrated" creator="Etext">
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title type="main">The Rembrandt</title>
<title type="sort">rembrandt</title>
<author>Wharton, Edith, 1862-1937</author>
<respStmt>
<resp>Creation of machine-readable version:</resp> 
<name>Judy Boss</name> 
<resp>Conversion to TEI.2-conformant markup:</resp>  
<name>University of Virginia Library Electronic Text Center</name>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt> 
<extent>ca. <num type="kilobytes">40</num> kilobytes</extent> 
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>University of Virginia Library</publisher>
<pubPlace>Charlottesville, Virginia</pubPlace> 
<idno type="ETC">WhaRemb</idno> 
<date value="1995">1995</date>
<availability status="public">
<p n="copyright">Copyright &copy; 1995 by the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia</p>
<p n="access">Publicly accessible</p>
</availability>
<idno type="uva-pid">uva-lib:476526</idno>
</publicationStmt>
<seriesStmt>
<title>University of Virginia Library, Text collection</title>
<idno type="uva-set">UVA-LIB-Text</idno>
</seriesStmt> 
<sourceDesc>
<biblFull>
<titleStmt>
<title type="main">The Rembrandt</title>
<title type="sort">rembrandt</title>
<author>Edith Wharton</author>
</titleStmt> 
<editionStmt>
<p>1st Edition</p>
</editionStmt> 
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>Cosmopolitan</publisher> 
<pubPlace>New York</pubPlace> 
<date value="1900">1900</date>
</publicationStmt> 
</biblFull>
</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc> 
<encodingDesc>
<projectDesc>
<p>Prepared for the University of Virginia Library ElectronicText Center</p>
</projectDesc> 
<editorialDecl>
<p>All quotation marks retained as data</p> 
<p>Verification made against printed text.</p> 
<p>All unambiguous end-of-line hyphens have been removed, and the  
trailing part of a word has been joined to the preceding line.</p> 
<p id="ETC">Keywords in the header are a local Electronic Text Center scheme  
to aid in establishing analytical groupings</p>
</editorialDecl> 
<refsDecl>
<p>ID elements are given for each page element and are composed of the text's 
unique cryptogram and the given page number, as in AusEmma1 for page one of  
Jane Austen's Emma.</p>
</refsDecl>
</encodingDesc> 
<profileDesc>
<creation>
<date value="1900">1900</date>
</creation> 
<langUsage>
<language id="eng" usage="main">English</language>
</langUsage> 
<textClass>
<keywords>
<term>fiction</term>
<term>prose</term> 
<term>Women Writers</term>
</keywords>
</textClass>
</profileDesc> 
<revisionDesc>
<change>
<date value="1995-04">April 1995</date> 
<respStmt>
<resp>corrector</resp> 
<name>Kelly Moulton</name>
</respStmt> 
<item>TEI tagging</item>
</change> 
<change>
<date value="2005-07">July 2005</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>Corrector</resp>
<name>Margaret Konkol</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Converted SGML to XML and fixed tagging.</item>
</change>
<change>
<date value="2007-09">September 2007</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>Migration</resp>
<name>Ethan Gruber, University of Virginia Library</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Converted XML markup from TEI Lite to uva-dl-tei (TEI P4 with local customizations).</item>
</change>
<change>
<date value="2008-01">January 2008</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>Migration</resp>
<name>Greg Murray, University of Virginia Library</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Programmatically updated TEI header markup (but not header content) for minimal compliance with current QA requirements.</item>
</change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader> 
<text id="d1">  
<body id="d2"> 

<div1 type="section" n="1" id="d3"> 
	<head>Wharton, Edith.  "The Rembrandt."<lb/>   
		<hi rend="italic"> Cosmopolitan</hi> 29 (Aug.1900): 429-37.<lb/>I.</head> 
 
 
<pb n="429"/>  
<p>  "YOU'RE <hi rend="italic"> so</hi> artistic," my cousin Eleanor Copt 
began.</p><p> 
     Of all Eleanor's exordiums it is the one I most dread.  When 
she tells me I'm so clever, I know this is merely the preamble to 
inviting me to meet the last literary obscurity of the moment: a 
trial to be evaded or endured, as circumstances dictate; whereas 
her calling me artistic fatally connotes the request to visit, in 
her company, some distressed gentlewoman whose future hangs on my 
valuation of her old Saxe or of her grandfather's Marc Antonios.  
Time was when I attempted to resist these compulsions of 
Eleanor's; 
but I soon learned that, short of actual flight, there was no 
refuge from her beneficent despotism.  It is not always easy for 
the curator of a museum to abandon his post on the plea of 
escaping 
a pretty cousin's importunities; and Eleanor, aware of my 
predicament, is none too magnanimous to take advantage of it.  
Magnanimity is, in fact, not in Eleanor's line.  The virtues, she 
once explained to me, are like bonnets: the very ones that look 
best on other people may not happen to suit one's own particular 
style; and she added, with a slight deflection of metaphor, that 
none of the ready-made virtues ever <hi rend="italic"> had</hi> fitted her: they 
all 
pinched somewhere, and she'd given up trying to wear them.</p><p> 
     Therefore when she said to me, "You're <hi rend="italic"> so</hi> artistic," 
emphasizing the conjunction with a tap of her dripping umbrella 
(Eleanor is out in all weathers: the elements are as powerless 
against her as man), I merely stipulated, "It's not old Saxe 
again?"</p><p> 
     She shook her head reassuringly.  "A picture&mdash;a 
Rembrandt!"</p><p> 
     "Good Lord!  Why not a Leonardo?"</p><p> 
     "Well"&mdash;she smiled&mdash;"that, of course, depends on <hi rend="italic"> 
you</hi>."</p><p> 
     "On me?"</p><p> 
     "On your attribution.  I dare say Mrs. Fontage would consent 
to the change, though she's very conservative."</p><p> 
     A gleam of hope came to me and I pronounced: "One can't 
judge 
of a picture in this weather."</p><p> 
     "Of course not.  I'm coming for you to-morrow."</p><p> 
     "I've an engagement to-morrow."</p><p> 
     "I'll come before or after your engagement."</p><p> 
     The afternoon paper lay at my elbow and I contrived a 
furtive 
consultation of the weather-report.  It said, "Rain to-morrow," 
and 
I answered briskly, "All right, then; come at ten"&mdash;rapidly 
calculating that the clouds on which I counted might lift by 
noon.</p><p> 
     My ingenuity failed of its due reward, for the heavens, as 
if 
in league with my cousin, emptied themselves before morning, and 
punctually at ten Eleanor and the sun appeared in my 
office.</p><p> 
     I hardly listened, as we descended the museum steps and got 
into Eleanor's hansom, to her vivid summing-up of the case.  I 
guessed beforehand that the lady we were about to visit had 
lapsed 
by the most distressful degrees from opulence to a hall-bedroom; 
that her grandfather, if he had not been Minister to France, had 
signed the Declaration of Independence; that the Rembrandt was an 
heirloom, sole remnant of disbanded treasures; that for years its 
possessor had been unwilling to part with it, and that even now 
the 
question of its disposal must be approached with the most 
diplomatic obliquity.</p><p> 
     Previous experience had taught me that all Eleanor's "cases" 
presented a harrowing similarity of detail.  No circumstance 
tending to excite the spectator's sympathy and involve his action 
was omitted from the history of her beneficiaries; the lights and 
shades were indeed so skilfully adjusted that any impartial 
expression of opinion took on the hue of cruelty.  I could have 
produced closetfuls of "Heirlooms" in attestation of this fact; 
for 
it is one more mark of Eleanor's competence that her friends 
usually pay the interest on her philanthropy.  My one hope was 
that 
in this case the object, being a picture, <pb n="430"/>  
might reasonably 
be rated beyond my means; and as our cab drew up before a 
blistered 
brown-stone door-step I formed the self-defensive resolve to 
place 
an extreme valuation on Mrs. Fontage's Rembrandt.  It is 
Eleanor's 
fault if she is sometimes fought with her own weapons.</p><p> 
     The house stood in one of those shabby provisional-looking 
New 
York streets that seem resignedly awaiting demolition.  It was 
the 
kind of house that, in its high days, must have had a bow-window 
with a bronze in it.  The bow-window had been replaced by a 
plumber's devanture, and one might conceive the bronze to have 
gravitated to the limbo where Mexican onyx tables and bric-a-brac 
in buffalo-horn await the first signs of our next esthetic 
reaction.</p><p> 
     Eleanor swept me through a hall that smelled of poverty, up 
unlit stairs, to a bare slit of a room.  "And she must leave this 
in a month!" she commented across her knock.</p><p> 
     I had prepared myself for the limp widow's weed of a woman 
that one figures in such a setting; and confronted abruptly with 
Mrs. Fontage's white-haired erectness, I had the disconcerting 
sense that I was somehow in her presence at my own solicitation.  
I instinctively charged Eleanor with this reversal of the 
situation; but a moment later I saw it must be ascribed to a 
something about Mrs. Fontage that precluded the possibility of 
her 
asking any one a favor.  It was not that she was of forbidding, 
or 
even majestic, demeanor; but that one guessed, under her aquiline 
prettiness, a dignity nervously on guard against the petty 
betrayal 
of her surroundings.  The room was unconcealably poor: the little 
faded "relics," the high-stocked ancestral silhouettes, the 
steel-engravings after Raphael and Correggio, grouped in a vain attempt 
to hide the most obvious stains on the wall-paper, served only to 
accentuate the contrast of a past evidently diversified by 
foreign 
travel and the enjoyment of the arts.  Even Mrs. Fontage's dress 
had the air of being a last expedient, the ultimate outcome of a 
much-taxed ingenuity in darning and turning.  One felt that all 
the 
poor lady's barriers were falling save that of her impregnable 
manner.</p><p> 
     To this manner I found myself conveying my appreciation of 
being admitted to a view of the Rembrandt.</p><p> 
     Mrs. Fontage's smile took my homage for granted.  "It is 
always," she conceded, "a privilege to be in the presence of the 
great masters."  Her slim wrinkled hand waved me to a dusky 
canvas 
near the window.</p><p> 
     "It's <hi rend="italic"> so</hi> interesting, dear Mrs. Fontage," I heard 
Eleanor 
exclaiming, "and my cousin will be able to tell you exactly."  
Eleanor, in my presence, always admits that she knows nothing 
about 
art; but she gives the impression that this is merely because she 
hasn't had time to look into the matter&mdash;and has had me to do it 
for her.</p><p> 
     Mrs. Fontage seated herself without speaking, as though 
fearful that a breath might disturb my communion with the 
masterpiece.  I felt that she thought Eleanor's reassuring 
ejaculations ill timed; and in this I was of one mind with her; 
for 
the impossibility of telling her exactly what I thought of her 
Rembrandt had become clear to me at a glance.</p><p> 
     My cousin's vivacities began to languish and the silence 
seemed to shape itself into a receptacle for my verdict.  I 
stepped 
back, affecting a more distant scrutiny; and as I did so my eye 
caught Mrs. Fontage's profile.  Her lids trembled slightly.  I 
took 
refuge in the familiar expedient of asking the history of the 
picture, and she waved me brightly to a seat.</p><p> 
     This was indeed a topic on which she could dilate.  The 
Rembrandt, it appeared, had come into Mr. Fontage's possession 
many 
years ago, while the young couple were on their wedding-tour, and 
under circumstances so romantic that she made no excuse for 
relating them in all their parenthetic fulness.  The picture 
belonged to an old Belgian Countess of redundant quarterings, 
whom 
the extravagances of an ungovernable nephew had compelled to part 
with her possessions (in the most private manner) about the time 
of 
the Fontages' arrival.  By a really remarkable coincidence, it 
happened that their courier (an exceptionally intelligent and 
superior man) was an old servant of the Countess's, and had thus 
been able to put them in the way of securing the Rembrandt under 
the very nose of an English Duke, whose agent <pb n="431"/>  
had been sent 
to Brussels to negotiate for its purchase.  Mrs. Fontage could 
not 
recall the Duke's name, but he was a great collector and had a 
famous Highland castle, where somebody had been murdered, and 
which 
she herself had visited (by moonlight) when she had traveled in 
Scotland as a girl.  The episode had, in short, been one of the 
most interesting "experiences" of a tour almost 
chromo-lithographic 
in vivacity of impression; and they had always meant to go back 
to 
Brussels for the sake of reliving so picturesque a moment.  
Circumstances (of which the narrator's surroundings declared the 
nature) had persistently interfered with the projected return to 
Europe, and the picture had grown doubly valuable as representing 
the high-water mark of their artistic emotions.  Mrs. Fontage's 
moist eye caressed the canvas.  "There is only," she added, with 
a 
perceptible effort, "one slight drawback: the picture is not 
signed.  But for that, the Countess, of course, would have sold 
it 
to a museum.  All the connoisseurs who have seen it pronounce it 
an 
undoubted Rembrandt, in the artist's best manner; but the 
museums"&mdash;she arched her brows in smiling recognition of a well-known weakness&mdash;"give the preference to signed examples&mdash;"</p><p> 
     Mrs. Fontage's words evoked so touching a vision of the 
young 
tourists of fifty years ago, intrusting to an accomplished and 
versatile courier the direction of their helpless zeal for art, 
that I lost sight for a moment of the point at issue.  The old 
Belgian Countess, the wealthy Duke with a feudal castle in 
Scotland, Mrs. Fontage's own maiden pilgrimage to Arthur's Seat 
and 
Holyrood, all the accessories of the naif transaction, seemed a 
part of that vanished Europe to which our young race carried its 
indiscriminate ardors, its tender romantic credulity: the 
legendary 
castellated Europe of keepsakes, brigands, and old masters, that 
compensated, by one such "experience" as Mrs. Fontage's, for an 
after-life of esthetic privation.</p><p> 
     I was restored to the present by Eleanor's looking at her 
watch.  The action mutely conveyed that something was expected of 
me.  I risked the temporizing statement that the picture was very 
interesting; but Mrs. Fontage's polite assent revealed the 
poverty 
of the expedient.  Eleanor's impatience overflowed.</p><p> 
     "You would like my cousin to give you an idea of its value?" 
she suggested.</p><p> 
     Mrs. Fontage grew more erect.  "No one," she corrected with 
great gentleness, "can know its value quite so well as I, who 
live 
with it&mdash;"</p><p> 
     We murmured our hasty concurrence.</p><p> 
     "But it might be interesting to hear"&mdash;she addressed herself 
to me&mdash;"as a mere matter of curiosity&mdash;what estimate would be put 
on it from the purely commercial points of view, if such a term 
may 
be used in speaking of a work of art."</p><p> 
     I sounded a note of deprecation.</p><p> 
     "Oh, I understand, of course," she delicately anticipated 
me, 
"that that could never be <hi rend="italic"> your</hi>, your personal view; but 
since 
occasions <hi rend="italic"> may</hi> arise&mdash;do arise&mdash;when it becomes necessary 
to&mdash;to 
put a price on the priceless, as it were&mdash;I have thought&mdash;Miss 
Copt 
has suggested&mdash;"</p><p> 
     "Some day," Eleanor encouraged her, "you might feel that the 
picture ought to belong to some one who has more&mdash;more 
opportunity 
of showing it&mdash;letting it be seen by the public&mdash;for educational 
reasons&mdash;"</p><p> 
     "I have tried," Mrs. Fontage admitted, "to see it in that 
light."</p><p> 
     The crucial moment was upon me.  To escape the challenge of 
Mrs. Fontage's brilliant composure, I turned once more to the 
picture.  If my courage needed reinforcement, the picture amply 
furnished it.  Looking at that lamentable canvas seemed the 
surest 
way of gathering strength to denounce it; but behind me, all the 
while, I felt Mrs. Fontage's shuddering pride drawn up in a final 
effort of self-defense.  I hated myself for my sentimental 
perversion of the situation.  Reason argued that it was more 
cruel 
to deceive Mrs. Fontage than to tell her the truth; but that 
merely 
proved the inferiority of reason to instinct in situations 
involving any concession to the emotions.  Along with her faith 
in 
the Rembrandt I must destroy not only the whole fabric of Mrs. 
Fontage's past, but even that lifelong habit of acquiescence in 
untested formulas that makes the best part of the average 
feminine 
fortitude.  I guessed the episode of the picture to be 
inextricably 
inter-<pb n="432"/> woven with the traditions and 
convictions which served 
to veil Mrs. Fontage's destitution not only from others, but from 
herself.  Viewed in that light, the Rembrandt had perhaps been 
worth its purchase-money; and I regretted that works of art do 
not 
commonly sell on the merit of the moral support they may have 
rendered.</p><p> 
     From this unavailing flight I was recalled by the sense that 
something must be done.  To place a fictitious value on the 
picture 
was at best a provisional measure; while the brutal alternative 
of 
advising Mrs. Fontage to sell it for a hundred dollars at least 
afforded an opening to the charitably disposed purchaser.  I 
intended, if other resources failed, to put myself forward in 
that 
light; but delicacy of course forbade my coupling my unflattering 
estimate of the Rembrandt with an immediate offer to buy it.  All 
I could do was to inflict the wound: the healing unguent must be 
withheld for later application.</p><p> 
     I turned to Mrs. Fontage, who sat motionless, her finely 
lined 
cheeks touched with an expectant color, her eyes averted from the 
picture which was so evidently the one object they beheld.</p><p> 
     "My dear madam&mdash;" I began.  Her vivid smile was like a light 
held up to dazzle me.  It shrouded every alternative in darkness, 
and I had the flurried sense of having lost my way among the 
intricacies of my contention.  Of a sudden, I felt the 
hopelessness 
of finding a crack in her impenetrable conviction.  My words 
slipped from me like broken weapons.  "The picture," I faltered, 
"would of course be worth more if it were signed.  As it is, I&mdash;I 
hardly think&mdash;on a conservative estimate&mdash;it can be valued at&mdash;at 
more&mdash;than&mdash;a thousand dollars, say&mdash;"</p><p> 
     My deflected argument ran on somewhat aimlessly till it 
found 
itself plunging full tilt against the barrier of Mrs. Fontage's 
silence.  She sat as impassive as though I had not spoken.  
Eleanor 
loosed a few fluttering words of congratulation and 
encouragement, 
but their flight was suddenly cut short.  Mrs. Fontage had risen 
with a certain solemnity.</p><p> 
     "I could never," she said gently&mdash;her gentleness was 
adamantine&mdash;"under any circumstances whatever, consider, for a 
moment even, the possibility of parting with the picture at such 
a 
price." 
 
</p> 
</div1> 
<div1 type="section" n="2" id="d4"> 
<head>II.</head> 
<p> 
     Within three weeks, a tremulous note from Mrs. Fontage 
requested the favor of another visit.  If the writing was 
tremulous, however, the writer's tone was firm.  She named her 
own 
day and hour, without the conventional reference to her visitor's 
convenience.</p><p> 
     My first impulse was to turn the note over to Eleanor.  I 
had 
acquitted myself of my share in the ungrateful business of coming 
to Mrs. Fontage's aid, and if, as her letter denoted, she had now 
yielded to the closer pressure of need, the business of finding a 
purchaser for the Rembrandt might well be left to my cousin's 
ingenuity.  But here conscience put in the uncomfortable reminder 
that it was I who in putting a price on the picture had raised 
the 
real obstacle in the way of Mrs. Fontage's rescue.  No one would 
give a thousand dollars for the Rembrandt; but to tell Mrs. 
Fontage 
so had become as unthinkable as murder.  I had, in fact, on 
returning from my first inspection of the picture, refrained from 
imparting to Eleanor my opinion of its value.  Eleanor is porous, 
and I knew that sooner or later the unnecessary truth would exude 
through the loose texture of her dissimulation.  Not infrequently 
she thus creates the miseries she alleviates; and I have 
sometimes 
suspected her of paining people in order that she might be sorry 
for them.  I had, at all events, cut off retreat in Eleanor's 
direction; and the remaining alternatives carried me straight to 
Mrs. Fontage.</p><p> 
     She received me with the same commanding sweetness.  The 
room 
was even barer than before&mdash;I believe the carpet was gone&mdash;but 
her 
manner built up about her a palace to which I was welcomed with 
high state; and it was as a mere incident of the ceremony that I 
was presently made aware of her decision to sell the Rembrandt.  
My 
previous unsuccess in planning how to deal with Mrs. Fontage had 
warned me to leave my farther course to chance; and I listened to 
her explanation with complete detachment.  She had resolved to 
travel for her health; her doctor advised it, and as her absence 
might be indefinitely pro-<pb n="433"/> longed, she had 
reluctantly 
decided to part with the picture in order to avoid the expense of 
storage and insurance.  Her voice drooped at the admission, and 
she 
hurried on, detailing the vague itinerary of a journey that was 
to 
combine long-promised visits to impatient friends with various 
"interesting opportunities" less definitely specified.  The poor 
lady's skill in rearing a screen of verbiage about her enforced 
avowal had distracted me from my own share in the situation, and 
it 
was with dismay that I suddenly caught the drift of her 
assumptions.  She expected me to buy the Rembrandt for the 
museum; 
she had taken my previous valuation as a tentative bid, and when 
I 
came to my senses she was in the act of accepting my 
offer.</p><p> 
     Had I had a thousand dollars of my own to dispose of, the 
bargain would have been concluded on the spot; but I was in the 
impossible position of being materially unable to buy the picture 
and morally unable to tell her that it was not worth acquiring 
for 
the museum.</p><p> 
     I dashed into the first evasion in sight.  I had no 
authority, 
I explained, to purchase pictures for the museum without the 
consent of the committee.</p><p> 
     Mrs. Fontage coped for a moment in silence with the 
incredible 
fact that I had rejected her offer; then she ventured, with a 
kind 
of pale precipitation: "But I understood&mdash;Miss Copt tells me that 
you practically decide such matters for the committee."  I could 
guess what the effort had cost her.</p><p> 
     "My cousin is given to generalizations.  My opinion may have 
some weight with the committee&mdash;"</p><p> 
     "Well, then&mdash;" she timidly prompted.</p><p> 
     "For that very reason I can't buy the picture."</p><p> 
     She said, with a drooping note, "I don't understand."</p><p> 
     "Yet you told me," I reminded her, "that you knew museums 
didn't buy unsigned pictures."</p><p> 
     "Not for what they are worth!  Every one knows that.  But 
I&mdash;I 
understood&mdash;the price you named&mdash;"  Her pride shuddered back from 
the abasement.  "It's a misunderstanding then," she 
faltered.</p><p> 
     To avoid looking at her, I glanced desperately at the 
Rembrandt.  Could I&mdash;?  But reason rejected the possibility.  
Even 
if the committee had been blind&mdash;and they all <hi rend="italic"> were</hi> but 
Crozier--I simply shouldn't have dared to do it.  I stood up, feeling 
that 
to cut the matter short was the only alleviation within 
reach.</p><p> 
     Mrs. Fontage had summoned her indomitable smile; but its 
brilliancy dropped, as I opened the door, like a candle blown out 
by a draft.</p><p> 
     "If there's any one else&mdash;if you knew any one who would care 
to see the picture, I should be most happy&mdash;"  She kept her eyes 
on 
me, and I saw that, in her case, it hurt less than to look at the 
Rembrandt.  "I shall have to leave here, you know," she panted; 
"if 
nobody cares to have it&mdash;" 
 
</p> 
</div1> 
<div1 type="section" n="3" id="d5"> 
<head>III.</head> 
<p> 
     That evening at my club, I had just succeeded in losing 
sight 
of Mrs. Fontage in the fumes of an excellent cigar, when a voice 
at 
my elbow evoked her harassing image.</p><p> 
     "I want to talk to you," the speaker said, "about Mrs. 
Fontage's Rembrandt."</p><p> 
     "There isn't any," I was about to growl; but looking up I 
recognized the confiding countenance of Mr. Jefferson 
Rose.</p><p> 
     Mr. Rose was known to me chiefly as a young man suffused 
with 
a vague enthusiasm for Virtue and my cousin Eleanor.</p><p> 
     One glance at his glossy exterior conveyed the assurance 
that 
his morals were as immaculate as his complexion and his linen.  
Goodness exuded from his moist eye, his liquid voice, the warm, 
damp pressure of his trustful hand.  He had always struck me as 
one 
of the most uncomplicated organisms I had ever met.  His ideas 
were 
as simple and inconsecutive as the propositions in a primer, and 
he 
spoke slowly, with a kind of uniformity of emphasis that made his 
words stand out like the raised type for the blind.  An obvious 
incapacity for abstract conceptions made him peculiarly 
susceptible 
to the magic of generalization, and one felt he would have been 
at 
the mercy of any Cause that spelled itself with a capital letter. 
 
It was hard to explain how, with such a superabundance of merit, 
he 
managed to be a good fellow: I can only say that he  
<pb n="434"/>  
performed the astonishing feat as naturally as he supported an 
invalid mother and two sisters on the slender salary of a 
banker's 
clerk.  He sat down beside me with an air of bright 
expectancy.</p><p> 
     "It's a remarkable picture, isn't it?" he said.</p><p> 
     "You've seen it?"</p><p> 
     "I've been so fortunate.  Miss Copt was kind enough to get 
Mrs. Fontage's permission; we went this afternoon."</p><p> 
     I inwardly wished that Eleanor had selected another victim; 
unless indeed the visit were part of a plan whereby some third 
person, better equipped for the cultivation of delusions, was to 
be 
made to think the Rembrandt remarkable.  Knowing the limitations 
of 
Mr. Rose's resources, I began to wonder if he had any rich 
aunts.</p><p> 
     "And her buying it in that way, too," he went on, with his 
limpid smile, "from that old Countess in Brussels, makes it all 
the 
more interesting, doesn't it?  Miss Copt tells me it's very 
seldom 
old pictures can be traced back for more than a generation.  I 
suppose the fact of Mrs. Fontage's knowing its history must add a 
good deal to its value?"</p><p> 
     Uncertain as to his drift, I said, "In her eyes it certainly 
appears to."</p><p> 
     Implications are lost on Mr. Rose, who glowingly continued: 
"That's the reason why I wanted to talk to you about it&mdash;to 
consult 
you.  Miss Copt tells me you value it at a thousand 
dollars."</p><p> 
     There was no denying this, and I grunted a reluctant 
assent.</p><p> 
     "Of course," he went on earnestly, "your valuation is based 
on 
the fact that the picture isn't signed&mdash;Mrs. Fontage explained 
that; and it <hi rend="italic"> does</hi> make a difference, certainly.  But the 
thing 
is&mdash;if the picture's really good&mdash;ought one to take advantage&mdash;?  
I mean&mdash;one can see that Mrs. Fontage is in a tight place, and I 
wouldn't for the world&mdash;"</p><p> 
     My astonished stare arrested him.</p><p> 
     <hi rend="italic">" You</hi> wouldn't&mdash;?"</p><p> 
     "I mean&mdash;you see, it's just this way"; he coughed and 
blushed; 
"I can't give more than a thousand dollars myself&mdash;it's as big a 
sum as I can manage to scrape together&mdash;but before I make the 
offer 
I want to be sure I'm not standing in the way of her getting more 
money."</p><p> 
     My astonishment lapsed to dismay.  "You're going to buy the 
picture for a thousand dollars?"</p><p> 
     His blush deepened.  "Why, yes.  It sounds rather absurd, I 
suppose.  It isn't much in my line, of course.  I can see the 
picture's very beautiful, but I'm no judge&mdash;it isn't the kind of 
thing, naturally, that I could afford to go in for; but in this 
case I'm very glad to do what I can; the circumstances are so 
distressing; and knowing what you think of the picture I feel 
it's 
a pretty safe investment&mdash;"</p><p> 
     "I don't think!" I blurted out.</p><p> 
     "You&mdash;?"</p><p> 
     "I don't think the picture's worth a thousand dollars; I 
don't 
think it's worth ten cents; I simply lied about it, that's 
all."</p><p> 
     Mr. Rose looked as frightened as though I had charged him 
with 
the offense.</p><p> 
     "Hang it, man, can't you see how it happened?  I saw the 
poor 
woman's pride and happiness hung on her faith in that picture.  I 
tried to make her understand that it was worthless&mdash;but she 
wouldn't; I tried to tell her so&mdash;but I couldn't.  I behaved like 
a maudlin ass, but you shan't pay for my infernal bungling&mdash;you 
mustn't buy the picture!"</p><p> 
     Mr. Rose sat silent, tapping one glossy boot-tip with 
another.  
Suddenly he turned on me a glance of stored intelligence.  "But 
you 
know," he said, good-humoredly, "I rather think I must."</p><p> 
     "You haven't&mdash;already?"</p><p> 
     "Oh, no; the offer's not made."</p><p> 
     "Well, then&mdash;"</p><p> 
     His look gathered a brighter significance.</p><p> 
     "But if the picture's worth nothing, nobody will buy 
it&mdash;"</p><p> 
     I groaned.</p><p> 
     "Except," he continued, "some fellow like me, who doesn't 
know 
anything.  <hi rend="italic"> I</hi> think it's lovely, you know; I mean to hang 
it in 
my mother's sitting-room."  He rose and clasped my hand in his 
adhesive pressure.  "I'm awfully obliged to you for telling me 
this; but perhaps you won't mind my asking you not to mention our 
talk to Miss Copt?  It might bother her, you know, to think the 
picture isn't exactly up to the mark; and it won't make a rap of 
difference to me." <pb n="435"/>  
 
</p> 
</div1> 
<div1 type="section" n="4" id="d6"> 
<head>IV.</head> 
 
<p> 
     Mr. Rose left me to a sleepless night.  The next morning my 
resolve was formed, and it carried me straight to Mrs. Fontage's. 
 
She answered my knock by stepping out on the landing, and as she 
shut the door behind her I caught a glimpse of her devastated 
interior.  She mentioned, with a careful avoidance of the note of 
pathos on which our last conversation had closed, that she was 
preparing to leave that afternoon; and the trunks obstructing the 
threshold showed that her preparations were nearly complete.  
They 
were, I felt certain, the same trunks that, strapped behind a 
rattling vettura, had accompanied the bride and groom on that 
memorable voyage of discovery of which the booty had till 
recently 
adorned her walls; and there was a dim consolation in the thought 
that those early "finds" in coral and Swiss wood-carving, in lava 
and alabaster, still lay behind the worn locks, secure in the 
inviolability of worthlessness.</p><p> 
     Mrs. Fontage, on the landing, among her strapped and corded 
treasures, maintained the same air of stability that made it 
impossible, even under such conditions, to regard her flight as 
anything less dignified than a departure.  It was the moral 
support 
of what she tacitly assumed that enabled me to set forth with 
proper deliberation the object of my visit; and she received my 
announcement with an absence of surprise that struck me as the 
very 
flower of tact.  Under cover of these mutual assumptions, the 
transaction was rapidly concluded; and it was not till the canvas 
passed into my hands that, as though the physical contact had 
unnerved her, Mrs. Fontage suddenly faltered.  "It's the giving 
it 
up&mdash;" she stammered, disguising herself to the last; and I 
hastened 
away from the collapse of her splendid effrontery.</p><p> 
     I need hardly point out that I had acted impulsively, and 
that 
reaction from the most honorable impulses is sometimes attended 
by 
moral perturbation.  My motives had indeed been mixed enough to 
justify some uneasiness, but this was allayed by the instinctive 
feeling that it is more venial to defraud an institution than a 
man.  Since Mrs. Fontage had to be kept from starving by means 
not 
wholly defensible, it was better that the obligation should be 
borne by a rich institution than an impecunious youth.  I doubt, 
in 
fact, if my scruples would have survived a night's sleep, had 
they 
not been complicated by some uncertainty as to my own future.  It 
was true that, subject to the purely formal assent of the 
committee, I had full power to buy for the museum, and that the 
one 
member of the committee likely to dispute my decision was 
opportunely traveling in Europe; but the picture once in place I 
must face the risk of any expert criticism to which chance might 
expose it.  I dismissed this contingency for future study, stored 
the Rembrandt in the cellar of the museum, and thanked heaven 
that 
Crozier was abroad.</p><p> 
     Six months later, he strolled into my office.  I had just 
concluded, under conditions of exceptional difficulty, and on 
terms 
unexpectedly benign, the purchase of the great Bartley Reynolds; 
and this circumstance, by relegating the matter of the Rembrandt 
to 
a lower stratum of consciousness, enabled me to welcome Crozier 
with unmixed pleasure.  My security was enhanced by his 
appearance.  
His smile was charged with amiable reminiscences, and I inferred 
that his trip had put him in the humor to approve of everything, 
or 
at least to ignore what fell short of his approval.  I had 
therefore no uneasiness in accepting his invitation to dine that 
evening.  It is always pleasant to dine with Crozier and never 
more 
so than when he is just back from Europe.  His conversation gives 
even the food a flavor of the Cafe Anglais.</p><p> 
     The repast was delightful, and it was not till we had 
finished 
a Camembert which he must have brought over with him, that my 
host 
said, in a tone of after-dinner perfunctoriness, "I see you've 
picked up a picture or two since I left."</p><p> 
     I assented.  "The Bartley Reynolds seemed too good an 
opportunity to miss, especially as the French government was 
after 
it.  I think we got it cheap&mdash;"</p><p> 
     "Connu, connu," said Crozier, pleasantly.  "I know all about 
the Reynolds.  It was the biggest kind of a haul and I 
congratulate 
you.  Best stroke of business <pb n="436"/>  we've done yet.  
But tell me 
about the other picture&mdash;the Rembrandt."</p><p> 
     "I never said it was a Rembrandt."  I could hardly have said 
why, but I felt distinctly annoyed with Crozier.</p><p> 
     "Of course not.  There's 'Rembrandt' on the frame, but I saw 
you'd modified it to 'Dutch School'; I apologize."  He paused, 
but 
I offered no explanation.  "What about it?" he went on.  "Where 
did 
you pick it up?"  As he leaned to the flame of the cigar-lighter, 
his face seemed ruddy with enjoyment.</p><p> 
     "I got it for a song," I said.</p><p> 
     "A thousand, I think?"</p><p> 
     "Have you seen it?" I asked abruptly.</p><p> 
     "Went over the place this afternoon and found it in the 
cellar.  Why hasn't it been hung, by the way?"</p><p> 
     I paused a moment.  "I'm waiting&mdash;"</p><p> 
     "To&mdash;?"</p><p> 
     "To have it varnished."</p><p> 
     "Ah!"  He leaned back and poured himself a second glass of 
Chartreuse.  The smile he confided to its golden depths provoked 
me 
to challenge him with&mdash;</p><p> 
     "What do you think of it?"</p><p> 
     "The Rembrandt?"  He lifted his eyes from the glass.  "Just 
what you do."</p><p> 
     "It isn't a Rembrandt."</p><p> 
     "I apologize again.  You call it, I believe, a picture of 
the 
same period?"</p><p> 
     "I'm uncertain of the period."</p><p> 
     "H'm."  He glanced appreciatively along his cigar.  "What 
are 
you certain of?"</p><p> 
     "That it's a damned bad picture," I said, savagely.</p><p> 
     He nodded.  "Just so.  That's all we wanted to know."</p><p> 
     <hi rend="italic">" We?"</hi></p><p> 
     "We&mdash;I&mdash;the committee, in short.  You see, my dear fellow, 
if 
you hadn't been certain it was a damned bad picture our position 
would have been a little awkward.  As it is, my remaining duty&mdash;I 
ought to explain that in this matter I'm acting for the 
committee&mdash; 
is as simple as it's agreeable."</p><p> 
     "I'll be hanged," I burst out, "if I understand one word 
you're saying!"</p><p> 
     He fixed me with a kind of cruel joyousness.  "You will&mdash;you 
will," he assured me; "at least, you'll begin to, when you hear 
that I've seen Miss Copt."</p><p> 
     "Miss Copt?"</p><p> 
     "And that she has told me under what conditions the picture 
was bought."</p><p> 
     "She doesn't know anything about the conditions!  That is," 
I 
added, hastening to restrict the assertion, "she doesn't know my 
opinion of the picture."  I thirsted for five minutes with 
Eleanor.</p><p> 
     "Are you quite sure?" Crozier took me up.  "Mr. Jefferson 
Rose 
does."</p><p> 
     "Ah&mdash;I see."</p><p> 
     "I thought you would," he reminded me.  "As soon as I'd laid 
eyes on the Rembrandt&mdash;I beg your pardon!&mdash;I saw that it&mdash;well, 
required some explanation."</p><p> 
     "You might have come to me."</p><p> 
     "I meant to; but I happened to meet Miss Copt, whose 
encyclopedic information has often before been of service to me.  
I always go to Miss Copt when I want to look up anything; and I 
found she knew all about the Rembrandt."</p><p> 
     <hi rend="italic">" All?"</hi></p><p> 
     "Precisely.  The knowledge was, in fact, causing her 
sleepless 
nights.  Mr. Rose, who was suffering from the same form of 
insomnia, had taken her into his confidence, and 
she&mdash;ultimately&mdash; 
took me into hers."</p><p> 
     "Of course!"</p><p> 
     "I must ask you to do your cousin justice.  She didn't speak 
till it became evident to her uncommonly quick perceptions that 
your buying the picture on its merits would have been infinitely 
worse for&mdash;for everybody&mdash;than your diverting a small portion of 
the museum's funds to philanthropic uses.  Then she told me the 
moving incident of Mr. Rose.  Good fellow, Rose.  And the old 
lady's case was desperate.  Somebody had to buy that picture."  I 
moved uneasily in my seat.  "Wait a moment, will you?  I haven't 
finished my cigar.  There's a little head of Il Fiammingo's that 
you haven't seen, by the way; I picked it up the other day in 
Parma.  We'll go in and have a look at it presently.  But 
meanwhile 
what I want to say is that I've been charged&mdash;in the most 
informal 
way&mdash;to express to you the committee's appreciation of your 
admirable promptness and energy in capturing the Bartley 
Reynolds.  
We shouldn't have got it at all if you hadn't been uncommonly 
wide-awake, and to get it at such <pb n="437"/>  a price is a 
double triumph.  
We'd have thought nothing of a few more thousands&mdash;"</p><p> 
     "I don't see," I impatiently interposed, "that, as far as 
I'm 
concerned, that alters the case."</p><p> 
     "The case&mdash;?"</p><p> 
     "Of Mrs. Fontage's Rembrandt.  I bought the picture because, 
as you say, the situation was desperate, and I couldn't raise a 
thousand myself.  What I did was of course indefensible; but the 
money shall be refunded to-morrow&mdash;"</p><p> 
     Crozier raised a protesting hand.  "Don't interrupt me when 
I'm talking ex cathedra.  The money's been refunded already.  The 
fact is, the museum has sold the Rembrandt."</p><p> 
     I stared at him wildly.  "Sold it?  To whom?"</p><p> 
     "Why&mdash;the committee.&mdash;Hold on a bit, please.&mdash;Won't you take 
another cigar?  Then perhaps I can finish what I've got to say.&mdash; 
Why, my dear fellow, the committee's under an obligation to you&mdash; 
that's the way we look at it.  I've investigated Mrs. Fontage's 
case, and&mdash;well, the picture had to be bought.  She's eating meat 
now, I believe, for the first time in a year.  And they'd have 
turned her out into the street that very day, your cousin tells 
me.  
Something had to be done at once, and you've simply given a 
number 
of well-to-do and self-indulgent gentlemen the opportunity of 
performing, at very small individual expense, a meritorious 
action 
in the nick of time.  That's the first thing I've got to thank 
you 
for.  And then&mdash;you'll remember, please, that I have the floor&mdash; 
that I'm still speaking for the committee&mdash;and secondly, as a 
slight recognition of your services in securing the Bartley 
Reynolds at a very much lower figure than we were prepared to 
pay, 
we beg you&mdash;the committee begs you&mdash;to accept the gift of Mrs. 
Fontage's Rembrandt.  Now we'll go in and look at that little 
head." 
</p> 
 
 
</div1> 
</body> 
</text> 
</TEI.2> 
