<?xml version="1.0"?>

<?dlps id="WhaVall"?>
<?dlps page-images="none" figure-images="no"?>
<?dlps transcription="other"?>

<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/tei-p4/tei2.dtd" [
<!ENTITY % POSTKB "INCLUDE">
<!ENTITY % TEI.extensions.ent SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.ent">
<!ENTITY % TEI.extensions.dtd SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.dtd">
<!ENTITY % ISOnum SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/charent/iso-num.ent"> %ISOnum;
<!ENTITY % ISOpub SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/charent/iso-pub.ent"> %ISOpub;

]>

<TEI.2 id="WhaVall"> 
<teiHeader type="migrated" creator="Etext">
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title type="main">The Valley of Childish Things, and Other Emblems</title>
<title type="sort">valley of childish things, and other emblems</title>
<author>Wharton, Edith, 1862-1937</author>
<respStmt>
<resp>Creation of machine-readable version</resp>
<name>Judy Boss</name>
</respStmt>
<respStmt>
<resp>Conversion to TEI-conformant markup</resp>
<name>University of Virginia Library Electronic Text Center</name>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt> 
<extent>ca. <num type="kilobytes">17</num> kilobytes</extent> 
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>University of Virginia Library</publisher>
<pubPlace>Charlottesville, Virginia</pubPlace> 
<idno type="ETC">WhaVall</idno> 
<date value="1994">1994</date>
<availability status="public">
<p n="copyright">Copyright &copy; 1994 by the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia</p>
<p n="access">Publicly accessible</p>
</availability>
<idno type="uva-pid">uva-lib:476531</idno>
</publicationStmt>
<seriesStmt>
<title>University of Virginia Library, Text collection</title>
<idno type="uva-set">UVA-LIB-Text</idno>
</seriesStmt> 
<sourceDesc>
<biblFull>
<titleStmt>
<title type="main">The Valley of Childish Things, and Other Emblems</title>
<title type="sort">valley of childish things, and other emblems</title>
<author>Edith Wharton</author>
</titleStmt> 
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>Century Magazine</publisher> 
<pubPlace>New York</pubPlace> 
<date value="1896">1896</date>
</publicationStmt> 
<seriesStmt>
<p>Volume</p>
</seriesStmt> 
</biblFull>
</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc> 
<encodingDesc>
<projectDesc>
<p>Prepared for the University of Virginia Library Electronic Text Center</p>
</projectDesc> 
<editorialDecl>
<p>All quotation marks retained as data</p> 
<p>Spell-check and verification made 
against printed text using WordPerfect spell checker</p> 
<p>All unambiguous end-of-line hyphens have been removed, and the 
trailing part of a word has been joined to the preceding line.</p> 
<p id="ETC">Keywords in the header are a local Electronic Text Center 
scheme 
to aid in establishing analytical groupings</p>
</editorialDecl> 
<refsDecl>
<p>ID elements are given for each page element and are composed of the 
text's 
unique cryptogram and the given page number, as in SpeFQue1 for page one of 
Spenser's Faerie Queene.</p>
</refsDecl>
</encodingDesc> 
<profileDesc>
<creation>
<date value="1896">1896</date>
</creation> 
<langUsage>
<language id="eng" usage="main">English</language>
</langUsage> 
<textClass>
<keywords>
<term>fiction</term>
<term>prose</term>
</keywords>
</textClass>
</profileDesc> 
<revisionDesc>
<change>
<date value="1994-11">November 1994</date> 
<respStmt>
<resp>corrector</resp>
<name>Monique Dull, University of Virginia Library Electronic Text Center</name>
</respStmt>
<item>basic conversion to TEI-conformant markup</item>
</change> 
<change>
<date value="2005-07">July 2005</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>Corrector</resp>
<name>Margaret Konkol</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Converted SGML to XML and fixed tagging.</item>
</change>
<change>
<date value="2007-09">September 2007</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>Migration</resp>
<name>Ethan Gruber, University of Virginia Library</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Converted XML markup from TEI Lite to uva-dl-tei (TEI P4 with local customizations).</item>
</change>
<change>
<date value="2008-01">January 2008</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>Migration</resp>
<name>Greg Murray, University of Virginia Library</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Programmatically updated TEI header markup (but not header content) for minimal compliance with current QA requirements.</item>
</change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader> 
 
<text id="d1">  
 
<body id="d2"> 
 
<div1 type="chapter" n="1" id="d3"> <pb n="467"/>  
	<head>Wharton, Edith.  "The Valley of Childish Things, and Other 
		Emblems." <lb/> 
		<hi rend="italic">Century Magazine</hi> 52 (July 1896): 467-469. <lb/>I.</head> 
<p>Once upon a time a number of children lived together in the Valley 
of Childish Things, playing all manner of delightful games, and 
studying the same lesson-books.  But one day a little girl, one of 
their number, decided that it was time to see something of the 
world about which the lesson-books had taught her; and as none of 
the other children cared to leave their games, she set out alone to 
climb the pass which led out of the valley. 
</p><p>It was a hard climb, but at length she reached a cold, bleak 
table-land beyond the mountains.  Here she saw cities and men, and 
learned many useful arts, and in so doing grew to be a woman.  But 
the table-land was bleak and cold, and when she had served her 
apprenticeship she decided to return to her old companions in the 
Valley of Childish Things, and work with them instead of with 
strangers. 
</p><p>It was a weary way back, and her feet were bruised by the 
stones, and her face was beaten by the weather; but half way down 
the pass she met a man, who kindly helped her over the roughest 
places.  Like herself, he was lame and weather-beaten; but as soon 
as he spoke she recognized him as one of her old playmates.  He too 
had been out in the world, and was going back to the valley; and on 
the way they talked together of the work they meant to do there. 
He had been a dull boy, and she had never taken much notice of him; 
but as she listened to his plans for building bridges and draining 
swamps and cutting roads through the jungle, she thought to 
herself, "Since he has grown into such a fine fellow, what splendid 
men and women my other playmates must have become!" 
</p><p>But what was her surprise to find, on reaching the valley, 
that her former companions, instead of growing into men and women, 
had all remained little children.  Most of them were playing the 
same old games, and the few who affected to be working were engaged 
in such strenuous occupations as building mud-pies and sailing 
paper boats in basins.  As for the lad who had been the favorite 
companion of her studies, he was playing marbles with all the 
youngest boys in the valley. 
</p><p>At first, the children seemed glad to have her back, but soon 
she saw that her presence interfered with their games; and when she 
tried to tell them of the great things that were being done on the 
table-land beyond the mountains, they picked up their toys and went 
farther down the valley to play. 
</p><p>Then she turned to her fellow-traveler, who was the only grown 
man in the valley; but he was on his knees before a dear little 
girl with blue eyes and a coral necklace, for whom he was making a 
garden out of cockle-shells and bits of glass, and broken flowers 
stuck in sand. 
</p><p>The little girl was clapping her hands and crowing (she was 
too young to speak articulately); and when she who had grown to be 
a woman laid her hand on the man's shoulder, and asked him if he 
did not want to set to work with her building bridges, draining 
swamps, and cutting roads through the jungle, he replied that at 
that particular moment he was too busy. 
</p><p>And as she turned away, he added in the kindest possible way, 
"Really, my dear, you ought to have taken better care of your 
complexion." 
</p> 
</div1> 
<div1 type="chapter" n="2" id="d4"> 
<head>II. 
</head> 
<p> 
There was once a maiden lady who lived alone in a commodious brick 
house facing north and south.  The lady was very fond of warmth and 
sunshine, but unfortunately her room was on the north side of the 
house, so that in winter she had no sun at all. 
</p><p>This distressed her so much that, after long deliberation, she 
sent for an architect, and asked him if it would be possible to 
turn the house around so that her room should face the south.  The 
architect replied that anything could be done for money; but the 
estimated cost of turning the house around was so high that the 
lady, who enjoyed a handsome income, was obliged to reduce her way 
of living and sell her securities at a sacrifice to raise money 
enough for the purpose.  
<pb n="468"/>  
At length, however, the house was 
turned around, and she felt almost consoled for her impoverishment 
by the first ray of sunlight which stole through her shutters the 
next morning. 
</p><p>That very day she received a visit from an old friend who had 
been absent a year; and this friend, finding her seated at her 
window in a flood of sunlight, immediately exclaimed: 
</p><p>"My dear, how sensible of you to have moved into a south room! 
I never could understand why you persisted so long in living on the 
north side of the house." 
</p><p>And the following day the architect sent in his bill. 
</p> 
</div1> 
<div1 type="chapter" n="3" id="d5"> 
<head>III. 
</head> 
<p> 
There was once a little girl who was so very intelligent that her 
parents feared that she would die. 
</p><p>But an aged aunt, who had crossed the Atlantic in a sailing-vessel, said, "My dears, let her marry the first man she falls in 
love with, and she will make such a fool of herself that it will 
probably save her life." 
</p> 
</div1> 
<div1 type="chapter" n="4" id="d6"> 
<head>IV. 
</head> 
<p> 
A thinly clad man, who was trudging afoot through a wintry and 
shelterless region, met another wrapped in a big black cloak.  The 
cloak hung heavily on its wearer, and seemed to drag him back, but 
at least it kept off the cold. 
</p><p>"That's a fine warm cloak you've got," said the first man 
through his chattering teeth. 
</p><p>"Oh," said the other, "it's none of my choosing, I promise 
you.  It's only my old happiness dyed black and made over into a 
sorrow; but in this weather a man must wear what he's got." 
</p><p>"To think of some people's luck!" muttered the first man, as 
the other passed on.  "Now I never had enough happiness to make a 
sorrow out of." 
</p> 
</div1> 
<div1 type="chapter" n="5" id="d7"> 
<head>V. 
</head> 
<p> 
There was once a man who married a sweet little wife; but when he 
set out with her from her father's house, he found that she had 
never been taught to walk.  They had a long way to go, and there 
was nothing for him to do but to carry her; and as he carried her 
she grew heavier and heavier. 
</p><p>Then they came to a wide, deep river, and he found that she 
had never been taught to swim.  So he told her to hold fast to his 
shoulder, and started to swim with her across the river.  And as he 
swam she grew frightened, and dragged him down in her struggles. 
And the river was deep and wide, and the current ran fast; and once 
or twice she nearly had him under.  But he fought his way through, 
and landed her safely on the other side; and behold, he found 
himself in a strange country, beyond all imagining delightful.  And 
as he looked about him and gave thanks, he said to himself: 
</p><p>"Perhaps if I hadn't had to carry her over, I shouldn't have 
kept up long enough to get here myself." 
</p> 
</div1> 
<div1 type="chapter" n="6" id="d8"> 
<head>VI. 
</head> 
<p> 
A soul once cowered in a gray waste, and a mighty shape came by. 
Then the soul cried out for help, saying, "Shall I be left to 
perish alone in this desert of Unsatisfied Desires?" 
</p><p>"But you are mistaken," the shape replied; "this is the land 
of Gratified Longings.  And, moreover, you are not alone, for the 
country is full of people; but whoever tarries here grows blind." 
</p> 
</div1> 
<div1 type="chapter" n="7" id="d9"> 
<head>VII. 
</head> 
<p> 
There was once a very successful architect who made a great name 
for himself.  At length he built a magnificent temple, to which he 
devoted more time and thought than to any of the other buildings he 
had erected; and the world pronounced it his masterpiece.  Shortly 
afterward he died, and when he came before the judgment angel he 
was not asked how many sins he had committed, but how many houses 
he had built. 
</p><p>He hung his head and said, more than he could count. 
</p><p>The judgment angel asked what they were like, and the 
architect said that he was afraid they were pretty bad. 
</p><p>"And are you sorry?" asked the angel. 
</p><p>"Very sorry," said the architect, with honest contrition. 
</p><p>"And how about that famous temple that you built just before 
you died?" the angel continued.  "Are you satisfied with that?" 
</p><p>"Oh, no," the architect exclaimed.  "I really think it has 
some good points about it,&mdash;I did try my best, you know,&mdash;but 
there's one dreadful mistake that I'd give my soul to go back and 
rectify." 
</p><p>"Well," said the angel, "you can't go back and rectify it, but 
you can take your choice of the following alternatives: either we 
can let the world go on thinking your temple a masterpiece and you 
the greatest architect that ever lived, or we can send to earth a 
young fellow we've got here who will discover 
 
<pb n="469"/>    
your mistake 
at a glance, and point it out so clearly to posterity that you'll 
be the laughing-stock of all succeeding generations of architects. 
Which do you choose?" 
</p><p>"Oh, well," said the architect, "if it comes to that, you 
know&mdash;as long as it suits my clients as it is, I really don't see 
the use of making such a fuss." 
</p> 
</div1> 
<div1 type="chapter" n="8" id="d10"> 
<head>VIII. 
</head> 
<p> 
A man once married a charming young person who agreed with him on 
every question.  At first they were very happy, for the man thought 
his wife the most interesting companion he had ever met, and they 
spent their days telling each other what wonderful people they 
were.  But by and by the man began to find his wife rather 
tiresome.  Wherever he went she insisted upon going; whatever he 
did, she was sure to tell him that it would have been better to do 
the opposite; and moreover, it gradually dawned upon him that his 
friends had never thought so highly of her as he did.  Having made 
this discovery, he naturally felt justified in regarding himself as 
the aggrieved party; she took the same view of her situation, and 
their life was one of incessant recrimination. 
</p><p>Finally, after years spent in violent quarrels and short-lived 
reconciliations, the man grew weary, and decided to divorce his 
wife. 
</p><p>He engaged an able lawyer, who assured him that he would have 
no difficulty in obtaining a divorce; but to his surprise, the 
judge refused to grant it. 
</p><p>"But&mdash;" said the man, and he began to recapitulate his 
injuries. 
</p><p>"That's all very true," said the judge, "and nothing would be 
easier than for you to obtain a divorce if you had only married 
another person." 
</p><p>"What do you mean by another person?" asked the man in 
astonishment. 
</p><p>"Well," replied the judge, "it appears that you inadvertently 
married yourself; that is a union no court has the power to 
dissolve." 
</p><p>"Oh, said the man; and he was secretly glad, for in his heart 
he was already longing to make it up again with his wife. 
</p> 
</div1> 
<div1 type="chapter" n="9" id="d11"> 
<head>IX. 
</head> 
<p> 
There was once a gentleman who greatly disliked to assume any 
responsibility.  Being possessed of ample means and numerous poor 
relatives, he might have indulged a variety of tastes and even a 
few virtues; but since there is no occupation that does not bring 
a few cares in its train, this gentleman resolutely refrained from 
doing anything. 
</p><p>He ceased to visit his old mother, who lived in the country, 
because it made him nervous to catch the train; he subscribed to no 
charities because it was a bother to write the checks; he received 
no visits because he did not wish to be under the obligation of 
returning them; he invited no guests to stay with him, for fear of 
being bored before they left; he gave no presents because it was so 
troublesome to choose them; finally, he even gave up asking his 
friends to dine because it was such a nuisance to tell the cook 
that they were coming. 
</p><p>This gentleman took an honest pride in his complete detachment 
from the trivial importunities of life, and was never tired of 
ridiculing those who complained of the weight of their 
responsibilities, justly remarking that if they really wished to be 
their own masters they had only to follow his example. 
</p><p>One day, however, one of his servants carelessly left the 
front door open, and Death walked in unannounced, and begged the 
gentleman to come along as quickly as possible, as there were a 
good many more people to be called for that afternoon. 
</p><p>"But I can't," cried the gentleman, in dismay.  "I really 
can't, you know.  I&mdash;why, I've asked some people to dine with me 
this evening." 
</p><p>"That's a little too much," said Death.  And the devil carried 
the gentleman off in a big black bag. 
</p> 
</div1> 
<div1 type="chapter" n="10" id="d12"> 
<head>X. 
</head> 
<p> 
There was once a man who had seen the Parthenon, and he wished to 
build his god a temple like it. 
</p><p>But he was not a skilful man, and, try as he would, he could 
produce only a mud hut thatched with straw; and he sat down and 
wept because he could not build a temple for his god. 
</p><p>But one who passed by said to him: 
</p><p>"There are two worse plights than yours.  One is to have no 
god; the other is to build a mud hut and mistake it for the 
Parthenon." 
</p><p>                              <hi rend="italic">Edith Wharton.</hi> 
</p> 
 
</div1> 
</body> 
</text> 
</TEI.2> 
 
