<?xml version="1.0"?>

<?dlps id="WhaWars"?>
<?dlps page-images="none" figure-images="no"?>
<?dlps transcription="other"?>

<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/tei-p4/tei2.dtd" [
<!ENTITY % POSTKB "INCLUDE">
<!ENTITY % TEI.extensions.ent SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.ent">
<!ENTITY % TEI.extensions.dtd SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.dtd">
<!ENTITY % ISOnum SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/charent/iso-num.ent"> %ISOnum;
<!ENTITY % ISOpub SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/charent/iso-pub.ent"> %ISOpub;
 
]> 
<TEI.2 id="WhaWars"> 
<teiHeader type="migrated" creator="Etext">
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title type="main">Writing a War Story</title>
<title type="sort">writing a war story</title>
<author>Wharton, Edith, 1862-1937</author>
<respStmt>
<resp>Creation of machine-readable version:</resp> 
<name>Judy Boss</name> 
<resp>Conversion to TEI.2-conformant markup:</resp>  
<name>University of Virginia Library Electronic Text Center</name>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt> 
<extent>ca. <num type="kilobytes">33</num> kilobytes</extent> 
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>University of Virginia Library</publisher>
<pubPlace>Charlottesville, Virginia</pubPlace> 
<idno type="ETC">WhaWars</idno> 
<date value="1995">1995</date>
<availability status="public">
<p n="copyright">Copyright &copy; 1995 by the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia</p>
<p n="access">Publicly accessible</p>
</availability>
<idno type="uva-pid">uva-lib:476535</idno>
</publicationStmt>
<seriesStmt>
<title>University of Virginia Library, Text collection</title>
<idno type="uva-set">UVA-LIB-Text</idno>
</seriesStmt> 
<sourceDesc>
<biblFull>
<titleStmt>
<title type="main">Writing a War Story</title>
<title type="sort">writing a war story</title>
<author>Edith Wharton</author>
</titleStmt> 
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>Woman's Home Companion</publisher> 
<pubPlace>Springfield, Ohio</pubPlace> 
<date value="1919-09">Sept 1919</date>
</publicationStmt> 
<seriesStmt>
<p>46</p>
</seriesStmt> 
<notesStmt>
<note>
<p>Wharton, Edith.  "Writing a War Story."  <hi rend="italic">Woman's  
Home Companion</hi> 46 (Sept. 1919): 17-19.</p>
</note>
</notesStmt>
</biblFull>
</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc> 
<encodingDesc>
<projectDesc>
<p>Prepared for the University of Virginia Library Electronic Text Center</p>
</projectDesc> 
<editorialDecl>
<p>All quotation marks retained as data</p> 
<p>All unambiguous end-of-line hyphens have been removed, and the 
trailing part of a word has been joined to the preceding line.</p> 
<p id="ETC">Keywords in the header are a local Electronic Text Center scheme  
to aid in establishing analytical groupings</p>
</editorialDecl> 
<refsDecl>
<p>ID elements are given for each page element and are composed of the text's 
unique cryptogram and the given page number, as in AusEmma1 for page one of  
Jane Austen's Emma.</p>
</refsDecl>
</encodingDesc> 
<profileDesc>
<creation>
<date value="1919-09">September 1919</date>
</creation> 
<langUsage>
<language id="eng" usage="main">English</language>
</langUsage> 
<textClass>
<keywords>
<term>fiction</term>
<term>prose</term> 
<term>Women Writers</term>
</keywords>
</textClass>
</profileDesc> 
<revisionDesc>
<change>
<date value="1995-08">August 1995</date> 
<respStmt>
<resp>corrector</resp> 
<name>Jamie L Spriggs, Electronic Text Center, University of Virginia</name>
</respStmt> 
<item>Added header, Tagged with TEI.2-compatible SGML, Parsed against "teilite" dtd</item>
</change> 
<change>
<date value="2005-07">July 2005</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>Corrector</resp>
<name>Margaret Konkol</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Converted SGML to XML and fixed tagging.</item>
</change>
<change>
<date value="2007-09">September 2007</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>Migration</resp>
<name>Ethan Gruber, University of Virginia Library</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Converted XML markup from TEI Lite to uva-dl-tei (TEI P4 with local customizations).</item>
</change>
<change>
<date value="2008-01">January 2008</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>Migration</resp>
<name>Greg Murray, University of Virginia Library</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Programmatically updated TEI header markup (but not header content) for minimal compliance with current QA requirements.</item>
</change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader> 
 
<text id="d1">  

<body id="d2">
<div1 type="story" id="d3"><pb n="17"/>  
<head>Writing a War Story
<lb/> 
     <hi rend="italic">Pretty Miss Ivy Spang, author of "Vibrations," 
          dips into literature&mdash;and life</hi> 
<lb/> 
               By EDITH WHARTON 
<lb/> 
          ILLUSTRATED BY CHARLES E. CHAMBERS </head> 
 
<p>MISS IVY SPANG of Cornwall-on-Hudson had published a little volume 
of verse before the war. 
</p><p>It was called "Vibrations," and was preceded by a "Foreword" 
in which the author stated that she had yielded to the urgent 
request of "friends" in exposing her first-born to the public gaze.  
The public had not gazed very hard or very long, but the Cornwall-on-Hudson "News-Dispatch" had a flattering notice by the wife of 
the rector of St. Dunstan's (signed "Asterisk"), in which, while 
the somewhat unconventional sentiment of the poems was gently 
deprecated, a graceful and lady-like tribute was paid to the 
"brilliant daughter of one of our most prominent and influential 
citizens, who has voluntarily abandoned <hi rend="italic">the primrose way of 
pleasure</hi> to scale <hi rend="italic">the rugged heights of Parnassus."</hi> 
</p><p>Also, after sitting one evening next to him at a bohemian 
dinner in New York, Miss Spang was honored by an article by the 
editor of "Zig-zag," the new "Weekly Journal of Defiance," in which 
that gentleman hinted that there was more than she knew in Ivy 
Spang's poems, and that their esoteric significance showed that she 
was a <hi rend="italic">vers-librist</hi> in thought as well as in technique.  He 
added that they would "gain incommensurably in meaning" when she 
abandoned the superannuated habit of beginning each line with a 
capital letter. 
</p><p>The editor sent a heavily-marked copy to Miss Spang, who was 
immensely flattered, and felt that at last she had been understood.  
But nobody she knew read "Zig-zag," and nobody who read "Zig-zag" 
seemed to care to know her.  So nothing in particular resulted from 
this tribute to her genius. 
</p><p>Then the war came, and she forgot all about writing poetry. 
<lb/> 
</p><p>THE war was two years old, and she had been pouring tea once a week 
for a whole winter in a big Anglo-American hospital in Paris, when 
one day, as she was passing through a flower-edged court on her way 
to her ward, she heard one of the doctors say to a pale gentleman 
in civilian clothes and spectacles, "But I believe that pretty Miss 
Spang writes.  If you want an American contributor, why not ask 
her?"  And the next moment the pale gentleman had been introduced 
and, beaming anxiously at her through his spectacles, was urging 
her to contribute a rattling war story to "The Man-at-Arms," a 
monthly publication that was to bring joy to the wounded and 
disabled in British hospitals. 
</p><p>"A good rousing story, Miss Spang; a dash of sentiment of 
course, but nothing to depress or discourage.  I'm sure you catch 
my meaning?  A tragedy with a happy ending&mdash;that's about the idea.  
But I leave it to you; with your large experience of hospital work 
of course you know just what hits the poor fellows' taste.  Do you 
think you could have it ready for our first number?  And have you 
a portrait&mdash;if possible in nurse's dress&mdash;to publish with it?  The 
Queen of Norromania has promised us a poem, with a picture of 
herself giving the baby Crown Prince his morning tub.  We want the 
first number to be an 'actuality,' as the French say; all the 
articles written by people who've done the thing themselves, or 
seen it done.  You've been at the front, I suppose?  As far as 
Rheims, once?  That's capital!  Give us a good stirring trench 
story, with a Coming-Home scene to close with . . . a Christmas 
scene, if you can manage it, as we hope to be out in November.  
Yes&mdash;that's the very thing; and I'll try to get Sargent to do us 
the wounded V. C. coming back to the old home on Christmas Eve&mdash; 
snow effect." 
</p><p>It was lucky that Ivy Spang's leave was due about that time, 
for, devoted though she was to her patients, the tea she poured for 
them might have suffered from her absorption in her new task. 
</p><p>Was it any wonder that she took it seriously? 
</p><p>She, Ivy Spang, of Cornwall-on-Hudson, had been asked to write 
a war story for the opening number of "The Man-at-Arms," to which 
Queens and Archbishops and Field Marshals were to contribute poetry 
and photographs and patriotic sentiment in autograph!  And her 
full-length photograph in nurse's dress was to precede her prose; 
and in the table of contents she was to figure as "Ivy Spang, 
author of <hi rend="italic">Vibrations: A Book of Verse</hi>." 
</p><p>She was dizzy with triumph, and went off to hide her 
exultation in a quiet corner of Brittany, where she happened to 
have an old governess, who took her in and promised to defend at 
all costs the sacredness of her mornings&mdash;for Ivy knew that the 
morning hours of great authors were always "sacred." 
</p><p>She shut herself up in her room with a ream of mauve paper, 
and began to think. 
</p><p>At first the process was less exhilarating than she had 
expected.  She knew so much about the war that she hardly knew 
where to begin; she found herself suffering from a plethora of 
impressions. 
</p><p>Moreover, the more she thought of the matter, the less she 
seemed to understand how a war story&mdash;or any story, for that 
matter&mdash;was written.  Why did stories ever begin, and why did they 
ever leave off?  Life didn't&mdash;it just went on and on. 
</p><p>This unforeseen problem troubled her exceedingly, and on the 
second morning she stealthily broke from her seclusion and slipped 
out for a walk on the beach.  She had been ashamed to make known 
her projected escapade, and went alone, leaving her faithful 
governess to mount guard on her threshold while she sneaked out by 
a back way. 
</p><p>There were plenty of people on the beach, and among them some 
whom she knew; but she dared not join them lest they should 
frighten away her "Inspiration."  She knew that "Inspirations" were 
fussy and contrarious, and she felt rather as if she were dragging 
along a reluctant dog on a string. 
</p><p>"If you wanted to stay indoors, why didn't you say so?" she 
grumbled to it.  But the inspiration continued to sulk. 
</p><p>She wandered about under the cliff till she came to an empty 
bench, where she sat down and gazed at the sea.  After a while her 
eyes were dazzled by the light, and she turned them toward the 
bench and saw lying on it a battered magazine&mdash;the midsummer "All-Story" number of "Fact and Fiction."  Ivy pounced upon it. 
</p><p>She had heard a good deal about not allowing one's self to be 
"influenced," about jealously guarding one's originality, and so 
forth; the editor of "Zig-zag" had been particularly strong on that 
theme.  But her story had to be written, and she didn't know how to 
begin it; so she decided just to glance casually at a few 
beginnings. 
</p><p>The first tale in the magazine was signed by a name great in 
fiction, one of the most famous names of the past generation of 
novelists.  "The opening sentence ran: "In the month of October, 
1914&mdash;" and Ivy turned the page impatiently.  She may not have 
known much about story-writing, but she did know that <hi rend="italic">that</hi> 
kind of a beginning was played out.  She turned to the next. 
</p><p>"'My God!' roared the engineer, tightening his grasp on the 
lever, while the white, sneering face under the red lamp . . ." 
</p><p>No; that was beginning to be out of date, too. 
</p><p>"They sat there and stared at it in silence.  Neither spoke; 
but the woman's heart ticked like a watch." 
</p><p>That was better; but best of all she liked: "Lee Lorimer 
leaned to him across the flowers.  She had always known that this 
was coming . . ."  Ivy could imagine tying a story on to 
<hi rend="italic">that</hi>. 
</p><p>But she had promised to write a war story; and in a war story 
the flowers must be at the end and not at the beginning. 
</p><p>At any rate, there was one clear conclusion to be drawn from 
the successive study of all these opening paragraphs; and that was 
that you must begin in the middle, and take for granted that your 
reader knew what you were talking about. <pb n="18"/>  [illustration 
omitted] 
</p><p>Yes; but where was the middle, and how could your reader know 
what you were talking about when you didn't know yourself? 
</p><p>After some reflection, and more furtive scrutiny of "Fact and 
Fiction," the puzzled authoress decided that perhaps, if you 
pretended hard enough that you knew what your story was about, you 
might end by finding out toward the last page.  "After all, if the 
reader can pretend, the author ought to be able to," she reflected.  
And she decided (after a cautious glance over her shoulder) to 
steal the magazine and take it home with her for private 
dissection. 
</p><p>On the threshold she met her governess, who beamed on her 
tenderly. 
</p><p>"Cherie, I saw you slip off, but I didn't follow.  I knew you 
wanted to be alone with your inspiration."  Mademoiselle lowered 
her voice to add: "Have you found your plot?" 
</p><p>Ivy tapped her gently on the wrinkled cheek.  "Dear old Madsy!  
People don't bother with plots nowadays." 
</p><p>"Oh, don't they, darling?  Then it must be very much easier," 
said Mademoiselle.  But Ivy was not so sure&mdash; 
</p><p>After a day's brooding over "Fact and Fiction," she decided to 
begin on the empiric system.  ("It's sure to come to me as I go 
along," she thought.)  So she sat down before the mauve paper and 
wrote "A shot rang out&mdash;" 
</p><p>But just as she was appealing to her Inspiration to suggest 
the next phrase a horrible doubt assailed her, and she got up and 
turned to "Fact and Fiction."  Yes, it was just as she had feared, 
the last story in "Fact and Fiction" began: "A shot rang out&mdash;" 
</p><p>Its place on the list showed what the editor and his public 
thought of that kind of an opening, and her contempt for it was 
increased by reading the author's name.  The story was signed "Edda 
Clubber Hump."  Poor thing! <pb n="19"/>  
</p><p>Ivy sat down and gazed at the page which she had polluted with 
that silly sentence. 
</p><p>And now (as they often said in "Fact and Fiction") a strange 
thing happened.  The sentence was there&mdash;she had written it&mdash;it was 
the first sentence on the first page of her story, it <hi rend="italic">was</hi> 
the first sentence of her story.  It was there, it had gone out of 
her, got away from her, and she seemed to have no further control 
of it.  She could imagine no other way of beginning, now that she 
had made the effort of beginning in that way. 
</p><p>She supposed that was what authors meant when they talked 
about being "mastered by their Inspiration."  She began to hate her 
Inspiration. 
<lb/> 
</p><p>ON THE fifth day an abased and dejected Ivy confided to her old 
governess that she didn't believe she knew how to write a short 
story. 
</p><p>"If they'd only asked me for poetry!" she wailed. 
</p><p>She wrote to the editor of "The Man-at-Arms," begging for 
permission to substitute a sonnet; but he replied firmly, if 
flatteringly, that they counted on a story, and had measured their 
space accordingly&mdash;adding that they already had rather more poetry 
than the first number could hold.  He concluded by reminding her 
that he counted on receiving her contribution not later than 
September first; and it was now the tenth of August. 
</p><p>"It's all so sudden," she murmured to Mademoiselle, as if she 
were announcing her engagement. 
</p><p>"Of course, dearest&mdash;of course!  I quite understand.  How 
could the editor expect you to be tied to a date?  But so few 
people know what the artistic temperament is; they seem to think 
one can dash off a story as easily as one makes an omelet." 
</p><p>Ivy smiled in spite of herself.  "Dear Madsy, what an unlucky 
simile!  So few people make good omelets." 
</p><p>"Not in France," said Mademoiselle firmly. 
</p><p>Her former pupil reflected.  "In France a good many people 
have written good short stories, too&mdash;but I'm sure they were given 
more than three weeks to learn how.  Oh, what shall I do?" she 
groaned. 
</p><p>The two pondered long and anxiously; and at last the governess 
modestly suggested: "Supposing you were to begin by thinking of a 
subject?" 
</p><p>"Oh, my dear, the subject's nothing!" exclaimed Ivy, 
remembering some contemptuous statement to that effect by the 
editor of "Zig-zag." 
</p><p>"Still&mdash;in writing a story, one has to have a subject.  Of 
course I know it's only the treatment that really matters; but the 
treatment, naturally, would be yours, quite yours. . . ." 
</p><p>The authoress lifted a troubled gaze upon her Mentor.  "What 
are you driving at, Madsy?" 
</p><p>"Only that during my year's work in the hospital here I picked 
up a good many stories&mdash;pathetic, thrilling, moving stories of our 
poor poilus; and in the evening sometimes I used to jot them down, 
just as the soldiers told them to me&mdash;oh, without any art at all . 
. . simply for myself, you understand. . . ." 
</p><p>Ivy was on her feet in an instant.  Since even Mademoiselle 
admitted that "only the treatment really mattered," why should she 
not seize on one of these artless tales and transform it into 
Literature?  The more she considered the idea, the more it appealed 
to her; she remembered Shakespeare and Moliere, and said gayly to 
her governess: "You darling Madsy!  Do lend me your book to look 
over&mdash;and we'll be collaborators!" 
</p><p>"Oh&mdash;collaborators!" blushed the governess, overcome.  But she 
finally yielded to her charge's affectionate insistence, and 
brought out her shabby copybook, which began with lecture notes on 
Mr. Bergson's course at the Sorbonne in 1913, and suddenly switched 
off to "Military Hospital No. 13.  November, 1914.  Long talk with 
the Chasseur Alpin Emile Durand, wounded through the knee and the 
left lung at the Hautes Chaumes.  I have decided to write down his 
story. . . ." 
</p><p>Ivy carried the little book off to bed with her, inwardly 
smiling at the fact that the narrative, written in a close, 
tremulous hand, covered each side of the page, and poured on and on 
without a paragraph&mdash;a good deal like life.  Decidedly, poor 
Mademoiselle did not even know the rudiments of literature! 
<lb/> 
</p><p>THE story, not without effort, gradually built itself up about the 
adventures of Emile Durand.  Notwithstanding her protests, 
Mademoiselle, after a day or two, found herself called upon in an 
advisory capacity, and finally as a collaborator.  She gave the 
tale a certain consecutiveness, and kept Ivy to the main point when 
her pupil showed a tendency to wander; but she carefully revised 
and polished the rustic speech in which she had originally 
transcribed the tale, so that it finally issued forth in the 
language that a young lady writing a composition on the Battle of 
Hastings would have used in Mademoiselle's school days. 
</p><p>Ivy decided to add a touch of sentiment to the anecdote, which 
was purely military, both because she knew the reader was entitled 
to a certain proportion of "heart interest," and because she wished 
to make the subject her own by this original addition.  The 
revisions and transpositions which these changes necessitated made 
the work one of uncommon difficulty; and one day, in a fit of 
discouragement, Ivy privately decided to notify the editor of "The 
Man-at-Arms" that she was ill and could not fulfill her engagement. 
</p><p>But that very afternoon the "artistic" photographer to whom 
she had posed for her portrait sent home the proofs; and she saw 
herself, exceedingly long, narrow and sinuous, robed in white and 
monastically veiled, holding out a refreshing beverage to an 
invisible sufferer with a gesture half way between Melisande 
lowering her braid over the balcony and Florence Nightingale 
advancing with the lamp. 
</p><p>The photograph was really too charming to be wasted, and Ivy, 
feeling herself forced onward by an inexorable fate, sat down again 
to battle with the art of fiction.  Her perseverance was rewarded, 
and after a while the fellow authors (though Mademoiselle 
disclaimed any right to the honors of literary partnership) arrived 
at what seemed to both a satisfactory result. 
</p><p>"You've written a very beautiful story, my dear," Mademoiselle 
sighed with moist eyes; and Ivy modestly agreed that she had. 
</p><p>The task was finished on the last day of her leave; and the 
next morning she traveled back to Paris, clutching the manuscript 
to her bosom, and forgetting to keep an eye on the bag that 
contained her passport and money, in her terror lest the precious 
pages should be stolen. 
</p><p>As soon as the tale was typed she did it up in a heavily-sealed envelope (she knew that only silly girls used blue ribbon 
for the purpose), and dispatched it to the pale gentleman in 
spectacles, accompanied by the Melisande-Nightingale photograph.  
The receipt of both was acknowledged by a courteous note (she had 
secretly hoped for more enthusiasm), and thereafter life became a 
desert waste of suspense.  The very globe seemed to cease to turn 
on its axis while she waited for "The Man-at-Arms" to appear. 
</p><p>Finally one day a thick packet bearing an English publisher's 
name was brought to her: she undid it with trembling fingers, and 
there, beautifully printed on the large rough pages, her story 
stood out before her. 
</p><p>At first, in that heavy text, on those heavy pages, it seemed 
to her a pitifully small thing, hopelessly insignificant and yet 
pitilessly conspicuous.  It was as though words meant to be 
murmured to sympathetic friends were being megaphoned into the ear 
of a heedless universe. 
</p><p>Then she began to turn the pages of the review: she analyzed 
the poems, she read the Queen of Norromania's domestic confidences, 
and she looked at the portraits of the authors.  The latter 
experience was peculiarly comforting.  The Queen was rather good-looking&mdash;for a Queen&mdash;but her hair was drawn back from the temples 
as if it were wound round a windlass, and stuck out over her 
forehead in the good old-fashioned Royal Highness fuzz; and her 
prose was oddly built out of London drawing-room phrases grafted 
onto German genitives and datives.  It was evident that neither 
Ivy's portrait nor her story would suffer by comparison with the 
royal contribution. 
</p><p>But most of all was she comforted by the poems.  They were 
nearly all written on Kipling rhythms that broke down after two or 
three wheezy attempts to "carry on," and their knowing mixture of 
slang and pathos seemed oddly old-fashioned to the author of 
"Vibrations."  Altogether, it struck her that "The Man-at-Arms" was 
made up in equal parts of tired compositions by people who knew how 
to write, and artless prattle by people who didn't.  Against such 
a background "His Letter Home" began to loom up rather large. 
</p><p>At any rate, it took such a place in her consciousness for the 
next day or two that it was bewildering to find that no one about 
her seemed to have heard of it.  "The Man-at-Arms" was 
conspicuously shown in the windows of the principal English and 
American book shops, but she failed to see it lying on her friends' 
tables, and finally, when her tea-pouring day came round, she 
bought a dozen copies and took them up to the English ward of her 
hospital, which happened to be full at the time. 
<lb/> 
</p><p>IT WAS not long before Christmas, and the men and officers were 
rather busy with home correspondence and the undoing and doing-up 
of seasonable parcels; but they all received "The Man-at-Arms" with 
an appreciative smile, and were most awfully pleased to know that 
Miss Spang had written something in it.  After the distribution of 
her tale Miss Spang became suddenly hot and shy, and slipped away 
before they had begun to read her. 
</p><p>The intervening week seemed long; and it was marked only by 
the appearance of a review of "The Man-at-Arms" in the "Times"&mdash;a 
long and laudatory article&mdash;in which, by some odd accident, "His 
Letter Home" and its author were not so much as mentioned.  
Abridged versions of this notice appeared in the English and 
American newspapers published in Paris, and one anecdotic and 
intimate article in a French journal celebrated the maternal graces 
and literary art of the Queen of Norromania.  It was signed "Fleur-de-Lys," and described a banquet at the Court of Norromania at 
which the writer hinted that she had assisted. 
</p><p>The following week, Ivy reentered her ward with a beating 
heart.  On the threshold one of the nurses detained her with a 
smile. 
</p><p>"Do be a dear and make yourself specially nice to the new 
officer in Number 5; he's only been here two days, and he's rather 
down on his luck.  Oh, by the way&mdash;he's the novelist, Harold 
Harbard; you know, the man who wrote the book they made such a fuss 
about." 
</p><p>Harold Harbard&mdash;the book they made such a fuss about!  What a 
poor fool the woman was&mdash;not even to remember the title of "Broken 
Wings!"  Ivy's heart stood still with the shock of the discovery; 
she remembered that she had left a copy of "The Man-at-Arms" in 
Number 5, and the blood coursed through her veins and flooded her 
to the forehead at the idea that Harold Harbard might at that very 
moment be reading "His Letter Home." 
</p><p>To collect herself, she decided to remain a while in the ward, 
serving tea to the soldiers and N. C. O.'s before venturing into 
Number 5, which the previous week had been occupied only by a polo-player drowsy with chloroform and uninterested in anything but his 
specialty.  Think of Harold Harbard lying in the bed next to that 
man! 
</p><p>Ivy passed into the ward, and as she glanced down the long 
line of beds she saw several copies of "The Man-at-Arms" lying on 
them, and one special favorite of hers, a young lance-corporal, 
deep in its pages. 
</p><p>She walked down the ward, distributing tea and greetings; and 
she saw that her patients were all very glad to see her.  They 
always were; but this time there was a certain unmistakable 
emphasis in their gladness; and she fancied they wanted her to 
notice it. 
</p><p>"Why," she cried gayly, "how uncommonly cheerful you all 
look!" 
</p><p>She was handing his tea to the young lance-corporal, who was 
usually the spokesman of the ward on momentous occasions.  He 
lifted his eyes from the absorbed perusal of "The Man-at-Arms," and 
as he did so she saw that it was open at the first page of her 
story. 
</p><p>"I say, you know," he said, "it's simply topping&mdash;and we're so 
awfully obliged to you for letting us see it." 
</p><p>She laughed, but would not affect incomprehension. 
</p><p>"That?"  She laid a light finger on the review.  "Oh, I'm 
glad&mdash;I'm awfully pleased, of course&mdash;you <hi rend="italic">do</hi> really like 
it?" she stammered. 
</p><p>"Rather&mdash;all of us&mdash;most tremendously&mdash;!" came a chorus from 
the long line of beds. 
</p><p>Ivy tasted her highest moment of triumph.  She drew a deep 
breath and shone on them with glowing cheeks. 
</p><p>"There couldn't be higher praise . . . there couldn't be 
better judges. . . .  You think it's really like, do you?" 
</p><p>"Really like?  Rather!  It's just topping," rand out the 
unanimous response. 
</p><p>She choked with emotion.  "Coming from you&mdash;from all of you&mdash; 
it makes me most awfully glad." 
</p><p>They all laughed together shyly, and then the lance-corporal 
spoke up. 
</p><p>"We admire it so much that we're going to ask you a most 
tremendous favor&mdash;" 
</p><p>"Oh, yes," came from the other beds. 
</p><p>"A favor&mdash;?" 
</p><p>"Yes; if it's not too much."  The lance-corporal became 
eloquent.  "To remember you by, and all your kindness; we want to 
know if you won't give one to each of us&mdash;" 
</p><p>("Why, of course, of course," Ivy glowed.) 
</p><p>"&mdash;to frame and take away with us," the lance-corporal 
continued sentimentally.  "There's a chap here who makes rather 
jolly frames out of Vichy corks." 
</p><p>"Oh&mdash;" said Ivy, with a protracted gasp. 
</p><p>"You see, in your nurse's dress, it'll always be such a jolly 
reminder," said the lance-corporal, concluding his lesson. 
</p><p>"I never saw a jollier photo," spoke up a bold spirit. 
</p><p>"Oh, do say yes, nurse," the shyest of the patients softly 
whispered; and Ivy, bewildered between tears and laughter, said, 
"Yes." 
</p><p>It was evident that not one of them had read her story. 
<lb/> 
</p><p>SHE stopped on the threshold of Number 5, her heart beating 
uncomfortably. 
</p><p>She had already recovered from her passing mortification: it 
was absurd to have imagined that the inmates of the ward, dear, 
gallant young fellows, would feel the subtle meaning of a story 
like "His Letter Home."  But with Harold Harbard it was different.  
Now, indeed, she was to be face to face with a critic. 
</p><p>She stopped on the threshold, and as she did so she heard a 
burst of hearty, healthy laughter from within.  It was not the 
voice of the polo-player; could it be that of the novelist? 
</p><p>She opened the door resolutely and walked in with her tray.  
The polo-player's bed was empty, and the face on the pillow of the 
adjoining cot was the brown, ugly, tumultuous-locked head of Harold 
Harbard, well-known to her from frequent photographs in the 
literary weeklies.  He looked up as she came in, and said in a 
voice that seemed to continue his laugh: "Tea?  Come, that's 
something like!"  And he began to laugh again. 
</p><p>It was evident that he was still carrying on the thread of his 
joke, and as she approached with the tea she saw that a copy of 
"The Man-at-Arms" lay on the bed at his side, and that he had his 
hand between the open pages. 
</p><p>Her heart gave an apprehensive twitch, but she determined to 
carry off the situation with a high hand. 
</p><p>"How do you do, Captain Harbard?  I suppose you're laughing at 
the way the Queen of Norromania's hair is done." 
</p><p>He met her glance with a humorous look, and shook his head, 
while the laughter still rippled the muscles of his throat. 
</p><p>"No&mdash;no; I've finished laughing at that.  It was the next 
thing; what's it called?  'His Letter Home,' by&mdash;"  The review 
dropped abruptly from his hands, his brown cheek paled, and he 
fixed her with a stricken stare. 
</p><p>"Good lord," he stammered out, "but it's <hi rend="italic">you!"</hi> 
</p><p>She blushed all colors, and dropped into a seat at his side.  
"After all," she faltered, half-laughing too, "at least you read 
the story instead of looking at my photograph." 
</p><p>He continued to scrutinize her with a reviving eye.  "Why&mdash;do 
you mean that everybody else&mdash;" 
</p><p>"All the ward over there," she assented, nodding in the 
direction of the door. 
</p><p>"They all forgot to read the story for gazing at its author?" 
</p><p>"Apparently."  There was a painful pause.  The review dropped 
from his lax hand. 
</p><p>"Your tea&mdash;?" she suggested, stiffly. 
</p><p>"Oh, yes; to be sure. . . .  Thanks." 
<lb/> 
</p><p>THERE was another silence, during which the act of pouring out the 
milk, and the dropping of the sugar into the cup, seemed to assume 
enormous magnitude, and make an echoing noise.  At length Ivy said, 
with an effort at lightness, "Since I know who you are, Mr. 
Harbard,&mdash;would you mind telling me what you were laughing at in my 
story?" 
</p><p>He leaned back against the pillows and wrinkled his forehead 
anxiously. 
</p><p>"My dear Miss Spang, not in the least&mdash;if I <hi rend="italic">could</hi>." 
</p><p>"If you could?" 
</p><p>"Yes; I mean in any understandable way." 
</p><p>"In other words, you think it so silly that you don't dare to 
tell me anything more?" 
</p><p>He shook his head.  "No; but it's queer&mdash;it's puzzling.  
You've got hold of a wonderfully good subject: and that's the main 
thing, of course&mdash;" 
</p><p>Ivy interrupted him eagerly.  "The subject is the main thing?" 
</p><p>"Why, naturally; it's only the people without invention who 
tell you it isn't." 
</p><p>"Oh," she gasped, trying to readjust her carefully acquired 
theory of esthetics. 
</p><p>"You've got hold of an awfully good subject," Harbard 
continued; "but you've rather mauled it, haven't you?" 
</p><p>She sat before him with her head drooping, and the blood 
running back from her pale cheeks.  Two tears had gathered on her 
lashes. 
</p><p>"There!" the novelist cried out irritably.  "I knew that as 
soon as I was frank you'd resent it!  What was the earthly use of 
asking me?" 
</p><p>She made no answer, and he added, lowering his voice a little, 
"Are you very angry with me, really?" 
</p><p>"No, of course not," she declared with a stony gayety. 
</p><p>"I'm so glad you're not; because I do want most awfully to ask 
you for one of these photographs," he concluded. 
</p><p>She rose abruptly from her seat.  To save her life she could 
not conceal her disappointment.  But she picked up the tray with 
feverish animation. 
</p><p>"A photograph?  Of course&mdash;with pleasure.  And now, if you've 
quite finished.  I'm afraid I must run back to my teapot." 
</p><p>Harold Harbard lay on the bed and looked at her.  As she 
reached the door he said, "Miss Spang!" 
</p><p>"Yes?" she rejoined, pausing reluctantly. 
</p><p>"You were angry just now because I didn't admire your story; 
and now you're angrier still because I do admire your photograph.  
Do you wonder that we novelists find such an inexhaustible field in 
Woman?" 
</p> 
</div1> 
 
 
</body> 
</text> 
</TEI.2> 
 
 
