<?xml version="1.0"?>

<?dlps id="WilRevo"?>
<?dlps page-images="none" figure-images="no"?>
<?dlps transcription="other"?>

<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/tei-p4/tei2.dtd" [
<!ENTITY % POSTKB "INCLUDE">
<!ENTITY % TEI.extensions.ent SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.ent">
<!ENTITY % TEI.extensions.dtd SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.dtd">
<!ENTITY % ISOnum SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/charent/iso-num.ent"> %ISOnum;
<!ENTITY % ISOpub SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/charent/iso-pub.ent"> %ISOpub;
]>

<TEI.2 id="WilRevo">
<teiHeader type="migrated" creator="Etext">
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title type="main">"The Revolt of 'Mother.'"</title>
<title type="sort">the revolt of mother</title>
<author>Wilkins, Mary E.</author>
<respStmt>
<resp>Creation of machine-readable version:</resp>
<name>Judy Boss</name>
<resp>Conversion to TEI.2-conformant markup:</resp> 
<name>University of Virginia Library Electronic Text Center</name>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt>
<extent>ca. <num type="kilobytes">39</num> kilobytes</extent>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>University of Virginia Library</publisher>
<pubPlace>Charlottesville, Virginia</pubPlace>
<idno type="ETC">WilRevo</idno>
<date value="1995">1995</date>
<availability status="public">
<p n="copyright">Copyright &copy; 1995 by the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia</p>
<p n="access">Publicly accessible</p>
</availability>
<idno type="uva-pid">uva-lib:476553</idno>
</publicationStmt>
<seriesStmt>
<title>University of Virginia Library, Text collection</title>
<idno type="uva-set">UVA-LIB-Text</idno>
</seriesStmt>
<sourceDesc>
<biblFull>
<titleStmt>
<title type="main">The Revolt of "Mother"</title>
<title type="sort">revolt of mother</title>
<author>Mary E. Wilkins</author>
</titleStmt>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>Harper &amp; Brothers, Publishers</publisher>
<pubPlace>327 to 335 Pearl Street, Franklin Square, New York</pubPlace>
<date value="1890">1890</date>
</publicationStmt>
<seriesStmt>
<p>
<hi rend="italic">Harper's New Monthly Magazine</hi>
</p>
</seriesStmt>
<notesStmt>
<note>
<p>Vol. 81 (Sept. 1890): 553-561.</p>
</note>
</notesStmt>
</biblFull>
</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc>
<encodingDesc>
<projectDesc>
<p>Prepared for the University of Virginia Library Electronic Text Center</p>
</projectDesc>
<editorialDecl>
<p>All quotation marks retained as data</p>
<p>Spell-check and verification made 
against printed text using WordPerfect spell checker</p> 
<p>All unambiguous end-of-line hyphens have been removed, and the 
trailing part of a word has been joined to the preceding line.</p> 
<p id="ETC">Keywords in the header are a local Electronic Text Center scheme  
to aid in establishing analytical groupings</p>
</editorialDecl> 
<refsDecl>
<p>ID elements are given for each page element and are composed of the text's 
unique cryptogram and the given page number, as in AusEmma1 for page one of  
Jane Austen's Emma.</p>
</refsDecl>
</encodingDesc> 
<profileDesc>
<creation>
<date value="1890">1890</date>
</creation> 
<langUsage>
<language id="eng" usage="main">English</language>
</langUsage> 
<textClass>
<keywords>
<term>fiction, prose</term> 
<term>Women Writers</term>
</keywords>
</textClass>
</profileDesc> 
<revisionDesc>
<change>
<date value="1995-08">August 1995</date> 
<respStmt>
<resp>corrector</resp> 
<name>Lorrie S. Chisholm, Electronic Text Center, University of 
Virginia Library System.</name>
</respStmt> 
<item>General Tei tagging, removed unambiguous line-end 
hyphenation and ran electronic spell-check using wp51.</item>
</change> 
<change>
<date value="2005-07">July 2005</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>Corrector</resp>
<name>Margaret Konkol</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Converted SGML to XML and fixed tagging.</item>
</change>
<change>
<date value="2007-09">September 2007</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>Migration</resp>
<name>Ethan Gruber, University of Virginia Library</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Converted XML markup from TEI Lite to uva-dl-tei (TEI P4 with local customizations).</item>
</change>
<change>
<date value="2008-01">January 2008</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>Migration</resp>
<name>Greg Murray, University of Virginia Library</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Programmatically updated TEI header markup (but not header content) for minimal compliance with current QA requirements.</item>
</change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader> 
 
<text id="d1">  
<body id="d2"> 
 
 
<div1 type="article" id="d3"> 
<head>THE REVOLT OF "MOTHER."
<lb/> 
BY MARY E. WILKINS.</head> <pb n="553"/> 
 
<p>"FATHER!" 
</p><p>"What is it?" 
</p><p>"What are them men diggin' over there in the field for?" 
</p><p>There was a sudden dropping and enlarging of the lower part of 
the old man's face, as if some heavy weight had settled therein; he 
shut his mouth tight, and went on harnessing the great bay mare.  
He hustled the collar on to her neck with a jerk. 
</p><p>"Father!" 
</p><p>The old man slapped the saddle upon the mare's back. 
</p><p>"Look here, father, I want to know what them men are diggin' 
over in the field for, an' I'm goin' to know." 
</p><p>"I wish you'd go into the house, mother, an' 'tend to your own 
affairs," the old man said then.  He ran his words together, and 
his speech was almost as inarticulate as a growl. 
</p><p>But the woman understood; it was her most native tongue.  "I 
ain't goin' into the house till you tell me what them men are doin' 
over there in the field," said she. 
</p><p>Then she stood waiting.  She was a small woman, short and 
straight-waisted like a child in her brown cotton gown.  Her 
forehead was mild and benevolent between the smooth curves of gray 
hair; there were meek downward lines about her nose and mouth; but 
her eyes, fixed upon the old man, looked as if the meekness had 
been the result of her own will, never of the will of another. 
</p><p>They were in the barn, standing before the wide open doors.  
The spring air, full of the smell of growing grass and unseen 
blossoms, came in their faces.  The deep yard in front was littered 
with farm wagons and piles of wood; on the edges, close to the 
fence and the house, the grass was a vivid green, and there were 
some dandelions. 
</p><p>The old man glanced doggedly at his wife as he tightened the 
last buckles on the harness.  She looked as immovable to him as one 
of the rocks in his pastureland, bound to the earth with 
generations of blackberry vines.  He slapped the reins over the 
horse, and started forth from the barn. 
</p><p><hi rend="italic">"Father!</hi> said she. 
</p><p>The old man pulled up.  "What is it?" 
</p><p>"I want to know what them men are diggin' over there in that 
field for." 
</p><p>"They're diggin' a cellar, I s'pose, if you've got to know." 
</p><p>"A cellar for what?" 
</p><p>"A barn." 
</p><p>"A barn?  You ain't goin' to build a barn over there where we 
was goin' to have a house, father?" 
</p><p>The old man said not another word.  He hurried the horse into 
the farm wagon, and clattered out of the yard, jouncing as sturdily 
on his seat as a boy. 
</p><p>The woman stood a moment looking after him, then she went out 
of the barn across a corner of the yard to the house.  The house, 
standing at right angles with  
 
<pb n="554"/>  
 the great barn and a long 
reach of sheds and out-buildings, was infinitesimal compared with 
them.  It was scarcely as commodious for people as the little boxes 
under the barn eaves were for doves. 
</p><p>A pretty girl's face, pink and delicate as a flower, was 
looking out of one of the house windows.  She was watching three 
men who were digging over in the field which bounded the yard near 
the road line.  She turned quietly when the woman entered. 
</p><p>"What are they diggin' for, mother?" said she.  "Did he tell 
you?" 
</p><p>"They're diggin' for&mdash;a cellar for a new barn." 
</p><p>"Oh, mother, he ain't goin' to build another barn?" 
</p><p>"That's what he says." 
</p><p>A boy stood before the kitchen glass combing his hair.  He 
combed slowly and painstakingly, arranging his brown hair in a 
smooth hillock over his forehead.  He did not seem to pay any 
attention to the conversation. 
</p><p>"Sammy, did you know father was goin' to build a new barn?" 
asked the girl. 
</p><p>The boy combed assiduously. 
</p><p>"Sammy!" 
</p><p>He turned, and showed a face like his father's under his 
smooth crest of hair.  "Yes, I s'pose I did," he said, reluctantly. 
</p><p>"How long have you known it?" asked his mother. 
</p><p>"'Bout three months, I guess." 
</p><p>"Why didn't you tell of it?" 
</p><p>"Didn't think 'twould do no good." 
</p><p>"I don't see what father wants another barn for," said the 
girl, in her sweet slow voice.  She turned again to the window, and 
stared out at the digging men in the field.  Her tender sweet face 
was full of a gentle distress.  Her forehead was as bald and 
innocent as a baby's, with the light hair strained back from it in 
a row of curl-papers.  She was quite large, but her soft curves did 
not look as if they covered muscles. 
</p><p>Her mother looked sternly at the boy.  "Is he goin' to buy 
more cows?" said she. 
</p><p>The boy did not reply; he was tying his shoes. 
</p><p>"Sammy, I want you to tell me if he's goin' to buy more cows." 
</p><p>"I s'pose he is." 
</p><p>"How many?" 
</p><p>"Four, I guess." 
</p><p>His mother said nothing more.  She went into the pantry, and 
there was a clatter of dishes.  The boy got his cap from a nail 
behind the door, took an old arithmetic from the shelf, and started 
for school.  He was lightly built, but clumsy.  He went out of the 
yard with a curious spring in the hips, that made his loose homemade  
jacket tilt up in the rear. 
</p><p>The girl went to the sink, and began to wash the dishes that 
were piled up there.  Her mother came promptly out of the pantry, 
and shoved her aside.  "You wipe 'em," said she; "I'll wash.  
There's a good many this mornin'." 
</p><p>The mother plunged her hands vigorously into the water, the 
girl wiped the plates slowly and dreamily.  "Mother," said she, 
"don't you think it's too bad father's goin' to build that new 
barn, much as we need a decent house to live in?" 
</p><p>Her mother scrubbed a dish fiercely.  "You 'ain't found out 
yet we're women-folks, Nanny Penn," said she.  "You 'ain't seen 
enough of men-folks yet to.  One of these days you'll find it out, 
an' then you'll know that we know only what men-folks think we do, 
so far as any use of it goes, an' how we'd ought to reckon men-folks in with Providence an' not complain of what they do any more 
than we do of the weather." 
</p><p>"I don't care; I don't believe George is anything like that, 
anyhow," said Nanny.  Her delicate face flushed pink, her lips 
pouted softly, as if she were going to cry. 
</p><p>"You wait an' see.  I guess George Eastman ain't no better 
than other men.  You hadn't ought to judge father, though.  He 
can't help it, 'cause he don't look at things jest the way we do.  
An' we've been pretty comfortable here, after all.  The roof don't 
leak&mdash;'ain't never but once&mdash;that's one thing.  Father kept it 
shingled right up." 
</p><p>"I do wish we had a parlor." 
</p><p>"I guess it won't hurt George Eastman any to come to see you 
in a nice clean kitchen.  I guess a good many girls don't have as 
good a place as this.  Nobody's ever heard me complain." 
</p><p>"I 'ain't complained either, mother." 
</p><p>"Well, I don't think you'd better, a good father an' a good 
home as you've got.  S'pose your father made you go out an' work 
for your livin'?  Lots of girls have to that ain't no stronger an' 
better able to than you be." 
</p><p>Sarah Penn washed the frying-pan with  
 
<pb n="555"/>  
 a conclusive 
air.  She scrubbed the outside of it as faithfully as the inside.  
She was a masterly keeper of her box of a house.  Her one livingroom  
never seemed to have in it any of the dust which the friction 
of life with inanimate matter produces.  She swept, and there 
seemed to be no dirt to go before the broom; she cleaned, and one 
could see no difference.  She was like an artist so perfect that he 
has apparently no art.  To-day she got out a mixing bowl and a 
board, and rolled some pies, and there was no more flour upon her 
than upon her daughter who was doing finer work.  Nanny was to be 
married in the fall, and she was sewing on some white cambric and 
embroidery.  She sewed industriously while her mother cooked, her 
soft milk-white hands and wrists showed whiter than her delicate 
work. 
</p><p>"We must have the stove moved out in the shed before long," 
said Mrs. Penn.  "Talk about not havin' things, it's been a real 
blessin' to be able to put a stove up in that shed in hot weather.  
Father did one good thing when he fixed that stove-pipe out there." 
</p><p>Sarah Penn's face as she rolled her pies had that expression 
of meek vigor which might have characterized one of the New 
Testament saints.  She was making mince-pies.  Her husband, 
Adoniram Penn, liked them better than any other kind.  She baked 
twice a week.  Adoniram often liked a piece of pie between meals.  
She hurried this morning.  It had been later than usual when she 
began, and she wanted to have a pie baked for dinner.  However deep 
a resentment she might be forced to hold against her husband, she 
would never fail in sedulous attention to his wants. 
</p><p>Nobility of character manifests itself at loop-holes when it 
is not provided with large doors.  Sarah Penn's showed itself today  
in flaky dishes of pastry.  So she made the pies faithfully, 
while across the table she could see, when she glanced up from her 
work, the sight that rankled in her patient and steadfast soul&mdash;the 
digging of the cellar of the new barn in the place where Adoniram 
forty years ago had promised her their new house should stand. 
</p><p>The pies were done for dinner.  Adoniram and Sammy were home 
a few minutes after twelve o'clock.  The dinner was eaten with 
serious haste.  There was never much conversation at the table in 
the Penn family.  Adoniram asked a blessing, and they ate promptly, 
then rose up and went about their work. 
</p><p>Sammy went back to school, taking soft sly lopes out of the 
yard like a rabbit.  He wanted a game of marbles before school, and 
feared his father would give him some chores to do.  Adoniram 
hastened to the door and called after him, but he was out of sight. 
</p><p>"I don't see what you let him go for, mother," said he.  "I 
wanted him to help me unload that wood." 
</p><p>Adoniram went to work out in the yard unloading wood from the 
wagon.  Sarah put away the dinner dishes, while Nanny took down her 
curl-papers and changed her dress.  She was going down to the store 
to buy some more embroidery and thread. 
</p><p>When Nanny was gone, Mrs. Penn went to the door.  "Father!" 
she called. 
</p><p>"Well, what is it?" 
</p><p>"I want to see you jest a minute, father." 
</p><p>"I can't leave this wood nohow.  I've got to git it unloaded 
an' go for a load of gravel afore two o'clock.  Sammy had ought to 
helped me.  You hadn't ought to let him go to school so early." 
</p><p>"I want to see you jest a minute." 
</p><p>"I tell ye I can't, nohow, mother." 
</p><p>"Father, you come here."  Sarah Penn stood in the door like a 
queen; she held her head as if it bore a crown; there was that 
patience which makes authority royal in her voice.  Adoniram went. 
</p><p>Mrs. Penn led the way into the kitchen, and pointed to a 
chair.  "Sit down, father," said she; "I've got somethin' I want to 
say to you." 
</p><p>He sat down heavily; his face was quite stolid, but he looked 
at her with restive eyes.  "Well, what is it, mother?" 
</p><p>"I want to know what you're buildin' that new barn for, 
father?" 
</p><p>"I 'ain't got nothin' to say about it." 
</p><p>"It can't be you think you need another barn?" 
</p><p>"I tell ye I 'ain't got nothin' to say about it, mother; an' 
I ain't goin' to say nothin'." 
</p><p>"Be you goin' to buy more cows?" 
</p><p>Adoniram did not reply; he shut his mouth tight. 
</p><p>"I know you be, as well as I want to.  Now, father, look 
here"&mdash;Sarah Penn had not sat down; she stood before her husband in 
the humble fashion of a Scripture  
 
<pb n="556"/>  
woman&mdash;"I'm goin' to talk 
real plain to you: I never have sence I married you, but I'm goin' 
to now.  I 'ain't never complained, an' I ain't goin' to complain 
now, but I'm goin' to talk plain.  You see this room here, father; 
you look at it well.  You see there ain't no carpet on the floor, 
an' you see the paper is all dirty, an' droppin' off the walls.  We 
'ain't had no new paper on it for ten year, an' then I put it on 
myself, an' it didn't cost but nine-pence a roll.  You see this 
room, father; it's all the one I've had to work in an' eat in an' 
sit in sence we was married.  There ain't another woman in the 
whole town whose husband 'ain't got half the means you have but 
what's got better.  It's all the room Nanny's got to have her 
company in; an' there ain't one of her mates but what's got better, 
an' their fathers not so able as hers is.  It's all the room she'll 
have to be married in.  What would you have thought, father, if we 
had had our weddin' in a room no better than this?  I was married 
in my mother's parlor, with a carpet on the floor, an' stuffed 
furniture, an' a mahogany card-table.  An' this is all the room my 
daughter will have to be married in.  Look here, father!" 
</p><p>Sarah Penn went across the room as though it were a tragic 
stage.  She flung open a door and disclosed a tiny bedroom, only 
large enough for a bed and bureau, with a path between.  "There, 
father," said she&mdash;"there's all the room I've had to sleep in for 
forty year.  All my children were born there&mdash;the two that died, 
an' the two that's livin'.  I was sick with a fever there." 
</p><p>She stepped to another door and opened it.  It led into the 
small, ill-lighted pantry.  "Here," said she, "is all the buttery 
I've got&mdash;every place I've got for my dishes to set away my 
victuals in, an' to keep my milk-pans in.  Father, I've been takin' 
care of the milk of six cows in this place, an' now you're goin' to 
build a new barn, an' keep more cows, an' give me more to do in 
it." 
</p><p>She threw open another door.  A narrow crooked flight of 
stairs wound upward from it.  "There, father!" said she; "I want 
you to look at the stairs that go up to them two unfinished 
chambers that are all the places our son an' daughter have had to 
sleep in all their lives.  There ain't a prettier girl in town nor 
a more ladylike one than Nanny, an' that's the place she has to 
sleep in.  It ain't so good as your horse's stall; it ain't so warm 
an' tight." 
</p><p>Sarah Penn went back and stood before her husband.  "Now, 
father," said she, "I want to know if you think you're doin' right 
an' accordin' to what you profess.  Here, when we was married, 
forty year ago, you promised me faithful that we should have a new 
house built in that lot over in the field before the year was out.  
You said you had money enough, an' you wouldn't ask me to live in 
no such place as this.  It is forty year now, an' you've been 
makin' more money, an' I've been savin' of it for you ever since, 
an' you 'ain't built no house yet.  You've built sheds, an' cow-houses an' one new barn, an' now you're goin' to build another.  
Father, I want to know if you think it's right.  You're lodgin' 
your dumb beasts better than you are your own flesh an' blood.  I 
want to know if you think it's right." 
</p><p>"I 'ain't got nothin' to say." 
</p><p>"You can't say nothin' without ownin' it ain't right, father.  
An' there's another thing&mdash;I ain't complained; I've got along forty 
year, an' I s'pose I should forty more, if it wa'n't for that&mdash;if 
we don't have another house, Nanny she can't live with us after 
she's married.  She'll have to go somewheres else to live away from 
us, an' it don't seem as if I could have it so, noways, father.  
She wa'n't ever strong.  She's got considerable color, but there 
wa'n't never any backbone to her.  I've always took the heft of 
everything off her, an' she ain't fit to keep house an' do 
everything herself.  She'll be all worn out inside of a year.  
Think of her doin' all the washin' an' ironin' an' bakin' with them 
soft white hands an' arms, an' sweepin'!  I can't have it so, 
noways, father." 
</p><p>Mrs. Penn's face was burning; her mild eyes gleamed.  She had 
pleaded her little cause like a Webster; she had ranged from 
severity to pathos; but her opponent employed that obstinate 
silence which makes eloquence futile with mocking echoes.  Adoniram 
arose clumsily. 
</p><p>"Father, 'ain't you got nothin' to say?" said Mrs. Penn. 
</p><p>"I've got to go off after that load of gravel.  I can't stan' 
here talkin' all day." 
</p><p>"Father, won't you think it over, an' have a house built there 
instead of a barn?" 
</p><p>"I 'ain't got nothin' to say."  
 
<pb n="557"/>  
 
</p><p>Adoniram shuffled out.  Mrs. Penn went into her bedroom.  When 
she came out, her eyes were red.  She had a roll of unbleached 
cotton cloth.  She spread it out on the kitchen table, and began 
cutting out some shirts for her husband.  The men over in the field 
had a team to help them this afternoon; she could hear their 
halloos.  She had a scanty pattern for the shirts; she had to plan 
and piece the sleeves. 
</p><p>Nanny came home with her embroidery, and sat down with her 
needle-work.  She had taken down her curl-papers, and there was a 
soft roll of fair hair like an aureole over her forehead; her face 
was as delicately fine and clear as porcelain.  Suddenly she looked 
up, and the tender red flamed all over her face and neck.  
"Mother," said she. 
</p><p>"What say?" 
</p><p>"I've been thinkin'&mdash;I don't see how we're goin' to have any&mdash; 
weddin' in this room.  I'd be ashamed to have his folks come if we 
didn't have anybody else." 
</p><p>"Mebbe we can have some new paper before then; I can put it 
on.  I guess you won't have no call to be ashamed of your 
belongin's." 
</p><p>"We might have the weddin' in the new barn," said Nanny, with 
gentle pettishness.  "Why, mother, what makes you look so?" 
</p><p>Mrs. Penn had started, and was staring at her with a curious 
expression.  She turned again to her work, and spread out a pattern 
carefully on the cloth.  "Nothin'," said she. 
</p><p>Presently Adoniram clattered out of the yard in his two-wheeled dump cart, standing as proudly upright as a Roman 
charioteer.  Mrs. Penn opened the door and stood there a minute 
looking out; the halloos of the men sounded louder. 
</p><p>It seemed to her all through the spring months that she heard 
nothing but the halloos and the noises of saws and hammers.  The 
new barn grew fast.  It was a fine edifice for this little village.  
Men came on pleasant Sundays, in their meeting suits and clean 
shirt bosoms, and stood around it admiringly.  Mrs. Penn did not 
speak of it, and Adoniram did not mention it to her, although 
sometimes, upon a return from inspecting it, he bore himself with 
injured dignity. 
</p><p>"It's a strange thing how your mother feels about the new 
barn," he said, confidentially, to Sammy one day. 
</p><p>Sammy only grunted after an odd fashion for a boy: he had 
learned it from his father. 
</p><p>The barn was all completed ready for use by the third week in 
July.  Adoniram had planned to move his stock in on Wednesday; on 
Tuesday he received a letter which changed his plans.  He came in 
with it early in the morning.  "Sammy's been to the post-office," 
said he, "an' I've got a letter from Hiram."  Hiram was Mrs. Penn's 
brother, who lived in Vermont. 
</p><p>"Well," said Mrs. Penn, "what does he say about the folks?" 
</p><p>"I guess they're all right.  He says he thinks if I come up 
country right off there's a chance to buy jest the kind of a horse 
I want."  He stared reflectively out of the window at the new barn. 
</p><p>Mrs. Penn was making pies.  She went on clapping the rolling-pin into the crust, although she was very pale, and her heart beat 
loudly. 
</p><p>"I dunno' but what I'd better go," said Adoniram.  "I hate to 
go off jest now, right in the midst of hayin', but the ten-acre 
lot's cut, an' I guess Rufus an' the others can git along without 
me three or four days.  I can't get a horse round here to suit me, 
nohow, an' I've got to have another for all that wood-haulin' in 
the fall.  I told Hiram to watch out, an' if he got wind of a good 
horse to let me know.  I guess I'd better go." 
</p><p>"I'll get out your clean shirt an' collar," said Mrs. Penn, 
calmly. 
</p><p>She laid out Adoniram's Sunday suit and his clean clothes on 
the bed in the little bedroom.  She got his shaving water and razor 
ready.  At last she buttoned on his collar and fastened his black 
cravat. 
</p><p>Adoniram never wore his collar and cravat except on extra 
occasions.  He held his head high, with a rasped dignity.  When he 
was all ready, with his coat and hat brushed, and a lunch of pie 
and cheese in a paper bag, he hesitated on the threshold of the 
door.  He looked at his wife, and his manner was defiantly 
apologetic.  <hi rend="italic">"If</hi> them cows come to-day, Sammy can drive 'em 
into the new barn," said he; "an' when they bring the hay up, they 
can pitch it in there." 
</p><p>"Well," replied Mrs. Penn. 
</p><p>Adoniram set his shaven face ahead and started.  When he had 
cleared the door-step, he turned and looked back with  
 
<pb n="558"/>  
 a 
kind of nervous solemnity.  "I shall be back by Saturday if nothin' 
happens," said he. 
</p><p>"Do be careful, father," returned his wife. 
</p><p>She stood in the door with Nanny at her elbow and watched him 
out of sight.  Her eyes had a strange, doubtful expression in them; 
her peaceful forehead was contracted.  She went in, and about her 
baking again.  Nanny sat sewing.  Her wedding day was drawing 
nearer, and she was getting pale and thin with her steady sewing.  
Her mother kept glancing at her. 
</p><p>"Have you got that pain in your side this mornin'?" she asked. 
</p><p>"A little." 
</p><p>Mrs. Penn's face, as she worked, changed, her perplexed 
forehead smoothed, her eyes were steady, her lips firmly set.  She 
formed a maxim for herself, although incoherently with her 
unlettered thoughts.  "Unsolicited opportunities are the guideposts 
of the Lord to the new roads of life," she repeated in effect, and 
she made up her mind to her course of action. 
</p><p>"S'posin' I <hi rend="italic">had</hi> wrote to Hiram," she muttered once, 
when she was in the pantry&mdash;"s'posin' I <hi rend="italic">had</hi> wrote, an' asked 
him if he knew of any horse?  But I didn't, an' father's goin' 
wa'n't none of my doin'.  It looks like a Providence."  Her voice 
rang out quite loud at the last. 
</p><p>"What you talkin' about, mother?" called Nanny. 
</p><p>"Nothin'." 
</p><p>Mrs. Penn hurried her baking; at eleven o'clock it was all 
done.  The load of hay from the west field came slowly down the 
cart track, and drew up at the new barn.  Mrs. Penn ran out.  
"Stop!" she screamed&mdash;"stop!" 
</p><p>The men stopped and looked; Sammy upreared from the top of the 
load, and stared at his mother. 
</p><p>"Stop!" she cried out again.  "Don't you put the hay in that 
barn; put it in the old one." 
</p><p>"Why, he said to put it in here," returned one of the 
haymakers, wonderingly.  He was a young man, a neighbor's son, whom 
Adoniram hired by the year to help on the farm. 
</p><p>"Don't you put the hay in the new barn; there's room enough in 
the old one, ain't there?" said Mrs. Penn. 
</p><p>"Room enough," returned the hired man, in his thick, rustic 
tones.  "Didn't need the new barn, nohow, far as room's concerned.  
Well, I s'pose he changed his mind."  He took hold of the horses' 
bridles. 
</p><p>Mrs. Penn went back to the house.  Soon the kitchen windows 
were darkened, and a fragrance like warm honey came into the room. 
</p><p>Nanny laid down her work.  "I thought father wanted them to 
put the hay into the new barn?" she said, wonderingly. 
</p><p>"It's all right," replied her mother. 
</p><p>Sammy slid down from the load of hay and came in to see if 
dinner was ready. 
</p><p>"I ain't goin' to get a regular dinner to-day, as long as 
father's gone," said his mother.  "I've let the fire go out.  You 
can have some bread an' milk an' pie.  I thought we could get 
along."  She set out some bowls of milk, some bread, and a pie on 
the kitchen table.  "You'd better eat your dinner now," said she.  
"You might jest as well get through with it.  I want you to help me 
afterward." 
</p><p>Nanny and Sammy stared at each other.  There was something 
strange in their mother's manner.  Mrs. Penn did not eat anything 
herself.  She went into the pantry, and they heard her moving 
dishes while they ate.  Presently she came out with a pile of 
plates.  She got the clothes-basket out of the shed, and packed 
them in it.  Nanny and Sammy watched.  She brought out cups and 
saucers, and put them in with the plates. 
</p><p>"What you goin' to do, mother?" inquired Nanny, in a timid 
voice.  A sense of something unusual made her tremble, as if it 
were a ghost.  Sammy rolled his eyes over his pie. 
</p><p>"You'll see what I'm goin' to do," replied Mrs. Penn.  "If 
you're through, Nanny, I want you to go up stairs an' pack up your 
things; an' I want you, Sammy, to help me take down the bed in the 
bed-room." 
</p><p>"Oh, mother, what for?" gasped Nanny. 
</p><p>"You'll see." 
</p><p>During the next few hours a feat was performed by this simple, 
pious New England mother which was equal in its way to Wolfe's 
storming of the Heights of Abraham.  It took no more genius and 
audacity of bravery for Wolfe to cheer his wondering soldiers up 
those steep precipices, under the sleeping eyes of the enemy, than 
for Sarah Penn, at the head of her children, to move all her little 
household  
 
<pb n="559"/>  
goods into the new barn while her husband was 
away. 
</p><p>Nanny and Sammy followed their mother's instructions without 
a murmur; indeed, they were overawed.  There is a certain uncanny 
and superhuman quality about all such purely original undertakings 
as their mother's was to them.  Nanny went back and forth with her 
light loads, and Sammy tugged with sober energy. 
</p><p>At five o'clock in the afternoon the little house in which the 
Penns had lived for forty years had emptied itself into the new 
barn. 
</p><p>Every builder builds somewhat for unknown purposes, and is in 
a measure a prophet.  The architect of Adoniram Penn's barn, while 
he designed it for the comfort of four-footed animals, had planned 
better than he knew for the comfort of humans.  Sarah Penn saw at 
a glance its possibilities.  Those great box-stalls, with quilts 
hung before them, would make better bedrooms than the one she had 
occupied for forty years, and there was a tight carriage-room.  The 
harness-room, with its chimney and shelves, would make a kitchen of 
her dreams.  The great middle space would make a parlor, by-and-by, 
fit for a palace.  Up stairs there was as much room as down.  With 
partitions and windows, what a house would there be!  Sarah looked 
at the row of stanchions before the allotted space for cows, and 
reflected that she would have her front entry there. 
</p><p>At six o'clock the stove was up in the harness-room, the 
kettle was boiling, and the table set for tea.  It looked almost as 
home-like as the abandoned house across the yard had ever done.  
The young hired man milked, and Sarah directed him calmly to bring 
the milk to the new barn.  He came gaping, dropping little blots of 
foam from the brimming pails on the grass.  Before the next morning 
he had spread the story of Adoniram Penn's wife moving into the new 
barn all over the little village.  Men assembled in the store and 
talked it over, women with shawls over their heads scuttled into 
each other's houses before their work was done.  Any deviation from 
the ordinary course of life in this quiet town was enough to stop 
all progress in it.  Everybody paused to look at the staid, 
independent figure on the side track.  There was a difference of 
opinion with regard to her.  Some held her to be insane; some, of 
a lawless and rebellious spirit. 
</p><p>Friday the minister went to see her.  It was in the forenoon, 
and she was at the barn door shelling pease for dinner.  She looked 
up and returned his salutation with dignity, then she went on with 
her work.  She did not invite him in.  The saintly expression of 
her face remained fixed, but there was an angry flush over it. 
</p><p>The minister stood awkwardly before her and talked.  She 
handled the pease as if they were bullets.  At last she looked up, 
and her eyes showed the spirit that her meek front had covered for 
a lifetime. 
</p><p>"There ain't no use talkin', Mr. Hersey," said she.  "I've 
thought it all over an' over, an' I believe I'm doin' what's right.  
I've made it the subject of prayer, an' it's betwixt me an' the 
Lord an' Adoniram.  There ain't no call for nobody else to worry 
about it." 
</p><p>"Well, of course if you have brought it to the Lord in prayer, 
and feel satisfied that you are doing right, Mrs. Penn," said the 
minister, helplessly.  His thin gray-bearded face was pathetic.  He 
was a sickly man; his youthful confidence had cooled; he had to 
scourge himself up to some of his pastoral duties as relentlessly 
as a Catholic ascetic, and then he was prostrated by the smart. 
</p><p>"I think it's right jest as much as I think it was right for 
our forefathers to come over from the old country 'cause they 
didn't have what belonged to 'em," said Mrs. Penn.  She arose.  The 
barn threshold might have been Plymouth Rock from her bearing.  "I 
don't doubt you mean well, Mr. Hersey," said she, "but there are 
things people hadn't ought to interfere with.  I've been a member 
of the church for over forty year.  I've got my own mind an' my own 
feet, an' I'm goin' to think my own thoughts an' go my own ways, 
an' nobody but the Lord is goin' to dictate to me unless I've a 
mind to have him.  Won't you come in an' set down?  How is Mis' 
Hersey?" 
</p><p>"She is well, I thank you," replied the minister.  He added 
some more perplexed apologetic remarks; then he retreated. 
</p><p>He could expound the intricacies of every character study in 
the Scriptures, he was competent to grasp the Pilgrim Fathers and 
all historical innovators, but Sarah Penn was beyond him.  He could 
deal with primal cases, but parallel ones worsted him.  But, after 
all, although it  
 
<pb n="560"/>  
 was aside from his province, he wondered 
more how Adoniram Penn would deal with his wife than how the Lord 
would.  Everybody shared the wonder.  When Adoniram's four new cows 
arrived, Sarah ordered three to be put in the old barn, the other 
in the house shed where the cooking-stove had stood.  That added to 
the excitement.  It was whispered that all four cows were domiciled 
in the house. 
</p><p>Toward sunset on Saturday, when Adoniram was expected home, 
there was a knot of men in the road near the new barn.  The hired 
man had milked, but he still hung around the premises.  Sarah Penn 
had supper all ready.  There were brown-bread and baked beans and 
a custard pie; it was the supper that Adoniram loved on a Saturday 
night.  She had on a clean calico, and she bore herself 
imperturbably.  Nanny and Sammy kept close at her heels.  Their 
eyes were large, and Nanny was full of nervous tremors.  Still 
there was to them more pleasant excitement than anything else.  An 
inborn confidence in their mother over their father asserted 
itself. 
</p><p>Sammy looked out of the harness-room window.  "There he is," 
he announced, in an awed whisper.  He and Nanny peeped around the 
casing.  Mrs. Penn kept on about her work.  The children watched 
Adoniram leave the new horse standing in the drive while he went to 
the house door.  It was fastened.  Then he went around to the shed.  
That door was seldom locked, even when the family was away.  The 
thought how her father would be confronted by the cow flashed upon 
Nanny.  There was a hysterical sob in her throat.  Adoniram emerged 
from the shed and stood looking about in a dazed fashion.  His lips 
moved; he was saying something, but they could not hear what it 
was.  The hired man was peeping around a corner of the old barn, 
but nobody saw him. 
</p><p>Adoniram took the new horse by the bridle and led him across 
the yard to the new barn.  Nanny and Sammy slunk close to their 
mother.  The barn doors rolled back, and there stood Adoniram, with 
the long mild face of the great Canadian farm horse looking over 
his shoulder. 
</p><p>Nanny kept behind her mother, but Sammy stepped suddenly 
forward, and stood in front of her. 
</p><p>Adoniram stared at the group.  "What on airth you all down 
here for?" said he.  "What's the matter over to the house?" 
</p><p>"We've come here to live, father," said Sammy.  His shrill 
voice quavered out bravely. 
</p><p>"What"&mdash;Adoniram sniffed&mdash;"what is it smells like cookin'?" 
said he.  He stepped forward and looked in the open door of the 
harness-room.  Then he turned to his wife.  His old bristling face 
was pale and frightened.  "What on airth does this mean, mother?" 
he gasped. 
</p><p>"You come in here, father," said Sarah.  She led the way into 
the harness-room and shut the door.  "Now, father," said she, "you 
needn't be scared.  I ain't crazy.  There ain't nothin' to be upset 
over.  But we've come here to live, an' we're goin' to live here.  
We've got jest as good a right here as new horses an' cows.  The 
house wa'n't fit for us to live in any longer, an' I made up my 
mind I wa'n't goin' to stay there.  I've done my duty by you forty 
year, an' I'm goin' to do it now; but I'm goin' to live here.  
You've got to put in some windows and partitions; an' you'll have 
to buy some furniture." 
</p><p>"Why, mother!" the old man gasped. 
</p><p>"You'd better take your coat off an' get washed&mdash;there's the 
wash-basin&mdash;an' then we'll have supper." 
</p><p>"Why, mother!" 
</p><p>Sammy went past the window, leading the new horse to the old 
barn.  The old man saw him, and shook his head speechlessly.  He 
tried to take off his coat, but his arms seemed to lack the power.  
His wife helped him.  She poured some water into the tin basin, and 
put in a piece of soap.  She got the comb and brush, and smoothed 
his thin gray hair after he had washed.  Then she put the beans, 
hot bread, and tea on the table.  Sammy came in, and the family 
drew up.  Adoniram sat looking dazedly at his plate, and they 
waited. 
</p><p>"Ain't you goin' to ask a blessin', father?" said Sarah. 
</p><p>And the old man bent his head and mumbled. 
</p><p>All through the meal he stopped eating at intervals, and 
stared furtively at his wife; but he ate well.  The home food 
tasted good to him, and his old frame was too sturdily healthy to 
be affected by his mind.  But after supper he went out and sat down 
on the step of the smaller door at the right of the barn, through 
 
<pb n="561"/>  
which he had meant his Jerseys to pass in stately file, but 
which Sarah designed for her front house door, and he leaned his 
head on his hands. 
</p><p>After the supper dishes were cleared away and the milk-pans 
washed, Sarah came out to him.  The twilight was deepening.  There 
was a clear green glow in the sky.  Before them stretched the 
smooth level of field; in the distance was a cluster of hay-stacks 
like the huts of a village; the air was very cool and calm and 
sweet.  The landscape might have been an ideal one of peace. 
</p><p>Sarah bent over and touched her husband on one of his thin, 
sinewy shoulders.  "Father!" 
</p><p>The old man's shoulders heaved: he was weeping. 
</p><p>"Why, don't do so, father," said Sarah. 
</p><p>"I'll&mdash;put up the&mdash;partitions, an'&mdash;everything you&mdash;want, 
mother." 
</p><p>Sarah put her apron up to her face; she was overcome by her 
own triumph. 
</p><p>Adoniram was like a fortress whose walls had no active 
resistance, and went down the instant the right besieging tools 
were used.  "Why, mother," he said, hoarsely, "I hadn't no idee you 
was so set on't as all this comes to." 
</p> 
 
</div1> 
</body> 
</text> 
</TEI.2> 
 
