<?xml version="1.0"?>

<?dlps id="WilWand"?>
<?dlps page-images="none" figure-images="no"?>
<?dlps transcription="other"?>

<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/tei-p4/tei2.dtd" [
<!ENTITY % POSTKB "INCLUDE">
<!ENTITY % TEI.extensions.ent SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.ent">
<!ENTITY % TEI.extensions.dtd SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.dtd">
<!ENTITY % ISOnum SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/charent/iso-num.ent"> %ISOnum;
<!ENTITY % ISOpub SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/charent/iso-pub.ent"> %ISOpub;
 
]> 
<TEI.2 id="WilWand"> 
<teiHeader type="migrated" creator="Etext">
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title type="main">A Wandering Samaritan</title>
<title type="sort">wandering samaritan</title>
<author>Wilkins, Mary E.</author>
<respStmt>
<resp>Creation of machine-readable version:</resp>  
<name>Judy Boss</name>  
<resp>Conversion to TEI.2-conformant markup:</resp>  
<name>Lisa Goldberg, University of Virginia Library Electronic Text Center.</name>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt>  
<extent>ca. <num type="kilobytes">29</num> kilobytes</extent>  
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>University of Virginia Library</publisher>
<pubPlace>Charlottesville, Virginia</pubPlace>  
<idno type="ETC">WilWand</idno>  
<date value="1996">1996</date>
<availability status="public">
<p n="copyright">Copyright &copy; 1996 by the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia</p>
<p n="access">Publicly accessible</p>
</availability>
<idno type="uva-pid">uva-lib:476556</idno>
</publicationStmt>
<seriesStmt>
<title>University of Virginia Library, Text collection</title>
<idno type="uva-set">UVA-LIB-Text</idno>
</seriesStmt>  
<notesStmt>
<note>
<p>Judy Boss has made the following changes to the text: page 28, 
para. 12: Lijah's] 'Lijah's; page 29, para. 5: She] "She; page 30, 
para. 10: s'ppose] s'pose; page 30, para. 19: Well that's] Well, 
that's; page 30, para. 31: aint me?] ain't me?; page 31, para. 12: 
a-goin] a-goin'; page 31, para. 15: I don't] "I don't; page 31, para. 
36: considerable] consider'ble</p>
</note>
</notesStmt>  
<sourceDesc>
<biblFull>
<titleStmt>
<title type="main">A Wandering Samaritan</title>
<title level="j">Cosmopolitan</title>
<title type="sort">wandering samaritan</title>
<author>Mary E. Wilkins</author>
</titleStmt>  
<extent>pp. 28-33</extent>  
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>Schlicht &amp; Field Co., Publishers and Printers</publisher>  
<pubPlace>Rochester, NY</pubPlace>  
<date value="1886-09">September 1886</date>  
<idno type="callNo">Print copy consulted: Microfilm version, University of Virginia 
library call no. S-147 reel 660</idno>
</publicationStmt>  
<notesStmt>
<note>
<p>The Cosmopolitan. A Monthly Illustrated Magazine. Vol. II. 
September 1886, pp. 28-33</p>
</note>  
</notesStmt>
</biblFull>
</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc>  
<encodingDesc>
<projectDesc>
<p>Prepared for the University of Virginia Library Electronic Text Center.</p>
</projectDesc>  
<editorialDecl>
<p>All quotation marks retained as data.</p>  
<p>All unambiguous end-of-line hyphens have been removed, and the trailing part of a word has been joined to the preceding line.</p>  
<p>Keywords in the header are a local Electronic Text Center scheme to aid in establishing analytical groupings.</p>
</editorialDecl>  
</encodingDesc>  
<profileDesc>
<creation>
<date value="1886">1886</date>
</creation>  
<langUsage>
<language id="eng" usage="main">English</language>
</langUsage>  
<textClass>
<keywords>  
<term>Women Writers</term>
</keywords>  
<keywords>
<term>fiction; prose</term>
</keywords>
</textClass>
</profileDesc>  
<revisionDesc>
<change>
<date value="1996-11">November 1996</date>  
<respStmt>
<resp>corrector</resp>  
<name>Lisa Goldberg, University of Virginia Library Electronic Text Center</name>
</respStmt>  
<item>Added TEI header and tags</item>
</change>  
<change>
<date value="2005-07">July 2005</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>Corrector</resp>
<name>Margaret Konkol</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Converted SGML to XML and fixed tagging.</item>
</change>
<change>
<date value="2007-09">September 2007</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>Migration</resp>
<name>Ethan Gruber, University of Virginia Library</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Converted XML markup from TEI Lite to uva-dl-tei (TEI P4 with local customizations).</item>
</change>
<change>
<date value="2008-01">January 2008</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>Migration</resp>
<name>Greg Murray, University of Virginia Library</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Programmatically updated TEI header markup (but not header content) for minimal compliance with current QA requirements.</item>
</change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>  
 
<text id="d1">  
<body id="d2"> 

<div1 type="story" id="d3">  
<head>A WANDERING SAMARITAN. 
<lb/> 
BY MARY E. WILKINS. 
</head> 
 <pb n="28"/>  
 
<p>A LOW stone wall bordered the lane on either side.  There were 
clumps of tansy and yarrow with straggling bushes of meadow-sweet 
and hardback clustering closely around the loosely piled rocks.  
Plenty of poison ivy vines clambered over them too.  The lane was 
narrow and grassy; even the deep wheel-ruts through the center were 
overgrown with grass.  And everything was dusty; there had been a 
little drought lately; the leaves were powdered thick with dust. 
 
</p><p>It was a hot day in August, and about four o'clock in the 
afternoon.  Midway of the lane stood an old twisted apple tree.  
Underneath it was a little circle of shade.  An old man sat beneath 
the tree, with his back against the shaggy, mossy trunk.  He was so 
motionless that a passer through the lane, happening accidentally 
to glance his way, would have taken in the fact of the proximity of 
a second animated being with a strange shock. 
 
</p><p>He looked as much a part of inanimate nature as the stones in 
the wall.  The sudden conviction of the possibility of motion in 
him was enough to send a startled thrill through one.  If his eyes 
had been closed in sleep, it might have been different; but they 
were wide open, staring peacefully straight ahead at the flowering 
bushes opposite.  They were of a light blue color, large and clear, 
and did not look filmy with age, though the man must have been over 
eighty. 
 
</p><p>His white hair, as fine and thick as wool, stood out on either 
side of his placid face.  He wore no beard.  His mouth was wide and 
curved slightly, not so much into a smile as into an expression of 
pleasant serenity.  His rusty, black clothes were loose and baggy; 
an old valise lay on the grass near him, and a stout stick that had 
evidently been cut for a cane. 
 
</p><p>He staid there motionless for a half hour or so.  No one came 
through the lane to disturb him.  The bees and the butterflies 
whirred by unceasingly, and the dusty sunbeams, which penetrated 
the apple-boughs here and there, slanted a little more.  Then he 
arose, took his valise on his arm, and moved slowly up the lane, 
leaning on his stout stick. 
 
</p><p>A few rods farther on, the lane inclined slightly to the 
right, and then a small story-and-a-half white house, which marked 
its terminus, appeared.  The lane merged imperceptibly into the 
grassy door yard.  There was a green curved trellis, which looked 
like a hood, over the door, and a prairie rose tree clung to it, 
but the roses were all gone by. 
 
</p><p>The sun had moved so far toward the west that a cool shadow 
lay over the front of the house and the yard.  There were two 
windows on each side of the front door.  The blinds of one of them 
were flung wide open, and a light&mdash;haired head of a woman and an arm 
and hand moving with the regular motion of sewing were visible. 
 
</p><p>The woman rose quietly and came to the door, when she looked 
out and saw the old man. 
 
</p><p>"Is that you, Doctor Ware?" said she. 
 
</p><p>She was a slim, round-shouldered woman.  Her light hair was 
strained back tightly from a full, blue-veined forehead.  There was 
a sweet expression about her thin, nervous mouth. 
 
</p><p>"Yes, it's me; I'm on my summer travels ag'in.  How's all your 
folks, Miss Hatton?" 
 
</p><p>"Well, Mary Anne ain't very smart.  I've been wishin' for some 
time that you'd come along.  She's been takin' some doctor's stuff, 
but it ain't seemed to do her much good, and I thought mebby some 
of your yerbs would give her a start.  Come right in.  'Lijah's out 
in the field to work, but he'll be real glad to see you.  He's said 
several times lately that it seemed 's if 'twas 'bout time for you 
to be comin'." 
 
</p><p>The old man followed her into the cool, sparsely-furnished 
sitting-room, and seated himself in the large cane-seated rocker 
that she placed for him. 
 
</p><p>"Mary Anne!" she called then, standing in the door, "come, 
come down stairs; there's somebody here wants to see you!" 
 
</p><p>Mary Anne, a slender girl, who looked like her mother, except 
that she was younger  
 
<pb n="29"/>   
 
and sweeter, came down presently.  She 
walked weakly, there was a bright flush on her soft cheeks, and her 
blue eyes had an eager, inquiring look in them. 
 
</p><p>"Who is it?" she asked tremulously.  "Oh, Doctor Ware!" 
 
</p><p>All the eagerness faded from her eyes. 
 
</p><p>"Well, Mary Anne, how air ye?" 
 
</p><p>"Pretty well, thank you." 
 
</p><p>"That's what she allers says," remarked her mother.  "She 
ain't well a bit!" 
 
</p><p>The girl did not contradict her; she dropped listlessly into 
a chair. 
 
</p><p>After a little while, her mother beckoned Dr. Ware furtively 
out of the room, and they had a whispered conference out in the 
kitchen.  Mary Anne crept wearily up stairs and laid down on her 
bed again.  Her mother heard her. 
 
</p><p>"There she goes to lay down again," said she; "she don't seem 
to hev no ambition nor interest in anythin'.  Her father an' me hev 
tried an' tried, but we can't rouse her a bit.  Here's the water 
for the yerbs, if you've got 'em ready." 
 
</p><p>Soon a peculiar, pungent steam from the simmering juices of 
certain medicinal plants floated through the house.  The old man 
brooded over the bubbling kettle like a benevolent witch. 
 
</p><p>"There ain't anythin' like this to give anybody an appetite, 
an' strengthen' of 'em up," he said complacently, as he poured 
finally the greenish-black decoction into a bowl. 
 
</p><p>Many such bowls did poor, ailing Mary Anne empty through the 
following days.  She patiently took everything that they gave her. 
 
</p><p>The itinerant vender of herbs, who might have been ranked as 
a physician after an innocent, primitive fashion, having a gentle 
craft in the use of healing plants, staid on.  He always stopped 
awhile with the Hattons while on his summer pilgrimages among these 
adjoining rural villages. 
 
</p><p>A good many people welcomed him gladly to their homes, for 
that matter.  They liked to dose their families with his herb teas 
once a year.  Then there was a religious sympathy between them too.  
Most of them hereabouts were devout Methodists, and he was an 
ardent member of that denomination. 
 
</p><p>But Mary Anne, in spite of her long draughts of these 
bitterish, pungent, aromatic teas, grew no better.  Doctor Ware 
kept up a scrutiny of her that was shrewd from its very simplicity 
and singleness. 
 
</p><p>"There ain't much use in givin' medicine to Mary Anne," he 
told her mother one day; "thar's troubles that nary a yerb that 
grows on this airth's goin' to cure.  Mebbe thar's some in the 
green fields King David sung about." 
 
</p><p>"What do you mean?" 
 
</p><p>"Mary Anne's got somethin' or other on her mind." 
 
</p><p>Mrs. Hatton's delicate face flushed a burning red. 
 
</p><p>"You're mistaken about that, Doctor Ware," she said; "I know 
you are.  Mary Anne can't hev nothin' on her mind; she ain't never 
hed a thing to fret her.  Her father an' me hev allers looked out 
for her, as ef she'd been a cosset-lamb.  She ain't never hed to 
work hard, an' we've bought her everything we could afford." 
 
</p><p>That afternoon the old man went into one of the neighboring 
houses.  A large, handsome woman, who was a great talker, lived 
there. 
 
</p><p>"How do you think Mary Anne is getting along?" said she. 
 
</p><p>"Well, she's rather slim." 
 
</p><p>"It'll take more than your herbs to cure her, Doctor Ware," 
said the woman, with a laugh that was not ill-natured, though 
unpleasantly knowing.  "Medicines for the body don't help the mind, 
I s'pose you know.  You needn't say anythin' about it; her mother'd 
never forgive me; but the long an' short of the whole business is, 
Mary Anne Hatton's lost her beau.  That's everythin' that ails her.  
She's goin' into a decline over it." 
 
</p><p>"Who was her beau?" 
 
</p><p>"That young Adams feller who lives 'bout a mile below here; 
you know him.  He went with her real stidy last winter and don't 
come nigh her now." 
 
</p><p>The old man asked her a few more questions and then took 
leave.  He walked straight down the road to the Adams farm.  Just 
as he approached it, a young man came out of the yard, leading a 
horse. 
 
</p><p>"How do you do, Doctor Ware," he said heartily, stopping and 
shaking hands. 
 
</p><p>He was a pretty, rather boyish-looking young fellow. 
 
</p><p>"Well, I'm pretty well, thanky, Henry."  
 
<pb n="30"/>  
 
</p><p>"Coming into the house, ain't you?" 
 
</p><p>"No, thanky; guess I can't stop.  I'll stan' here an' talk a 
minute.  I'm a stoppin' up to 'Lijah Hatton's, mebbe you know." 
 
</p><p>The other started. 
 
</p><p>"No, I didn't." 
 
</p><p>"Yes, I've been thar some days.  Mary Anne's pretty 
miser'ble." 
 
</p><p>"You don't mean it!  I ain't heard of it.  She ain't very 
sick, is she?" 
 
</p><p>"Well, I don't like to see anybody lookin' the way she does." 
 
</p><p>"What's the matter?" 
 
</p><p>"It's pretty hard tellin'." 
 
</p><p>"Say&mdash;of course she ain't&mdash;I know she ain't.  But you don't 
s'pose she's&mdash;you don't s'pose it's possible she's worryin' over 
anything, do you?" 
 
</p><p>"It acts more like that than anythin' else, ef I was to say 
what I really thought." 
 
</p><p>The young fellow's fair face was all burning with blushes.  He 
looked at the old man, then away again. 
 
</p><p>"Look here," he stammered, "you ain't heard anything said, 
have you?  You don't suppose it is anything to do with&mdash;me?" 
 
</p><p>"Well, I've heard a leetle.  Look a'here, Henry, mebbe you 
think it ain't any of my business, an' it ain't reely; but I'm 
a-goin' to tell you just what I think.  You ain't been showin' out 
yourself to be the kind of young man I thought you was." 
 
</p><p>"Then&mdash;you think&mdash;that is it?" 
 
</p><p>"Well, Henry, I've 'bout come to that conclusion." 
 
</p><p>The young man groaned out, "Oh dear!" and hid his face for a 
minute against his horse's neck. 
 
</p><p>"Look here," said he, raising his head presently.  "I ain't 
meant to do anything mean.  Hang it!  I ain't that kind of a 
fellow, you know.  But&mdash;I'm young, and I'd been going with Mary 
Anne pretty steady, and I didn't have much to get married on, and 
I reckon I got kind of scared, you know.  Then mother she talked 
some; she hadn't a thing against her, but she thought I might wait 
and do a little better.  So I thought maybe I'd better haul off a 
little while, and see how we both stood it." 
 
</p><p>"I never heard a word till this minute about her being sick," 
he continued.  "I've been awful busy and I've been away.  If I had 
heard, I guess&mdash;I don't see why mother didn't tell me.  She must 
have known.  Well, that's all there is to it.  I ain't been any too 
happy myself lately.  Look here, I'll be up there to-night.  Poor 
little thing!  I guess if I had known&mdash;" 
 
</p><p>"Well, don't you go to feelin' too bad.  I dassay you didn't 
mean no harm, an' if you act like a man about it now, 't'll be all 
right." 
 
</p><p>That night the old man watched eagerly.  He kept sauntering 
out to the head of the lane and looking, but Henry never came in 
sight. 
 
</p><p>Presently the candle-light behind Mary Anne's little curtain 
went out, and he gave up the watch with gathering indignation. 
 
</p><p>"He's a mean feller after all," he muttered, plodding heavily 
through the dewy grass back to the house. 
 
</p><p>Early the next morning, he set out for the Adams place.  As he 
approached the house, he peered about the yard sharply, but he 
could see nothing of the delinquent young man.  He knocked on the 
side door, and presently a woman opened it. 
 
</p><p>She was tall and large, and her blue eyes stared out of her 
heavy face with a sort of reflective uncertainty, though her mouth 
was smiling. 
 
</p><p>"Good evenin', Miss Adams." 
 
</p><p>"Good mornin'," said she stiffly. 
 
</p><p>"I guess you don't know who I am, Miss Adams." 
 
</p><p>"I can't say as I do, jest." 
 
</p><p>"My name is Ware." 
 
</p><p>"Oh, yes, I couldn't think for a minute who you was.  It's 
quite a spell since you've been round.  Fine weather we're havin', 
ain't we?  Come in, won't you?" 
 
</p><p>She had a large earthen bowl under her arm, and she was 
beating eggs in it with a heavy iron spoon as she talked.  She beat 
energetically, and the spoon made a din against the sides of the 
bowl. 
 
</p><p>"No, thanky, Miss Adams, I guess I can't stop.  I'm a stayin' 
up to Hatton's, an' I'm goin' to help him a leetle this forenoon 
whilst the sun's high 'bout spreadin' his hay.  Whar's Henry?" 
 
</p><p>"Henry?  Oh, he ain't here." 
 
</p><p>"Gone far?" 
 
</p><p>"No, not very far.  Well, he's been thinkin' of goin' over to 
his uncle's in Dover for some time." 
 
</p><p>"Over to his uncle's, hey?  Goin' to stay long?"  
 
<pb n="31"/>  
 
</p><p>"Well, I dunno jest how long." 
 
</p><p>"Shouldn't think he could leave very well in hayin' time." 
 
</p><p>"Well, he didn't know how to." 
 
</p><p>Mrs. Adams screwed up her mouth moodily between her answers, 
and beat the eggs fiercely. 
 
</p><p>The old man hesitated. 
 
</p><p>"Didn't Henry say nothin' 'bout comin' up to our house last 
evenin'?" he asked finally. 
 
</p><p>The woman's eyes flashed suddenly under their drooping lids.  
The iron spoon jumped in her nervous hand. 
 
</p><p>"Well, I dunno as he did." 
 
</p><p>"I saw him yesterday afternoon, an' he said he was." 
 
</p><p>"Did he?" 
 
</p><p>Doctor Ware stepped up closer to her.  His old voice quivered. 
 
</p><p>"Look a-here, Miss Adams, I'm a-goin' to speak to you 'bout 
it.  You're his mother, an' you'd orter hev some influence over him 
an' coax him to do what's right, ef he ain't inclined to himself.  
Mebbe you know somethin' 'bout it.  You know your son's been up to 
see the Hatton girl consider'ble." 
 
</p><p>"I don't know nothin' about it." 
 
</p><p>"Well, she got real kind of interested in him, as near as I 
can make out, an' he ain't been there lately, an' she's worried a 
good deal.  She's real poorly, accordin' to my way of thinkin'." 
 
</p><p>"I don't want to hear nothin' about it." 
 
</p><p>"Miss Adams, you don't mean to say you don't want Henry to do 
what's right?" 
 
</p><p>"I don't want to talk about it at all!" 
 
</p><p>"You don't want to see that poor child frettin' herself to 
death before your face and eyes an' not do anythin' to stop it, 
when it's your own son's fault?" 
 
</p><p>"I don't want to say another word about it, an' I ain't goin' 
to!  Henry's got to manage his own affairs." 
 
</p><p>Suddenly the old man started. 
 
</p><p>"Hark a minute!  What's that?" said he. 
 
</p><p>Mrs. Adams clattered her spoon furiously. 
 
</p><p>"What's what?" she asked. 
 
</p><p>"I thought I heard somebody holler." 
 
</p><p>"Guess 'twas Mr. Jackson over there with his oxen.  He hollers 
like all possessed at 'em sometimes. 
 
</p><p>"I've got somethin' in the oven, an' I guess I shall hev to go 
in." 
 
</p><p>"Miss Adams!" 
 
</p><p>But she had fairly shut the door in his face. 
 
</p><p>That morning, out in the hay field, he asked Mr. Hatton, after 
a long spell of work and reflection: 
 
</p><p>"I s'pose you know Miss Adams, down below here, Henry Adams' 
mother, don't ye?" 
 
</p><p>"Known her ever since I knew anythin'." 
 
</p><p>"Good kind of a woman, ain't she?" 
 
</p><p>"Guess she's good enough; awful set when she gits her mind 
made up." 
 
</p><p>"Henry don't look as if he was." 
 
</p><p>Mary Anne's father turned around and faced the old man 
fiercely.  His dark, leathery face with heavy seams about the mouth 
and eyes worked.  He was a slow, taciturn man, and he had never 
before mentioned this subject to his visitor. 
 
</p><p>"I wish the Lord," he said, "I had my hands on that feller 
sometimes.  That's what ails Mary Anne.  Come jest long enough to 
git her to thinkin' consider'ble of him an' then&mdash;  She ain't tough 
like some girls, an' she takes everythin' to heart dreadful.  An' 
there's some things mother an' me can't do for her.  We've allers 
tried to do everythin'.  Seems as there ain't no need of it, an' 
there ain't.  Henry Adams ain't the only feller in the world.  But 
that don't make no difference to her.  There ain't no use scoldin' 
her.  She's failin' every day." 
 
</p><p>"You ain't never said anythin' to him?" 
 
</p><p>"Said anythin'?  Guess I shouldn't say much, unless I said it 
with my fists!" 
 
</p><p>Mary Anne's poor father bore down upon the sweet, dying clover 
and grasses with his angry foot, and raked again sternly. 
 
</p><p>That evening Doctor Ware went down to the Adams house again.  
As he drew near, he heard a voice singing to a melodeon 
accompaniment.  When he knocked the music ceased a minute, and Mrs. 
Adams put her head out of the sitting-room window. 
 
</p><p>"Has Henry got home?" asked he. 
 
</p><p>"No, he ain't.  Won't you come in, Doctor Ware?" 
 
</p><p>"No, thanky; I jest thought I'd luk round an' see ef he was to 
home." 
 
</p><p>The music began again directly.  Mrs. Adams had a sweet voice.  
She had sung in the choir when she was a girl, and had an enduring 
love for music, which age and prosaicness could not affect.  Her 
melodeon was her dear household god.  Her voice rang out  
 
<pb n="32"/>  
 
sweet and shrill in a psalm tune after Doctor Ware, as he plodded 
up the road. 
 
</p><p>The next day he went to Dover, a town about six miles distant.  
Part of the way he rode, begging lifts from passing teams; part of 
the way he walked. 
 
</p><p>In Dover, he found Henry's uncle's house easily enough, but 
not Henry.  He was not there; had not been there at all. 
 
</p><p>It was late in the afternoon when the old man reached home.  
He was stiff and tired, but he did not eat or rest.  He went 
straight to the Adams' again.  He knocked.  No one came to the 
door, but he heard, like an echo to the knock, the cry that he had 
heard the other day.  The echo was a double and triple one too; it 
came again and again; it resolved itself into words.  He heard 
distinctly: 
 
</p><p>"Help! help!  Let me out!  Let&mdash;me&mdash;o-ut!" 
 
</p><p>"What's the matter?  Who is it?" he shouted back. 
 
</p><p>"It's me&mdash;Henry.  Mother's got me locked down here!" 
 
</p><p>The poor young fellow, who was hardly more than a boy, was 
evidently terribly shaken.  The words ended in a groan. 
 
</p><p>"I'll let you out, Henry.  Whar air you?" 
 
</p><p>The old man knelt down on the ground and put his ear close to 
a tiny grated cellar window.  The voice seemed to come from that 
direction, though from a long distance; it was almost smothered. 
 
</p><p>"I'm down here&mdash;in the cellar&mdash;in a little room we store 
things in.  Get the key off the kitchen shelf.  Oh!" 
 
</p><p>"Thar, thar, Henry, I'm a comin'." 
 
</p><p>The house door was not locked.  Doctor Ware hastened into the 
kitchen.  There was a bunch of keys on the corner of the high, 
drab-painted shelf.  He caught them up and opened doors till he 
found the cellar stairs.  Henry sang out again when he heard his 
steps on them: 
 
</p><p>"Here I am, here!  Over to the left!" 
 
</p><p>The store-room, which had served as a dungeon, was a small 
apartment staunchly petitioned off in a corner of the cellar.  The 
stone cellar walls formed two of its sides; stout posts and planks 
the others.  The door was thick and firmly hung. 
 
</p><p>"The little, nasty key!" Henry cried, when he heard his 
deliverer working at the lock. 
 
</p><p>"What on airth does all this mean?" asked the old man, when 
the door was open and the young fellow came out. 
 
</p><p>The prisoner's face was white, and his blue eyes looked out of 
it wild and scared.  He sank down on the cellar stairs and rested 
a minute, he trembled so. 
 
</p><p>"Mother&mdash;she locked me in here night before last." 
 
</p><p>"What fur?" 
 
</p><p>"I told her I was goin' over to see Mary Anne.  She kinder 
tried to git me off the notion, and didn't act as ef she cared 
much.  But when I stuck to it I was goin', she got real upset.  I 
didn't think she minded so much either.  She wanted me to come down 
here an' bring her up some pork before I started, and she asked me 
pleasant enough.  She must have come down after me like a cat; I 
didn't hear her.  I was just getting the pork out of the barrel, 
when I heard the door bang to and the key turn.  I'd left it in the 
lock.  I hollered, but she wouldn't say a word.  I kept screaming 
about all night and next day, but she wouldn't let me out, and I 
couldn't raise anybody else.  I'd 'bout given it up when I heard 
you knock just now.  See anything of mother when you come in?" 
 
</p><p>"No; I guess she's gone out somewhere.  Ain't you hungry?" 
 
</p><p>"No; she left enough for me to eat.  There were mince pies 
stored away there, and a lot of fruit cake.  She knew I wouldn't 
starve.  If I'd had a hatchet or something, I could have broken the 
door down, but I didn't have so much as a jack-knife.  Oh!" 
 
</p><p>"Don't go to feelin' bad, Henry.  Le's go up stairs." 
 
</p><p>"I can't help it.  Seems as if I should go crazy&mdash;to think of 
mother doing such a thing!" 
 
</p><p>But he arose and went up the stairs inanely, with Doctor Ware 
following.  They had been standing talking in the kitchen a moment, 
when they heard steps. 
 
</p><p>"That's mother," whispered Henry, and pulled his companion 
into the sitting-room.  They stood there listening.  They heard the 
door open and the sound of the steps across the kitchen floor.  The 
cellar stairs creaked. 
 
</p><p>There was a cry from below, and the steps returned rapidly.  
Mrs. Adams walked into the sitting-room directly, as if she knew 
they were there. 
 
</p><p>"Henry!" she gasped.  
 
<pb n="33"/>  
 
</p><p>Then she leaned back against the wall and looked at him. 
 
</p><p>Through all his life, Henry Adams had never seen fear in his 
mother's face.  He saw it now. 
 
</p><p>"Mother," he said sternly, "I should like to have you tell me 
what you mean by such actions." 
 
</p><p>"I was jest comin' to let you out," she murmured feebly. 
 
</p><p>"What did you mean by doin' such a thing?  Are you crazy?" 
 
</p><p>"No, I ain't, Henry.  Don't be mad.  I'll tell you all about 
it." 
 
</p><p>She looked at him with abashed, pleading eyes.  His boyish 
face seemed strange to her.  Mrs. Adams was a keen, shrewd woman; 
but one of the simplest of the facts in her daily life, which stood 
out before her glaringly, she had not noted: her son was no longer 
her property, but his own.  She looked up at him, trembling.  He 
was small, but taller than she. 
 
</p><p>"Oh, Henry, I was jest a-comin' down to let you out, Henry, I 
was!  I'd been over to the neighborhood meetin', an' they got to 
talkin' 'bout her, 'bout Mary Anne, you know.  I come right home to 
let you out.  I didn't mean no harm no how.  Only you're all I've 
got, and her folks ain't very forehanded, an' she's been petted, 
an' she ain't very strong.  I thought mebbe you could do better." 
 
</p><p>"But I've been thinkin' of it over this afternoon," she 
continued, "an' I thought I wouldn't say anythin' more 'bout it.  
You could do jest as you was a mind to, an' I'd make the best of 
it.  I was comin' right home to let you out.  Henry, you ain't 
goin' to be set against me for it?" 
 
</p><p>"No, it's all right, mother; we won't say anything more about 
it." 
 
</p><p>"I'll give you a bottle of my blackberry wine to carry over to 
her when you go to-night.  It'll do her good." 
 
</p><p>That night when it was dusk, after tea, Mary Anne and her 
mother were in the sitting-room by the window.  Suddenly Mary Anne 
gave a little gasping cry: 
 
</p><p>"Oh, mother, here's Henry!" 
 
</p><p>Pretty soon the full moon rose.  Doctor Ware came down from 
his chamber and found Mrs. Hatton by the window, leaning out 
cautiously, her face toward the front door.  She drew her head in 
when he entered. 
 
</p><p>"Mary Anne's got company," she whispered, her lips trembling 
into smiles.  "Henry Adams." 
 
</p><p>"I know it.  I think she seems consider'ble better.  Well, I 
guess I'll say good-bye, Miss Hatton." 
 
</p><p>"You ain't goin'?" 
 
</p><p>"Well, yes; I orter be movin'.  I've staid here 'bout long 
enough.  I'm a-goin' to Mr. Thomas' to-night an' on to Somerset 
to-morrer.  I see Thomas this arternoon.  I thought 'twould be cooler 
goin' to-night.  You kin tell your husband good-bye.  I see him 
goin' down to the village." 
 
</p><p>"Yes, I'll tell him.  Well, good-bye, Doctor Ware, if you feel 
as if you must go.  I hope you'll feel free to come ag'in any 
time." 
 
</p><p>Before he had left the room, she was peeping from the window 
again, and straining to listen to the low murmur of voices on the 
doorstep.  Her face was alive with the tenderest and sweetest 
curiosity. 
 
</p><p>The old herb-man, coming around the house from a side door, 
glanced at the young couple seated together under the green 
trellis.  They must have seen him as he turned off down the lane, 
but they never spoke a word.  The old man plodded on through the 
crisp dew-white grass, between the wet bushes, which were bushes of 
silver in the moonlight. 
 
</p><p>"When the sick folks get well, the doctor goes," he said to 
himself. 
 
 
 
</p> 
</div1> 
 
</body> 
</text> 
</TEI.2> 
 
