<?xml version="1.0"?>

<?dlps id="ZitPaga"?>
<?dlps page-images="none" figure-images="no"?>
<?dlps transcription="other"?>

<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/tei-p4/tei2.dtd" [
<!ENTITY % POSTKB "INCLUDE">
<!ENTITY % TEI.extensions.ent SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.ent">
<!ENTITY % TEI.extensions.dtd SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.dtd">
<!ENTITY % ISOnum SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/charent/iso-num.ent"> %ISOnum;
<!ENTITY % ISOpub SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/charent/iso-pub.ent"> %ISOpub;
]> 
<TEI.2 id="ZitPaga"> 
<teiHeader type="migrated" creator="Etext">
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title type="main">Why I Am a Pagan</title>
<title type="sort">why i am a pagan</title>
<author>Zitkala-Sa</author>
<respStmt>
<resp>Creation of machine-readable version</resp>
<name>Judy Boss, University of Omaha</name>
</respStmt>
<respStmt>
<resp>Conversion to TEI-conformant markup</resp>
<name>University of Virginia Library Electronic Text Center</name>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt> 
<extent>ca. <num type="kilobytes">11</num> kilobytes</extent> 
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>University of Virginia Library</publisher>
<pubPlace>Charlottesville, Virginia</pubPlace> 
<idno type="ETC">ZitPaga</idno> 
<date value="1994">1994</date>
<availability status="public">
<p n="copyright">Copyright &copy; 1994 by the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia</p>
<p n="access">Publicly accessible</p>
</availability>
<idno type="uva-pid">uva-lib:476568</idno>
</publicationStmt>
<seriesStmt>
<title>University of Virginia Library, Text collection</title>
<idno type="uva-set">UVA-LIB-Text</idno>
</seriesStmt> 
<sourceDesc>
<biblFull>
<titleStmt>
<title type="main">Why I Am a Pagan</title>
<title type="sort">why i am a pagan</title>
<author>Zitkala-Sa</author>
</titleStmt> 
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>Atlantic Monthly</publisher> 
<pubPlace>New York</pubPlace> 
<date value="1902">1902</date>
</publicationStmt> 
<seriesStmt>
<p>Volume 90</p>
</seriesStmt> 
<notesStmt>
<note>
<p>pp. 801-803</p>
</note>
</notesStmt>
</biblFull>
</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc> 
<encodingDesc>
<projectDesc>
<p>Prepared for the University of Virginia Library Electronic Text Center</p>
</projectDesc> 
<editorialDecl>
<p>All quotation marks retained as data</p> 
<p>All unambiguous end-of-line hyphens have been removed, and the 
trailing part of a word has been joined to the preceding line.</p> 
<p id="ETC">Keywords in the header are a local Electronic Text Center scheme  
to aid in establishing analytical groupings</p>
</editorialDecl> 
<refsDecl>
<p>ID elements are given for each page element and are composed of the text's 
unique cryptogram and the given page number, as in SpeFQue1 for page one of  
Spenser's Faerie Queene.</p>
</refsDecl>
</encodingDesc> 
<profileDesc>
<creation>
<date value="1902">1902</date>
</creation> 
<langUsage>
<language id="eng" usage="main">English</language>
</langUsage> 
<textClass>
<keywords>
<term>nonfiction; prose</term> 
<term>Native American</term>
<term>Women Writers</term>
<term>Young Readers</term>
</keywords>
</textClass>
</profileDesc> 
<revisionDesc>
<change>
<date value="1994-08">August 1994</date> 
<respStmt>
<resp>corrector</resp>
<name>Kelly Tetterton</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Minimal TEI tagging</item>
</change> 
<change>
<date value="2005-07">July 2005</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>Corrector</resp>
<name>Margaret Konkol</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Converted SGML to XML and fixed tagging.</item>
</change>
<change>
<date value="2007-09">September 2007</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>Migration</resp>
<name>Ethan Gruber, University of Virginia Library</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Converted XML markup from TEI Lite to uva-dl-tei (TEI P4 with local customizations).</item>
</change>
<change>
<date value="2008-01">January 2008</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>Migration</resp>
<name>Greg Murray, University of Virginia Library</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Programmatically updated TEI header markup (but not header content) for minimal compliance with current QA requirements.</item>
</change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader> 

<text id="d1">  
<body id="d2"> 


<div1 type="essay" id="d3">
<head>
Zitkala-Sa.  "Why I Am a Pagan."
<lb/>
<hi rend="italic">Atlantic Monthly</hi> 90 (1902):  801-803.</head><pb n="801"/>  

<p>WHEN the spirit swells my breast I love to roam leisurely 
among the green hills; or sometimes, sitting on the brink of the 
murmuring Missouri, I marvel at the great blue overhead.  With half 
closed eyes I watch the huge cloud shadows in their noiseless play 
upon the high bluffs opposite me, while into my ear ripple the 
sweet, soft cadences of the river's song.  Folded hands lie in my 
<pb n="802"/>  
lap, for the time forgot.  My heart and I lie small upon 
the earth like a grain of throbbing sand.  Drifting clouds and 
tinkling waters, together with the warmth of a genial summer day, 
bespeak with eloquence the loving Mystery round about us.  During 
the idle while I sat upon the sunny river brink, I grew somewhat, 
though my response be not so clearly manifest as in the green grass 
fringing the edge of the high bluff back of me. 
</p><p>At length retracing the uncertain footpath scaling the 
precipitous embankment, I seek the level lands where grow the wild 
prairie flowers.  And they, the lovely little folk, soothe my soul 
with their perfumed breath. 
</p><p>Their quaint round faces of varied hue convince the heart 
which leaps with glad surprise that they, too, are living symbols 
of omnipotent thought.  With a child's eager eye I drink in the 
myriad star shapes wrought in luxuriant color upon the green.  
Beautiful is the spiritual essence they embody. 
</p><p>I leave them nodding in the breeze but take along with me 
their impress upon my heart.  I pause to rest me upon a rock 
embedded on the side of a foothill facing the low river bottom.  
Here the Stone-Boy, of whom the American aborigine tells, frolics 
about, shooting his baby arrows and shouting aloud with glee at the 
tiny shafts of lightning that flash from the flying arrow-beaks.  
What an ideal warrior he became, baffling the siege of the pests of 
all the land till he triumphed over their united attack.  And here 
he lay, &mdash; Invan, our great-great-grandfather, older than the hill he 
rested on, older than the race of men who love to tell of his 
wonderful career. 
</p><p>Interwoven with the thread of this Indian legend of the rock, 
I fain would trace a subtle knowledge of the native folk which 
enabled them to recognize a kinship to any and all parts of this 
vast universe.  By the leading of an ancient trail, I move toward 
the Indian village. 
</p><p>With the strong, happy sense that both great and small are so 
surely enfolded in His magnitude that, without a miss, each has his 
allotted individual ground of opportunities, I am buoyant with good 
nature. 
</p><p>Yellow Breast, swaying upon the slender stem of a wild 
sunflower, warbles a sweet assurance of this as I pass near by.  
Breaking off the clear crystal song, he turns his wee head from 
side to side eyeing me wisely as slowly I plod with moccasined 
feet.  Then again he yields himself to his song of joy.  Flit, flit 
hither and yon, he fills the summer sky with his swift, sweet 
melody.  And truly does it seem his vigorous freedom lies more in 
his little spirit than in his wing. 
</p><p>With these thoughts I reach the log cabin whither I am 
strongly drawn by the tie of a child to an aged mother.  Out bounds 
my four-footed friend to meet me, frisking about my path with 
unmistakable delight.  Chan is a black shaggy dog, "a thorough bred 
little mongrel," of whom I am very fond.  Chan seems to understand 
many words in Sioux, and will go to her mat even when I whisper the 
word, though generally I think she is guided by the tone of the 
voice.  Often she tries to imitate the sliding inflection and long 
drawn out voice to the amusement of our guests, but her 
articulation is quite beyond my ear.  In both my hands I hold her 
shaggy head and gaze into her large brown eyes.  At once the 
dilated pupils contract into tiny black dots, as if the roguish 
spirit within would evade my questioning. 
</p><p>Finally resuming the chair at my desk I feel in keen sympathy 
with my fellow creatures, for I seem to see clearly again that all 
are akin. 
</p><p>The racial lines, which once were bitterly real, now serve 
nothing more than marking out a living mosaic of human beings.  And 
even here men of the same color are like the ivory keys of one 
instrument where each represents all the rest, yet varies from them 
in pitch and 
<pb n="803"/>  
quality of voice.  And those creatures who are 
for a time mere echoes of another's note are not unlike the fable 
of the thin sick man whose distorted shadow, dressed like a real 
creature, came to the old master to make him follow as a shadow.  
Thus with a compassion for all echoes in human guise, I greet the 
solemn-faced "native preacher" whom I find awaiting me.  I listen 
with respect for God's creature, though he mouth most strangely the 
jangling phrases of a bigoted creed. 
</p><p>As our tribe is one large family, where every person is 
related to all the others, he addressed me: &mdash;  
</p><p>"Cousin, I came from the morning church service to talk with 
you." 
</p><p>"Yes," I said interrogatively, as he paused for some word from 
me. 
</p><p>Shifting uneasily about in the straight-backed chair he sat 
upon, he began: "Every holy day (Sunday) I look about our little 
God's house, and not seeing you there, I am disappointed.  This is 
why I come to-day.  Cousin, as I watch you from afar, I see no 
unbecoming behavior and hear only good reports of you, which all 
the more burns me with the wish that you were a church member.  
Cousin, I was taught long years ago by kind missionaries to read 
the holy book.  These godly men taught me also the folly of our old 
beliefs. 
</p><p>"There is one God who gives reward or punishment to the race 
of dead men.  In the upper region the Christian dead are gathered 
in unceasing song and prayer.  In the deep pit below, the sinful 
ones dance in torturing flames. 
</p><p>"Think upon these things, my cousin, and choose now to avoid 
the after-doom of hell fire!"  Then followed a long silence in 
which he clasped tighter and unclasped again his interlocked 
fingers. 
</p><p>Like instantaneous lightning flashes came pictures of my own 
mother's making, for she, too, is now a follower of the new 
superstition. 
</p><p>"Knocking out the chinking of our log cabin, some evil hand 
thrust in a burning taper of braided dry grass, but failed of his 
intent, for the fire died out and the half burned brand fell inward 
to the floor.  Directly above it, on a shelf, lay the holy book.  
This is what we found after our return from a several days' visit.  
Surely some great power is hid in the sacred book!" 
</p><p>Brushing away from my eyes many like pictures, I offered 
midday meal to the converted Indian sitting wordless and with 
downcast face.  No sooner had he risen from the table with "Cousin, 
I have relished it," than the church bell rang. 
</p><p>Thither he hurried forth with his afternoon sermon.  I watched 
him as he hastened along, his eyes bent fast upon the dusty road 
till he disappeared at the end of a quarter of a mile. 
</p><p>The little incident recalled to mind the copy of a missionary 
paper brought to my notice a few days ago, in which a "Christian" 
pugilist commented upon a recent article of mine, grossly 
perverting the spirit of my pen.  Still I would not forget that the 
pale-faced missionary and the hoodooed aborigine are both God's 
creatures, though small indeed their own conceptions of Infinite 
Love.  A wee child toddling in a wonder world, I prefer to their 
dogma my excursions into the natural gardens where the voice of the 
Great Spirit is heard in the twittering of birds, the rippling of 
mighty waters, and the sweet breathing of flowers.  If this is 
Paganism, then at present, at least, I am a Pagan.
</p>
<signed> 
                              <hi rend="italic">Zitkala-Sa.</hi>
</signed>
 
</div1> 
</body> 
</text> 
</TEI.2> 
