<?xml version="1.0"?>

<?dlps id="AddWome"?>
<?dlps page-images="color" figure-images="no"?>
<?dlps transcription="other"?>

<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/tei-p4/tei2.dtd" [
<!ENTITY % POSTKB "INCLUDE">
<!ENTITY % TEI.extensions.ent SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.ent">
<!ENTITY % TEI.extensions.dtd SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.dtd">
<!ENTITY % ISOpub SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/charent/iso-pub.ent"> %ISOpub;
<!ENTITY DSSR_000002629_0001 SYSTEM "000002629_0001" NDATA uvaHighRes>
<!ENTITY DSSR_000002629_0002 SYSTEM "000002629_0002" NDATA uvaHighRes>
]>
<TEI.2 id="AddWome">
    <teiHeader type="migrated" creator="Etext">
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title type="main">Women and Public Housekeeping</title>
                <title type="sort">women and public housekeeping</title>
                <author>Addams, Jane</author>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Creation of machine-readable version:</resp>
                    <name>Sharla Richards</name>
                    <resp>Creation of digital images:</resp>
                    <name>University of Virginia Special Collections</name>
                    <resp>Conversion to TEI.2-conformant markup:</resp>
                    <name>Sharla Richards</name>
                </respStmt>
            </titleStmt>
            <extent>ca. <num type="kilobytes">10</num> kilobytes</extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>University of Virginia Library</publisher>
                <pubPlace>Charlottesville, Virginia</pubPlace>
                <idno type="ETC">AddWome</idno>
                <date value="1996">1996</date>
                <availability status="public">
                    <p n="copyright">Copyright &#xa9; 1996 by the Rector and Visitors of the
                        University of Virginia</p>
                    <p n="access">Publicly accessible</p>
                </availability>
                <idno type="uva-pid">uva-lib:476619</idno>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title>University of Virginia Library, Text collection</title>
                <idno type="uva-set">UVA-LIB-Text</idno>
            </seriesStmt>
            <notesStmt>
                <note>
                    <p>Images of the broadside have been included from the print version. Figure in
                        image of verso contains "119." This may be related to the number of
                        printings or print edition.</p>
                </note>
                <note>
                    <p>TEI Project for University of Virginia Rare Book School 1996 Course 26,
                        Introduction to Electronic Texts</p>
                </note>
            </notesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull>
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title type="main">Women and Public Housekeeping</title>
                        <title type="sort">women and public housekeeping</title>
                        <author>Jane Addams</author>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <date value="1913">1913</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <seriesStmt>
                        <p>19th-Century American History: Manuscripts and Typescripts. Broadside
                            1913 .A44. Clifton Waller Barrett Library, University of Virginia
                            Special Collections.</p>
                    </seriesStmt>
                </biblFull>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>Prepared for the University of Virginia Library Electronic Text Center.</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <p>All quotation marks retained as data.</p>
                <p>The images exist as archived TIFF images, one or more JPEG versions for general
                    use, and thumbnail GIFs.</p>
                <p>Keywords in the header are a local Electronic Text Center scheme to aid in
                    establishing analytical groupings.</p>
            </editorialDecl>
            <refsDecl>
                <p>ID elements are given for each page element and are composed ofthe text's unique
                    cryptogram and the given page number, as in AusEmma1 for pageone of Jane
                    Austen's Emma.</p>
            </refsDecl>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <creation>
                <date value="1913">1913</date>
            </creation>
            <langUsage>
                <language id="eng" usage="main">English</language>
            </langUsage>
            <textClass>
                <keywords>
                    <term>non-fiction; prose</term>
                    <term>Women Writers</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords>
                    <term>24-bit color; 400 dpi</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change>
                <date value="1996-07">July 1996</date>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>corrector</resp>
                    <name>Catherine Tousignant</name>
                </respStmt>
                <item>Added information to header and figure descriptions about print source;
                    adjusted minor tagging errors; corrected minor typing errors</item>
            </change>
            <change>
                <date value="1999-03">March 1999</date>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>corrector</resp>
                    <name>Elizabeth Styron, University of Virginia Electronic Text Center</name>
                </respStmt>
                <item>Corrected and closed open tags; XML compliance check</item>
            </change>
            <change>
                <date value="2005-06">June 2005</date>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>corrector</resp>
                    <name>John Ivor Carlson</name>
                </respStmt>
                <item>Converted sgml to xml.</item>
            </change>
            <change>
                <date value="2007-09">September 2007</date>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Migration</resp>
                    <name>Ethan Gruber, University of Virginia Library</name>
                </respStmt>
                <item>Converted XML markup from TEI Lite to uva-dl-tei (TEI P4 with local
                    customizations).</item>
            </change>
            <change>
                <date value="2008-01">January 2008</date>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Migration</resp>
                    <name>Greg Murray, University of Virginia Library</name>
                </respStmt>
                <item>Programmatically updated TEI header markup (but not header content) for
                    minimal compliance with current QA requirements.</item>
            </change>
<change>
<date value="2009-03">March 2009</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>Migration</resp>
<name>Scholarly Resources, University of Virginia Library</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Added and/or replaced the digital images accompanying the electronic text. Scanning of exterior and interior (ie. pages) of item was done only for items found in the University of Virginia Special Collections Library.</item>
</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>

    <text id="d1">
        <body id="d2">
            <div1 type="story" n="1913" id="d3"><pb entity="DSSR_000002629_0001"/>
                <head>WOMEN AND PUBLIC HOUSEKEEPING<lb/> By Jane Addams</head>             

                <p> A city is in many respects a great business corporation, but in other <orig
                        reg="respects"> re-<lb/> spects </orig> it is enlarged housekeeping. If
                    American cities have failed in the first,<lb/> partly because officeholders have
                    carried with them the predatory instinct<lb/> learned in competitive business,
                    and cannot help "working a good thing"<lb/> when they have an opportunity, may
                    we not say that city housekeeping has<lb/> failed partly because women, the
                    traditional housekeepers, have not been<lb/> consulted as to its multiform
                    activities? The men of the city have been<lb/> carelessly indifferenct to much
                    of its civic housekeeping, as they have always<lb/> been indifferent to the
                    details of the household. They have totally <orig reg="disregarded">dis-<lb/>
                        regarded</orig> a candidate's capacity to keep the streets clean, preferring
                    to <orig reg="consider">con-<lb/> sider</orig> him in relation to the national
                    tariff or to the necessity for increasing<lb/> the national navy, in a pure
                    spirit of reversion to the traditional type of<lb/> government, which had to do
                    only with enemies and outsiders. </p>
                <p> It is difficult to see what military prowess has to do with the multiform<lb/>
                    duties which, in a modern city, include the care of parks and libraries, <orig
                        reg="superintendence">super-<lb/> intendence</orig> of markets, sewers and
                    bridges, the inspection of provisions and<lb/> boilers, and the proper disposal
                    of garbage. It has nothing to do with the<lb/> building department, which the
                    city maintains that it may see to it that the<lb/> basements are dry, that the
                    bedrooms are large enough to afford the required<lb/> cubic feet of air, that
                    the plumbing is sanitary, that the gas pipes do not leak,<lb/> that the tenement
                    house court is large enough to afford light and ventilation,<lb/> that the
                    stairways are fireproof. The ability to carry arms has nothing to do<lb/> with
                    the health department maintained by the city, which provides that <orig
                        reg="children">chil-<lb/> dren</orig> are vaccinated, that contagious
                    diseases are isolated and placarded, that<lb/> the spread of tuberculosis is
                    curbed, that the water is free from typhoid <orig reg="infection">infec-<lb/>
                        tion.</orig> Certainly the military conception of society is remote from the
                    functions<lb/> of the school boards, whose concern it is that children are
                    educated, that they<lb/> are supplied with kindergartens, and are given a decent
                    place in which to<lb/> play. The very multifariousness and complexity of a city
                    government<lb/> demand the help of minds accustomed to detail and variety of
                    work, to a<lb/> sense of obligation for the health and welfare of young
                    children, and to<lb/> responsibility for the cleanliness and comfort of other
                    people. </p>
                <p> Because all these things have traditionally been in the hands of women,<lb/> if
                    they take no part in them now they are not only missing the education<lb/> which
                    the natural participation in civic life would bring to them, but they<lb/> are
                    losing what they have always had. From the beginning of tribal life,<lb/></p>
                    <pb entity="DSSR_000002629_0002"/>
                    <p> they have been held responsible for the health of the community, a
                    function<lb/> which is now represented by the health department. From the days
                    of the<lb/> cave dwellers, so far as the home was clean and wholesome, it was
                    due to their<lb/> efforts, which are now represented by the Bureau of Tenement
                    House <orig reg="Inspection">Inspec-<lb/> tion.</orig> From the period of the
                    primitive village, the only public sweeping which<lb/> was performed was what
                    they undertook in their divers dooryards, that which<lb/> is now represented by
                    the Bureau of Street Cleaning. Most of the <orig reg="departments">depart-<lb/>
                        ments</orig> in a modern city can be traced to woman's traditional activity;
                    but, in<lb/> spite of this, so soon as these old affairs were turned over to the
                    city they<lb/> slipped from woman's hands, apparently because they then became
                    matters<lb/> for collective action and implied the use of the
                    franchise&mdash;because the <orig reg="franchise">fran-<lb/> chise</orig>
                    had in the first instance been given to the man who could fight, because<lb/> in
                    the beginning he alone could vote who could carry a weapon, it was <orig
                        reg="considered">consid-<lb/> ered</orig> an improper thing for a woman to
                    possess it. </p>
                <p> Is it quite public spirited for woman to say, "We will take care of these<lb/>
                    affairs so long as they stay in our own houses, but if they go outside and <orig
                        reg="concern">con-<lb/> cern</orig> so many people that they cannot be
                    carried on without the mechanism<lb/> of the vote, we will drop them; it is true
                    that these activities which women<lb/> have always had are not at present being
                    carried on very well by the men<lb/> in most of the great American cities, but,
                    because we do not consider it 'lady-<lb/> like' to vote, we will let them
                    alone?" </p>
            </div1>
        </body>

        <back id="d4">
            <div1 type="advertisement" id="d5">
               <p> FOR FURTHER INFORMATION ON WOMAN SUFFRAGE<lb/>
                </p>

                <p>The history, extent and results; the endorsements of organizations and
                    eminent<lb/> persons, the general arguments and the specific answers to
                    anti-suffrage objections.</p>

                <p>SEND TWO CENT STAMP FOR FREE CATALOG OF LITERATURE AND <lb/> SUPPLIES</p>
                <p> Address<lb/> National American Woman Suffrage Association<lb/> 505 Fifth Avenue
                    New York City<lb/>
                    <date value="1913"> 1913 </date></p>

            </div1>
        </back>
    </text>
</TEI.2>
