<?xml version="1.0"?>

<?dlps id="AhnIndi"?>
<?dlps page-images="none" figure-images="yes"?>
<?dlps transcription="other"?>

<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/tei-p4/tei2.dtd" [
<!ENTITY % POSTKB "INCLUDE">
<!ENTITY % TEI.extensions.ent SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.ent">
<!ENTITY % TEI.extensions.dtd SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.dtd">
<!ENTITY % ISOpub SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/charent/iso-pub.ent"> %ISOpub;


<!ENTITY DSSR_000002604_0001 SYSTEM "000002604_0001" NDATA uvaHighRes>
<!ENTITY DSSR_000002604_0002 SYSTEM "000002604_0002" NDATA uvaHighRes>
<!ENTITY DSSR_000002604_0003 SYSTEM "000002604_0003" NDATA uvaHighRes>
<!ENTITY DSSR_000002604_0004 SYSTEM "000002604_0004" NDATA uvaHighRes>
<!ENTITY DSSR_000002604_0005 SYSTEM "000002604_0005" NDATA uvaHighRes>
<!ENTITY DSSR_000002604_0006 SYSTEM "000002604_0006" NDATA uvaHighRes>
<!ENTITY DSSR_000002604_0007 SYSTEM "000002604_0007" NDATA uvaHighRes>
<!ENTITY DSSR_000002604_0008 SYSTEM "000002604_0008" NDATA uvaHighRes>
]>

<TEI.2 id="AhnIndi">
<teiHeader type="migrated" creator="Etext">
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title type="main">An Indian Boy's Story</title>
<title type="sort">indian boys story</title>
<author>Ah-nen-la-de-ni [La France, Daniel]</author>
<respStmt>
<resp>Creation of machine-readable version:</resp>
<name>Judy Boss</name>
<resp>Conversion to TEI.2-conformant markup:</resp>
<name>University of Virginia Library Electronic Text Center</name>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt>
<extent>ca. <num type="kilobytes">36</num> kilobytes</extent>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>University of Virginia Library</publisher>
<pubPlace>Charlottesville, Virginia</pubPlace>
<idno type="ETC">AhnIndi</idno>
<date value="1995">1995</date>
<availability status="public">
<p n="access">Publicly accessible</p>
</availability>
<idno type="uva-pid">uva-lib:476620</idno>
</publicationStmt>
<seriesStmt>
<title>University of Virginia Library, Text collection</title>
<idno type="uva-set">UVA-LIB-Text</idno>
</seriesStmt>
<notesStmt>
<note>
<p>Illustration of author has been included from the print version.</p>
</note>
</notesStmt>
<sourceDesc>
<biblFull>
<titleStmt>
<title type="main">An Indian Boy's Story</title>
<title type="sort">indian boys story</title>
<author>Ah-nen-la-de-ni [Daniel La France]</author>
<respStmt>
<resp>Editor</resp>
<name>anonymous; see editorial note preceding story</name>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt>
<publicationStmt>
<pubPlace>New York City</pubPlace>
<date value="1903-07-30">30 July 1903</date>
</publicationStmt>
<seriesStmt>
<p>The Independent, vol 55; pp. 1780-1787</p>
</seriesStmt>
<notesStmt>
<note>
<p>UVa library AP2 .I53</p>
</note>
<note>
<p>Note: On page 1787, paragraph 2, line 5, I have changed "schol" to
"school"; on page 1787, paragraph 3, line 1, I have changed
"chools" to "schools" [Judy Boss]</p>
</note>
</notesStmt>
</biblFull>
</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc>
<encodingDesc>
<projectDesc>
<p>Prepared for the University of Virginia Library Electronic Text Center</p>
</projectDesc>
<editorialDecl>
<p>All quotation marks retained as data</p>
<p>Spell-check and verification made
against printed text using WordPerfect spell checker</p>
<p>All unambiguous end-of-line hyphens have been removed, and the
trailing part of a word has been joined to the preceding line.</p>
<p id="ETC">Keywords in the header are a local Electronic Text Center scheme
to aid in establishing analytical groupings</p>
</editorialDecl>
<refsDecl>
<p>ID elements are given for each page element and are composed of the text's
unique cryptogram and the given page number, as in AusEmma1 for page one of
Jane Austen's Emma.</p>
</refsDecl>
</encodingDesc>
<profileDesc>
<creation>
<date value="1903-07-30">30 July 1903</date>
</creation>
<langUsage>
<language id="eng" usage="main">English</language>
<language id="moh">Mohawk</language>
</langUsage>
<textClass>
<keywords>
<term>non-fiction; prose</term>
<term>Native American</term>
<term>Young Readers</term>
</keywords>
</textClass>
</profileDesc>
<revisionDesc>
<change>
<date value="1995-11">November 1995</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>corrector</resp>
<name>Monique Dull, University of Virginia Library Electronic Text Center</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Basic conversion to TEI.2-conformant markup.</item>
</change>
<change>
<date value="2005-06">June 2005</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>corrector</resp>
<name>John Ivor Carlson</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Converted sgml to xml.</item>
</change>
<change>
<date value="2007-09">September 2007</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>Migration</resp>
<name>Ethan Gruber, University of Virginia Library</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Converted XML markup from TEI Lite to uva-dl-tei (TEI P4 with local customizations).</item>
</change>
<change>
<date value="2008-01">January 2008</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>Migration</resp>
<name>Greg Murray, University of Virginia Library</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Programmatically updated TEI header markup (but not header content) for minimal compliance with current QA requirements.</item>
</change>
<change>
<date value="2009-03">March 2009</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>Migration</resp>
<name>Scholarly Resources, University of Virginia Library</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Added and/or replaced the digital images accompanying the electronic text. Scanning of exterior and interior (ie. pages) of item was done only for items found in the University of Virginia Special Collections Library.</item>
</change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>
<text id="d1">
<body id="d2">


<div1 type="story" id="d3">
  <pb entity="DSSR_000002604_0001" n="1780"/>
<head type="main">An Indian Boy's Story</head>
<lb/>
  <p rend="center">By Ah-nen-la-de-ni</p>

<p>[Ah-nen-la-de-ni, whose American name is Daniel La France,
told his own tale in neat typewritten form, and has been aided only
to the extent of some rewriting and rearrangement.&mdash;EDITOR.]
</p>
  <cb n="1"/>
<p>I was born in Governeur Village, N. Y., in April, 1879, during one
of the periodical wanderings of my family, and my first
recollection is concerning a house in Toronto, Canada, in which I
was living with my father and mother, brother and grandmother.  I
could not have been much more than three years old at the time.
</p><p>My father was a pure-blooded Indian of the Mohawk tribe of the
Six Nations, and our home was in the St. Regis reservation in
Franklin County, N. Y., but we were frequently away from that place
because my father was an Indian medicine man, who made frequent
journeys, taking his family with him and selling his pills and
physics in various towns along the border line between Canada and
the United States.
</p><p>This house in Toronto was winter quarters for us.  In the
summer time we lived in a tent.  We had the upper part of the
house, while some gypsies lived in the lower part.

</p>
<p>All sorts of people came to consult the "Indian doctor," and
the gypsies sent them upstairs to us, and mother received 
<cb n="2"/>
them, and
then retired into another room with my brother and myself.  She did
not know anything about my father's medicines, and seemed to hate
to touch them.  When my father was out mother was frequently asked
to sell the medicines, but she would not, telling the patients that
they must wait until the doctor came home.  She was not pure-blooded Indian, her father being a French Canadian, while her
mother, my grandmother, was a pure-blooded Indian, who lived with
us.
</p><p>What made it all the more strange that mother would have
nothing to do with the medicines was the fact that grandmother was,
herself, a doctor of a different sort than my father.  Her remedies
were probably the same but in cruder form.  I could have learned
much if I had paid attention to her, because as I grew older she
took me about in the woods when she went there to gather herbs, and
she told me what roots and leaves to collect, and how to dry and
prepare them and how to make the extracts and what sicknesses they
were good for.  But I was soon tired of such matters, and would
stray off by myself
  <pb entity="DSSR_000002604_0002" n="1781"/>
  <cb n="1"/>
picking the berries&mdash;raspberry and blackberry, strawberry and blueberry&mdash;in
their seasons, and hunting the birds and little animals with my bow and
arrows.  So I learned very little from all this lore.
</p><p>My father was rather a striking figure.  His hair was long and
black, and he wore a long Prince Albert coat while in the winter
quarters, and Indian costume, fringed and beaded, while in the
tent.  His medicines were put up in pill boxes and labeled bottles,
and were the results of knowledge that had been handed down through
many generations in our tribe.
</p><p>My brother and I also wore long hair, and were strange enough
in appearance to attract attention from the white people about us,
but mother kept us away from them as much as possible.
</p><p>My father was not only a doctor, but also a trapper,
fisherman, farmer and basket maker.
</p><p>The reservation in Franklin County is a very beautiful place,
fronting on the main St. Lawrence River.  Tributaries of the St.
Lawrence wander through it, and its woods still preserve their wild
beauty.  On this reservation we had our permanent home in a log
house surrounded by land, on which we planted corn, potatoes and
such other vegetables as suited our fancies.  The house was more
than fifty years old.
</p><p>The woods provided my father and grandmother with their herbs
and roots, and they gathered there the materials for basket making.
There were also as late as 1880 some beavers, muskrats and minks to
be trapped, and pickerel, salmon and white perch to be caught in
the streams.  These last sources of revenue for the Indians no
longer exist; the beavers, minks and muskrats are extinct, while
the mills of the ever encroaching white man have filled the streams
with sawdust and banished the fish.
</p><p>We were generally on the reservation in early spring,
planting, fishing, basket making, gathering herbs and making
medicine, and then in the fall, when our little crop was brought
in, we would depart on our tour of the white man's towns and
cities, camping in a tent on the outskirts of some place, selling
our wares, which included bead work that mother and grandmother
were clever at 
<cb n="2"/>
making, and moving on as the fancy took us until
cold weather came, when my father would generally build a little
log house in some wood, plastering the chinks with moss and clay,
and there we would abide, warm amid ice and snow, till it was time
to go to the reservation again.
</p><p>One might imagine that with such a great variety of
occupations we would soon become rich&mdash;especially as we raised much
of our own food and seldom had any rent to pay&mdash;but this was not
the case.  I do not know how much my father charged for his
treatment of sick people, but his prices were probably moderate,
and as to our trade in baskets, furs and bead work, we were not any
better business people than Indians generally.
</p><p>Nevertheless, it was a happy life that we led, and lack of
money troubled us little.  We were healthy and our wants were few.
</p><p>Father did not always take his family with him on his
expeditions, and as I grew older I passed a good deal of time on
the reservation.  Here, tho the people farmed and dressed somewhat
after the fashion of the white man, they still kept up their
ancient tribal ceremonies, laws and customs, and preserved their
language.  The general government was in the hands of twelve
chiefs, elected for life on account of supposed merit and ability.
</p><p>There were four Indian day schools on the reservation, all
taught by young white women.  I sometimes went to one of these, but
learned practically nothing.  The teachers did not understand our
language, and we knew nothing of theirs so much progress was not
possible.
</p><p>Our lessons consisted of learning to repeat all the English
words in the books that were given us.  Thus, after a time, some of
us, myself included, became able to pronounce all the words in the
Fifth and Sixth readers, and took great pride in the exercise.  But
we did not know what any of the words meant.
</p><p>Our arithmetic stopped at simple numeration, and the only
other exercise we had was in writing, which, with us, resolved
itself into a contest of speed without regard to the form of
letters.
</p><p>The Indian parents were disgusted with the schools, and did
not urge their
  <pb entity="DSSR_000002604_0003" n="1782"/>
  <cb n="1"/>
children to attend, and when the boys and
girls did go of their own free will it was more for sociability and
curiosity than from a desire to learn.  Many of the boys and girls
were so large that the teachers could not preserve discipline, and
we spent much of our time in the school in drawing pictures of each
other and the teacher, and in exchanging in our own language such
remarks as led to a great deal of fighting when we regained the
open air.  Often boys went home with their clothing torn off them
in these fights.
</p><p>Under the circumstances, it is not strange that the attendance
at these schools was poor and irregular, and that on many days the
teachers sat alone in the schoolhouses because there were no
scholars.  Since that time a great change has taken place, and
there are now good schools on the reservation.
</p><p>I was an official of one of the schools, to the extent that I
chopped wood for it, but I did not often attend its sessions, and
when I was thirteen years of age, and had been nominally a pupil of
the school for six years, I was still so ignorant of English that
I only knew one sentence, which was common property among us
alleged pupils:
</p><p>"Please, ma'am, can I go out?" pronounced:
"Peezumgannigowout!"
</p><p>When I was thirteen a great change occurred, for the honey-tongued agent of a new Government contract Indian school appeared
on the reservation, drumming up boys and girls for his institution.
He made a great impression by going from house to house and
describing, through an interpreter, all the glories and luxuries of
the new place, the good food and teaching, the fine uniforms, the
playground and its sports and toys.
</p><p>All that a wild Indian boy had to do, according to the agent,
was to attend this school for a year or two, and he was sure to
emerge therefrom with all the knowledge and skill of the white man.
</p><p>My father was away from the reservation at the time of the
agent's arrival, but mother and grandmother heard him with growing
wonder and interest, as I did myself, and we all finally decided
that I ought to go to this wonderful school and become a great
man&mdash;perhaps at last 
<cb n="2"/>
a chief of our tribe.  Mother said that it was
good for Indians to be educated, as white men were "so tricky with
papers."
</p><p>I had, up to this time, been leading a very happy life,
helping with the planting, trapping, fishing, basket making and
playing all the games of my tribe&mdash;which is famous at lacrosse&mdash;but
the desire to travel and see new things and the hope of finding an
easy way to much knowledge in the wonderful school outweighed my
regard for my home and its joys, and so I was one of the twelve
boys who in 1892 left our reservation to go to the Government
contract school for Indians, situated in a large Pennsylvania city
and known as the &mdash; Institute.
</p><p>Till I arrived at the school I had never heard that there were
any other Indians in the country other than those of our
reservation, and I did not know that our tribe was called Mohawk.
My people called themselves "Ga-nien-ge-ha-ga," meaning "People of
the Beacon Stone," and Indians generally they termed "On-give-hon-we," meaning "Real-men" or "Primitive People."
</p><p>My surprise, therefore, was great when I found myself
surrounded in the school yard by strange Indian boys belonging to
tribes of which I had never head, and when it was said that my
people were only the "civilized Mohawks," I at first thought that
"Mohawk" was a nickname and fought any boy who called me by it.
</p><p>I had left home for the school with a great deal of hope,
having said to my mother: "Do not worry.  I shall soon return to
you a better boy and with a good education!"  Little did I dream
that that was the last time I would ever see her kind face.  She
died two years later, and I was not allowed to go to her funeral.
</p><p>The journey to Philadelphia had been very enjoyable and
interesting.  It was my first ride on the "great steel horse," as
the Indians called the railway train, but my frame of mind changed
as soon as my new home was reached.
</p><p>The first thing that happened to me and to all other freshly
caught young redskins when we arrived at the institution was a bath
of a particularly disconcerting sort.  We were used to baths of the
swimming variety, for on the reservation
  <pb entity="DSSR_000002604_0004" n="1783"/>
  <cb n="1"/>
we boys spent a
good deal of our time in the water, but this first bath at the
institution was different.  For one thing, it was accompanied by
plenty of soap, and for another thing, it was preceded by a haircut
that is better described as a crop.
</p><p>The little newcomer, thus cropped and delivered over to the
untender mercies of larger Indian boys of tribes different from his
own, who laughingly attacked his bare skin with very hot water and
very hard scrubbing brushes, was likely to emerge from the
encounter with a clean skin but perturbed mind.  When, in addition,
he was prevented from expressing his feelings in the only language
he knew, what wonder if some rules of the school were broken.
</p><p>After the astonishing bath the newcomer was freshly clothed
from head to foot, while the raiment in which he came from the
reservation was burned or buried.  Thereafter he was released by
the torturers, and could be seen sidling about the corridors like
a lonely crab, silent, sulky, immaculately clean and most
disconsolate.
</p><p>After my bath and reclothing and after having had my name
taken down in the records I was assigned to a dormitory, and began
my regular school life, much to my dissatisfaction.  The recording
of my name was accompanied by a change which, though it might seem
trifling to the teachers, was very important to me.  My name among
my own people was "Ah-nen-la-de-ni," which in English means
"Turning crowd" or "Turns the crowd," but my family had had the
name "La France" bestowed on them by the French some generations
before my birth, and at the institution my Indian name was
discarded, and I was informed that I was henceforth to be known as
Daniel La France.
</p><p>It made me feel as if I had lost myself.  I had been proud of
myself and my possibilities as "Turns the crowd," for in spite of
their civilized surroundings the Indians of our reservation in my
time still looked back to the old warlike days when the Mohawks
were great people, but Daniel La France was to me a stranger and a
nobody with no possibilities.  It seemed as if my prospect of a
<cb n="2"/>
chiefship had vanished.  I was very homesick for a long time.
</p><p>The dormitory to which I was assigned had twenty beds in it,
and was under a captain, who was one of the advanced scholars.  It
was his duty to teach and enforce the rules of the place in this
room, and to report to the white authorities all breaches of
discipline.
</p><p>Out in the school yard there was the same sort of supervision.
Whether at work or play, we were constantly watched, and there were
those in authority over us.  This displeased us Mohawks, who were
warriors at fourteen years of age.
</p><p>After the almost complete freedom of reservation life the
cramped quarters and the dull routine of the school were maddening
to all us strangers.  There were endless rules for us to study and
abide by, and hardest of all was the rule against speaking to each
other in our own language.  We must speak English or remain silent,
and those who knew no English were forced to be dumb or else break
the rules in secret.  This last we did quite frequently, and were
punished, when detected, by being made to stand in the "public
hall" for a long time or to march about the yard while the other
boys were at play.
</p><p>There were about 115 boys at this school, and three miles from
us was a similar Government school for Indian girls, which had
nearly as many inmates.
</p><p>The system when I first went to this school contemplated every
Indian boy learning a trade as well as getting a grammar school
education.  Accordingly we went to school in the morning and to
work in the afternoon, or the other way about.
</p><p>There were shoemakers, blacksmiths, tinsmiths, farmers,
printers, all sorts of mechanics among us.  I was set to learn the
tailoring trade, and stuck at it for two and a half years, making
such progress that I was about to be taught cutting when I began to
cough, and it was said that outdoor work would be better for me.
Accordingly I went, during the vacation of 1895, up into Bucks
County, Pa., and worked on a farm with benefit to my health, tho I
was not a very successful farmer&mdash;the methods of the people
  <pb entity="DSSR_000002604_0005" n="1784"/>
  <cb n="1"/>
who employed me were quite different from those of our reservation.
</p><p>Tho I was homesick soon after coming to the Institute I
afterward recovered so completely that I did not care to go back to
the reservation at vacation time, tho at first I was offered the
opportunity.  I spent my vacations working for Quaker farmers.  All
the money I earned at this and other occupations was turned in to
the Institute bank credited to my account, and I drew from thence
money for my expenses and for special occasions like Christmas and
the Fourth of July.
</p><p>When I returned from Bucks County in 1895 I found that some of
the boys of my class were attending the public school outside the
institution, and on application I was allowed to join them, and
finally graduated there from the grammar department, tho held back
by the fact that I was spending half my time in some workshop.  I
never went back to tailoring, except to finish a few suits that
were left when the Institute shop closed, but I worked for a time
at printing and afterward at making cooking apparatuses.
</p><p>After I had finished with the grammar school I got a situation
in the office of a lawyer while still residing in the institution.
I also took a course of stenography and typewriting at the
Philadelphia Young Men's Christian Association.  So practically I
was only a boarder at the Institute during the latter part of my
eight years' stay there.
</p><p>Nevertheless, I was valuable to the authorities there for
certain purposes, and when I wanted to leave and go to Carlisle
school, which I had heard was very good, I could not obtain
permission.
</p><p>This Institute, as I have said, was a contract Government
school for teaching Indians.  The great exertions made by the
agent, who visited our reservation in the first place, were caused
by the fact that a certain number of Indian children had to be
obtained before the school could be opened.  I do not think that
the Indian parents signed any papers, but we boys and girls were
supposed to remain at the school for five years.  After that, as I
understand it, we were free from any obligation.
</p><p>The reason why I and others like me 
  <cb n="2"/>
  were kept at the school
was that we served as show scholars&mdash;as results of the system and
evidences of the good work the Institute was doing.
</p><p>When I first went to the school the superintendent was a
clergyman, honest and well meaning, and during the first five years
thereafter while he remained in charge the general administration
was honest, but when he went away the school entered upon a period
of changing administrations and general demoralization.  New
superintendents succeeded each other at short intervals, and some
of them were violent and cruel, while all seemed to us boys more or
less dishonest.  Boys who had been inmates of the school for eight
years were shown to visitors as results of two years' tuition, and
shoes and other articles bought in Philadelphia stores were hung up
on the walls at public exhibition or concert and exhibited as the
work of us boys.  I was good for various show purposes.  I could
sing and play a musical instrument, and I wrote essays which were
thought to be very good.  The authorities also were fond of
displaying me as one who had come to the school a few years before
unable to speak a word of English.
</p><p>Some of my verses that visitors admired were as follows: </p>

<lg type="stanza">
<head> THE INDIAN'S CONCEPTION. </head>
<l>When first the white man's ships appeared</l>
<l>  To Redmen of this wooded strand,</l>
<l>The Redmen gazed, and vastly feared,</l>
<l>  That they could not those "birds" withstand;</l>
<l>As they mistook the ships for birds.</l>
<l>  And this ill omen came quite true&mdash;</l>
<l>For later came more; hungrier birds.</l>
</lg>
<lg type="stanza">
<head> SLEEP SONG FOR THE PAPOOSE. </head>
<l>Look, little papoose, your cradle's unbound,</l>
<l>It's strappings let loose for you to be bound.</l>
<l>    Refrain:&mdash;Oh little papoose!.............</l>
<l>         On cradle-board bound;</l>
<l>         My swinging papoose,</l>
<l>         Your slumber be sound.</l>
<l>Tawn little papoose, your mother is in:</l>
<l>She's roasting the goose, on the sharp wooden pin.</l>
<l>                                   Ref.</l>
<l>Bound little papoose, your father is out;</l>
<l>He's hunting the moose that makes you grow stout.</l>
<l>                                   Ref.</l>
<l>Brawn little papoose, great hunter shall be;</l>
<l>And trap the great moose behind the pine tree.</l>
<l>                                   Ref.</l>
  <pb entity="DSSR_000002604_0006" n="1785"/>
  <cb n="1"/>
<l>My little papoose, swing, swing from the bough.</l>
<l>Grow! then you'll get loose&mdash;put plumes on your brow!</l>
<l>                                   Ref.</l>
<l>So little papoose, dream, dream as you sleep;</l>
<l>While friendly old spruce shall watch o'er you keep.</l>
<l>                                   Ref.</l>
<l>Now, little papoose, swing on to your rest.</l>
<l>My red browed papoose, swing east and swing west.</l>
<l>                                   Ref.</l>
</lg>
<p>Over the superintendent of the Institute there was a Board of
Lady Managers with a Lady Directress, and these visited us
occasionally, but there was no use laying any complaint before
them.  They were arbitrary and almost unapproachable.  Matters went
from bad to worse, and when the Spanish-American War broke out, and
my employer, the lawyer, resolved to go to it in the Red Cross
service, and offered to take me with him I greatly desired to go,
but was not allowed.  I suppose that the lawyer could easily have
obtained my liberty, but did not wish to antagonize the Lady
Managers, who considered any criticism of the institution as an
attack on their own infallibility.
</p><p>While waiting for a new situation after the young lawyer had
gone away, I heard of the opportunities there were for young men
who could become good nurses, and of the place where such training
could be secured.  I desired to go there, and presented this
ambition to the superintendent, who at first encouraged me to the
extent of giving a fair recommendation.  But when the matter was
laid before the Head Directress in the shape of an application for
admission ready to be sent by me to the authorities of the Nurses'
Training School she flatly refused it consideration without giving
any good reason for so doing.
</p><p>She, however, made the mistake of returning the application to
me, and it was amended later and sent to the Training School in
Manhattan.  It went out through a secret channel, as all the
regular mail of the institution's inmates, whether outgoing or
incoming, was opened and examined in the office of the
superintendent.
</p><p>A few days before the 4th of July, 1899, the answer to my
application arrived in the form of notice to report at the school
for the entrance examination.  This communication found me in the
<cb n="2"/>
school jail, where I had been placed for the first time in all my
life at the institution.
</p><p>I had been charged with throwing a nightgown out of the
dormitory window, and truly it was my nightgown that was found in
the school yard, for it had my number upon it.  But I never threw
it out of the window.  I believe that one of the official
underlings did that in order to found upon it a charge against me,
for the school authorities had discovered that I and other boys of
the institution had gone to members of the Indian Rights
Association and had made complaint of conditions in the school, and
that an investigation was coming.  They, therefore, desired to
disgrace and punish me as one of the leaders of those who were
exposing them.
</p><p>I heard about the letter from the Training School, and was
very anxious to get away, but my liberation in time to attend that
entrance examination seemed impossible.  The days passed, and when
the 4th of July arrived I was still in the school jail, which was
the rear part of a stable.
</p><p>At one o'clock my meal of bread and water was brought to me by
the guard detailed to look after my safe keeping.  After he had
delivered this to me he went outside, leaving the door open, but
standing there.  The only window of that stable was very small,
very high on the wall and was protected by iron bars&mdash;but here was
the door left open.
</p><p>I fled, and singularly enough the guard had his back turned
and was contemplating nature with great assiduity.  As soon as I
got out of the inclosure I dashed after and caught a trolley car,
and a few hours later I was in New York.
</p><p>That was the last I saw of the Institute and it soon afterward
went out of existence, but I heard that as a result of the demand
for an investigation the Superintendent of Indian Schools had
descended on it upon a given day and found everything beautiful&mdash;
for her visit had been announced.  But she returned again the next
day, when it was supposed that she had left the city, and then
things were not beautiful at all, and much that we had told about
was proven.
</p><p>I had $15 in the Lincoln Institute bank when I ran away, but
I knew that was
  <pb entity="DSSR_000002604_0007" n="1786"/>
  <cb n="1"/>
past crying for and I depended on $3 that
I had in my pocket and with which I got a railroad ticket to New
York.
</p><p>I was assisted in my escape and afterward by a stedfast friend
and had comparatively plain sailing, as I passed the entrance
examination easily and was admitted to the Training School on
probation.
</p><p>The Institute people wrote and wrote after me, but could not
get me back or cause the Training School to turn me out, and they
soon had their own troubles to attend to.  The school was closed in
1900 as the Government cut off all appropriations.
</p><p>When I first entered the Training School on probation I was
assigned to the general surgical ward and there took my first
lessons in the duties of a nurse, being taught how to receive a
patient&mdash;whether walking or carried&mdash;how to undress him and put him
in bed, to make a list of his property, to make a neat bundle of
his clothes, to enter his name and particulars about him in the
records, and how to properly discharge patients, returning their
property and clothes, and all about bed making, straightening out
the ward, making bandages and scores of other details.  I studied
all books on nursing and attended all the lectures.  Bed making, as
I soon found, was an art in itself and a most important art, and so
in regard to other details, all of which may look trivial to an
outsider, but which count in sanitation.
</p><p>This new life was very much to my liking.  I was free, for one
thing, and was working for myself with good hope of accomplishing
something.
</p><p>Our evenings were our own after our work was done, and tho we
had to return to the nurses' quarters at 10.30 o'clock at the
latest, that was not a hardship and we could enjoy some of the
pleasures of the city.  While in the Training School I received my
board and $10 a month pay, a very decided gain over the Institute.
Besides, the food and quarters were far better.
</p><p>After I had been for twelve months in the Training School I
was allowed to go to our reservation for a ten days' vacation.  It
was the first time in nine years that I had seen my old home and I
found things much changed.  My mother and 
<cb n="2"/>
grandmother were dead,
and there had died also a little sister whom I had never seen.  My
father was alive and still wandering as of old.  Many of my
playmates had scattered and I felt like a stranger.  But it was
very pleasant to renew acquaintance with the places and objects
that had been familiar in my childhood&mdash;the woods, the streams, the
bridge&mdash;that used to look so big and was now so small to me&mdash;the
swimming hole, and with the friends who remained.
</p><p>I found that our people had progressed.  The past and its
traditions were losing their hold on them and white man's ways were
gaining.
</p><p>During the visit I lived at the house of my brother, who is
ten years older than me and is a farmer and manufacturer of snow
shoes and lacrosse sticks.  The ten days passed all too quickly.
</p><p>Since that time I have paid one other and much longer visit to
the reservation and have quite renewed touch with my own people,
who are always glad to see me and who express much astonishment at
the proficiency I show in my native tongue.  Most of the boys who
are away from the reservation for three or four years forget our
language, but, as I have said, there were some of us at the
Institute who practiced in secret.
</p><p>What I saw in the reservation convinced me that our people are
not yet ready for citizenship and that they desire and should be
allowed to retain their reservation.  They are greatly obliged to
those who have aided them in defeating the Vreeland bill.  The
whole community is changing and when the change advances a little
further it will be time to open the reservation gates and let in
all the world.
</p><p>Of course, so far as the old Indians are concerned, they will
not and cannot change.  They have given up the idea that the
Mohawks will ever again be a great people, but they cannot alter
their habits and it only remains for them to pass away.  They want
to end their days in comfort and peace, like the cat by the
fireside&mdash;that is all.
</p><p>To the white man these old people may not seem important, but
to us young Indians they are very important.  The family tie is
strong among Indians.  White people are aggravated because so many
  <pb entity="DSSR_000002604_0008" n="1787"/>
  <cb n="1"/>
young Indians, after their schooling, go back to their
reservations and are soon seen dressed and living just like the
others.  But they must do that if they desire to keep in touch with
the others.
</p><p>Supposing the young Indian who has been to school did not
return to his father's house, but stayed out among the white men.
The old folks would say "He won't look at us now.  He thinks
himself above us."  And all parents who observed this would add:
"We won't send our children to school.  They would never come back
to us."
</p><p>The young Indians are right to go back to the reservation and
right to dress and act like the others, to cherish the old folks
and make their way easy, and not to forget their tribe.  It is a
mistake to think that they soon lose all that they have learned in
the school.  Compare the school Indians with those who have not
been at school and a very marked difference is found.  You find on
their farms improved methods and in their houses pianos, which
their wives, who have also been at school, can play.  All these
boys and girls who have been to school are as missionaries to the
reservation.
</p><p>The schools are doing a great deal of good to the Indians and
are changing them fast, and there is another force at work occupied
with another change.  On all the reservations the pure blooded
Indians are becoming rarer and rarer, and the half and quarter
breeds more and more common&mdash;technically they're Indians.  Thus tho
the tribe is increasing, the real Indians are decreasing.  They are
becoming more and more white.  On our reserve now you can see boys
and girls with light hair and blue eyes, children of white fathers
and Indian mothers.  They have the rosy cheeks of English children,
but they cannot speak a word of English.
</p><p>After returning to the Training School I completed the two
years' course and afterward took a special course in massage
treatment for paralysis.
</p><p>I have since been employed principally in private practice.
I like the work and 
<cb n="2"/>
the pay, tho the former is very exacting.  The
nurse must be very clean and very regular in his habits; he must be
firm and yet good-tempered&mdash;able to command the patient when
necessary.  He must maintain a cheerful attitude of mind and
demeanor toward a patient, who is often most abusive and ill
tempered.  He must please the doctor, the patient's family, and to
as great an extent as possible the patient himself.  He must be
watchful without appearing to watch.  He must be strong and
healthy.  Nursing is tiresome and confining.  Nevertheless I
console myself with the remunerations, financial and educational,
and with the thought that my present occupation, assisting in
saving lives, is an advance on that of scalp taking ancestors.
</p><p>I have been asked as to prejudice against Indians among white
people.  There is some, but I don't think it amounts to much.
Perhaps there were some in my Training School class who objected to
being associated with an Indian.  I never perceived it, and I don't
think I have suffered anywhere from prejudice.
</p><p>I have suffered many times from being mistaken for a Japanese.
</p><p>Some people when they find I am an Indian seek me out and have
much to say to me, but it is generally merely for curiosity and I
do not encourage them.  On the other hand, I have good, stedfast,
old-time friends among white people.
</p><p>When I first began to learn I thought that when I knew English
and could read and write it would be enough.  But the further I
have climbed the higher the hills in front of me have grown.  A few
years ago the point I have reached would have seemed very high.
Now it seems low, and I am studying much in my spare time.  I don't
know what the result will be.
</p><p>Some ask me whether or not I will ever return to my tribe.
How can I tell?  The call from the woods and fields is very clear
and moving, especially in these pleasant summer days.
</p>
<trailer>NEW YORK CITY. </trailer>

</div1>
</body>
</text>
</TEI.2>
