<?xml version="1.0"?>

<?dlps id="AlcBlin"?>
<?dlps page-images="color" figure-images="no"?>
<?dlps transcription="other"?>

<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/tei-p4/tei2.dtd" [
<!ENTITY % POSTKB "INCLUDE">
<!ENTITY % TEI.extensions.ent SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.ent">
<!ENTITY % TEI.extensions.dtd SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.dtd">
<!ENTITY % ISOpub SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/charent/iso-pub.ent"> %ISOpub;
<!ENTITY DSSR_000002630_0001 SYSTEM "000002630_0001" NDATA uvaHighRes>
<!ENTITY DSSR_000002630_0002 SYSTEM "000002630_0002" NDATA uvaHighRes>
<!ENTITY DSSR_000002630_0003 SYSTEM "000002630_0003" NDATA uvaHighRes>
<!ENTITY DSSR_000002630_0004 SYSTEM "000002630_0004" NDATA uvaHighRes>
<!ENTITY DSSR_000002630_0005 SYSTEM "000002630_0005" NDATA uvaHighRes>
<!ENTITY DSSR_000002630_0006 SYSTEM "000002630_0006" NDATA uvaHighRes>
<!ENTITY DSSR_000002630_0007 SYSTEM "000002630_0007" NDATA uvaHighRes>
<!ENTITY DSSR_000002630_0008 SYSTEM "000002630_0008" NDATA uvaHighRes>
]>
<TEI.2 id="AlcBlin">
    <teiHeader type="migrated" creator="Etext">
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title type="main">The Blind Lark / Alcott, Louisa M.; illustrated by W. H. Drake</title>
                <title type="sort">blind lark alcott, louisa m illustrated by w h drake</title>
                <author>Alcott, Louisa May, 1832-1888</author>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Illustrator</resp>
                    <name>Drake, W. H.</name>
                    <resp>Creation of machine-readable version:</resp>
                    <name>Judy Boss</name>
                    <resp>Creation of digital images:</resp>
                    <name>Greg Murray, Electronic Text Center</name>
                    <resp>Conversion to TEI.2-conformant markup:</resp>
                    <name>University of Virginia Library Electronic Text Center.</name>
                </respStmt>
            </titleStmt>
            <extent>ca. <num type="kilobytes">36</num> kilobytes</extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>University of Virginia Library</publisher>
                <pubPlace>Charlottesville, Virginia</pubPlace>
                <idno type="ETC">AlcBlin</idno>
                <date value="1998">1998</date>
                <availability status="public">
                    <p n="copyright">Copyright &#xa9; 1998 by the Rector and Visitors of the
                        University of Virginia</p>
                    <p n="access">Publicly accessible</p>
                </availability>
                <idno type="uva-pid">uva-lib:476625</idno>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title>University of Virginia Library, Text collection</title>
                <idno type="uva-set">UVA-LIB-Text</idno>
            </seriesStmt>
            <notesStmt>
                <note>
                    <p>Illustrations have been included from the original source.</p>
                </note>
                <note>
                    <p>In this etext, contractions have been closed, "do n't" becoming "don't" for
                        example.</p>
                </note>
            </notesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull>
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title type="main">The Blind Lark</title>
                        <title level="j">St. Nicholas</title>
                        <title type="sort">blind lark</title>
                        <author>Louisa M. Alcott</author>
                        <respStmt>
                            <resp>Illustrator</resp>
                            <name>W. H. Drake</name>
                        </respStmt>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Scribner &amp; Co.</publisher>
                        <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                        <date value="1943">1873-1943</date>
                        <idno type="callNo">Source copy consulted: Univ. of Virginia Library, AP201
                            .S3 vol. 14</idno>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <notesStmt>
                        <note>
                            <p>Vol. XIV, No. 1 (November 1886), pages 12-19.</p>
                        </note>
                    </notesStmt>
                </biblFull>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>Prepared for the University of Virginia Library Electronic Text Center.</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <p>All unambiguous end-of-line hyphens have been removed, and the trailing part of a
                    word has been joined to the preceding line.</p>
                <p id="ETC">Some keywords in the header are a local Electronic Text Center scheme to
                    aid in establishing analytical groupings.</p>
            </editorialDecl>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <creation>
                <date value="1886">1886</date>
            </creation>
            <langUsage>
                <language id="eng" usage="main">English</language>
            </langUsage>
            <textClass>
                <keywords>
                    <term>fiction</term>
                    <term>prose</term>
                    <term>feminine</term>
                    <term>Women Writers/Young Readers</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change>
                <date value="1998-10">October 1998</date>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>corrector</resp>
                    <name>Greg Murray, Electronic Text Center</name>
                </respStmt>
                <item>Added TEI header and tags.</item>
            </change>
            <change>
                <date value="2005-06">June 2005</date>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>corrector</resp>
                    <name>John Ivor Carlson</name>
                </respStmt>
                <item>Converted sgml to xml.</item>
            </change>
            <change>
                <date value="2007-09">September 2007</date>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Migration</resp>
                    <name>Ethan Gruber, University of Virginia Library</name>
                </respStmt>
                <item>Converted XML markup from TEI Lite to uva-dl-tei (TEI P4 with local
                    customizations).</item>
            </change>
            <change>
                <date value="2008-01">January 2008</date>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Migration</resp>
                    <name>Greg Murray, University of Virginia Library</name>
                </respStmt>
                <item>Programmatically updated TEI header markup (but not header content) for
                    minimal compliance with current QA requirements.</item>
            </change>
<change>
<date value="2009-03">March 2009</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>Migration</resp>
<name>Scholarly Resources, University of Virginia Library</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Added and/or replaced the digital images accompanying the electronic text. Scanning of exterior and interior (ie. pages) of item was done only for items found in the University of Virginia Special Collections Library.</item>
</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>

    <text id="d1">
        <body id="d2">
            <div1 type="story" id="d3">
                <pb entity="DSSR_000002630_0001" n="12"/>
                <head>THE BLIND LARK.<lb/> By<lb/> LOUISA M. ALCOTT.</head>

                   <p>HIGH up in an old house, full of poor people, lived Lizzie, with her mother and
                    baby Billy. The street was a narrow, noisy place, where carts rumbled and dirty
                    children played; where the sun seldom shone, the fresh wind seldom blew, and the
                    white snow of winter was turned at once to black mud. One bare room was Lizzie's
                    home, and out of it she seldom went, for she was a prisoner. We all pity the
                    poor princesses who were shut up in towers by bad fairies, the men and women in
                    jails, and the little birds in cages, but Lizzie was a sadder prisoner than any
                    of these. </p>
                <p>The prince always comes to the captive princess, the jail doors open in time, and
                    the birds find some kind hand to set them free; but there seemed no hope of
                    escape for this poor child. Only nine years old, and condemned to life-long
                    helplessness, loneliness, and darkness &mdash; for she was blind. </p>
                <p>She could dimly remember the blue sky, green earth, and beautiful sun; for the
                    light went out when she was six, and the cruel fever left her a pale little
                    shadow to haunt that room ever since. The father was dead, the mother worked
                    hard for daily bread, they had no friends, and the good fairies seemed to have
                    forgotten them. Still, like the larks one sees in Brittany, the eyes of which
                    cruel boys put out, that they may sing the sweeter, Lizzie made music in her
                    cage, singing to baby; and when he slept, she sat by the window listening to the
                    noise below for company, crooning to herself till she, too, fell asleep and
                    forgot the long, long days that had no play, no school, no change for her such
                    as other children know. </p>
                <p>Every morning Mother gave them their porridge, locked the door, and went away to
                    work, leaving something for the children's dinner, and Lizzie to take care of
                    herself and Billy till night. There was no other way, for both were too helpless
                    to be trusted elsewhere, and there was no one to look after them. But Lizzie
                    knew her way about the room, and could find the bed, the window, and the table
                    where the bread and milk stood. There was seldom any fire in the stove, and the
                    window was barred, so the little prisoners were safe, and day after day they
                    lived together a sad, solitary, unchildlike life that makes one's heart ache to
                    think of. </p>
                <p>Lizzie watched over Billy like a faithful little mother, and Billy did his best
                    to bear his trials, and comfort sister, like a man. He was not a rosy,
                    rollicking fellow, like most year-old boys, but pale and thin and quiet, with a
                    pathetic look in his big blue eyes, as if he said, "Something is wrong; will
                    some one kindly put it right for us?" But he seldom complained unless in pain,
                    and would lie for hours on the old bed, watching the flies, which were his only
                    other playmates, stretching out his little hands to the few rays of sunshine
                    that crept in now and then, as if longing for them, like a flower in a cellar.
                    When Lizzie sung, he hummed softly; and when he was hungry, cold, or tired, he
                    called "Lib! Lib!" meaning "Lizzie," and nestled up to her, forgetting all his
                    baby woes in her tender arms. </p>
                <p>Seeing her so fond and faithful, the poor neighbors loved as well as pitied her,
                    and did what they could for the afflicted child. The busy women would pause at
                    the locked door to ask if all was right; the dirty children brought her
                    dandelions <pb entity="DSSR_000002630_0002" n="13"/> from the park, and the rough workmen of the factory
                    opposite, with a kind word would toss an apple or a cake through the open
                    window. They had learned to look for the little wistful face behind the bars,
                    and loved to listen to the childish voice which caught and imitated the songs
                    they sung and whistled, like a sweet echo. They called her "the blind lark,"
                    and, though she never knew it, many were the better for the pity they gave her. </p>
                <p>Baby slept a great deal, for life offered him few pleasures, and, like a small
                    philosopher, he wisely tried to forget the troubles which he could not cure; so
                    Lizzie had nothing to do but sing, and try to imagine how the world looked. She
                    had no one to tell her, and the few memories grew dimmer and dimmer each year.
                    She did not know how to work or to play, never having been taught, and Mother
                    was too tired at night to do anything but get supper and go to bed. </p>
                <p>"The child will be an idiot soon, if she does not die," people said; and it
                    seemed as if this would be the fate of the poor little girl, since no one came
                    to save her during those three weary years. She often said, "I'm of <hi
                        rend="italic">some</hi> use. I take care of Billy, and I couldn't live
                    without him." </p>
                <p>But even this duty and delight was taken from her, for that cold spring nipped
                    the poor little flower, and one day Billy shut his blue eyes with a patient sigh
                    and left her all alone. </p>
                <p>Then Lizzie's heart seemed broken, and people thought she would soon follow him,
                    now that her one care and comfort was gone. All day she laid with her cheek on
                    Billy's pillow, holding the battered tin cup and a little worn-out shoe, and it
                    was pitiful to hear her sing the old lullabies as if baby still could hear them. </p>
                <p>"It will be a mercy if the poor thing doesn't live; blind folks are no use and a
                    sight of trouble," said one woman to another as they gossiped in the hall after
                    calling on the child during her mother's absence, for the door was left unlocked
                    since she was ill. </p>
                <p>"Yes, Mrs. Davis would get on nicely if she hadn't such a burden. Thank Heaven,
                    my children aren't blind," answered the other, hugging her baby closer as she
                    went away. </p>
                <p>Lizzie heard them, and hoped with all her sad little soul that death would set
                    her free, since she was of no use in the world. To go and be with Billy was all
                    her desire now, and she was on her way to him, growing daily weaker and more
                    content to be dreaming of dear baby well and happy, waiting for her somewhere in
                    a lovely place called Heaven. </p>
                <p>The summer vacation came, and hundreds of eager children were hurrying away to
                    the mountains and seashore for two months of healthful pleasure. Even the dirty
                    children in the lane felt the approach of berry-time, and rejoiced in their
                    freedom from cold as they swarmed like flies about the corner grocery where
                    over-ripe fruit was thrown out for them to scramble over. </p>
                <p>Lizzie heard about good times when some of these young neighbors were chosen to
                    go on the poor children's picnics, and came back with big sandwiches buttoned up
                    in their jackets; pickles, peanuts, and buns in their pockets; hands full of
                    faded flowers, and hearts brimming over with childish delight at a day in the
                    woods. She listened with a faint smile, enjoyed the "woodsy" smell of the green
                    things, and wondered if they had nice picnics in Heaven, being sorry that Billy
                    had missed them here. But she did not seem to care much, or hope for any
                    pleasure for herself except to see baby again. </p>
                <p>I think there were few sadder sights in that great city than this innocent
                    prisoner waiting so patiently to be set free. Would it be by the gentle angel of
                    death, or one of the human angels who keep these little sparrows from falling to
                    the ground? </p>
                <p>One hot August day, when not a breath came into the room, and the dust and noise
                    and evil smells were almost unendurable, poor Lizzie lay on her bed singing
                    feebly to herself about "the beautiful blue sea." She was trying to get to sleep
                    that she might dream of a cool place, and her voice was growing fainter and
                    fainter, when suddenly it seemed as if the dream had come, for a sweet odor was
                    near, something damp and fresh touched her feverish cheek, and a kind voice said
                    in her ear: </p>
                <p>"Here is the little bird I've been following. Will you have some flowers, dear?" </p>
                <p>"Is it Heaven? Where's Billy?" murmured Lizzie, groping about her, half awake. </p>
                <p>"Not yet. I'm not Billy, but a friend who carries flowers to little children who
                    can not go and get them. Don't be afraid, but let me sit and tell you about it,"
                    answered the voice, as a gentle hand took hers. </p>
                <p>"I thought, may be, I'd died, and I was glad, for I do want to see Billy so much.
                    He's baby, you know." And the clinging hands held the kind one fast till it
                    filled them with a great bunch of roses that seemed to bring all summer into the
                    close, hot room with their sweetness. </p>
                <p>"Oh, how nice! how nice! I never had such a lot. They're bigger 'n' better 'n
                    dandelions, aren't they? What a good lady you must be to go 'round giving folks
                    posies like these!" cried Lizzie, trying to realize the astonishing fact. </p>
                <p>Then, while the new friend fanned her, she lay luxuriating in her roses, and
                    listening to the sweet story of the Flower Mission which, like many other
                    pleasant things, she knew nothing of in her prison. Presently she told her own
                    little tale, never guessing <pb entity="DSSR_000002630_0003" n="14"/> how pathetic it was, till, lifting her
                    hand to touch the new face, she found it wet with tears. </p>
                <p>"Are you sorry for me?" she asked. "Folks are very kind, but I'm a burden, you
                    know, and I'd better die and go to Billy; I was some use to him, but I never can
                    be to any one else. I heard 'em say so, and poor [illustration omitted] Mother
                    would do better if I wasn't here." </p>
                <p>"My child, I know a little blind girl who is no burden but a great help to her
                    mother, and a happy, useful creature, as you might be if you were taught and
                    helped as she was," went on the voice, sounding more than ever like a good
                    fairy's as it told fresh wonders till Lizzie was sure it <hi rend="italic"
                    >must</hi> be all a dream. </p>
                <p>"Who taught her? Could I do it? Where's the place?" she asked, sitting erect in
                    her eagerness, like a bird that hears a hand at the door of its cage. </p>
                <p>Then, with the comfortable arm around her, the roses stirring with the flutter of
                    her heart, and the sightless eyes looking up as if they could see the face of
                    the deliverer, Lizzie heard the wonderful story of the House Beautiful standing
                    white and spacious on the hill, with the blue sea before it, the fresh wind
                    always blowing, the green gardens and parks all about, and, inside, music, happy
                    voices, shining faces, busy hands, and year after year the patient teaching by
                    those who dedicate themselves to this noble and tender task. </p>
                <p>"It must be better 'n Heaven!" cried Lizzie, as she heard of work and play,
                    health and happiness, love and companionship,usefulness and independence,
                    &mdash; all the dear rights and simple joys young creatures hunger for, and
                    perish, soul and body, without. </p>
                <p>It was too much for her little mind to grasp at once, and she lay as if in a
                    blissful dream long after the kind visitor had gone, promising to come again and
                    to find some way for Lizzie to enter into that lovely place where darkness is
                    changed to light. </p>
                <p>That visit was like magic medicine, and the child grew better at once, for hope was born in her heart. The heavy
                    gloom seemed to lift, discomforts were easier to bear, and solitude was peopled
                    now with troops of happy children living in that wonderful place where blindness
                    was not a burden. She told it all to her mother, and the poor woman tried to
                    believe it, but said, sadly: <pb entity="DSSR_000002630_0004" n="15"/>
                </p>
                <p>"Don't set your heart on it, child. It's easy to promise and to forget. Rich
                    folks don't trouble themselves about poor folks if they can help it." </p>
                <p>But Lizzie's faith never wavered, though the roses faded as day after day went by
                    and no one came. The mere thought that it was possible to teach blind people to
                    work and study and play seemed to give her strength and courage. She got up and
                    sat at the window again, singing to herself as she watched and waited, with the
                    dead flowers carefully arranged in Billy's mug, and a hopeful smile on the
                    little white face behind the bars. </p>
                <p>Every one was glad she was better, and nodded to one another as they heard the
                    soft crooning, like a dove's coo, in the pauses of the harsher noises that
                    filled the street. The workmen tossed her sweeties and whistled their gayest
                    airs, the children brought their dilapidated toys to amuse her, and one woman
                    came every day to put her baby in Lizzie's lap, it was such a pleasure to her to
                    feel the soft little body in the loving arms that longed for Billy. </p>
                <p>Poor Mother went to her work in better spirits, and the long, hot days were less
                    oppressive as she thought, while she scrubbed, of Lizzie up again; for she loved
                    her helpless burden, heavy though she found it. </p>
                <p>When Saturday came around, it rained hard, and no one expected "the flower lady."
                    Even Lizzie said, with a patient sigh and a hopeful smile: </p>
                <p>"I don't believe she'll come; but, may be, it will clear up, and then I guess she
                    will." </p>
                <p>It did not clear up, but the flower lady came, and as the child sat listening to
                    the welcome sound of her steps, her quick ear caught the tread of two pairs of
                    feet, the whisper of two voices, and presently two persons came in to fill her
                    hands with midsummer flowers. </p>
                <p>"This is Minna, the little girl I told you of. She wanted to see you very much,
                    so we paddled away like a pair of ducks, and here we are," said Miss Grace
                    gayly; and as she spoke Lizzie felt soft fingers glide over her face, and a pair
                    of childish lips find and kiss her own. The groping touch, the hearty kiss, made
                    the blind children friends at once, and, dropping her flowers, Lizzie hugged the
                    new-comer, trembling with excitement and delight. Then they talked, and how the
                    tongues went as one asked questions and the other answered them, while Miss
                    Grace sat by enjoying the happiness of those who do <hi rend="italic">not</hi>
                    forget the poor, but seek them out to save and bless. </p>
                <p>Minna had been for a year a pupil in the happy school, where she was taught to
                    see with her hands, as one might say; and the tales she told of the good times
                    there made Lizzie cry eagerly: </p>
                <p>"Can I go? Oh, <hi rend="italic">can</hi> I go?" </p>
                <p>"Alas, no, not yet," answered Miss Grace sadly, "I find that children under ten
                    can not be taken, and there is no place for the little ones unless kind people
                    care for them." </p>
                <p>Lizzie gave a wail, and hid her face in the pillow, feeling as if she could not
                    bear the dreadful disappointment. </p>
                <p>Minna comforted her, and Miss Grace went on to say that generous people were
                    trying to get another school for the small children, that all the blind children
                    were working hard to help on the plan, that money was coming in, and soon they
                    hoped to have a pleasant place for every child who needed help. </p>
                <p>Lizzie's tears stopped falling as she listened, for hope was not quite gone. </p>
                <p>"I'll not be ten till next June, and I don't see how I <hi rend="italic">can</hi>
                    wait 'most a year. Will the little school be ready 'fore then?" she asked. </p>
                <p>"I fear not, dear, but I will see that the long waiting is made as easy as
                    possible, and perhaps you can help us in some way," answered Miss Grace, anxious
                    to atone for her mistake in speaking about the school before she had made sure
                    that Lizzie could go. </p>
                <p>"Oh, I'd love to help; only I can't do anything," sighed the child. </p>
                <p>"You can sing, and that is a lovely way to help. I heard of 'the blind lark,' as
                    they call you, and when I came to find her, your little voice led me straight to
                    the door of the cage. That door I mean to open and let you hop out into the
                    sunshine; then, when you are well and strong, I hope you will help us get the
                    home for other little children who else must wait years before <hi rend="italic"
                        >they</hi> find the light. Will you?" </p>
                <p>As Miss Grace spoke, it was beautiful to see the clouds lift from Lizzie's
                    wondering face, till it shone with the sweetest beauty any face can wear, the
                    happiness of helping others. She forgot her own disappointment in the new hope
                    that came, and held on to the bed-post as if the splendid plan were almost too
                    much for her. </p>
                <p>"Could I help that way?" she cried. "Would anybody care to hear me sing? Oh, how
                    I'd love to do anything for the poor little ones who will have to wait." </p>
                <p>"You shall. I'm sure the hardest heart would be touched by your singing, if you
                    look as you do now. We need something new for our fair and concert, and by that
                    time you will be ready," said Miss Grace, almost afraid she had said too much;
                    for the child looked so frail, it seemed as if even joy would hurt her. </p>
                <p>Fortunately her mother came in just then, and, while the lady talked to her,
                    Minna's childish <pb entity="DSSR_000002630_0005" n="16"/> chatter soothed Lizzie so well that when they left
                    she stood at the window smiling down at them and singing like the happiest
                    bobolink that ever tilted on a willow branch in spring-time. </p>
                <p>All the promises were kept, and soon a new life began for Lizzie. A better room
                    and well-paid work were found for Mrs. Davis. Minna came as often as she could
                    to cheer up her little friend, and, best of all, Miss Grace taught her to sing,
                    that by and by the little voice might plead with its pathetic music for others
                    less blest than she. So the winter months went by, and Lizzie grew like
                    mayflowers underneath the snow, getting ready to look up, sweet and rosy, when
                    spring set her free and called her to be glad. She counted the months and weeks,
                    and when the time dwindled to days, she could hardly sleep or eat for thinking
                    of the happy hour when she could go to be a pupil in the school where miracles
                    were worked. </p>
                <p>Her birthday was in June, and, thanks to Miss Grace, her coming was celebrated by
                    one of the pretty festivals of the school, called Daisy Day. Lizzie knew nothing
                    of this surprise, and when her friends led her up the long flight of steps she
                    looked like a happy little soul climbing to the gates of Heaven. </p>
                <p>Mr. Constantine, the ruler of this small kingdom, was a man whose fatherly heart
                    had room for every suffering child in the world, and it rejoiced over every one
                    who came, though the great house was overflowing and many waited as Lizzie had
                    done. </p>
                <p>He welcomed her so kindly that the strange place seemed like home at once, and
                    Minna led her away to the little mates who proudly showed her their small
                    possessions and filled her hands with the treasures children love, while pouring
                    into her ears delightful tales of the study, work, and play that made their
                    lives so happy. </p>
                <p>Lizzie was bewildered, and held fast to Minna, whose motherly care of her was
                    sweet to see. Kind teachers explained rules and duties with the patience that
                    soothes fear and wins love, and soon Lizzie began to feel that she was a "truly
                    pupil" in this wonderful school where the blind could read, sew, study, sing,
                    run, and play. Boys raced along the galleries and up and down the stairs as
                    boldly as if all had eyes. Girls swept and dusted like tidy housewives; little
                    fellows hammered and sawed in the workshop and never hurt themselves; small
                    girls sewed on pretty work as busy as bees, and in the schoolroom lessons went
                    on as if both teachers and pupils were blessed with eyes. </p>
                <p>Lizzie could not understand it, and was content to sit and listen wherever she
                    was placed, while her little fingers fumbled at the new objects near her, and
                    her hungry mind opened like a flower to the sun. She had no tasks that day, and
                    in the afternoon was led away with a flock of children, all chattering like
                    magpies, on the grand expedition. Every year, when the fields were white with
                    daisies, these poor little souls were let loose among them to enjoy the holy day
                    of this child's flower. Ah, but wasn't it a pretty sight to see the meeting
                    between them, when the meadows were reached and the children scattered far and
                    wide with cries of joy as they ran and rolled in the white sea, or filled their
                    eager hands, or softly felt for the dear daisies and kissed them like old
                    friends! The flowers seemed to enjoy it, too, as they danced and nodded, while
                    the wind rippled the long grass like waves of a green sea, and the sun smiled as
                    if he said: </p>
                <p>"Here's the sort of thing I like to see. Why don't I find more of it?" </p>
                <p>Lizzie's face looked like a daisy, it was so full of light as she stood looking
                    up with the wide brim of her new hat like the white petals all round it. She did
                    not run nor shout, but went slowly wading through the grass, feeling the flowers
                    touch her hands, yet picking none, for it was happiness enough to know that they
                    were there. Presently she sat down and let them tap her cheeks and rustle about
                    her ears as though telling secrets that made her smile. Then, as if weary with
                    so much happiness, she lay back and let the daisies hide her with their pretty
                    coverlet. </p>
                <p>Miss Grace was watching over her, but left her alone, and by and by, like a lark
                    from its nest in the grass, the blind girl sent up her little voice, singing so
                    sweetly that the children gathered around to hear, while they made chains and
                    tied up their nosegays. </p>
                <p>This was Lizzie's first concert, and no little prima donna was ever more pelted
                    with flowers than she; for when she had sung all her songs, new and old, a daisy
                    crown was put upon her head, a tall flower for a scepter in her hand, and all
                    the boys and girls danced around her as if she had been Queen of the May. </p>
                <p>A little feast came out of the baskets, that they might be empty for the harvest
                    to be carried home, and, while they ate, stories were told and shouts of
                    laughter filled the air, for all were as merry as if there was no darkness,
                    pain, or want in the world. Then they had games, and Lizzie was taught to play,
                    for till now she never knew what a good romp meant. Her cheeks grew rosy, her
                    sad little face waked up, she ran and tumbled with the rest, and actually
                    screamed, to Minna's great delight. </p>
                <p>Two or three of the children could see a little, and these were very helpful in
                    taking care of the little ones. Miss Grace found them playing some game with
                    Lizzie, and observed that all but she <pb  entity="DSSR_000002630_0006" n="17"/> were blindfolded. When she
                    asked why, one whispered, "We thought we should play fairer if we were all
                    alike." And another added, "It seems somehow as if we were proud if we see
                    better than the rest." </p>
                <p>Lizzie was much touched by this sweet spirit, and a little later showed that she
                    had already learned one lesson in the school, when she gathered about her some who
                    had never seen, and told them what she could remember of green fields and
                    daisy-balls before the light went out forever. </p>
                <p>"Surely my little lark was worth saving, if only for this one happy day," thought
                    Miss Grace, as she watched the awakened look in the blind faces, all leaning
                    toward the speaker, whose childish story pleased them well. </p>
                <p>In all her long and useful life, Lizzie never forgot that Daisy Day, for it
                    seemed as if she were born anew, and, like a butterfly, had left the dark
                    chrysalis all behind her then. It was the first page of the beautiful book just
                    opening before the eyes of her little mind, &mdash; a lovely page,
                    illustrated with flowers, kind faces, sunshine, and happy hopes. The new life
                    was so full, so free, she soon fell into her place and enjoyed it all. People
                    worked there so heartily, so helpfully, it was no wonder things went as if by
                    magic, and the poor little creatures who came in so afflicted went out in some
                    years independent people, ready to help themselves and often to benefit others. </p>
                <p>There is no need to tell all Lizzie learned and enjoyed that summer, nor how
                    proud her mother was when she heard her read in the curious books, making eyes
                    of the little fingers that felt their way along so fast, when she saw the neat
                    stitches she set, the pretty clay things she modeled, the tidy way she washed
                    dishes, swept and dusted, and helped keep her room in order. But the poor
                    woman's heart was too full for words when she heard the child sing, &mdash;
                    not as before, in the dreary room, sad, soft lullabies to Billy, &mdash; but
                    beautiful, gay songs, with flutes and violins to lift and carry the little voice
                    along on waves of music. </p>
                <p>Lizzie really had a great gift, but she was never happier than when they all sang
                    together, or when she sat quietly listening to the band as they practiced <pb entity="DSSR_000002630_0007"
                        n="18"/> for the autumn concert. She was to have a part in it, and the
                    thought that she could help to earn money for the Kindergarten made the shy
                    child bold and glad to do her part. Many people knew her now, for she was very
                    pretty, with the healthful roses in her cheeks, curly yellow hair, and great
                    blue eyes that seemed to see. Her mates and teachers were proud of her, for,
                    though she was not as quick as some of the pupils, her sweet temper, grateful
                    heart, and friendly little ways made her very dear to all, aside from the
                    musical talent she possessed. </p>
                <p>Every one was busy over the fair and the concert; and fingers flew, tongues
                    chattered, feet trotted, and hearts beat fast with hope and fear as the time
                    drew near, for all were eager to secure a home for the poor children still
                    waiting in darkness. It was a charity which appealed to all hearts when it was
                    known; but, in this busy world of ours, people have so many cares of their own
                    that they are apt to forget the wants of others unless something brings these
                    needs very clearly before their eyes. Much money was needed, and many ways had
                    been tried to add to the growing fund, that all might be well done. </p>
                <p>"We wish to interest children in this charity for children, so that they may
                    gladly give a part of their abundance to these poor little souls who have
                    nothing. I think Lizzie will sing some of the pennies out of their pockets,
                    which would otherwise go for bonbons. Let us try; so make her neat and pretty,
                    and we'll have a special song for her." </p>
                <p>Mr. Constantine said this, and Miss Grace carried out his wish so well that, when
                    the time came, the little prima donna did her part better even than they had
                    hoped. </p>
                <p>The sun shone splendidly on the opening day of the fair, and cars and carriages
                    came rolling out from the city, full of friendly people with plump purses and
                    the sympathetic interest we all take in such things when we take time to see,
                    admire, and reproach ourselves that we do so little for them. </p>
                <p>There were many children, and when they had bought the pretty handiwork of the
                    blind needle-women, eaten cake and ices, wondered at the strange maps and books,
                    twirled the big globe in the hall, and tried to understand how so many blind
                    people could be so busy and so happy, they all were seated at last to hear the
                    music, full of expectation, for "the pretty little girl was going to sing." </p>
                <p>It was a charming concert, and every one enjoyed it, though many eyes grew dim as
                    they wandered from the tall youths blowing the horns so sweetly, to the small
                    ones chirping away like so many sparrows, for the blind faces made the sight
                    pathetic, and such music touched the hearts as no other music can. </p>
                <p>"Now she's coming!" whispered the eager children, as a little girl climbed up the
                    steps and stood before them, waiting to begin. </p>
                <p>A slender little creature, in a blue gown, with sunshine falling on her pretty
                    hair, a pleading look in the soft eyes that had no sign of blindness but their
                    steadfastness, and a smile on the lips that trembled at first, for Lizzie's
                    heart beat fast, and only the thought, "I'm helping the poor little ones," gave
                    her courage for her task. </p>
                <p>But, when the flutes and violins began to play like a whispering wind, she forgot
                    the crowd before her, and, lifting up her face, sang in clear sweet tones</p>

                <lg type="verse">
                    <head>THE BLIND LARK'S SONG.</head>


                    <l>WE are sitting in the shadow</l>
                    <l rend="indent"> Of a long and lonely night,</l>
                    <l>Waiting till some gentle angel</l>
                    <l rend="indent"> Comes to lead us to the light.</l>
                    <l>For we know there is a magic</l>
                    <l rend="indent"> That can give eyes to the blind.</l>
                    <l>Oh, well-filled hands, be generous!</l>
                    <l rend="indent"> Oh, pitying hearts, be kind!</l>
                </lg>
                <lg type="verse">
                    <l>Help stumbling feet that wander,</l>
                    <l rend="indent"> To find the upward way;</l>
                    <l>Teach hands that now lie idle</l>
                    <l rend="indent"> The joys of work and play.</l>
                    <l>Let pity, love, and patience</l>
                    <l rend="indent"> Our tender teachers be,</l>
                    <l>That, though the eyes be blinded,</l>
                    <l rend="indent"> The little souls may see.</l>
                </lg>
                <lg type="verse">
                    <l>Your world is large and beautiful,</l>
                    <l rend="indent"> Our prison dim and small;</l>
                    <l>We stand and wait, imploring &mdash;</l>
                    <l rend="indent"> "Is there not room for all?</l>
                    <l>Give us our children's garden,</l>
                    <l rend="indent"> Where we may safely bloom,</l>
                    <l>Forgetting in God's sunshine</l>
                    <l rend="indent"> Our lot of grief and gloom."</l>
                </lg>
                <lg type="verse">
                    <l>A little voice comes singing,</l>
                    <l rend="indent"> Oh, listen to its song!</l>
                    <l>A little child is pleading</l>
                    <l rend="indent"> For those who suffer wrong.</l>
                    <l>Grant them the patient magic</l>
                    <l rend="indent"> That gives eyes to the blind!</l>
                    <l>Oh, well-filled hands, be generous!</l>
                    <l rend="indent"> Oh, pitying hearts, be kind!</l>
                </lg>


                <p>It was a very simple little song, but it proved wonderfully effective, for Lizzie
                    was so carried away by her own feeling that as she sang the last lines she
                    stretched out her hands imploringly, and two great tears rolled down her cheeks.
                    For a minute many hands were too busy fumbling for handkerchiefs to clap, but
                    the children were quick to answer that gesture and those tears, and one
                    impetuous little lad tossed a small purse containing his last ten cents at
                    Lizzie's feet, the first contribution won by her innocent appeal. Then there was
                    great applause, <pb entity="DSSR_000002630_0008" n="19"/> and many of the flowers just bought were thrown to
                    the little Lark, who was obliged to come back and sing again and again, smiling
                    brightly as she dropped pretty curtsies, and sang song after song with all the
                    added sweetness of a grateful heart. </p>
                <p>Hidden behind the organ, Miss Grace and Mr. Constantine shook hands joyfully, for
                    this was the sort of interest they wanted, and they knew that while the children
                    clapped and threw flowers, the wet-eyed mothers were thinking,
                    self-reproachfully, "I must help this lovely charity," and the stout old
                    gentlemen who pounded with their canes were resolving to go home and write some
                    generous checks, which would be money invested in God's savings-bank. </p>
                <p>It was a very happy time for all, and made strangers friends in the sweet way
                    which teaches heart to speak to heart. When the concert was over, Lizzie felt
                    many hands press hers and leave something there, many childish lips kiss her
                    own, with promises to "help about the Kindergarten," and her ears were full of
                    kind voices thanking and praising her for doing her part so well. Still later,
                    when all were gone, she proudly put the rolls of bills into Mr. Constantine's
                    hand, and, throwing her arms about Miss Grace's neck, said, trembling with
                    earnestness, "I'm not a burden any more, and I can truly help! How can I ever
                    thank you both for making me so happy?" </p>
                <p>One can fancy what their answer was and how Lizzie helped; for, long after the
                    Kindergarten was filled with pale little flowers blooming slowly as she had
                    done, the Blind Lark went on singing pennies out of pockets, and sweetly
                    reminding people not to forget this noble charity.</p>


            </div1>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI.2>
