<?xml version="1.0"?>

<?dlps id="AnoLoui"?>
<?dlps page-images="color" figure-images="no"?>
<?dlps transcription="other"?>

<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/tei-p4/tei2.dtd" [
<!ENTITY % POSTKB "INCLUDE">
<!ENTITY % TEI.extensions.ent SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.ent">
<!ENTITY % TEI.extensions.dtd SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.dtd">
<!ENTITY % ISOnum SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/charent/iso-num.ent"> %ISOnum;
<!ENTITY % ISOpub SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/charent/iso-pub.ent"> %ISOpub;
<!ENTITY DSSR_000002631_0001 SYSTEM "000002631_0001" NDATA uvaHighRes>
<!ENTITY DSSR_000002631_0002 SYSTEM "000002631_0002" NDATA uvaHighRes>
]>

<TEI.2 id="AnoLoui">
    <teiHeader type="migrated" creator="Etext">
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title type="main">The Louisiana Amendment the Same as Ours!</title>
                <title type="sort">louisiana amendment the same as ours</title>
                <author>Anonymous</author>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Creation of machine-readable version:</resp>
                    <name>Irene Tichenor</name>
                    <resp>Creation of digital images:</resp>
                    <name>University of Virginia Special Collections</name>
                    <resp>Conversion to TEI.2-conformant markup:</resp>
                    <name>Irene Tichenor</name>
                </respStmt>
            </titleStmt>
            <extent>ca. <num type="kilobytes">21</num> kilobytes</extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>University of Virginia Library</publisher>
                <pubPlace>Charlottesville, Virginia</pubPlace>
                <idno type="ETC">AnoLoui</idno>
                <date value="1996">1996</date>
                <availability status="public">
                    <p n="copyright">Copyright &#xa9; 1996 by the Rector and Visitors of the
                        University of Virginia</p>
                    <p n="access">Publicly accessible</p>
                </availability>
                <idno type="uva-pid">uva-lib:476654</idno>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title>University of Virginia Library, Text collection</title>
                <idno type="uva-set">UVA-LIB-Text</idno>
            </seriesStmt>
            <notesStmt>
                <note>
                    <p>Images of the broadside have been included.</p>
                </note>
            </notesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull>
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title type="main">The Louisiana Amendment the Same as Ours!</title>
                        <title type="sort">louisiana amendment the same as ours</title>
                        <author>Anonymous</author>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <extent>2 pages</extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <date value="1900">1900</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <seriesStmt>
                        <p>19th-Century American History: Manuscripts and Typescripts. Broadside
                            1900 .L68. Clifton Waller Barrett Library, University of Virginia
                            Special Collections</p>
                    </seriesStmt>
                </biblFull>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>Prepared for the University of Virginia Library Electronic Text Center.</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <p>The images exist as archived TIFF images, one or more JPEG versions for general
                    use, and thumbnail GIFs.</p>
                <p>Keywords in the header are a local Electronic Text Center scheme to aid in
                    establishing analytical groupings.</p>
            </editorialDecl>
            <refsDecl>
                <p>ID elements are given for each page element and are composed ofthe text's unique
                    cryptogram and the given page number, as in AusEmma1 for pageone of Jane
                    Austen's Emma.</p>
            </refsDecl>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <creation>
                <date value="1900">1900</date>
            </creation>
            <langUsage>
                <language id="eng" usage="main">English</language>
            </langUsage>
            <textClass>
                <keywords>
                    <term>non-fiction; prose</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords>
                    <term>24-bit color; 400 dpi</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change>
                <date value="1996-07">July 1996</date>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>corrector</resp>
                    <name>Catherine Tousignant</name>
                </respStmt>
                <item>Added information to header and figure descriptions about print source;
                    adjusted minor tagging errors; corrected minor typing errors</item>
            </change>
            <change>
                <date value="2005-06">June 2005</date>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>corrector</resp>
                    <name>John Ivor Carlson</name>
                </respStmt>
                <item>Converted sgml to xml.</item>
            </change>
            <change>
                <date value="2007-09">September 2007</date>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Migration</resp>
                    <name>Ethan Gruber, University of Virginia Library</name>
                </respStmt>
                <item>Converted XML markup from TEI Lite to uva-dl-tei (TEI P4 with local
                    customizations).</item>
            </change>
            <change>
                <date value="2008-01">January 2008</date>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Migration</resp>
                    <name>Greg Murray, University of Virginia Library</name>
                </respStmt>
                <item>Programmatically updated TEI header markup (but not header content) for
                    minimal compliance with current QA requirements.</item>
            </change>
<change>
<date value="2009-03">March 2009</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>Migration</resp>
<name>Scholarly Resources, University of Virginia Library</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Added and/or replaced the digital images accompanying the electronic text. Scanning of exterior and interior (ie. pages) of item was done only for items found in the University of Virginia Special Collections Library.</item>
</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>

    <text id="d1">
        <body id="d2">


            <div1 type="statement" n="1900" id="d3">
                <pb entity="DSSR_000002631_0001" n="1"/>
                <milestone unit="column" n="1"/>
                <head>THE LOUISIANA AMENDMENT THE SAME AS OURS!<lb/> IT IS CONSTITUTIONAL AND WORKS
                    WELL&mdash;ITS OPERATION ENTIRELY SATISFACTORY TO ALL CLASSES OF WHITE
                    PEOPLE.</head>

                <p>The pending amendment in this State is a copy of the Suffrage Amendment in
                    Louisiana except the property clause. The Constitutional Convention of Louisiana
                    adopted the amendment in 1898. It went into effect soon after. There has been
                    the fullest possible opportunity to study the question in all its detail. The
                    city elections last year were held under the provisions of the new constitution.
                    This year the State election was held under it. No word of complaint has been
                    heard. No white man has stated that his right to vote was denied. No test has
                    been made of the question in the courts. So we take it that the working of the
                    amendment in Louisiana will be its working in this State. It has stood a
                    practical test there. In order that the people of the State might have the
                    fullest information on this subject, Hon. Josephus Daniels, editor of the <hi
                        rend="italic">News and Observer,</hi> has been to the State of Louisiana and
                    made a study of the question in all its bearings. He was specially active in
                    seeking information as to whether white people are disfranchised. His letters
                    from the South are interesting reading. He interviewed men of every shade of
                    political opinion. He did not confine his investigation to the towns. The County
                    Parishes&mdash;our townships-were visited and people themselves sounded on
                    the subject. Attention is invited to some of the leading points taken from his
                    articles. In the light of experience the people of Louisiana declare unanimously
                    that their amendment was the only possible solution of the suffrage question,
                    and the amendment is regarded as an entirely satisfactory solution of it.</p>

                <p>The interviews had by him with well posted citizens of Louisiana, bear on the
                    following phases of this question:</p>

                <list>

                    <item>
                        <hi rend="bold">1. Eliminating the Negro.</hi>
                    </item>

                    <item>
                        <hi rend="bold">2. Guaranteeing the right to vote to every native white man,
                            whether educated or not.</hi>
                    </item>

                    <item>
                        <hi rend="bold">3. Eliminating reprehensible features from politics, and
                            elevating politics and political action.</hi>
                    </item>
                </list>

                <p>
                    <hi rend="bold">1. Eliminating the Negro.</hi>
                </p>

                <p>Among others in New Orleans I had a talk with Hon. John Fitzpatrick, who is a
                    wealthy citizen and was a member of the convention that framed the
                    Constitutional Amendment. He knows the a b c's of city politics. He said:
                    &ldquo;The amendment works very well. It takes in every white man, educated
                    or not, who registered under the grandfather clause. The practical effect in
                        <milestone unit="column" n="2"/> my ward was to reduce a negro registration
                    of about 2,000 to 112. In St. Mary's Parish, with a population of about 17,000
                    negroes and about 4,000 whites, only about one dozen negroes
                    registered.&rdquo;</p>

                <p>&ldquo;There were only 5,300 negroes registered in the State at the recent
                    election. The paucity of the negro vote took away entirely their importance as
                    voters. They were not counted or sought after. As a natural result those who did
                    register will have no incentive to do it again, and at the new registration
                    after the present registration expires, which will be December 31st, 1900, there
                    will be fewer negro voters who desire to register.&rdquo;&mdash;<hi
                        rend="italic">
                        <name>Hon. H. C. Cage, of New Orleans.</name>
                    </hi></p>

                <p>&ldquo;In this city the adoption of the Constitutional Amendment, similar to
                    the one pending in North Carolina, resulted in reducing the negro vote from
                    14,177 to 1,493. These are official figures, taken this morning from the books
                    in the office of <name>Mr. Jere M. Gleason</name>, State Registrar of voters for
                    the parish of Orleans.</p>

                <p>&ldquo;In November, 1899, the first election was held under the new
                    Constitutional Amendment. The total registration was 38,964, of which number
                    1,368 were negroes, a reduction of the negro vote from the 1896 registration,
                    which was the fullest known, of 12,709. This city election showed to the whole
                    State the value of the amendment, and opened the way for the result seen in the
                    State election held last month. The State election was held on the 17th of
                    April. Registration closed on the 17th of March, as the law requires it to close
                    thirty days before the election. The registration in the parish (it embraces
                    only the 17 wards in New Orleans) for the State election was 38,894, of which
                    number 1,493 were negroes.&rdquo;&mdash;<hi rend="italic">
                        <name>Hon. Jere M. Gleason, State Registrar of Voters for Orleans.</name>
                    </hi></p>

                <p>
                    <hi rend="bold">2. Guaranteeing the right to vote to every white man, whether
                        educated or not.</hi>
                </p>

                <p>&ldquo;Under the Constitutional Amendment, by reason of section five, every
                    uneducated man, who could vote in 1867, or who is a son or grandson of such
                    voter, could register on a permanent roll and vote as long as he lives, provided
                    he registered on that roll by September 1, 1898. In this parish we took interest
                    to see that every illiterate white man was registered under that section. I
                    registered under it myself, and there were very few white illiterates who did
                    not avail themselves of this provision. <milestone unit="column" n="3"/> The
                    amendment works splendidly, elections are fair, the educated and uneducated
                    whites vote as heretofore, and there is better feeling in politics than for many
                        years.&rdquo;&mdash;<hi rend="italic">
                        <name>Judge L. P. Caillonett.</name>
                    </hi></p>

                <p>&ldquo;Prior to 1878, there were no public schools except mixed schools, open
                    alike to white and negro children, and as the white people would not send to
                    them, many children grew up without education. We were unwilling to disfranchise
                    these neglected men or their children, the soldiers who followed Lee, or the men
                    who helped rescue the State in 1876. That is why we put in section five. The
                    illiterate white voters are delighted with the
                        amendment.&rdquo;&mdash;<hi rend="italic">
                        <name>Hon. Thos. B. Badeaux</name>
                    </hi>.</p>

                <p>&ldquo;Nearly all the illiterate whites registered. As an example, I may
                    mention that in ward five (a country township) there are 540 voters. I know
                    every man in the ward, about one-half of whom are uneducated. All registered
                    except about twelve.&rdquo;&mdash;<hi rend="italic">
                        <name>Sheriff James Beary</name>
                    </hi>.</p>

                <p>&ldquo;The amendment has more than met public expectations. Our elections
                    under it are closely contested and perfectly fair, white illiterates registered
                    under section five and voted, few negroes vote, they are satisfied and there is
                    good feeling between the races.&rdquo;&mdash;<hi rend="italic">
                        <name>Hon. Andrew Price</name>
                    </hi>.</p>

                <p>&ldquo;In Lafayette, St. Martin's, Vermilion, the Arcadian and other parishes
                    there are many illiterates. Many of them are Creoles. There were no better
                    soldiers than the Creole regiments. They are men who, though illiterate, have
                    all the civic virtues, take a keen interest in public affairs, and stood by good
                    government all the way through. We could not disfranchise such true men and
                    brave soldiers.</p>

                <p>&ldquo;The men enrolled under section five (the grandfather clause), know
                    that behind them is the manhood of the State. It is a white man's and an
                    American roll. The late <name>Hon. Thos. J. Semmes,</name> President of the
                    American Bar Association, registered under this clause. It is a roll of honor.
                    Most of the illiterate white men in the State registered under this clause and
                    are now permanently on the registration rolls.&rdquo; &mdash;<hi
                        rend="italic"><name>Hon. H. C. Cage</name>, of New Orleans</hi>.</p>

                <p>I next asked Mr. Gleason this question: &ldquo;Have any illiterate white men
                    in New Orleans been denied the privilege of voting <pb entity="DSSR_000002631_0002" n="2"/>
                    <milestone unit="column" n="4"/>
                    because they could not read and write?&rdquo; He understood the
                    question, and made this answer:</p>

                <p>&ldquo;None whatever. Every white man who wants to vote is permitted to vote.
                    Public sentiment is such that no man in politics would attempt to throw
                    obstacles in the way of an illiterate white man's voting. Practically all who
                    couldn't read and write registered under the grandfather clause in the time
                    prescribed by law and are on a permanent roll of qualified voters, and are
                    guaranteed the right to vote all their lives.</p>

                <p>&ldquo;No white men&mdash;none whatever&mdash;have been
                    disfranchised.&rdquo;</p>

                <p>Mr. Gleason said: &ldquo;It took two years to educate the people of Louisiana
                    up to the point that it would not result in the disfranchisement of any white
                    people. Now they all see it and like it and wouldn't go back to old conditions
                    under any circumstances. This is as true of the uneducated portion as of the
                    educated portion of our population.</p>

                <p>
                    <hi rend="bold">3. Eliminating reprehensible features from politics and
                        elevating politics and political action.</hi>
                </p>

                <p><name>Hon. Samuel L. Gilmore</name>, City Attorney, and one of the leading men in
                    New Orleans, speaking of what had followed the practical workings of the
                    amendment, said: &ldquo;It has rendered our elections free from any just
                    taint of fraud. It has worked well in every way, particularly is its beneficial
                    effect felt in giving a higher tone to our politics. There has been no suspicion
                    of irregularity in the two elections held under it. It has not only eliminated
                    the negro vote, thus removing corruption and many evils, but has resulted in
                    guaranteeing fair white primaries. The negro question has been eliminated. No
                    one now thinks about the negro vote, and in fact very few of them care to
                    vote.&rdquo;</p>

                <p><name>Mr. Peter F. Pescud</name>, a native of Raleigh, who is now one of the
                    leading and influential citizens of New Orleans, told me that the amendment had
                    worked well in every respect, and secured peaceful and fair elections,
                    eliminated the negro from politics, and had not disfranchised any white man
                    because of his lack of education and property. Mr. Pescud has been living here
                    for seventeen years, and has made himself universally respected and popular, and
                    is a business man of large interests and wide acquaintance. He says that he is
                    in no sense a politician, taking only that part in politics that a good citizen
                    is called upon to take. His observations are of great value and weight,
                    particularly to North Carolinians who know him as a careful, intelligent and
                    wise business man. Though a leader in New Orleans financial circles, Mr. Pescut
                    is proud that the tar still sticks to his heels, and he rejoices in whatever
                    helps esses North Carolina. &ldquo;The passage of mendment,&rdquo; he
                    said, &ldquo;will eliminate the negro question and give the people freedom
                    to think about the industrial expansion which promises so much for North
                    Carolina.&rdquo;</p>

                <milestone unit="column" n="5"/>

                <p>One of the foremost editors in the South is <name>Major H. J. Hensay</name>,
                    editor of the <hi rend="italic">New Orleans State,</hi> the most ardent and
                    vigorous advocate of White Supremacy in this city of believers in the white
                    man's party. I asked him how the amendment had operated and whether it had
                    justified the expectations of its supporters. He said:</p>

                <p>&ldquo;It has worked admirably in the last two elections. There hasn't been a
                    kick against it. No specification has been made of any fraud or wrong. It has
                    put Louisiana on the old system of a white basis, brought it back to the era
                    when it was noted far and near for the chivalry of its people and the bravery of
                    its sons. Its adoption was a grand and magnificent revolution. It has put the
                    State on the high road to prosperity, and I believe that there is a higher tone
                    in public life than in twenty years. There is a feeling of relief that the negro
                    question has been eliminated and that we have returned to the old time
                    honor.&rdquo;</p>

                <p>&ldquo;What has been the result of the adoption of your new constitution on
                    the elections,&rdquo; I asked Mr. Gleason. Here is his answer:</p>

                <p>&ldquo;Elections are now absolutely fair. The most bitter enemy has been
                    unable to substantiate a charge of the least unfairness. The opposition, after
                    election, were forced to say, &rdquo;We haven't a word to say.&ldquo;
                    There is not a suspicion of unfairness about our elections. I believe that the
                    registration in this city is the cleanest of any city on the
                    continent.&rdquo;</p>

                <p>
                    <hi rend="bold">All trouble on farms or plantations has vanished.</hi>
                </p>

                <p>&ldquo;The Constitutional Amendment has brought about a better feeling in the
                    State. In absolute and unquestioned control, the white men feel the
                    responsibility of protecting the negro in all his rights. The white people of
                    North Carolina, regardless of party, will miss an opportunity to put their
                    politics on a higher plane if they do not adopt the amendment. They owe it to
                    themselves and their children to do what we have done. Here the negro is
                    eliminated as an important political factor, fair elections leave no excuse for
                    complaints, the white man and negro are on friendly terms, no native-born
                    illiterate white man loses his vote&mdash;and all these blessings have been
                    brought about by the amendment.&rdquo;&mdash;<hi rend="italic">
                        <name>Governor Foster</name>
                    </hi>.</p>

                <p>&ldquo;The elimination of the illiterate black vote in Louisiana has placed
                    our politics upon a higher plane and ushered in a new era in our civic
                        life.&rdquo;&mdash;<hi rend="italic">
                        <name>Dr. C. Alphonso Smith, Professor of English in the University of
                            Louisiana</name>
                    </hi>.</p>

                <p>&ldquo;The amendment has brought about a condition as if in 1866 the white
                    electorate then existing had been maintained and the door opened to negro voters
                    who possessed $300 worth of property or had reasonably good educational
                    qualifications to become voters.&rdquo;&mdash;<hi rend="italic">
                        <name>Hon. Leon Jastremski, Commissioner of Agriculture</name>
                    </hi>.</p>

                <p>Senator Pritchard undertakes to say that the amendment in Louisiana has
                    disfranchised <milestone unit="column" n="6"/> the illiterate white vote, and to
                    prove that he gives the white vote registered in 1896, and then shows the number
                    of votes cast in the recent State election, and argues from this that the
                    balance are disfranchised.</p>

                <p>The books in the office of the Secretary of State in Baton Rouge show that in
                    1896 28,371 illiterate white men registered and made their mark to the
                    application which the law of the State then required. In the April election of
                    1900 the same books show that 31,079 registered under the grandfather clause.
                    This shows that the illiterate white men were practically all registered, and
                    any shortage in the registration was on the part of those who could read and
                    write, and who were of course not disfranchised. They simply exercised their
                    choice not to register and vote in 1900 because they felt that there was no
                    contest that called for it. The fact is that the vote in no State is ever up to
                    the registration. It falls as far short in Massachusetts as in Louisiana. In our
                    own State the actual vote generally falls short of the registered vote 50,000 to
                    75,000, and our registered vote is from 50,000 to 60,000 less than the number of
                    men entitled to vote. This is so in nearly all the States in the Union. To
                    illustrate, in Massachusetts in 1890 the registered vote was 665,000, and the
                    actual vote cast that year was 285,000. In Connecticut in 1890 the registered
                    vote was 224,000, and the vote cast was 125,000. Does any one contend that those
                    persons who were registered in these two States and did not vote that year were
                    disfranchised?</p>

                <p>But <name>Hon. H. C. Cage</name>, President of the Louisiana Senate, answers this
                    charge of <name>Senator Pritchard</name> as follows:</p>

                <p>&ldquo;The only white illiterates disfranchised in Louisiana are those
                    foreigners who were permitted under the Constitution of 1879 to vote under a
                    mere declaration of intention to become citizens. Of this number those who took
                    out naturalization papers were very few, but thousands continued to vote from
                    1879 to 1898 under their declaration of intention. This illiterate foreign-born
                    vote, especially that portion which was Italian, had gotten under the control of
                    so-called political bosses, and a prejudice against it had arisen in the better
                    element of the people, second only in intensity to that against the negro vote,
                    and when the Constitutional Convention of 1898 undertook to eliminate the negro
                    vote, there was, especially in the city of New Orleans, a determined demand that
                    this illiterate boss-controlled foreign vote should also be eliminated, and the
                    effect of the suffrage provision adopted was to eliminate every illiterate
                    foreigner who had not been naturalized previous to January 1st, 1898.</p>

                <p>&ldquo;The elimination of these thousands of illiterate foreigners, voting
                    upon declaration of intention only, accounts for the falling off of the white
                    registration in Louisiana.</p>

                <p>&ldquo;Every native-born white man in Louisiana, whether educated or
                    uneducated, votes and is protected in his vote.&rdquo;</p>

                <p>This statement fully accounts for the falling off of the registration there in
                    1900. </p>
            </div1>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI.2>
