<?xml version="1.0"?>

<?dlps id="AusBitt"?>
<?dlps page-images="color" figure-images="no"?>
<?dlps transcription="other"?>

<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/tei-p4/tei2.dtd" [
<!ENTITY % POSTKB "INCLUDE">
<!ENTITY % TEI.extensions.ent SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.ent">
<!ENTITY % TEI.extensions.dtd SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.dtd">
<!ENTITY % ISOlat1 SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/charent/iso-lat1.ent"> %ISOlat1;
<!ENTITY % ISOpub SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/charent/iso-pub.ent"> %ISOpub;





<!ENTITY DSSR_000002656_0001 SYSTEM "000002656_0001" NDATA uvaHighRes>
<!ENTITY DSSR_000002656_0002 SYSTEM "000002656_0002" NDATA uvaHighRes>
]>

<TEI.2 id="AusBitt">
    <teiHeader type="migrated" creator="Etext">
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title type="main">Bitterness of Women</title>
                <title type="sort">bitterness of women</title>
                <author>Austin, Mary</author>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Creation of machine-readable version:</resp>
                    <name>Judy Boss</name>
                    <resp>Creation of digital images:</resp>
                    <name>Catherine Tousignant</name>
                    <resp>Conversion to TEI.2-conformant markup:</resp>
                    <name>University of Virginia Library Electronic Text Center.</name>
                </respStmt>
            </titleStmt>
            <extent>ca. <num type="kilobytes">19</num> kilobytes</extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>University of Virginia Library</publisher>
                <pubPlace>Charlottesville, Virginia</pubPlace>
                <idno type="ETC">AusBitt</idno>
                <date value="1996">1996</date>
                <availability status="public">
                    <p n="copyright">Copyright &#xa9; 1996 by the Rector and Visitors of the
                        University of Virginia</p>
                    <p n="access">Publicly accessible</p>
                </availability>
                <idno type="uva-pid">uva-lib:476670</idno>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title>University of Virginia Library, Text collection</title>
                <idno type="uva-set">UVA-LIB-Text</idno>
            </seriesStmt>
            <notesStmt>
                <note>
                    <p>Illustrations have been included from the print version.</p>
                </note>
                <note>
                    <p>Page 23, last line: wonder of world] wonder of the world (Judy Boss)</p>
                </note>
            </notesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull>
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title type="main">Bitterness of Women</title>
                        <title level="j">
                            <hi rend="italic">Harper's Weekly</hi>
                        </title>
                        <title type="sort">bitterness of women</title>
                        <author>Mary Austin</author>
                        <respStmt>
                            <resp>Editor</resp>
                            <name>George Harvey</name>
                        </respStmt>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <p>53</p>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent>22-23.</extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Harper &amp; Brothers</publisher>
                        <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                        <date value="1909-10-09">9 October, 1909</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                </biblFull>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>Prepared for the University of Virginia Library Electronic Text Center.</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <p>All quotation marks retained as data.</p>
                <p>Spell-check and verification made against printed text using WordPerfect spell
                    checker.</p>
                <p>All unambiguous end-of-line hyphens have been removed, and the trailing part of a
                    word has been joined to the preceding line.</p>
                <p>The images exist as archived TIFF images, one or more JPEG versions for general
                    use, and thumbnail GIFs.</p>
                <p id="ETC">Keywords in the header are a local Electronic Text Center scheme to aid
                    in establishing analytical groupings.</p>
            </editorialDecl>
            <refsDecl>
                <p>ID elements are given for each page element and are composed of the text's unique
                    cryptogram and the given page number, as in AusEmma1 for page one of Jane
                    Austen's Emma.</p>
            </refsDecl>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <creation>
                <date value="1996">1996</date>
            </creation>
            <langUsage>
                <language id="eng" usage="main">English</language>
                <language id="fre">French</language>
            </langUsage>
            <textClass>
                <keywords>
                    <term>fiction; prose</term>
                    <term>Women Writers</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords>
                    <term type="artist">Denman Fink</term>
                    <term type="visual work">Illustrations</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords>
                    <term>24-bit color; 300 dpi</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change>
                <date value="1996-05">May 1996</date>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>corrector</resp>
                    <name>Catherine Tousignant</name>
                </respStmt>
                <item>Added TEI header and tags</item>
            </change>
            <change>
                <date value="2005-06">June 2005</date>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>corrector</resp>
                    <name>John Ivor Carlson</name>
                </respStmt>
                <item>Converted sgml to xml.</item>
            </change>
            <change>
                <date value="2007-09">September 2007</date>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Migration</resp>
                    <name>Ethan Gruber, University of Virginia Library</name>
                </respStmt>
                <item>Converted XML markup from TEI Lite to uva-dl-tei (TEI P4 with local
                    customizations).</item>
            </change>
            <change>
                <date value="2008-01">January 2008</date>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Migration</resp>
                    <name>Greg Murray, University of Virginia Library</name>
                </respStmt>
                <item>Programmatically updated TEI header markup (but not header content) for
                    minimal compliance with current QA requirements.</item>
            </change>
<change>
<date value="2009-03">March 2009</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>Migration</resp>
<name>Scholarly Resources, University of Virginia Library</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Added and/or replaced the digital images accompanying the electronic text. Scanning of exterior and interior (ie. pages) of item was done only for items found in the University of Virginia Special Collections Library.</item>
</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>

    <text id="d1">
        <body id="d2">




            <div1 type="story" id="d3">
                <pb entity="DSSR_000002656_0001" n="22"/>
                <head>Bitterness of Women<lb/> By Mary Austin<lb/> ILLUSTRATIONS BY DENMAN FINK<lb/></head>
                <p>LOUIS CHABOT was sitting under the fig tree in her father's garden at Tres Pinos
                    when he told Marguerita Dupr&eacute; that he could not love her. This sort
                    of thing happened so often to Louis that he did it very well and rather enjoyed
                    it, for he was one of those before whom women bloomed instinctively and preened
                    themselves, and that Marguerita loved him very much was known not only to Louis,
                    but to all Tres Pinos. </p>
                <p>It was bright mid-afternoon and there was no sound in Dupr&eacute;'s garden
                    louder than the dropping of ripe figs and the drip of the hydrant under the
                    Castilian roses. A mile out of town Chabot's flock dozed on their feet with
                    their heads under one another's bellies, and his herders dozed on the ground
                    with their heads under the plaited tops of the sage. Old Dupr&eacute; sat
                    out in front of his own front yard, with a handkerchief over his face, and slept
                    very soundly. Chabot finished his claret to the last drop&mdash;it was
                    excellent claret, this of Dupr&eacute;'s&mdash;turned the tumbler upside
                    down, sat back in his chair, and explained to Marguerita point by point why he
                    did not love her. </p>
                <p>Marguerita leaned her fat arms on the table, wrapped in her blue reboza; it was
                    light blue and she was too dark for it, but it was such a pretty color; she
                    leaned forward, looking steadily and quietly at Louis, because she was afraid if
                    she so much as let her lids droop the tears would come and if she smiled her
                    lips would quiver. Marguerita felt that she had not invited this, neither had
                    she known how to avoid it. </p>
                <p>She would have given anything to have told Louis to his face that he need not
                    concern himself so much on her account, as she was not the least interested in
                    him; she had called on all her pride to that end, but nothing came. </p>
                <p>She was a good girl, Louis told her, such as, if she had pleased him, he would
                    gladly have married. She was a very good girl and she understood about sheep.
                    Tr&egrave;s bien! Old Dupr&eacute; had taught her that; but she lacked a
                    trifle&mdash;a nuance&mdash;but everything where love is concerned, <hi
                        rend="italic">l'art d'&ecirc;tre d&eacute;sir&eacute;</hi>,
                    explained the little Frenchman; for, though he was only a sheep-herder of Lost
                    Borders, if he had been a boulevardier he could not have been more of a
                    Frenchman or less of a cad. He leaned back in his chair with the air of having
                    delivered himself very well. </p>
                <p>"Salty Bill loves me," ventured Marguerita. </p>
                <p>"Eh, Bill!" Louis looked hurt; for, though he frequently disposed of his ladies
                    in this negligent fashion, he did not care to have them snapped up so quickly.
                    Marguerita felt convicted of l&egrave;se-majest&eacute; by the look and
                    hastened to reassure him that she cared nothing whatever for Salty Bill. It was
                    a false move and she knew it as soon as it was done, but she could not bear to
                    have Louis look at her like that and Marguerita had never in her life learned
                    the good of pretending. Chabot poured him another glass of claret and returned
                    to his point. </p>
                <p>There was Suzon Moynier, he explained. Such an eye as Suzon had! There was a
                    spark for you! And an ankle! More lovers than few had been won by an ankle.
                    Marguerita, under cover of the table, drew her feet together beneath her skirts.
                    Her ankles were thick and there was no disguising it. </p>
                <p>"So it is Suzon you love?" </p>
                <p>"Eh," said the herder, "that is as may be. I have loved many women." Then perhaps
                    because the particular woman did not matter so much as that there should be
                    womanhood, and perhaps because he could no more help it than she could help
                    being wondrously flooded by it, he threw her a look from the tail of his eye and
                    such a smile as drew all the blood from her heart, bent above her, brushing her
                    hair with his lips in such a lingering tenderness of farewell that, though he
                    had just told her she was not to be loved, the poor girl was not sure but he was
                    beginning to love her. Women suffered things like that from Louis Chabot, each
                    being perfectly sure she was the only one, and perhaps, like Marguerita, finding
                    it worth while to be made to suffer if it could be done so exquisitely. </p>
                <p>Marguerita was only half French herself, old Dupr&eacute; having married her
                    mother, Se&ntilde;orita Carrasco, who was only half a se&ntilde;orita,
                    since, in fact, most people in Tres Pinos were a little this or that, with no
                    chance for name calling. Dupr&eacute; had been a herder of sheep risen to an
                    owner whom the desert had bitten. The natural consequence was that when he was
                    old, instead of returning to France, he had married Marguerita's mother and
                    settled down in Tres Pinos to live on the interest of his money. 
                </p>
                <p>It was a fact that his daughter had at heart all the fire and tenderness that
                    promised in Suzon's glance; but of what use to Louis Chabot that she had a soul
                    warm and alight if no glow of it suffused her cheek and no spark of it drew him
                    in her eye? She was swarthy and heavy of face; she had no figure, which means
                    she had a great deal too much of it, and there was a light shadow like a finger
                    smudge on her upper lip. Not that the girl did not have her good points. She
                    could cook&mdash;that was the French strain in her father; she could
                    dance&mdash;that was Castilian from her mother; and such as she was Salty
                    Bill wanted her. Bill drove an eighteen-mule team for the borax works and was
                    seven times a better man than Chabot, but she would have no more of him than
                    Louis would have of her. She continued to say her prayers regularly and told Tia
                    Juna, who reproached her with losing a good marriage, that she believed yet the
                    saints would give her the desire of her heart, whereat Tia Juna pitied her. </p>
                <p>Chabot brought his sheep up from the spring shearing at Bakersfield each year and
                    made three loops about Tres Pinos, so that it brought him to the town about once
                    in three months to replenish his supplies; and the only reason there was not a
                    new object of his attentions each time was that there were not girls enough, for
                    Chabot's taste required them young, pretty, and possessed of the difficult art
                    of being desired. Therefore, he had time to keep hope alive in Marguerita with
                    the glint of his flattering eyes and the trick of his flattering lips, which was
                    such very common coin with him that he did not quite know himself how free he
                    was with it. And after old Dupr&eacute; died and his daughter inherited his
                    house and the interest on his money she was enough of a figure in Tres Pinos to
                    make a little attention worth while, even though she had a smudge of black on
                    her upper lip and no art but that of being faithful. She lived in the house
                    under the fig tree with old Tia Juna for a companion and was much respected; she
                    was said to have more clothes than anybody, though they never became her. </p>
                <p>Marguerita kept a candle burning before the saints and another in her heart for
                    the handsome little herder, who went on making love to ladies and being loved by
                    them for three years. Then the saints took a hand in his affairs, though, of
                    course, it did not look that way to Louis. </p>
                <p>He was sleeping out on Black Mountain in the spring of the year with his flock.
                    The herder whose business it was to have done that was at Tres Pinos on a two
                    days' leave, confessing himself and getting a nice, jolly little claret drunk.
                    Somewhere up in the blown lava holes of Black Mountain there was a bear with two
                    cubs, who had said to them, bear fashion: "Come down to the flock with me
                    to-night and I will show you how killing is done. There will be dogs there, and
                    men, but do not be afraid; I will see to it that they do not hurt you." </p>
                <p>Along about the time Orion's sword sloped down the west Chabot heard their
                    gruntled noises and the scurry of the flock. Chabot was not a coward, perhaps
                    because he knew that in general bears are; he got up and laid about him with his
                    staff. This he never would have done if he had known about the cubs; he trod on
                    the foot of one in the dark and the bear mother heard it. She came lumbering up
                    in the soft blackness and took Chabot in her arms. </p>
                <p>Toward four of the next afternoon the herder coming back, still very merry and
                    very comfortable in his mind, found a maimed bleeding thing by the water-hole
                    that moaned and babbled. One of its arms was gone to the elbow, its face was
                    laid open, and long red gashes lay along its sides and down one thigh. After a
                    while, when he had washed away the blood and dust, he discovered that this thing
                    was Chabot. The herder laid it as tenderly as he could on the campo burro and
                    took it to Tres Pinos. If there was any question of the propriety of the care of
                    Chabot falling to Marguerita Dupr&eacute; it counted for nothing against the
                    fact that nobody was found willing to do it in her stead, and Marguerita was
                    very discreet. Tia Juna was put in charge of the sick-room and Marguerita gave
                    her whole soul to the cooking. </p>
                <p>And if any question had arisen later, when Chabot began to hobble about with a
                    crutch under his good arm and his sleeve pinned up where the other had been, he
                    put an end to it by marrying her. He was thought to have done very well in this,
                    since he could get no more good of himself; and since Marguerita wanted him, it
                    was a handsome way of paying her, but there had something gone before that. Tia
                    Juna had been careful there should be no scrap of a mirror about when Chabot
                    began to slip his bandages, and perhaps he had not had the courage to ask for
                    it; certainly there had been no change in Marguerita's face for any change she
                    saw in him. And the day that he knew the thing he was he asked her to marry him.
                    He had slipped out into the street for the first time, wearying a little of the
                    solicitations of the two women, and come upon children playing in the open way.
                    They broke and scuttled like young quail at sight of him; and he sat down
                    suddenly, for he was not so strong as he had thought, and tried to be clear in
                    his mind what this might mean. And in a little while he was quite clear; he
                    heard the rustle and whisper behind him that advised him of shoulders hunched
                    and fingers laid on lips over irrepressible giggles of excitement and knew that
                    they dared each other to come on through the black sage and peek at a fearsome
                    thing. </p>
                <p>It was that afternoon when she came in with the soup and claret that he asked
                    Marguerita. The poor girl put down the bowl and came and knelt by him very
                    humble and gentle. </p>
                <p>"Are you quite sure, Louis?" she asked, with her cheek upon his hand. </p>
                <p>"I am sure of nothing," said he, "except that I cannot live without you." </p>
                <p>It was very curious that no sooner had he said that than he began to discover it
                    would be very hard to live with her, for to lose an ear and an eye and to have
                    one's mouth drawn twisty by a scar does not make a kiss relish better if it
                    falls not in with the natural desire. </p>
                <p>Marguerita did not grow any prettier after she was married, but showed a tendency
                    to take on fat; and she did not dress quite so well, because she could not
                    afford it; though there are times, as, for instance, when he has gone out in
                    company and seen the young married women hustled out of sight of him, that her
                    plain face looks almost good to him. Marguerita insists on their going out a
                    great deal to cock-fights and to <hi rend="italic">bailes</hi>, where he sits in
                    the corner with his good side carefully disposed toward the guests; and his wife
                    has given up dancing, though she is very fond of it, to sit beside him and keep
                    him company; <pb entity="DSSR_000002656_0002" n="23"/> though, to tell the truth, Chabot could bear very well
                    to do without that if only he could find himself surrounded by the lightness,
                    the laughter, the half-revealing draperies, the delicious disputed moves of the
                    game he loves. As he will not any more, for he knows now that such as these are
                    not given save when there is something to be got by them, and, though he is only
                    thirty-four, poor Louis is no longer possessed of <hi rend="italic">l'art
                        &ecirc;tre d&eacute;sir&eacute;</hi>. </p>
                <p>For the rest of his life he will have to make the best of knowing that his wife
                    carries his name with credit and does not cost him anything. They are not
                    without their comfortable hours. Marguerita takes excellent care of him and she
                    understands about sheep. If she sees the dust of a flock arising, can tuck up
                    her skirts and away to the edge of the town, getting back with as much news of
                    where they go, whence they came, and the conditions of the wethers as Chabot
                    could have brought himself, and not even her husband knows the extent of her
                    devices for keeping him surrounded with the sense and stir of life. For it was
                    not long after his marriage that Chabot made the discovery that all the quick
                    desire of him toward lovely women warmed in his wife's spirit toward the maimed
                    and twisted thing that he is and, thwarted of the subtle play of lip and limb
                    and eye, spends itself in offices of homely comfort. </p>
                <p>And this is the bitterness of women, that it matters not so much that they should
                    have passion as the power to provoke it, and, lacking the spark of a glance, the
                    turn of an ankle, the treasures of tenderness in them wither unfulfilled. Shut
                    behind his wife's fat commonplace exterior lies the pulse of music, the delight
                    of motion, the swimming sense, the quick white burning fenced within his scars.
                    Times like this he remembers what has passed between him and many women and
                    finds his complacency sicken and die in him. Knowing what he does of the state
                    of her heart and not being quite a cad, he does not make her an altogether bad
                    husband; and if sometimes, looking at her with abhorring eyes&mdash;the
                    shaking bosom, the arms enormous, the shade of her upper lip no longer to be
                    mistaken for a smudge&mdash;resenting her lack of power to move him, he
                    gives her a bad quarter of an hour, even though she has the best of him. For however
                    unhappy he makes her, with one kiss of his crooked mouth he can set it all right
                    again. But for Louis the lift, the exultation, the exquisite unmatched wonder of
                    the world will not happen any more; never any more.</p>

            </div1>

        </body>
    </text>
</TEI.2>
