<?xml version="1.0"?>

<?dlps id="AusWell"?>
<?dlps page-images="color" figure-images="yes"?>
<?dlps transcription="other"?>

<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/tei-p4/tei2.dtd" [
<!ENTITY % POSTKB "INCLUDE">
<!ENTITY % TEI.extensions.ent SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.ent">
<!ENTITY % TEI.extensions.dtd SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.dtd">
<!ENTITY % ISOpub SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/charent/iso-pub.ent"> %ISOpub;


<!ENTITY DSSR_000002660_0001 SYSTEM "000002660_0001" NDATA uvaHighRes>
<!ENTITY DSSR_000002660_0002 SYSTEM "000002660_0002" NDATA uvaHighRes>
<!ENTITY DSSR_000002660_0003 SYSTEM "000002660_0003" NDATA uvaHighRes>
]>
<TEI.2 id="AusWell">
   <teiHeader type="migrated" creator="Etext">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">An Appreciation of H. G. Wells, Novelist</title>
            <title type="sort">appreciation of h g wells, novelist</title>
            <author>Austin, Mary</author>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Creation of machine-readable version:</resp>
               <name>Judy Boss</name>
               <resp>Creation of digital images:</resp>
               <name>Catherine Tousignant</name>
               <resp>Conversion to TEI.2-conformant markup:</resp>
               <name>University of Virginia Library Electronic Text Center.</name>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <extent>ca. <num type="kilobytes">13</num> kilobytes</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>University of Virginia Library</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Charlottesville, Virginia</pubPlace>
            <idno type="ETC">AusWell</idno>
            <date value="1996">1996</date>
            <availability status="public">
               <p n="copyright">Copyright &#xa9; 1996 by the Rector and Visitors of the
                  University of Virginia</p>
               <p n="access">Publicly accessible</p>
            </availability>
            <idno type="uva-pid">uva-lib:476688</idno>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>University of Virginia Library, Text collection</title>
            <idno type="uva-set">UVA-LIB-Text</idno>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>
               <p>Illustrations have been included from the print version.</p>
            </note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title type="main">An Appreciation of H. G. Wells, Novelist</title>
                  <title level="j">American Magazine</title>
                  <title type="sort">appreciation of h g wells, novelist</title>
                  <author>Mary Austin</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <editionStmt>
                  <p>Volume 72</p>
               </editionStmt>
               <extent>733-735.</extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>The Crowell Publishing Company</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                  <date value="1911-10">October 1911</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>
                     <p>Copy consulted: UVA Library call number AP2 .A346</p>
                  </note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Prepared for the University of Virginia Library Electronic Text Center.</p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>All quotation marks retained as data.</p>
            <p>Spell-check and verification madeagainst printed text using WordPerfect spell
               checker.</p>
            <p>All unambiguous end-of-line hyphens have been removed, and thetrailing part of a word
               has been joined to the preceding line.</p>
            <p>The images exist as archived TIFF images, one or more JPEG versionsfor general use,
               and thumbnail GIFs.</p>
            <p>Keywords in the header are a local Electronic Text Center scheme to aid in
               establishing analytical groupings.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <refsDecl>
            <p>ID elements are given for each page element and are composed of the text'sunique
               cryptogram and the given page number, as in AusEmma1 for page one of Jane Austen's
               Emma.</p>
         </refsDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <creation>
            <date value="1911">1911</date>
         </creation>
         <langUsage>
            <language id="eng" usage="main">English</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords>
               <term>non-fiction; prose</term>
               <term>Women Writers</term>
            </keywords>
            <keywords>
               <term>Illustration</term>
            </keywords>
            <keywords>
               <term>24-bit color; 300 dpi</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date value="1996-05">May 1996</date>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>corrector</resp>
               <name>Catherine Tousignant</name>
            </respStmt>
            <item>Added TEI header and tags.</item>
         </change>
         <change>
            <date value="2005-06">June 2005</date>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>corrector</resp>
               <name>John Ivor Carlson</name>
            </respStmt>
            <item>Converted sgml to xml.</item>
         </change>
         <change>
            <date value="2007-09">September 2007</date>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Migration</resp>
               <name>Ethan Gruber, University of Virginia Library</name>
            </respStmt>
            <item>Converted XML markup from TEI Lite to uva-dl-tei (TEI P4 with local
               customizations).</item>
         </change>
         <change>
            <date value="2008-01">January 2008</date>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Migration</resp>
               <name>Greg Murray, University of Virginia Library</name>
            </respStmt>
            <item>Programmatically updated TEI header markup (but not header content) for minimal
               compliance with current QA requirements.</item>
         </change>
<change>
<date value="2009-03">March 2009</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>Migration</resp>
<name>Scholarly Resources, University of Virginia Library</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Added and/or replaced the digital images accompanying the electronic text. Scanning of exterior and interior (ie. pages) of item was done only for items found in the University of Virginia Special Collections Library.</item>
</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>

   <text id="d1">

      <body id="d2">
         <div1 type="essay" id="d3">
            <pb entity="DSSR_000002660_0001" n="733"/>
            <p>THE very ancient conception of a genius as one seized upon by the waiting Powers for
               the purpose of rendering themselves intelligible to men has its most modern exemplar
               in the person of Herbert George Wells, a maker of amazing books. It is impossible to
               call Mr. Wells a novelist, for up to this time the bulk of his work has not been
               novels; and scarcely accurate to call him a sociologist, since most of his social
               science is delivered in the form of fiction. </p>
            <p>There are people who call him a Socialist, and that, with some definition, is what
               Mr. Wells calls himself; there are others who call him a revolutionist; but, under
               whatever caption, he is distinguishedly a maker of books, informing vitalizing,
               indispensable books; and when one attempts to account for the range and variety of
               Mr. Wells' product, the first inescapable inference is that behind them is a man of
               broad and specific learning. </p>
            <p>It is not possible, by naming the schools where he has been educated, to give any
               notion to an American audience of the quality of Mr. Wells' scholarship. He is not,
               as we understand it, a University man, but so far as his learning relates him to his
               time, better educated than most University men dare profess to be&mdash;a scholar
               of human conditions. Chiefly, besides finding out how the things that are came to be,
               Mr. Wells' preparation for his work consists in living. </p>
            <p>He has lived, not episodically nor by proxy, as so many literary men tend to do, but
               consciously and actively, for forty odd years. <pb entity="DSSR_000002660_0002" n="734"/> How many American men
               one knows who let their wives and children do half their living for them! But Mr.
               Wells has done his own living, which probably accounts for his having done so much of
               his own thinking. At any rate he has never clouded his genius with the obscurations
               of an "Art Atmosphere." </p>
            <p>All the time I knew Mr. Wells in London I never persuaded him to speak but once of
               Art. </p>
            <p>"An artist," said he, "has nothing to do with success; neither must he concern
               himself whether he is read by one or one million; he must just do his work." And Mr.
               Wells has demonstrated that, if an artist does that sincerely, success will have much
               to do with him. </p>
            <p>The first book of Mr. Wells to attract attention in America, though it was not his
               first writing, was "The War of the Worlds," published in 1898, the first of a group
               of singular but irresistible romances in which Mr. Wells, by anticipating the bent of
               scientific discovery, or by deflecting it slightly from its present course, created
               an original background against which he worked out the socialistic remedy for the
               economic disorder. </p>
            <p>It was just here that the Powers seized upon Mr. Wells. The pressure of economic
               discontent in England, so much greater than the home-bred American can realize, the
               chafing of regenerative forces against the social superstitions (conservatism is the
               stately word for it, but really there is a lot of it on a par with the objection to
               sitting down with thirteen at table) produced the electrical conditions which
               demanded a man as the medium of discharge. No doubt Mr. Wells was primarily a
               novelist, but then and for a long time the social forces were too much for him. All
               through his earlier work the artist can be seen shaken in the teeth of the Social
               Consciousness. Even in his latest work, "The New Machiavelli," it runs neck and neck
               with the story until the reader is left a little in doubt which of the two had the
               better of it. But in 1900 Mr. Wells wrote "Love and Mr. Lewisham," and gave the first
               intimation of what his work might become when he had subordinated the reforming
               impulse to the simple mastery of human life. "Love and Mr. Lewisham" is the story of
               a very usual young man and the struggle of his ambitions and egoisms with the mating
               instinct. It is so satisfying as a story that it is not until a long while after
               reading it you discover that what Mr. Wells has been saying all the time is that it
               is only our disordered social system that sets the mating instinct at war with a
               man's personal development. The real trouble with Mr. Lewisham was not that he was in
               love or ambitious, but that he found it difficult to make a living. That, in one way
               or another, is the crying difficulty of Young England, and none sees more clearly
               than Mr. Wells the relation of all our so-called immoralities to the economic
               condition and the impossibilities of remedying one without correcting the other. </p>
            <p>Socialism is Mr. Wells' remedy, but it must be understood that his particular brand
               of it is not so much a system as a state of mind; a kind of awareness, a realization
               of the pain of social maladjustment in the farthest, least little toe of the social
               organization. Earlier in his career Mr. Wells was active in the society of Fabians,
               and the various tentative measures by which the growing pains of social discontent
               manifested. But of the theory of Socialism as it exists now in England he says, "It
               has gone up into the clouds and the practice of it into the drains." Those who are
               interested can find the best explication of Socialism as it appeals to Mr. Wells as a
               "plain human enterprise" in "The Misery of Boots," first published as a Fabian tract.
               It is impossible to avoid the conclusion, on reading it, that you are some kind of a
               Socialist yourself. </p>
            <p>Mr. Wells is the most contemporaneous of writers. He has more and more sensitive
               tentacles laid along the lines of growth of Modern England than any other writer, and
               they outreach the budding tendency by so much as makes his work hopeful. When Mr.
               Wells writes about a no more striking person than a draper's clerk bicycling for a
               holiday, you perceive not only how he came to be just there in the social order, but
               also how he might have been bettered in the making. In this Mr. Wells differs from
               his contemporaries, Mr. Galsworthy, who leaves the reader under the impression that
               things are so bad that something ought really to be done about it if anybody only
               knew how, and Mr. Bennett, who sets you wondering if it ever occurred to him that
               anything could be done. </p>
            <p>In nothing is this contemporaneous character of Mr. Wells' work so notable as in his
               acceptance of the machine. Gears and coherers, radioactivities and the powers are as
               much a factor of Mr. Wells' world as pounds, shillings and pence. They are part of
               the communicating medium. That is, perhaps, why he is able to make them pass current
               in his tales as no other, not excepting Mr. Kipling, has done. Mr. Kipling's feeling
               for machinery is the feeling of a poet, it comes <pb entity="DSSR_000002660_0003" n="735"/> alive for him,
               presents itself as personality; but Mr. Wells' feeling is of a man stretching himself
               and realizing to the full his extended capacities and powers. </p>
            <p>His motors and aeroplanes are the swift feet and the wings of a man, and somehow Mr.
               Wells convinces you that it is not in the least surprising for a man to be possessed
               of such conveniences, or even of others much more remarkable. </p>
            <p>The quality of Mr. Wells' work is uneven, which is perhaps natural to the earlier
               stages of an artist's development, but it is of increasing humanness. In "Tono
               Bungay," his most successful novel, the story of the rise and decline of a
               patent-medicine millionaire, it is possible to forget for whole chapters that the
               author is writing in England of Englishmen. </p>
            <p>The locale of the story is never actively a protagonist except in the presence of the
               ladies. Barring the accent and a difference in taste in neckties, it is possible to
               find most of Mr. Wells' men in Indiana, but his women are all Englishwomen. There is
               sometimes a touch of the method of Balzac in the sense Mr. Wells gives of having got
               to the bottom of his male characters; there is nothing left in the crucible. But it
               is conceivable that of his women the best of them might have known the novelist
               better than he knew them. But Mr. Wells is an avowed feminist, and has been active in
               the dramatic struggle now going on in England for the enfranchisement of women, and
               this failure of the world-touch in the delineation of femininity might very well be
               due to the fact that women themselves are not yet molded to the world type, but
               retain longer than men the stamp of their particular environment. It is the
               possibility that Mr. Wells may be able to pass even this limitation that gives the
               fillip of interest to his forthcoming novel, "Marriage," which is to begin in the
               November AMERICAN MAGAZINE. If he can lift the subject out of little London, into the
               universality achieved in "Tono Bungay," he will at the same time raise himself to a
               citizenship in the world of human understanding not attained by any Englishman since
               Mr. Dickens, and by few before him. </p>
            <p>It is because Mr. Wells exhibits possibilities of doing just this thing that he is so
               well worth watching. There is no writer to-day who gives his readers such a
               satisfying sense, by the mere delight of attending to him, of having participated in
               a social solution.</p>
         </div1>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI.2>
