<?xml version="1.0"?>

<?dlps id="branegr"?>
<?dlps page-images="color" figure-images="no"?>
<?dlps transcription="other"?>

<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/tei-p4/tei2.dtd" [
<!ENTITY % POSTKB "INCLUDE">
<!ENTITY % TEI.extensions.ent SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.ent">
<!ENTITY % TEI.extensions.dtd SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.dtd">
<!ENTITY % ISOpub SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/charent/iso-pub.ent"> %ISOpub;

<!ENTITY DSSR_000001475_0001 SYSTEM "uva-lib:510502" NDATA uvaHighRes>
<!ENTITY DSSR_000001475_0002 SYSTEM "uva-lib:510503" NDATA uvaHighRes>
<!ENTITY DSSR_000001475_0003 SYSTEM "uva-lib:510504" NDATA uvaHighRes>
<!ENTITY DSSR_000001475_0004 SYSTEM "uva-lib:510505" NDATA uvaHighRes>
]>
<TEI.2 id="branegr">
    <teiHeader creator="Etext" type="migrated">
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title type="main">The Negro Genius</title>
                <title type="sort">negro genius</title>
                <author>Brawley, Benjamin</author>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Creation of machine-readable version:</resp>
                    <name>Judy Boss</name>
                    <resp>Creation of digital images:</resp>
                    <name>Lisa Spiro, Electronic Text Center</name>
                    <resp>Conversion to TEI.2-conformant markup:</resp>
                    <name>Text prepared by the 1997-98 J. Wallace Sieg Graduate Fellow Lisa Spiro
                        for the University of Virginia Library Electronic Text Center.</name>
                </respStmt>
            </titleStmt>
            <extent>ca. <num type="kilobytes">13</num> kilobytes</extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>University of Virginia Library</publisher>
                <pubPlace>Charlottesville, Virginia</pubPlace>
                <idno type="ETC">branegr</idno>
                <date value="1997">1997</date>
                <availability status="public">
                    <p n="copyright">Copyright &#xa9; 1997 by the Rector and Visitors of the
                        University of Virginia</p>
                    <p n="access">Publicly accessible</p>
                </availability>
                <idno type="uva-pid">uva-lib:476722</idno>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title>University of Virginia Library, Text collection</title>
                <idno type="uva-set">UVA-LIB-Text</idno>
            </seriesStmt>
            <notesStmt>
                <note>
                    <p>This e-text includes an image of the cover of The Southern Workman.</p>
                </note>
            </notesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull>
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title type="main">The Negro Genius</title>
                        <title level="j">The Southern Workman, Vol. 44</title>
                        <title type="sort">negro genius</title>
                        <author>Benjamin Brawley</author>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <p>First edition</p>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Press of The Hampton Normal and Agricultural Institute</publisher>
                        <pubPlace>Hampton, Virginia</pubPlace>
                        <date value="1915-05">May 1915</date>
                        <idno type="callNo">Print copy consulted: University of Virginia Library
                            call number LC2701.S7</idno>
                    </publicationStmt>
                </biblFull>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>Prepared for the University of Virginia Library Electronic Text Center.</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <p>All quotation marks retained as data.</p>
                <p>All unambiguous end-of-line hyphens have been removed, and the trailing part of a
                    word has been joined to the preceding line.</p>
                <p>The images exist as archived TIFF images, one or more JPEG versions for general
                    use, and thumbnail GIFs.</p>
                <p>Keywords in the header are a local Electronic Text Center scheme to aid in
                    establishing analytical groupings.</p>
            </editorialDecl>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <creation>
                <date value="1915">1915</date>
            </creation>
            <langUsage>
                <language id="eng" usage="main">English</language>
            </langUsage>
            <textClass>
                <keywords>
                    <term>prose; non-fiction</term>
                    <term>African American</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords>
                    <term type="visual work">front cover</term>
                    <term type="format">24 bit color; 400 dpi</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change>
                <date value="1997-05">May, 1997</date>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>corrector</resp>
                    <name>Lisa Spiro, Electronic Text Center</name>
                </respStmt>
                <item>Added TEI header and tags.</item>
            </change>
            <change>
                <date value="2005-06">June 2005</date>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>corrector</resp>
                    <name>John Ivor Carlson</name>
                </respStmt>
                <item>Converted sgml to xml.</item>
            </change>
            <change>
                <date value="2007-09">September 2007</date>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Migration</resp>
                    <name>Ethan Gruber, University of Virginia Library</name>
                </respStmt>
                <item>Converted XML markup from TEI Lite to uva-dl-tei (TEI P4 with local
                    customizations).</item>
            </change>
            <change>
                <date value="2008-01">January 2008</date>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Migration</resp>
                    <name>Greg Murray, University of Virginia Library</name>
                </respStmt>
                <item>Programmatically updated TEI header markup (but not header content) for
                    minimal compliance with current QA requirements.</item>
            </change>
<change>
<date value="2009-03">March 2009</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>Migration</resp>
<name>Scholarly Resources, University of Virginia Library</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Added and/or replaced the digital images accompanying the electronic text. Scanning of exterior and interior (ie. pages) of item was done only for items found in the University of Virginia Special Collections Library.</item>
</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>


    <text id="d1">
        <front id="d2">
            <pb/>
        </front>
        <body id="d3">

            <div1 id="d4" type="essay">
                <pb entity="DSSR_000001475_0001" n="305" pid="uva-lib:510502"/>
                <head>The Negro Genius<lb/> By Benjamin Brawley<lb/> Dean of Morehouse College,
                    Atlanta, Georgia</head>

                <p>In his lecture on "The Poetic Principle," in leading down to his definition of
                    poetry, Edgar Allan Poe has called attention to the three faculties, intellect,
                    feeling, and will, and shown that poetry, that the whole realm of aesthetics in
                    fact, is concerned primarily and solely with the second of these. Does it appeal
                    to a sense of beauty? This is his sole test of a poem or of any work of art, the
                    aim being neither to appeal to the intellect by satisfying the reason or
                    inculcating truth, nor to appeal to the will by satisfying the moral sense or
                    inculcating duty. </p>
                <p>This standard has often been criticized as narrow; yet it embodies a large and
                    fundamental element of truth. If, now, we study the races that go to make up our
                    cosmopolitan American life we shall find that the three which most distinctively
                    represent the faculties, intellect, feeling, and will, are respectively the
                    Anglo-Saxon, the Negro, and the Jewish. Whatever achievement has been made by
                    the Anglo-Saxon has been primarily in the domain of pure intellect. In religion,
                    in business, in invention, in pure scholarship, the same principle holds; and
                    examples are found in Jonathan Edwards, J. Pierpont Morgan, Thomas A. Edison,
                    and in such scholars as Royce and Kittredge of the Harvard of today. Similarly
                    the outstanding race in the history of the world for emphasis on the moral or
                    religious element of life has been the Jewish. Throughout the Old Testament the
                    heart of Israel cries out to Jehovah, and through the law given on Sinai, the
                    songs of the Psalmist, and the prophecies of Isaiah, the tradition of Israel has
                    thrilled and inspired the entire human race. </p>
                <p>With reference now to the Negro two things are observable. One is that any
                    distinction so far won by a member of the race in America has been almost always
                    in some one of the arts; and the other is that any influence so far exerted by
                    the Negro on American civilization has been primarily in the field of esthetics.
                    A man of science like Benjamin Banneker is the exception. To prove the point we
                    may refer to a long line of beautiful singers, to the fervid oratory of
                    Douglass, to the sensuous poetry of Dunbar, to the picturesque style of Du Bois,
                    to the impressionism <pb entity="DSSR_000001475_0002" n="306"
                        pid="uva-lib:510503"/> of the paintings of Tanner, and to the elemental
                    sculpture of Meta Warrick Fuller. Even Booker Washington, most practical of
                    Americans, proves the point, the distinguishing qualities of his speeches being
                    anecdote and brilliant concrete illustration. </p>
                <p>Everyone must have observed the radical difference in the appearance of the homes
                    of white people and Negroes of the peasant class in the South. If the white man
                    is not himself cultivated, and if he has not been able to give to his children
                    the advantages of culture, his home is most likely to be a bare, blank abode
                    with no pictures and no flowers. Such is not the case with the Negro. He is
                    determined to have a picture, and if nothing better is obtainable he will paste
                    a circus poster or a flaring advertisement on the walls. The instinct for beauty
                    insists upon an outlet; and there are few homes of Negroes of the humbler class
                    that will not have a geranium on the windowsill or a rose-bush in the garden.
                    If, too, we look at the matter conversely, we shall find that those things which
                    are most picturesque make to the Negro the readiest appeal. Red is his favorite
                    color, simply because it is the most pronounced of all colors. Goethe's "Faust"
                    can hardly be said to be a play designed primarily for the galleries. In general
                    it might be supposed to rank with "Macbeth" or "She Stoops to Conquer" or
                    "Richelieu." One never sees it fail, however, that in any Southern city "Faust"
                    will fill the gallery with the so-called lower class of Negro people, who would
                    never dream of going to see one of the other plays just mentioned; and the
                    applause never leaves one in doubt as to the reasons for Goethe's popularity. It
                    is the suggestiveness of the love scenes, the red costume of Mephistopheles, the
                    electrical effects, and the rain of fire, that give the thrill
                    desired&mdash;all pure melodrama of course. "Faust" is a good show as well
                    as a good play. </p>
                <p>In some of our communities Negroes are frequently known to "get happy" in church.
                    Now a sermon on the rule of faith or the plan of salvation is never known to
                    awaken such ecstacy. This rather accompanies a vivid portrayal of the beauties
                    of heaven, with its walls of jasper, the angels with palms in their hands, and
                        (<hi rend="italic">summum bonum!</hi>) the feast of milk and honey. And just
                    here is the dilemma faced by the occupants of a great many pulpits in Negro
                    churches. Do the Negroes want scholarly training? Very frequently the cultured
                    preacher will be inclined to answer in the negative. Do they want rant and
                    shouting? Such a standard fails at once to satisfy the ever-increasing
                    intelligence of the audience itself. The trouble is that the educated Negro
                    minister too often leaves out of account the basic psychology of his audience.
                    That preacher who will ultimately be the most successful with the Negro
                    congregation will be the <pb entity="DSSR_000001475_0003" n="307"
                        pid="uva-lib:510504"/> one who to scholarship and culture can join brilliant
                    imagination and fervid rhetorical expression. When all of these qualities are
                    brought together in their finest proportion the effect is irresistible. Some
                    distinguished white preachers, who to their deep spirituality have joined lively
                    rhetorical expression, have never failed to succeed with a Negro audience as
                    well as with an Anglo-Saxon one. Noteworthy examples within recent years have
                    been Dr. P. S. Henson and Dr. R. S. MacArthur. </p>
                <p>Gathering up the threads of our discussion so far, we find that there is constant
                    striving on the part of the Negro for beautiful or striking effect, that those
                    things which are most picturesque make the readiest appeal to his nature, and
                    that in the sphere of religion he receives with most appreciation those
                    discourses which are most imaginative in quality. In short, so far as the last
                    point is concerned, it is not too much to assert that the Negro is thrilled, not
                    so much by the moral as by the artistic and pictorial elements in religion. </p>
                <p>But there is something deeper than the sensuousness of beauty that makes for the
                    possibilities of the Negro in the realm of the arts, and that is the soul of the
                    race. The wail of the old melodies and the plaintive quality that is ever
                    present in the Negro voice are but the reflection of a background of tragedy. No
                    race can rise to the greatest heights of art until it has yearned and suffered.
                    The Russians are a case in point. Such has been their background in oppression
                    and striving that their literature and art today are marked by an unmistakable
                    note of power. The same future beckons to the American Negro. There is something
                    very elemental about the heart of the race, something that finds its origin in
                    the African forest, in the sighing of the night-wind, and in the falling of the
                    stars. There is something grim and stern about it all too, something that speaks
                    of the lash, of the child torn from its mother's bosom, of the dead body riddled
                    with bullets and swinging all night from a limb by the roadside. </p>
                <p>What does all this mean but that the Negro is a thorough-going romanticist? The
                    philosophy, the satires, the conventionalities of the age of reason mean little
                    to him; but the freedom, the picturesqueness, the moodiness of Wordsworth's day
                    mean much. In his wild, weird melodies we follow once more the wanderings of the
                    Ancient Mariner. In the fervid picture of the New Jerusalem we see the same
                    emphasis on the concrete as in "To a Skylark" or the "Ode to the West Wind;" and
                    under the spell of the Negro voice at its best we once more revel in the
                    sensuousness of "The Eve of St. Agnes." </p>
                <p>All of this of course does not mean that the Negro cannot rise to distinction in
                    any sphere other than the arts, any more <pb entity="DSSR_000001475_0004"
                        n="308" pid="uva-lib:510505"/> than it means that the Anglo-Saxon has not
                    produced great painting and music. It does mean, however, that every race has
                    its peculiar genius, and that, so far as we are at present able to judge, the
                    Negro, with all of his manual labor, is destined to reach his greatest heights
                    in the field of the artistic. But the impulse needs to be watched. Romanticism
                    very soon becomes unhealthy. The Negro has great gifts of voice and ear and
                    soul; but so far much of his talent has not soared above the vaudeville stage.
                    This is due mostly largely of course to economic instability. It is the call of
                    patriotism, however, that America should realize that the Negro has peculiar
                    gifts which need all possible cultivation, and which will one day add to the
                    glory of the country. Already his music is recognized as the most distinctive
                    that the United States has yet produced. The possibilities of the race in
                    literature and oratory, in sculpture and painting, are illimitable. </p>
            </div1>

        </body>
    </text>
</TEI.2>
