<?xml version="1.0"?>

<?dlps id="CanIvan"?>
<?dlps page-images="none" figure-images="yes"?>
<?dlps transcription="other"?>

<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/tei-p4/tei2.dtd" [
<!ENTITY % POSTKB "INCLUDE">
<!ENTITY % TEI.extensions.ent SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.ent">
<!ENTITY % TEI.extensions.dtd SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.dtd">
<!ENTITY % ISOlat1 SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/charent/iso-lat1.ent"> %ISOlat1;
<!ENTITY % ISOlat2 SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/charent/iso-lat2.ent"> %ISOlat2;
<!ENTITY % ISOpub SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/charent/iso-pub.ent"> %ISOpub;





<!ENTITY DSSR_000002642_0001 SYSTEM "000002642_0001" NDATA uvaHighRes>
<!ENTITY DSSR_000002642_0002 SYSTEM "000002642_0002" NDATA uvaHighRes>
<!ENTITY DSSR_000002642_0003 SYSTEM "000002642_0003" NDATA uvaHighRes>
<!ENTITY DSSR_000002642_0004 SYSTEM "000002642_0004" NDATA uvaHighRes>
<!ENTITY DSSR_000002642_0005 SYSTEM "000002642_0005" NDATA uvaHighRes>
<!ENTITY DSSR_000002642_0006 SYSTEM "000002642_0006" NDATA uvaHighRes>
]>
<TEI.2 id="CanIvan">
    <teiHeader type="migrated" creator="Etext">
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title type="main">Ivanhoe and the German Measles</title>
                <title type="sort">ivanhoe and the german measles</title>
                <author>Canfield, Dorothy</author>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Creation of machine-readable version:</resp>
                    <name>Judy Boss</name>
                    <resp>Creation of digital images:</resp>
                    <name>Michele Ierardi</name>
                    <resp>Conversion to TEI.2-conformant markup:</resp>
                    <name>University of Virginia Library Electronic Text Center.</name>
                </respStmt>
            </titleStmt>
            <extent>ca. <num type="kilobytes">24</num> kilobytes</extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>University of Virginia Library</publisher>
                <pubPlace>Charlottesville, Virginia</pubPlace>
                <idno type="ETC">CanIvan</idno>
                <date value="1996">1996</date>
                <availability status="public">
                    <p n="copyright">Copyright &#xa9; 1996 by the Rector and Visitors of the
                        University of Virginia</p>
                    <p n="access">Publicly accessible</p>
                </availability>
                <idno type="uva-pid">uva-lib:476758</idno>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title>University of Virginia Library, Text collection</title>
                <idno type="uva-set">UVA-LIB-Text</idno>
            </seriesStmt>
            <notesStmt>
                <note>
                    <p>Illustrations have been included from the print version. These images have
                        been scanned from printouts of the microfilm.</p>
                </note>
            </notesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull>
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title type="main">Ivanhoe and the German Measles</title>
                        <title level="j">American Magazine</title>
                        <title type="sort">ivanhoe and the german measles</title>
                        <author>Dorothy Canfield</author>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <extent>pp. 398-403</extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Colver Publishing House</publisher>
                        <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                        <date value="1906-08">August 1906</date>
                        <idno type="callNo">Print copy consulted: UVA library call no. Micfilm S-147
                            reel 689.</idno>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <notesStmt>
                        <note>
                            <p>
                                <hi rend="italic">American Magazine</hi> vol. 62, no. 4 (Aug. 1906):
                                398-403.</p>
                        </note>
                    </notesStmt>
                </biblFull>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>Prepared for the University of Virginia Library Electronic Text Center.</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <p>All quotation marks retained as data.</p>
                <p>All unambiguous end-of-line hyphens have been removed, and the trailing part of a
                    word has been joined to the preceding line.</p>
                <p>The images exist as archived TIFF images, one or more JPEG versions for general
                    use, and thumbnail GIFs.</p>
                <p>Keywords in the header are a local Electronic Text Center scheme to aid in
                    establishing analytical groupings.</p>
            </editorialDecl>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <creation>
                <date value="1906">1906</date>
            </creation>
            <langUsage>
                <language id="eng" usage="main">English</language>
            </langUsage>
            <textClass>
                <keywords>
                    <term>fiction; prose</term>
                    <term>Women Writers</term>
                    <term>Young Readers</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords>
                    <term type="artist">Greer, Blanche</term>
                    <term type="visual work">illustration</term>
                    <term type="format">256-shade greyscale, 400 dpi</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change>
                <date value="1996-10">October 1996</date>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>corrector</resp>
                    <name>Michele Ierardi, Electronic Text Center</name>
                </respStmt>
                <item>Added TEI header and tags.</item>
            </change>
            <change>
                <date value="2005-06">June 2005</date>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>corrector</resp>
                    <name>John Ivor Carlson</name>
                </respStmt>
                <item>Converted sgml to xml.</item>
            </change>
            <change>
                <date value="2007-09">September 2007</date>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Migration</resp>
                    <name>Ethan Gruber, University of Virginia Library</name>
                </respStmt>
                <item>Converted XML markup from TEI Lite to uva-dl-tei (TEI P4 with local
                    customizations).</item>
            </change>
            <change>
                <date value="2008-01">January 2008</date>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Migration</resp>
                    <name>Greg Murray, University of Virginia Library</name>
                </respStmt>
                <item>Programmatically updated TEI header markup (but not header content) for
                    minimal compliance with current QA requirements.</item>
            </change>
<change>
<date value="2009-03">March 2009</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>Migration</resp>
<name>Scholarly Resources, University of Virginia Library</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Added and/or replaced the digital images accompanying the electronic text. Scanning of exterior and interior (ie. pages) of item was done only for items found in the University of Virginia Special Collections Library.</item>
</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>


    <text id="d1">

        <body id="d2">


            <div1 type="story" id="d3">
                <pb entity="DSSR_000002642_0001" n="398"/>
                <head> Ivanhoe and the German Measles<lb/> By Dorothy Canfield <lb/> WITH
                ILLUSTRATIONS BY BLANCHE GREER </head>
                
                <p> HIS name was Reginald Gerald Whitefield, and he was the sort of little boy who
                    surprised observers by not having freckles. He had the honest look that goes
                    with freckles and a turned-up nose, although his complexion was irreproachable
                    and his nose neither turned up or down but was quite uninterestingly straight.
                    He was the sort of little boy who endures a scientific and expensive bringing up
                    and is not spoiled by it. He had a French house-governess, he took "talking
                    walks" with a spectacled and conscientious German, he was sent in a black velvet
                    suit to dancing-school, he took riding lessons from a severe ex-cavalryman who
                    contrived in a miraculous way to exclude from the exercise all the fun that
                    naturally goes with it; he was taken to the concerts of the Boston Symphony, and
                    bore with fortitude lectures on "What the Nibelungenlied may mean to a child,"
                    and he became neither priggish nor misanthropic. It must be plain, therefore,
                    that he was a remarkable little boy. In short he did not deserve his exuberant
                    name. </p>
                <p>At the period when this story begins he did not, as a matter of fact, bear his
                    unfortunate name except at home. His real name was Wamba, and Wamba he had 
                    <pb entity="DSSR_000002642_0002" n="399"/>
                    become. In the model and scientific school where he was being
                    educated, the old-fashioned "reader" was scorned and the savor taken out of
                    spontaneous novel-reading by using the classics for drill in declamation and
                    spelling. The class to which Reginald Gerald Whitefield had attained always read
                    "Ivanhoe." They did more than read "Ivanhoe" the year he was in
                    it&mdash;they lived and moved and had their being in "Ivanhoe," they talked
                    and dreamed and discussed and played and ate and drank "Ivanhoe." The class was
                    organized on a completely feudal basis, with the characters of the novel
                    distributed as far as they would go, and the rest were known vaguely and
                    collectively as "vassals." Reginald Gerald's imagination had been the torch
                    which had fired all this conflagration of interest, but Wamba was the only
                    r&ocirc;le he was allowed because he was short and thin-legged and not in
                    the least imposing. In fact, he was irresistibly comic in appearance, in spite
                    of the careful distinction with which his mother always dressed him. His bullet
                    head, little twinkling gray eyes and clown's flexible smile, wide and
                    undignified, made him impossible for a picturesque r&ocirc;le in any of the
                    imaginative games which he invented with such wonderful facility. </p>
                <p>The authorities of the school, being highly scientific, believed on principle in
                    allowing much scope to "individual initiative," although, as a rule, they made
                    every kindly and mistaken effort to shut off this valuable quality by thinking
                    of all pleasant enterprises before the children possibly could. The proposition
                    of the Sixth Form to make a play of "Ivanhoe" and act it before the school was
                    received, therefore, with the most modern and up-to-date approval, almost enough
                    to take the fun out of the scheme. But with Wamba's eager spirit flashing from
                    desk to desk, interest could not fail to rise high. The play was written by the
                    Sixth Form <hi rend="italic">en masse</hi>, a feudal loyalty so welding them
                    together that they acted as one mind. Beside that, they had "played 'Ivanhoe'"
                    so much that there was really little to do beyond arranging chronologically the
                    various scenes they were accustomed to act with prodigious vigor in their model
                    and scientific playground. </p>
                <p>With a truly modern feeling for spectacular effect, the parts had been cast long
                    ago according to looks. Helen Armstrong was the worst speller in her class (and
                    that is saying 
                    <pb entity="DSSR_000002642_0003" n="400"/> 
                    a good deal); was slow and stolid and unutterably
                    spiritless in her acting, but anyone with such large blue eyes and such an
                    astonishing flood of golden curls was evidently intended by Providence to be
                    Rowena, and, forgetting the qualities of the real Helen Armstrong, the Sixth
                    Form accorded to Rowena, the fair symbol of their ideal, a devotion which could
                    not have been greater in the Dark Ages. Peter Stuyvesant, Jr., never could quite
                    make out the sequence of the story in spite of many repetitions, but a boy who
                    was so astonishingly big for eleven years, and who had so handsome a dull, blond
                    face was "Ivanhoe by the grace of God," as Wamba put it to their teacher in
                    explaining the matter to her. He, himself, accepted the r&ocirc;le of
                    faithful fool, which nobody else would take, and lost himself in a very passion
                    of loyalty to Ivanhoe which was quaintly disassociated from his accurate
                    estimate of Peter Stuyvesant, Junior's, heavy and thick-witted personality. </p>
                <p>He had only one speech to make in the play, although he appeared in many scenes.
                    His time came when he followed Ivanhoe into exile, after everyone had deserted
                    him. Kneeling before him he cried out, "Sir! Though all the world forsake thee,
                    Wamba the faithful fool will ever be thy loyal servitor!" Into this one sentence
                    he put all the imaginative fervor which this feudal game of his invention
                    kindled in his heart. He did not envy the others their long and grandiloquent
                    remarks, taken bodily from the book. Brian de Bois Guilbert might shout with all
                    the force of his ten-year-old lungs, "Then take your place in the lists and look
                    your last upon the sun, for this night thou shalt sleep in Paradise." And
                    Ivanhoe might answer, boldly, "Gramercy for thy courtesy, and, to requite it, I
                    advise thee to take a new lance, for, by my honor, thou wilt have need thereof!"
                    But Wamba, looking on the stirring combat which followed, would shout with an
                    excitement untinged by envy of their distinguished r&ocirc;les, even
                    untinged by disillusion in the face of the fact that Ivanhoe had revealed to him
                    a few minutes before that he thought the "gramercy" of his speech referred to
                    the park on which he lived. </p>
                <p>The hermit in the scene with Richard C&oelig;ur-de-Lion might rollick most
                    jovially and win laurels untold by making the teachers present at the rehearsals
                    laugh over his singing and jokes, but Wamba was content with his own part. There
                    was a single-hearted ardor about that speech which the teachers did not applaud
                    as they sometimes did the fiery remarks of Front-de-B&oelig;uf or Ulrica,
                    but nobody offered him any suggestions as to how it should be said, and there
                    was always a little hushed silence after he had finished and caught Ivanhoe's
                    fat Dutch hand in his, which he rightly, although but half-consciously, took to
                    be a tribute to his interpretation. </p>
                <p>There was another advantage about his part: it took up very little of his time,
                    and as he was stage-manager, scene-shifter, property-man and guardian of the
                    costumes, it was essential that he be left free. As the fateful day approached
                    his excitement grew more and more intense. His laughing, little gray eyes
                    gleamed with a breathless interest in every detail, and his thin little hands
                    ached with pulling and hauling on the home-made scenery, and with much
                    manufacture of armor from wire-ring dish-cloths. His unfettered originality had
                    seen the possibilities in these clanking implements of the cook at a time when
                    chain-armor had seemed an unattainable ideal. </p>
                <p>The presentation of Ivanhoe by the Sixth Form had come to be the central event of
                    the whole institution, and Wamba held his head high with pride as he overheard
                    the big boys and girls from the High School talking curiously about it. His
                    geography and arithmetic lesson went by the board as the actual performance grew
                    nearer and nearer and as rehearsals grew thicker. He was now prompter in
                    addition to all his other duties, as, from much hearing of the r&ocirc;les,
                    he had come to know the words the other children spoke better than they did. He
                    walked to school through the park with a base-ball mitt dangling from one button
                    of his coat and the self-manufactured bauble of a medi&aelig;val fool
                    hanging from another. </p>
                <p>To Wamba, as the head of this fantastic enterprise, there came, the evening
                    before the play, a blurred and tragic scrawl from Peter Stuyvesant, Jr. </p>
                <p>Dere Wamba, the doctor says I've got the german meesels and can't go to school
                    for a weak. What shall I do, Ivanhoe. </p>
                <p>(They learn feeling for Botticelli in modern scientific schools, but English
                    spelling is a lost art, there as elsewhere.) </p>
                <p>Wamba was stunned, overwhelmed. It 
                    
                    <pb entity="DSSR_000002642_0004" n="401"/>
                    
                   was impossible&mdash;so hideous a catastrophe came upon him like a
                    thunderclap. When he caught his breath, however, his valiant and intrepid mind
                    faced the situation bravely. What could be done? The play must go on, of course,
                    but how could it? At once there flamed into his mind the vision of himself as
                    Ivanhoe, resplendent in tin armor and floating plumes. Why not? He knew the
                    part, he was the only one who did, and how he could act it! He saw himself
                    putting fire into the scenes where Peter Stuyvesant, Jr., had lagged and
                    mumbled; he heard his own ringing, high treble delivering those speeches which
                    were like chased gold and glowing purple to his boy's imagination. In a moment
                    his humble r&ocirc;le of Wamba lost its value. He felt that his former
                    content with it had been, after all, but making the best of what he had. With
                    the possibility of this glorious opportunity before him, his one poor speech
                    seemed homespun and dull. He rushed down the street to Ivanhoe's house, his
                    heart on fire with ambition, reciting aloud, "On foot, on horseback, with spear,
                    with axe or with sword I am alike ready to encounter thee!" and other choice
                    bits of his hero's r&ocirc;le. He was transfigured into Ivanhoe, and
                    Gramercy Park was the veritable Forest of Robin Hood, as his thin legs, clad in
                    silk stockings and irreproachably bench-made shoes, carried him to Peter's door. </p>
                <p>Peter's mother was out of town, his father was still at his office, and the
                    butler knew Wamba well, so that there was no hindrance to his rushing directly
                    to the room of the sick boy who was supposed to be quarantined for a contagious
                    disease. Of so much avail are the decrees of Boards of Health when confronted
                    with youth, even scientifically educated youth. Wamba found Ivanhoe in a
                    deplorable state. His pillow was wet with tears, unmanly but not to be choked
                    back, in spite of careful training in self-control. The disappointment was more
                    than he could bear. At intervals he howled aloud violently, like any other child
                    in the clutch of desolation. "It's too dern mean!" he sobbed as Wamba stood by
                    the bed, awed at the sight of his schoolmate's suffering. "I'd just like to kill
                    that doctor, I would! He could have put it off another day if he wanted to! He
                    just did it to be mean!" </p>
                <p>He relapsed into incoherent exclamations and cries, the vocabulary of a boy who
                    is scientifically brought up being lamentably weak in objurgations. Wamba lost,
                    for a moment, his usually keen knowledge of the other's far from elevated point
                    of view, and fell into the error of attributing to him the
                    <pb entity="DSSR_000002642_0005" n="402"/>
                    generosity of grief which would have been his own in like case. "Well, Ivanhoe,
                    old boy, don't feel so bad. We'll pull through somehow without you. You needn't
                    feel as though you were to blame for breaking up the whole show. Somebody can
                    take your place, though it won't be so good." </p>
                <p>Ivanhoe sat up in bed, and shouted an indignant disclaimer of any such
                    consideration for the common good. "I <hi rend="italic">know</hi> you'll get on
                    without me!" he cried bitterly. "And that is what makes me so mad at the doctor!
                    Somebody else will wear those clothes, and that helmet&mdash;you
                    probably&mdash;and somebody else will fight with Bois-Guilbert, and
                    everybody will applaud; and I'll never have a chance again 'slong as I live to
                    be Ivanhoe. It's not fair! It's not fair! I had the best part. Now if it was you
                    with your measly little speech&mdash;anybody could say that! And I just
                    finished putting a new dishcloth on the back of the helmet!" </p>
                <p>He writhed in agony and motioned Wamba furiously away when he tried to speak. </p>
                <p>Gramercy Park was no longer the forest of Robin Hood as Wamba walked back through
                    it very soberly, with his head hanging; nor was he Ivanhoe. He was two
                    persons&mdash;one Reginald Gerald Whitefield, wild with delight and
                    excitement over the sudden opening of a path of gold before his feet to certain
                    glory, and the other, Wamba the soul of unreasoning devotion, plunged deep in
                    poignant sympathy with the sorrow of his liege lord and whipping his invention
                    feverishly to contrive some way by which a loyal servitor could help him. He was
                    silent at dinner, and abstracted during the reading to him by his French
                    governess of selected passages from French classics. After he was in bed he lay
                    wide awake in his carefully ventilated room, staring into the dark. All at once
                    he gave a little start and cried aloud. </p>
                <p><hi rend="italic">"Qu-as tu, mon petit?"</hi> asked Marie opening the door. </p>
                <p><hi rend="italic">"Rien</hi>," he said bravely, with iron resolution, <hi
                        rend="italic">"Rien &mdash;une pens&eacute;e</hi>." But after she
                    had shut the door he was ashamed to let even the dark see the crumpled and
                    tragic discomposure of his clown's face and he hid it in the pillows with a moan
                    of shame at his own weakness. </p>
                <p>Peter's butler scarcely knew Reginald Gerald the next day, so white and stern was
                    his odd little countenance, as he marched up the stairs to Peter's room. </p>
                <p>"Here, Pete, you get up and dress and skin out to the school. You'll get there in
                    time for the first act. I'm going to undress and get into bed and be asleep
                    every time the maid comes in. I'll draw the covers all close around my head and
                    she cannot tell our hair apart. We'll pull down the curtains and make the room
                    dark and I told her I'd seen you and you wanted to sleep all the afternoon. You
                    can be back by six o'clock and it won't make any difference if they do find out
                    then, and maybe we can bribe Simmons to keep still about letting you in. Here,
                    get a move on you!" </p>
                <p>Peter fell out of bed in trembling, incredulous joy, obeying without a word, as
                    he invariably did, the all-wise mandates of his friend. In frantic haste one boy
                    dressed and the other undressed, Wamba assuming the discarded pajamas of the
                    sick boy without a murmur, although, being scientifically brought up, he was as
                    much under the nightmare spell of germs as the most enlightened of us. Ivanhoe's
                    mind worked slowly, and it was not until he had opened the door and made a wary
                    reconnoiter of the hall to see whether the coast was clear, that he thought of
                    Wamba's side of the transaction. "Say!" he whispered to the tuft of sandy hair,
                    all that was visible of his substitute. "You'll catch it, lying in my bed in my
                    nightclothes." </p>
                <p>"Who cares?" said Wamba, gloomily. </p>
                <p>"Say, it's too bad you have to miss it!" </p>
                <p>No answer. </p>
                <p>"Well, yours was such a little part, anyhow," was Ivanhoe's excusing farewell, as
                    he crept cautiously down the stairs. </p>
                <p>In the darkened room which he left behind him it was very still. The clock ticked
                    loudly, marking away the quarter hours at which the maid came faithfully to look
                    at the silent head buried in the covers. Wamba did not sleep. The time seemed
                    interminable to him. As the clock struck half-past three he knew that the play
                    was beginning. He followed in his imagination every scene of it, speech by
                    speech. He waved his gay and tinkling fool's cap in the crowd about the lists
                    where the tourney took place, he crowded among the people in the streets of
                    York, he crouched at the feet of Rowena during the banquet scene, he mocked at
                    Isaac and he pitied Rebecca with all the fervor of a sore and aching heart. Then
                    his scene&mdash;his great scene came. Ivanhoe was cast out from his
                    inheritance, 
                    
                    <pb entity="DSSR_000002642_0006" n="403"/>
                  
                  all his friends deserted him, an intolerably cruel and irrevocable
                    fate hung over him, alone but for the hero of devotion who was about to speak.
                    In his imagination Wamba felt the audience looking at him with their thousand
                    eyes, he felt within him the swelling power to move them, and as an actual fact
                    he lay in a hot bed in a darkened room. He drew long breaths and blinked his
                    eyes rapidly as he realized that his great opportunity was passing by. But at
                    least Ivanhoe was there, with his handsome, dull face happy in the marvelous
                    helmet. Wamba felt, through his misery, unutterable pride that he had been able
                    to rescue his lord, and self-forgetting joy in another's pleasure. He half rose
                    to his knees, the sheets tumbling about him. "Sir!" he cried in ringing tones,
                    "Sir! Though all the world forsake thee, Wamba the faithful fool will ever be
                    thy loyal servitor!" And then it is to be feared that Wamba the witty, the
                    invincibly humorous, fell forward on his pillow and wet it with the tears of a
                    very bitterly disappointed little boy. </p>
                <p>This was on a Friday. On Monday Wamba went to school to face, with what grace he
                    could, the reproaches of the Sixth Form for his desertion. He had no answer to
                    give beyond, "Oh, I <hi rend="italic">couldn't</hi> get here. Had something else
                    to do." He thought his cup was full, but it brimmed over with the appearance of
                    Peter Stuyvesant, Jr., ex-Ivanhoe. </p>
                <p>"Why, I thought you were quarantined!" he cried, his head whirling. </p>
                <p>Peter looked confused. "I was just sure that old doctor didn't know what he was
                    talking about. He says now it isn't German measles at all, but just a rash from
                    something I've eaten. I might have come to school as well as not on Friday,
                    too." </p>
                <p>Reginald Gerald looked at him, quivering with an intolerable sense of bitterness,
                    rent with the pangs of furious rebellion against fate. It seemed that he was
                    called upon for more endurance than flesh and blood could muster. But Ivanhoe
                    went on, "Say, Wamba, you acted awful square about that. I didn't have time to
                    think much about it then, but I have, since. Say, there's not another boy in
                    school who'd have done that." </p>
                <p>Wamba's heart suddenly glowed with the pure and generous flame of final
                    disinterestedness. The flower of the feudal spirit was his, the essence of
                    loyalty, the fine disregard of material outcome. </p>
                <p>"Oh, anybody could say my little speech," he said, and, although his voice
                    quavered a little, he held his head bravely high. </p>

            </div1>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI.2>
