<?xml version="1.0"?>

<?dlps id="CanPlay"?>
<?dlps page-images="color" figure-images="yes"?>
<?dlps transcription="other"?>

<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/tei-p4/tei2.dtd" [
<!ENTITY % POSTKB "INCLUDE">
<!ENTITY % TEI.extensions.ent SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.ent">
<!ENTITY % TEI.extensions.dtd SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.dtd">
<!ENTITY % ISOpub SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/charent/iso-pub.ent"> %ISOpub;



<!ENTITY DSSR_000002643_0001 SYSTEM "000002643_0001" NDATA uvaHighRes>
<!ENTITY DSSR_000002643_0002 SYSTEM "000002643_0002" NDATA uvaHighRes>
<!ENTITY DSSR_000002643_0003 SYSTEM "000002643_0003" NDATA uvaHighRes>
<!ENTITY DSSR_000002643_0004 SYSTEM "000002643_0004" NDATA uvaHighRes>
<!ENTITY DSSR_000002643_0005 SYSTEM "000002643_0005" NDATA uvaHighRes>
<!ENTITY DSSR_000002643_0006 SYSTEM "000002643_0006" NDATA uvaHighRes>
<!ENTITY DSSR_000002643_0007 SYSTEM "000002643_0007" NDATA uvaHighRes>
]>
<TEI.2 id="CanPlay">
<teiHeader type="migrated" creator="Etext">
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title type="main">The Playmate</title>
<title type="sort">playmate</title>
<author>Canfield, Dorothy</author>
<respStmt>
<resp>Creation of machine-readable version:</resp>
<name>Judy Boss</name>
<resp>Creation of digital images:</resp>
<name>Michele Ierardi</name>
<resp>Conversion to TEI.2-conformant markup:</resp>
<name>University of Virginia Library Electronic Text Center.</name>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt>
<extent>ca. <num type="kilobytes">27</num> kilobytes</extent>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>University of Virginia Library</publisher>
<pubPlace>Charlottesville, Virginia</pubPlace>
<idno type="ETC">CanPlay</idno>
<date value="1996">1996</date>
<availability status="public">
<p n="copyright">Copyright &#xa9; 1996 by the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia</p>
<p n="access">Publicly accessible</p>
</availability>
<idno type="uva-pid">uva-lib:476761</idno>
</publicationStmt>
<seriesStmt>
<title>University of Virginia Library, Text collection</title>
<idno type="uva-set">UVA-LIB-Text</idno>
</seriesStmt>
<notesStmt>
<note>
<p>Illustrations have been included from the print version. Images were scanned from printouts of the microfilm copy.</p>
</note>
<note>
<p>Judy Boss has made the following changes: p.85, its] it's</p>
</note>
</notesStmt>
<sourceDesc>
<biblFull>
<titleStmt>
<title type="main">The Playmate</title>
<title level="j">American Illustrated Magazine</title>
<title type="sort">playmate</title>
<author>Dorothy Canfield</author>
</titleStmt>
<editionStmt>
<p>First Edition</p>
</editionStmt>
<extent>pp. 80-86</extent>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>Colver Publishing House</publisher>
<pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
<date value="1905-11">November 1905</date>
<idno type="callNo">Copy consulted: UVA library call no. Micfilm S-147 reel 689</idno>
</publicationStmt>
<notesStmt>
<note>
<p>American Illustrated Magazine, vol. 61, no. 1.</p>
</note>
</notesStmt>
</biblFull>
</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc>
<encodingDesc>
<projectDesc>
<p>Prepared for the University of Virginia Library Electronic Text Center.</p>
</projectDesc>
<editorialDecl>
<p>All quotation marks retained as data.</p>
<p>All unambiguous end-of-line hyphens have been removed, and the trailing part of a word has been joined to the preceding line.</p>
<p>The images exist as archived TIFF images, one or more JPEG versions for general use, and thumbnail GIFs.</p>
<p>Keywords in the header are a local Electronic Text Center scheme to aid in establishing analytical groupings.</p>
</editorialDecl>
</encodingDesc>
<profileDesc>
<creation>
<date value="1905">1905</date>
</creation>
<langUsage>
<language id="eng" usage="main">English</language>
</langUsage>
<textClass>
<keywords>
<term>fiction; prose</term>
<term>Women Writers</term>
</keywords>
<keywords>
<term>O'Neill, Rose Cecil</term>
<term>illustration</term>
<term>256-shade greyscale, 400 dpi</term>
</keywords>
</textClass>
</profileDesc>
<revisionDesc>
<change>
<date value="1996-09">September 1996</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>corrector</resp>
<name>Michele Ierardi, Electronic Text Center</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Added TEI headers and tags.</item>
</change>
<change>
<date value="2005-06">June 2005</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>corrector</resp>
<name>John Ivor Carlson</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Converted sgml to xml.</item>
</change>
<change>
<date value="2007-09">September 2007</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>Migration</resp>
<name>Ethan Gruber, University of Virginia Library</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Converted XML markup from TEI Lite to uva-dl-tei (TEI P4 with local customizations).</item>
</change>
<change>
<date value="2008-01">January 2008</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>Migration</resp>
<name>Greg Murray, University of Virginia Library</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Programmatically updated TEI header markup (but not header content) for minimal compliance with current QA requirements.</item>
</change>
<change>
<date value="2009-03">March 2009</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>Migration</resp>
<name>Scholarly Resources, University of Virginia Library</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Added and/or replaced the digital images accompanying the electronic text. Scanning of exterior and interior (ie. pages) of item was done only for items found in the University of Virginia Special Collections Library.</item>
</change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>
    
    
<text id="d1">
<front id="d2">
<div1 type="figure" id="d3">
    <pb entity="DSSR_000002643_0001"/>
<p rend="center">Mary felt a timid presence in the dark not far from her.</p>

</div1>
</front>


<body id="d4">

<div1 type="story" id="d5"><pb n="81"/>
<head>

<hi rend="bold">THE PLAYMATE.</hi>
<lb/>
By Dorothy Canfield
<lb/>
ILLUSTRATED BY Rose Cecil O'Neill

</head>

    <pb entity="DSSR_000002643_0002" n="81"/>

<p>MRS. O'HERN looked about her with beaming eyes.  "Well, it may
seem queer to think of living in a barn," she observed to her old
friend, "but it suits me fine!  Ever since I left Ireland I've lived too
much indoors, and it does seem good to be cooking half in the air
again."
</p><p>The older woman jangled her keys meditatively.  "I thought
you were crazy when you first talked about it," she admitted, "but it
does seem sort o' cozy like, and it'll be fine for the childer to be in
the country this summer."
</p><p>"Aye!  It'll be the makin' of Pollie that's growin' so fast, an'
Patsy'll be away from them bad boys on the street.  Though we
moved in but yesterday, I can see now what a grand time the
childer'll have in the lovely grounds, an' it was the only way of
being wid Pat while he's on that brick-layin' job on the new country
house.  Sure it's a good friend you are, to lave us do it."
</p><p>The old crone answered with a proprietary air.  "Oh, why not?
There ain't been a soul in this barn for fifteen years, not since I
begun takin' care of the big house, an' sure it can't hurt the old loft to
have the beds of all the blessed childer in it instead of cobwebs, nor
the open shed to have a stove set up, wid decent Irish praties cookin'
over it.  I niver thought you cud make it look so like a real home&mdash;pictures of the saints and flowers and cushions and all."
</p><p>Mrs. O'Hern laughed comfortably as she looked about the
clean room where they sat, and out the open door into the wide-spreading orchard trees all a pink glory of blossom.  "Cud any place
wid your eight childer and your own man be aught but home&mdash;barn
or no barn?" she inquired.
</p><p>The old woman nodded appreciatively, and for a few moments
there was silence, broken only by the cooing of doves on the roof of
the shed.  Then she spoke again.  "It's a good thing th' old man&mdash;him
as owns the big house&mdash;niver comes a-near no more."
</p><p>"Why?" asked Mrs. O'Hern.
</p><p>"He'd have something to say about your camping out here!"
</p><p>"We won't hurt his old barn!" cried the other.  "Look how
clean I've made it, white curtains to the windys and all!"
</p><p>"It's the swarmin' childer of ye he'd be mindin'.  He'd not care
about his barn bein' used, because he's not that kind, but he niver
could abide childer&mdash;it's my belief he niver cared a crumb for his
own son, till he was half grown up&mdash;fifteen or sixteen.  An' that just
the age whin sinsible folks is beginning to think less of thim and
more of the babies!  It was fair enough to break a body's heart&mdash;the
life that poor child led."
</p><p>Mrs. O'Hern's black eyes flashed and the mother in her rose in
indignation.  "Was he treated bad?" she asked hotly.
</p><p>"Well, not to say <hi rend="italic">bad</hi>.  He had always two or three
hired creatures to look after him, and enough to play wid to drive
any well child mad, and governesses and perfessors and muzic
lessons&mdash;oh, it was fair sickenin'!  An' him, the pale, little, skinny-legs,
niver knowin' for wan minute what it was to be a child.  I don't
suppose he <hi rend="italic">iver</hi> played&mdash;what ye might call <hi rend="italic">played</hi>&mdash;wan
blessed minute in all his life.  Th' old man was always away
makin' more money&mdash;not that <hi rend="italic">he</hi> would ha' been much to
play wid&mdash;Heaven knows!"
</p><p>The other's soft Irish eyes melted almost
    <pb entity="DSSR_000002643_0003" n="82"/>
to tears at the
picture she saw, and she drew her little Denny to her and kissed him
before she asked: "Did he die, the poor little boy?"
</p><p>"Arrah!  That I don't know.  Whin it was time for him to begin
to think of goin' to college, th' old man moved away an' I've niver
heard of him since.  But I've a notion he's dead&mdash;he had that kind of
eyes of them that do!"
</p><p>The quick darkness of early spring evenings in New England
shut down and the old gossip rose to go.  "Well, Mary, my dear,"
she said affectionately, "it seems like living again to have some
folks around.  I've been stark alone so long in that gloomy old house
and grounds I'll be in the way of neighboring you to death with
always dropping in."
</p><p>As a matter of fact she did spend much time in the midst of the
rosy, chattering, romping family of Irish-Americans who ran wild,
like little Indians, in the grounds, and their own very considerable
numbers augmented by battalions of cousins and regiments of
friends filled to overflowing the big lofts of the deserted barn.
</p><p>Mrs. O'Hern, for all her thirty-five years, matronly figure and
eight children, ran and played with them like a girl.  Denny
announced one day: "It didn't seem as though we could love mother
more than we did in town, but out here I love her so it hurts."
</p><p>Patrick O'Hern, busy with his brick-laying on a country house
down the road, was only too glad to have his family with him, and
loved and scolded and petted and stormed at his children with all
the gusto of the true Irish parent.  They were a noisy family.  The
mother said sometimes: "Now, for the love of Heaven, childer, can't
ye quiet down a bit!  Remember ye're in a place where gentry has
lived&mdash;can't ye try, just for a change, to have gentry manners?"  But
almost always, when she had said that, she remembered the pale
little boy, passing a joyless childhood in the big house, and had
rejoiced in the wild peals of laughter from her own unruly brood.
</p><p>It was quite soon after their arrival that she became aware of
something strange about the place.  One evening, late, she had gone
into the big room where the four youngest children slept, to make
sure that Denny was covered.  The child had been a little feverish at
supper, and she was anxious about him.  She laughed at herself as
she felt her way up the steep stairs.
</p><p>"'Tis only that it's Denny!  I'm that foolish about the child.
He's different from the rest of us black Irish!  There do be times
when I think he has the second-sight&mdash;like brother Tim that died."
She pushed open the door and started, for, although the room was
quite dark, she felt instantly that one of the children was out of bed.
"Denny!" she called softly, fumbling for a match.  Denny answered
from his cot at the other end of the room, and as she struck the
match she saw that the four little beds were all occupied and the
room was quite still.
</p><p>Denny was wide awake, his big, blue eyes shining in the light
of the match.  "Have you been in bed all the time?" asked his
mother.  The child nodded his head without speaking.  "Queer," said
Mary, dropping the half burned match.  "I thought one of yez was
out on the floor as I came in."  Denny said nothing, and after
settling the covers about his throat, his mother stooped to kiss him.
As she did so, she felt suddenly that a child was standing close to
her.  "Who's that?" she said sharply.  "One of the other ones playin'
a trick on me!"  But the light of another match showed only the
three black heads half buried in their pillows and Denny's soft eyes
looking at her over the coverlet.  His lips moved and she bent over
to hear what he said.  "Don't drive him away, mother; let him stay."
</p><p>"Let <hi rend="italic">who</hi> stay?" she asked, bewildered, but Denny's
eyes were drooping sleepily, and he said no more.
</p><p>"Some queer child's fancy!" she thought as she groped her way
from the darkened room.
</p><p>The next day Denny was not quite himself and she made him
stay in bed.  After the morning's work was done she went up to sit in
the room with him, taking a big bag of the never-ending darning.
The sun shone brightly on his fair head as he bent over a game of
dominoes spread on the coverlet.
</p><p>"Playin' dominoes all by yourself, dear?" asked his mother,
tenderly, sitting down by the bed.
</p><p>Denny looked up soberly and said, "No, I'm playing with a
pretend little boy."
    <pb entity="DSSR_000002643_0004" n="83"/>
</p><p>Mary sometimes said, "After bringin' up a family of eight
childer,&mdash;and Mary Mother only knows how many more to come,"&mdash;that
no queer freak that could enter a child's head would surprise
her.  "After Pollie's make-believe monkeys and little Pat's having
conniptions over a table with five legs, and Anastasia's being that
afraid of butterflies that she 'most fainted, you can't tell <hi rend="italic">me</hi>
any tale about childer I won't believe.  They all have those queer
spells, but they all get over them."  So at Denny's "pretend"
domino-player she only smiled indulgently and said nothing.  Denny had
counted on his mother's understanding, and went on with his game,
murmuring disjointed bits of talk to himself.  Mary darned in the
furious haste that is always upon the mother of eight children, and
paid no attention to Denny, beyond glancing at him from time to
time in great satisfaction with his improved looks.
</p><p>She glanced up once in this manner and paused, her mouth
open, and her darning needle suspended in the air.  "Denny!" she
exclaimed, "Whatever are you doing?"  The child looked at her
quietly, and did not answer.  Mrs. O'Hern's astonishment passed
suddenly into incredulity, and she resumed her work.  "Your poor
mother's getting that old!" she laughed.  "She's losing her senses!
Sure!  I thought I saw one of them dominoes lift all by itself, and set
down in a different place."
</p><p>Denny's eyes gleamed with pleasure, and he turned to explain.
"Isn't it fine, mother?  Sometimes he can do that when we're all
alone and I want him to so very much.  Mostly he can only stand by
and look,&mdash;though he likes that fine,&mdash;but once in a while he gets
<hi rend="italic">so</hi> interested, and I want him <hi rend="italic">so</hi> to have a good time,
he can do something himself.  But not very often, and never when
we're all playing together."
</p><p>Mrs. O'Hern looked at him in amazement and some alarm.
The next moment he said sadly, "Oh, there!  We've frightened him
away, and its always so hard to make him not afraid again."
</p><p>Mary had begun to say something in her hasty, Irish way,
about Denny's stopping such nonsense or she'd box his ears, when,
as she afterwards told Father McGinn, "I can't tell you how it was,
but I just felt another child there besides Denny, another child, and a
scared little child, and so lonesome, and the first thing I knew
Denny was crying as though his heart would break, and so was I!
And Denny was saying, 'Oh mother, I'm so sorry for him!'  And
then,&mdash;oh, I don't know,&mdash;Pat called me from the foot of the stairs,
and the childer came busting in to know if they could go out in the
boat, and&mdash;it was all over, everything just the way it always is, only
Denny and me, with red noses.  'What's the matter, mother?' they all
asked, and I said, 'I wish you could tell, for I can't.'"
</p><p>That was the first time, and a week passed before Mary again
felt a breath of mystery blow through her hearty, active life.  It was
on an afternoon full of golden early June sunlight, and the children
were playing with a host of cousins and little friends in the big
orchard not far from the barn.  The delicious country air had gone to
their heads, and they were half-mad with animal spirits, shouting
and racing about, and laughing till they sank down exhausted on the
soft grass in a happy ecstacy.  Denny was romping with the others,
his shrill little treble ringing out in a high-pitched joy that made his
mother smile in sympathy.  She was ironing in the cool, open room
they had taken for kitchen, and looked out at the boisterous crowd
of youthful bacchantes, intoxicated with freedom and fresh air, with
a whimsical remembrance of her own happy childhood in County
Kerry.  At the same time, there ran through her mind almost
unconsciously, the steady and puzzled query as to the meaning of
the odd experience in Denny's room.
</p><p>Denny caught sight of his mother, passing to and fro, and came
running to the barn, his loving little heart eager to share his joy with
her.  "Oh, mother!" he cried, "We are having such a good time!  It's
like a fairy story, so pretty out there, and we're laughing&mdash;
laughing&mdash;"  He stopped, his child's vocabulary unable to cope with
the exultation that glowed in his eyes and shone from his rosy
cheeks.  As he stood, silent, Mary turned to the stove for a fresh
iron, and it was suddenly as though someone else was going on with
the story Danny could not tell.  The room was filled with the joyous
elation of a child, so exquisite, so complete, that Mary's eyes
    <pb entity="DSSR_000002643_0005" n="84"/>
moistened.  Her heart swelled with a strange softness.
</p><p>Denny spoke again.  "He's so glad,&mdash;he never had a good time
here before!"  Mary did not dare to turn around.  Of a sudden she
knew, and knowing, her mother soul yearned over the joy that now
seemed so pathetic to her.  She could almost hear the rapid beats of
a little heart fairly tired out in one of those bursts of delight in
joyous companionship that sometimes overwhelm little children.
When she finally turned back to her ironing board, Denny had
slipped away, but the joyous presence lingered a moment longer, as
though basking in her sympathy.  Then that too, vanished, and
Mary, sitting down, wept tears of mingled sorrow, sympathy and
comprehension.
</p><p>That evening she and Denny sat by the fire, kindled because of
the spring coolness that still lingered in the air.  The others were all
gone for a moonlight walk.  The mother and her little son sat in
silence, their Irish hearts very soft as they thought the same
thoughts.  It was quite still.  The faint flicker of the fire showed the
strong motherly hand resting on Denny's head, and occasionally
stroking the yellow curls softly, but no word was spoken.  They
were both waiting, with the Celtic sixth sense quiveringly alert.  All
at once Denny gave a soft little cry&mdash;of welcome, it seemed, and
Mary felt a timid presence standing in the dark not far from her.
She did not look toward it, nor turn away from the fire, but her hand
dropped to Denny's shoulder and gave him a little hug.  Denny rose
to his knees and put his arm around her waist.  "Oh mother, I love
you so!" he said, his child's voice quivering with emotion, "I love
you so!  You always understand!"
</p><p>"I love you, too, Denny," she answered, and then, choosing her
words very carefully, "I love all little childer,&mdash;<hi rend="italic">all!"</hi>  She
thought she heard a happy little sigh and went on, her arm around
Denny, "The more I have the more I love them, and if one was
unhappy or sorrowin' I'd love him the best of all."
</p><p>There was a moment's silence, in which the fire dropped
sleepily together and then Denny moved a little, as though to make
room for someone else at his mother's knee.  After that no word was
spoken, but in a brooding peace that filled Mary's heart, they sat
quite still, until the returning children broke in, laughing at them for
letting the fire go out.
</p><p>After this Mary often felt the shy, gentle presence, and never
without a glow at her mother's heart.  Once she asked herself why
she was not afraid, and then all her Celtic mysticism overwhelmed
the materialistic query.  That night, as she stepped into the
children's room, she felt unusually tender and rejoiced to feel in the
warm, quiet room a contented little fifth child, peacefully happy in
the new-found companionship.
</p><p>The summer slipped on,&mdash;a happy, busy, idle summer, and the
early apples in the orchard were almost ripe when Mary had a great
shock.  Their old neighbor of the big house dropped in with a bag-full of
gossip to turn over.  After discussing several mutual
acquaintances she said, "Do you remember my tellin' ye about the
little lad that used to live here, and had such a miserable, mopy time
of it?  Well, I had a letter from my cousin in New York, and he said
he seen him."
</p><p>Mary's amazed start and frightened gaze at her companion
passed unnoticed in the twilight.  The old woman went on.  "My
cousin has a foine place as ilivator-boy,&mdash;not but what he's grown up
and has been these many years,&mdash;in the office buildin' where th' old
man and his son has their offices, and he says he knew 'em the first
time he took 'em up.  The son, for all he's got some gray hairs and
looks as drawn-out as if he was fifty, looks just as he used to here,
and th' old man, well, ye'd know he'd niver change in a thousand
years."
</p><p>There was a little pause, in which Mary tried to compose the
confused and terrifying ideas that whirled through her head.  The
other spoke again, "It gives me a queer turn, somehow, to think of
his bein' alive,&mdash;the son, I mean,&mdash;because I'd always sort o'&mdash;"
</p><p>Mary broke in breathlessly, "Why, he <hi rend="italic">must</hi> be dead!"
</p><p>"There! that's just the way I feel about it.  My cousin says they
tell awful queer stories about him,&mdash;that he's got kind o' fits or
something,&mdash;times when he'll set an' stare in front of him and niver
know a word you say to him.  The office byes don't think he's quite
right.  I'm as sure as though the saints had told me that it's his queer
bringin' up that did it."
    <pb entity="DSSR_000002643_0006" n="85"/>
</p><p>Mary interrupted with an eager question.  "How do you mean,
&mdash;fits and spells?"
</p><p>"Oh, I dunno," said the other comfortably, preparing to leave.
"My cousin he niver seen him in one, and so I dunno.  The office
byes says it's like as though he wasn't there at all, although his eyes
is wide starin' open."
</p><p>As she shuffled down the gravel path the woman she had left
sank on the steps, an indefinite horror in her mind.  Denny came
softly over the grass, dangling two tiny trout from a twig.  He
looked tired, but very proud as he displayed them to his mother.
</p><p>"They're only little fellers," he said, dropping into the speech
of the country-side, "but they're the first I ever catched."  Then,
lowering his voice, and making sure no one was near, he added
confidentially, "It was the first time he'd ever been a-fishing, and he
thought it was such bully fun!"  Denny rarely spoke of his "pretend"
playmate, and then, only to his mother, whose understanding he
knew to be limitless.
</p><p>This time, however, Mary seized him by the shoulder and
asked in a queer, strained voice: "Denny, who is he?  How do we
know who he is?"  She was shivering in a terror of the unknown, her
ignorant mind inflamed with half-remembered, ghastly tales of
superstitious old women sitting over peat fires in County Kerry.
She caught Denny up and held him close, as though she would
protect him from the powers of evil.
</p><p>The child struggled a little in her grasp and then said, in a low
tone: "I thought you were sorry for all little, lonesome boys.  Do
you have to know who they are?"  Mary started.  "No; but, Denny,
you don't&mdash;"  She paused, aware in every finely attuned motherly
fiber of a grieved little presence at her knee.  "Denny, aren't ye ever
afraid, darlint?" she asked as if begging courage from her little son.
Denny answered soberly: "No, mother, it makes him so glad."  And
Mary, too, was no longer afraid.  But during the few weeks that they
stayed in the country she had occasional, quick, shivering doubts
that sent her out in a mad rush to see that Denny was safe, and when
they moved to town she felt an acknowledged relief.
</p><p>During the long hours, so curiously still, when the children
were all away at school, she often sat lost in a maze of surmises and
half explanations.  She had very little reasoning power&mdash;the warm-blooded,
Irish-woman, all mother&mdash;and most of her thinking was
done with her heart, which may have been the reason why she
finally came out of her doubt and confusion, little by little, and
arrived at a clear certainty.  With this glowing on her face, she took
the long walk out to the big house.  Her old friend looked up
surprised at a visitor in that lonely spot, and nodded drowsily as
Mary said she wished to go up to the room in the barn the youngest
children had used to get something they had left behind.
</p><p>She opened the door gently, stepped into the now so desolate
room and stood waiting.  Not for long.  In a moment she fell on her
knees, her arms outstretched, the tears running down her face, and
incoherent words forcing themselves between her sobs.  "Now I
know&mdash;poor darlint! now I know.  'Tis the child in ye that could
never pass away because it had never lived its life!  And to have me
suspicionin' ye!  And now to leave you alone again!  Can't you
come with&mdash;"  She stopped, sobbing violently, as she heard a forlorn
little sigh, and felt the grieved and desolate presence of an utterly
lonely child.  A moment later it vanished, and Mary, her face still
distorted with grief, was shutting the door with reluctant hands.
"Arrah!" she cried to herself, "it's like shutting in little Denny to
long days alone."
</p><p>The shadow rested on her broad, smooth face until the coming
of the next summer.  In the midst of the wildest romps of her
black-haired brood, the tears would come to her soft eyes and she would
catch up little Denny for a passionate embrace.  Her old crony,
sitting by the open window one day, observed one of these passing
clouds with some impatience.  "What's the matter with ye, Mary,
woman?" she demanded.  "Ye act like somebody that's lost a child
and can't help thinkin' of him in sorrow all the time."  A moment
later she added: "Speakin' of childer, did I tell ye I heard from my
cousin in New York the other day that th' old man's a grandfather?
The son's married, and they have got a baby&mdash;a boy.  My cousin says
the new father looks like another man&mdash;all the queerness gone out of
his eyes
    <pb entity="DSSR_000002643_0007" n="86"/>
like.  Sure I'm glad it's not th' old man that's to have
the bringin' up of the kid.  Wherever are ye goin' at this time of the
day?"  For Mary had snatched her shawl from a chair and was
already darting down the street.
</p><p>As she followed the long country road she talked half
inarticulately to herself.  "Oh, surely now&mdash;with a child of his
own&mdash;and a son&mdash;oh, Mother of Jesus! surely <hi rend="italic">now&mdash;!"</hi>  She did not
venture to formulate her hope more clearly even to herself.  She half
ran through the lower rooms and slipped rapidly up the steep stairs,
but at the door she hesitated, and finally fell to her knees and
murmured an Ave Maria, with her rosary at her lips, before she
ventured to enter.
</p><p>As she pushed open the door and went in she shivered a little,
but soon stood very still, tears of joy welling in her eyes.  It was as
she had hoped.  The bare, echoing room was quite, quite empty.

</p>

</div1>
</body>
</text>
</TEI.2>
