<?xml version="1.0"?>

<?dlps id="CanUgly"?>
<?dlps page-images="color" figure-images="yes"?>
<?dlps transcription="other"?>

<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/tei-p4/tei2.dtd" [
<!ENTITY % POSTKB "INCLUDE">
<!ENTITY % TEI.extensions.ent SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.ent">
<!ENTITY % TEI.extensions.dtd SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.dtd">
<!ENTITY % ISOpub SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/charent/iso-pub.ent"> %ISOpub;


<!ENTITY DSSR_000002644_0001 SYSTEM "000002644_0001" NDATA uvaHighRes>
<!ENTITY DSSR_000002644_0002 SYSTEM "000002644_0002" NDATA uvaHighRes>
<!ENTITY DSSR_000002644_0003 SYSTEM "000002644_0003" NDATA uvaHighRes>
<!ENTITY DSSR_000002644_0004 SYSTEM "000002644_0004" NDATA uvaHighRes>
<!ENTITY DSSR_000002644_0005 SYSTEM "000002644_0005" NDATA uvaHighRes>
]>
<TEI.2 id="CanUgly">
<teiHeader type="migrated" creator="Etext">
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title type="main">The Ugly Duckling</title>
<title type="sort">ugly duckling</title>
<author>Canfield, Dorothy</author>
<respStmt>
<resp>Creation of machine-readable version:</resp>
<name>Judy Boss</name>
<resp>Creation of digital images:</resp>
<name>Michele Ierardi</name>
<resp>Conversion to TEI.2-conformant markup:</resp>
<name>University of Virginia Library Electronic Text Center.</name>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt>
<extent>ca. <num type="kilobytes">22</num> kilobytes</extent>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>University of Virginia Library</publisher>
<pubPlace>Charlottesville, Virginia</pubPlace>
<idno type="ETC">CanUgly</idno>
<date value="1996">1996</date>
<availability status="public">
<p n="copyright">Copyright &#xa9; 1996 by the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia</p>
<p n="access">Publicly accessible</p>
</availability>
<idno type="uva-pid">uva-lib:476762</idno>
</publicationStmt>
<seriesStmt>
<title>University of Virginia Library, Text collection</title>
<idno type="uva-set">UVA-LIB-Text</idno>
</seriesStmt>
<notesStmt>
<note>
<p>These images were scanned from printouts of the microfilm.</p>
</note>
<note>
<p>Judy Boss has made the following changes: page 436, para. 7: its] it's; page 436, para. 8: talent.'] talent,"; page 436, para. 9: pretty] pretty,; page 438, para. 9: "It's] "'It's</p>
</note>
</notesStmt>
<sourceDesc>
<biblFull>
<titleStmt>
<title type="main">The Ugly Duckling</title>
<title level="j">American Illustrated Magazine</title>
<title type="sort">ugly duckling</title>
<author>Dorothy Canfield</author>
</titleStmt>
<editionStmt>
<p>First Edition</p>
</editionStmt>
<extent>pp. 435-439</extent>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>Colver Publishing House</publisher>
<pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
<date value="1906-02">February 1906</date>
<idno type="callNo">Print copy consulted: UVA Library call no. Micfilm S-147 reel 689.</idno>
</publicationStmt>
<notesStmt>
<note>
<p>
<hi rend="italic">American Illustrated Magazine</hi>, vol. 61, no. 4 (Feb. 1906).</p>
</note>
</notesStmt>
</biblFull>
</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc>
<encodingDesc>
<projectDesc>
<p>Prepared for the University of Virginia Library Electronic Text Center.</p>
</projectDesc>
<editorialDecl>
<p>All quotation marks retained as data.</p>
<p>All unambiguous end-of-line hyphens have been removed, and the trailing part of a word has been joined to the preceding line.</p>
<p>The images exist as archived TIFF images, one or more JPEG versions for general use, and thumbnail GIFs.</p>
<p>Keywords in the header are a local Electronic Text Center scheme to aid in establishing analytical groupings.</p>
</editorialDecl>
</encodingDesc>
<profileDesc>
<creation>
<date value="1906">1906</date>
</creation>
<langUsage>
<language id="eng" usage="main">English</language>
</langUsage>
<textClass>
<keywords>
<term>fiction; prose</term>
<term>Women Writers</term>
</keywords>
<keywords>
<term>illustration</term>
<term>256-shade greyscale, 400 dpi</term>
</keywords>
</textClass>
</profileDesc>
<revisionDesc>
<change>
<date value="1996-09">September 1996</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>corrector</resp>
<name>Michele Ierardi</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Added TEI header and TEI tags.</item>
</change>
<change>
<date value="2005-06">June 2005</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>corrector</resp>
<name>John Ivor Carlson</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Converted sgml to xml.</item>
</change>
<change>
<date value="2007-09">September 2007</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>Migration</resp>
<name>Ethan Gruber, University of Virginia Library</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Converted XML markup from TEI Lite to uva-dl-tei (TEI P4 with local customizations).</item>
</change>
<change>
<date value="2008-01">January 2008</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>Migration</resp>
<name>Greg Murray, University of Virginia Library</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Programmatically updated TEI header markup (but not header content) for minimal compliance with current QA requirements.</item>
</change>
<change>
<date value="2009-03">March 2009</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>Migration</resp>
<name>Scholarly Resources, University of Virginia Library</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Added and/or replaced the digital images accompanying the electronic text. Scanning of exterior and interior (ie. pages) of item was done only for items found in the University of Virginia Special Collections Library.</item>
</change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>
<text id="d1">

<body id="d2">
    <div1 type="story" id="d3">
        <pb entity="DSSR_000002644_0001" n="435"/>
<head><hi rend="bold">THE UGLY DUCKLING</hi>
<lb/>By Dorothy Canfield
<lb/>AUTHOR OF "THE PLAYMATE"
</head>
<p>
THE fire on the nursery hearth gave a little flicker and the sleepy
child opened his eyes as the story finished.  "&mdash;arching his neck and
looking down into the clear water the ugly duckling saw that he had
become a beautiful white swan, and all the sorrows he had suffered
while he was an ugly duckling vanished away and he was as happy
as sunshine and&mdash;"  The fire fell together with a soft purr and the
child was asleep.
</p><p>When the young mother came back, empty-armed from the
bedroom, she sank down before the fire and the occupant of the big
chair.  "Dear Mother-Aunt," she said, "how sweet to have you in my
own home.  Every day of life with my children is like a fresh
revelation of all you were to us in those days of childhood you
made so happy.  I took it then as unconsciously as the sunlight or
any other blessed thing, but now I know what sacrifices and never-ending
care it meant.  And after all&mdash;though that is so hard to
realize&mdash;we weren't your own children and you were giving up your
own life to us, day by day.  It is such a joy now to have you see me
trying to be to my little ones what you were to us&mdash;to have you hear
me telling them the lovely tales you told us.  I think my favorite is
the one I told to-night.  I can always hear your voice as I end it, and
if my children feel as happy over the joy of the swan as I used to&mdash;"
</p><p>The older woman laughed a little, and then sighed.  "I have
just seen the other ending to that story, and I don't know if I am glad
or sorry&mdash;if I dare be sad!  I think it would be wrong to grieve&mdash;and
yet&mdash;"
</p><p>"What can you mean?" asked the niece.  "How can there be
any story in the family at Boston that you have not known before?"
</p><p>"It wasn't there.  It was in West Ripley."
</p><p>The niece sat up with arched eyebrows of question.
</p><p>"You never even heard of West Ripley, did you?  Yet that was
the chapter in my life before I came to the long, dear story of your
childhood&mdash;yours and all the rest&mdash;after your mother's death."
</p><p>"Oh!" cried the other, "is there a story you never told me?
Auntie dear, pretend I am your little girl again, and tell me a new
story."
</p><p>The white-haired woman stroked the sunny head at her knee.
"This is a tale for a grown woman, dear, not for a child, and perhaps
you can help me decide what its meaning is.  It's all a part of the
only little scrap of life of my very own I ever had.
</p><p>"I was twenty-five before they let me go away from Boston
and the sweet but narrow bonds of our life there.  They never could
understand my wanting to&mdash;girls didn't thirty years ago as they do
now&mdash;and they were disappointed that I didn't marry.  Father blamed
my music&mdash;'the girl's in love with her piano instead of a decent
marrying man,' he used to say; and I imagine he was right.  I had a
horror of decent marrying people and all that they meant, and was
always living in a fancy world where everyone was gay for the mere
joy of all the lovely things there are.  I so loved my music I seemed
to need no other friend and it was like a bird's swoop out of an open
window into the sunlight, when I found myself at West Ripley, free
from all the round of unending home duties and the endless chain of
aunts and uncles and cousins who were so kind but so alien.
</p><p>"It is true I had my music pupils,&mdash;what seemed to me such a
flight into freedom, was in reality only going up to a little mountain
town to teach music&mdash;but they
    <pb entity="DSSR_000002644_0002" n="436"/>
and all the rest were frankly
strangers to me, and could not come knocking at the door of my real
life with the kindly brutality of the people in Boston, presuming on
a long but shallow acquaintance.  So I lived my life and dreamed
my dreams, and wrote a few songs out of the many I heard in my
new and peaceful solitude and liberty."
</p><p>She fell to musing, eyes on the fire, till her niece said: "Why,
auntie I never heard of all this before&mdash;and how is your ugly
duckling in it?"
</p><p>"I stopped in West Ripley on the way here from Boston, the
first time I have been back.  It brought all that life up with such
startling clearness.  I don't think I ever spoke of it to you; it was one
of the things I put aside.
</p><p>"The ugly duckling was one of my pupils, a big ungainly boy
of seventeen, his parent's despair and bewilderment, and my joy.  I
remember the first time I heard him play&mdash;and the second!  His
mother, kindly, capable New England housewife asked me to tea
and Dan was there, all big dark eyes and awkward hands and feet.
They talked about him and what a problem he was with the frank
cruelty of devoted families.
</p><p>"'He's bright enough, if he'd apply himself,' said the father, 'and
you'd think any boy with his prospects in life would take an interest
in his studies.'
</p><p>"'Yes,' explained the mother, 'my husband's business is the best
in town and we've always looked forward so to having Dan (he's the
only child we have living) take his place in the factory.  But we
want him educated&mdash;I'd like to have him go to the business college
here, and learn just how to keep accounts and all, but he's so crazy
over music he can't put his mind on anything else.  Wherever he got
that kink we can't imagine.  There never has been anybody
<hi rend="italic">queer</hi> in the family since I can remember.'
</p><p>"I looked over at Dan with a sudden interest.  I knew what that
sort of talk meant.  He was crumbling his bread with a sullen flush
on his face, and in pity I tried to turn the conversation.
</p><p>"After tea we went into the front room, where Dan's piano
stood.  Mr. Marvin looked at it with great disapproval.  'I got that for
Dan when he was a little fellow.  His mother wanted to have
accomplishments, but I declare, I think it's bewitched him.'
</p><p>"I asked eagerly to have Dan play; it sounded as though he
were a misunderstood genius.  His mother said, 'yes, of course he
would play.  Play the "Maiden's Prayer" for the lady.'  Dan protested
hopelessly but ended by sitting down and banging through that old
show piece with the irritating monotony of a hand organ.  I smiled
at the prompt disappearance of the little romance I had begun to
weave about him,&mdash;'Another village talent,' I thought amusedly.
</p><p>"In spite of themselves the parents looked pleased as he
finished.  'It sounds real pretty, don't it, mother?' said Mr. Marvin
with a shamefaced pride, and Mrs. Marvin, 'Sometimes I think Dan
does play real good.'
</p><p>"I was asked to play, and sure of their comfortable denseness, I
threw my whole soul into the 'Sonata Appassionata.'  They did not
ask me to play again, and could only say, with a bewildered
politeness, that 'It must have taken you a long time to learn to play
such a hard piece.'  Dan had disappeared, and when I started home
in the pleasant summer twilight he was nowhere to be found to bid
me good-night.  His father was irritated, and said sharply: 'He's got
to stop his foolishness and tend to his work at school.  I know he
has a Latin lesson to get to-night.'
</p><p>"As I went through a little clump of young pines near the
house where I was living, I was startled by hurrying footsteps
behind me.  Dan was there, his long, thin face pale in the starlight
and distorted with some strong feeling.  'Oh,' he cried, carried out of
his shy hesitancy, 'I didn't think anybody could play like that.  How
can you look so like people!  It's like being an angel to be able to do
that!  And you <hi rend="italic">mustn't</hi> think I am like what I was to-night,&mdash;I
never saw anybody before I wanted to play for as I do for myself&mdash;how
<hi rend="italic">could</hi> I know till you played?  Can't I come now and
show you on your piano?  I can't bear to have you sleep thinking I
am like that&mdash;when you are the only one I ever saw who&mdash;oh,
<hi rend="italic">please</hi> let me play for you!'
</p><p>"When we were inside the house he hurried to the piano and
began the 'Spring Song.'  I sat transfixed with astonishment and an
odd pain, for I felt as though
    <pb entity="DSSR_000002644_0003" n="437"/>
a powerful intruder had
pushed his way into my own domain.  And yet he could be no
intruder&mdash;this joyful apparition of youth and ecstacy, who sat
uncovering to me the hidden sweet things of his heart.  When he
had finished he whirled about, still glowing with the fire of his
music, but was suddenly smitten dumb with his old awkward
embarrassment, a crimson shame at his own boldness flaming in his
cheeks, and a sudden doubt of himself quivering in his sensitive
mouth.  I am always proud when I think I had the generosity to
welcome him to his own.  'Dan,' I said, 'you are one of the chosen.
Never let anything come between you and your music.  It is your
kingdom.'
</p><p>"The boy looked at me for a moment in silence.  Then
suddenly his face twisted like a child's and he broke into loud sobs.
He rushed out of the house as rapidly as he had rushed in, and
following him to the door, I heard the sound of weeping from the
dark group of silent pine trees.
</p><p>"After that there was a long time when I could never catch
sight of him, until one day his mother came in with him to ask me to
give him lessons.  'We think he plays plenty good enough a'ready,'
she said cheerfully, 'but he's promised to study real hard and
graduate with his class if his father will let him take lessons of you.
He never liked that other teacher we had here.'  I agreed, and Dan
and I were left alone together&mdash;the boy all blushes and shamefaced
embarrassment in speaking of his art.
</p><p>"It was only after many months of work together that he came
to trust me with his half-formed aspirations and ideals, though I
lavished on the big rustic lad every atom of tact and sympathy I had.
It was not that he was hard to lead.  On the contrary, he had that
curious plastic yielding to circumstances so often accompanying the
lyric gift, and once he told me that just before I came he had been
on the point of giving up his music altogether.  I exclaimed in horror
at this, and he explained.  'Father and mother were so much
disappointed over me, and the minister came to talk to me about
what was right to them, and my Aunt Jane told me there were other
ways of going wrong and breaking your folk's hearts than by getting
drunk, and&mdash;'
</p><p>"I flamed at this with missionary fervor.  It was like a soul to
be saved.  'Dan!' I cried.  'Don't listen to them,&mdash;they don't know
what a precious,&mdash;what an inestimable, what a sacred treasure you
have.  It is a holy gift from Heaven.  They are like blind people,&mdash;trust
me who can see!'
</p><p>"We were under the pine trees that day, it was in early spring,
and Dan was lying on his back on the brown needles.  The tears
came into his eyes as I spoke, and he said fervently: 'It's like being
let out of prison to hear you say that.  I want to do what's right, and
it nearly kills me to be made to think it's wrong to go on with my
music.'
</p><p>"'Never think so again, Dan,' I cried with youthful sureness of
my convictions.
</p><p>"He shook his head uncertainly.  'When I am with you I don't,
but at home&mdash;' he paused, 'I'm all they have got&mdash;'
</p><p>"I knew the way to exorcise this demon of a New England
conscience, and took him into the house to the piano, where he was
soon playing Beethoven with a premature power and vigor that
surprised me.  I had heard all the great pianists of that day and I had
never seen one who could move me more, one who could equal the
occasional felicities of expression which were absolutely ravishing
in Dan's playing.  At times, through the roughness of his technic,
there pierced a poignant beauty that used to leave me quite
breathless.  I have heard all the great artists since then, but a certain
throbbing spontaneity which was his, and which recreated the music
he played, they all lack.
</p><p>"The scene under the pines came back to me with a pang of
compunction the next fall when his mother came to see me, her face
swollen with weeping, to ask me to use my influence with Dan in
turning him to his duty.  'He'll kill his father yet!' she sobbed.  'My
husband is just heart-broken over his shiftlessness&mdash;the only child
we have, and we've done everything in the world for him!  To think
a son of mine should be so lacking in a sense of duty!  He's just told
his father that he won't go into the factory at all&mdash;and I thought
Daniel would have a stroke!  I'm going to get the minister to talk to
him again, and I thought if you would&mdash;'  She hurried away, her face
buried in her handkerchief, leaving me with the first
    <pb entity="DSSR_000002644_0004" n="438"/>
hesitation in my youthful, one-sided view of life.  For a moment I
blamed myself for fostering rebellion in Dan, and I almost decided
to withdraw altogether from the responsibility of shaping his life,
but later I felt again that, if I stood aloof, I would be leaving an
exquisite and fragile flower to be ruthlessly thrust under the sod by
a plow.
</p><p>"Although I had decided, I had no opportunity to act on my
decision, for that very evening came the letter from your father,
telling of your mother's death, and begging me, his only sister, with
no family of her own, to come to his desolate house."
</p><p>The younger woman caught her hand and kissed it.  "I know
your side of the story from that moment, dearest&mdash;absorbing care, so
loving and so complete that father's children never knew they had
lost a mother.  Did you see your boy again before you left?"
</p><p>"Yes, he played for me once, something from a Wagner opera,
I had somehow secured, though nobody knew him then.  How he
did play that!  Ah, what would he have said to modern music?"
</p><p>There was a pause, and then the niece said: "You speak as
though he were dead.  Is he?"
</p><p>"No&mdash;and yes.  I saw him in West Ripley last week&mdash;the first
time since those days.  I had not even heard of him, I was so busy
those first years with my new and beautiful duty of caring for you
little ones.  I only heard that his father died soon after I left, but that
was all till I saw him!"
</p><p>"What is he like now, Auntie?"
</p><p>"Old and fat and bald.  I felt positively sick when I learned that
the pallid, fat old man with puffy hands who took up the collection
in church was all that was left of my joyous, youthful genius,
singing his heart away at the piano.
</p><p>"He is a pillar of the church, the prominent citizen of West
Ripley, a member of the State Senate.  His mother&mdash;still a vigorous
old lady&mdash;told me with thankful and remorseful tears in her eyes
how she had misjudged Daniel.  'I used to think he might go wrong
or queer, when he was a boy.  Maybe you remember how odd he
was, but the minister and I kept working with him, and praying for
him, and then when his father died and he had me to take care of
and the factory to run he seemed to sober down.  He worked like a
madman for three or four years, and then once he told me he was
trying to make enough to stop and learn some more music.  That
upset me so as I can't <hi rend="italic">say</hi>.  It just seemed to me as though I
couldn't <hi rend="italic">bear</hi> it, when I'd thought he was all cured of that
nonsense.  And I thought anyway 'twas time for him to be settling
down with a family of his own, and so I sort o' engineered him
toward my cousin's step-daughter.  She was an awful pretty girl and
dead in love with Dan.  After they were married, he did really and
truly sober down and I've never heard him say a word about music
since.
</p><p>"'It's queer, he swung right t'other way and never would touch
the piano, not even to play hymns of a Sunday evening, as we'd like
to have him.  He won't stay in the room where one of his girls is
practisin'&mdash;seems to despise it now as much as he used to love it.
Unreasonable, ain't it?  She's a real, practical, sensible woman&mdash;his
wife is&mdash;and anyway there's nothing so settling for a young man as
being married and having a family.  He's been the best son and
husband and father you can think of&mdash;he's a good man, Daniel is, if
he is my son.'
</p><p>"She told me all this while we were waiting for dinner in Dan's
house.  A little later his rosy, buxom daughters came in, talking
animatedly of a church fair.  Dan was late, through some extra
business at the factory and had to hurry through his dinner.
</p><p>"Afterwards, old Mrs. Marvin asked me to play, and with all
my soul torn between pity and sorrow and content, I played the
'Sonata Appassionata.'  When I finished I looked at Dan.  He was
paler than usual and the big pouches under his eyes hung down
heavily, but for one instant he looked at me with the eyes of the boy
under the pine trees&mdash;eyes filled with tears.  And then it was all
over&mdash;like the last flicker of a dying candle.  He puffed his big black
cigar, played with his youngest daughter who sat on his knee,
repelled good-naturedly the importunate demands of the others for
his purse, and looked at me and the world with the keen and shallow
eyes of the successful business man.  The ugly duckling had
developed into no useless swan, but had satisfied the reasonable and
    <pb entity="DSSR_000002644_0005"  n="439"/>
loving demands of the duck yard.  How could I do
anything but sorrow?  How dared I do anything but rejoice?"
</p><p>Her niece rose to her knees and threw her arms about the older
woman.  "You've been telling me two stories," she cried, "yours as
well as your boy's.  Dear Mother-Aunt, I never knew before that
you, too, were an ugly duckling who was not allowed to develop
into a swan!  I never knew what you were sacrificing for all the
loving service that made our childhood so sweet.  But dearest, I
cannot regret it&mdash;there is no life but that for you, the best life can
give you&mdash;love in a home, and children.  Why, when I think of my
own children!" her face all alight with a soft fervor of domesticity,
"would I give them up for all the music in the world.  And think
how we love you!  You may not have grown to be a beautiful swan,
but you have grown to be something better&mdash;to be an angel!"
</p><p>Her aunt smiled at her affectionately, "you are right dear,&mdash;love
is best&mdash;of course you are right,&mdash;and yet&mdash;"

</p>

</div1>
</body>
</text>
</TEI.2>
