<?xml version="1.0"?>

<?dlps id="DunEdou"?>
<?dlps page-images="color" figure-images="no"?>
<?dlps transcription="other"?>

<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/tei-p4/tei2.dtd" [
<!ENTITY % POSTKB "INCLUDE">
<!ENTITY % TEI.extensions.ent SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.ent">
<!ENTITY % TEI.extensions.dtd SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.dtd">
<!ENTITY % ISOlat1 SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/charent/iso-lat1.ent"> %ISOlat1;
<!ENTITY % ISOpub SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/charent/iso-pub.ent"> %ISOpub;


<!ENTITY DSSR_000002584_0001 SYSTEM "000002584_0001" NDATA uvaHighRes>
<!ENTITY DSSR_000002584_0002 SYSTEM "000002584_0002" NDATA uvaHighRes>
<!ENTITY DSSR_000002584_0003 SYSTEM "000002584_0003" NDATA uvaHighRes>
<!ENTITY DSSR_000002584_0004 SYSTEM "000002584_0004" NDATA uvaHighRes>
<!ENTITY DSSR_000002584_0005 SYSTEM "000002584_0005" NDATA uvaHighRes>
<!ENTITY DSSR_000002584_0006 SYSTEM "000002584_0006" NDATA uvaHighRes>
<!ENTITY DSSR_000002584_0007 SYSTEM "000002584_0007" NDATA uvaHighRes>
]>
<TEI.2 id="DunEdou">
    <teiHeader creator="Etext" type="migrated">
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title type="main">Edouard</title>
                <title type="sort">edouard</title>
                <author>Dunbar, Alice</author>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Creation of machine-readable version:</resp>
                    <name>Judy Boss</name>
                    <resp>Creation of digital images:</resp>
                    <name>Stephen Ramsay, Electronic Text Center</name>
                    <resp>Conversion to TEI.2-conformant markup:</resp>
                    <name>University of Virginia Library Electronic Text Center.</name>
                </respStmt>
            </titleStmt>
            <extent>ca. <num type="kilobytes">23</num> kilobytes</extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>University of Virginia Library</publisher>
                <pubPlace>Charlottesville, Virginia</pubPlace>
                <idno type="ETC">DunEdou</idno>
                <date value="1996">1996</date>
                <availability status="public">
                    <p n="copyright">Copyright &#xa9; 1996 by the Rector and Visitors of the
                        University of Virginia</p>
                    <p n="access">Publicly accessible</p>
                </availability>
                <idno type="uva-pid">uva-lib:476915</idno>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title>University of Virginia Library, Text collection</title>
                <idno type="uva-set">UVA-LIB-Text</idno>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull>
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title type="main">Edouard</title>
                        <title level="j">The Southern Workman</title>
                        <title type="sort">edouard</title>
                        <author>Alice Dunbar</author>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <extent>pp. 358-364</extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Hampton Institute</publisher>
                        <pubPlace>Hampton, VA</pubPlace>
                        <date value="1900-06">June 1900</date>
                        <idno type="callNo">Print copy consulted: Alderman Library LC2701 .S7</idno>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <notesStmt>
                        <note>
                            <p>Southern Workman, Vol. 29, No. 6, June 1900.</p>
                        </note>
                        <note>
                            <p>The following emendations were made to the text by Judy Boss:</p>
                            <list type="simple">
                                <item>p. 360, para. 1 -villas, to to ] villas, to;</item>
                                <item>p. 360, para. 8 -manner of ] of manner;</item>
                                <item>p. 362, para. 4 -not whether. ] not whither.;</item>
                                <item>p. 362, para. 5 -came a ] came to a;</item>
                                <item>p. 362, para. 6 -overhead ] overhead.;</item>
                                <item>p. 363, para. 1 -hand. .The ] hand. The;</item>
                                <item>p. 363, para. 3 -his his ] hid his.</item>
                            </list>
                        </note>
                    </notesStmt>
                </biblFull>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>Prepared for the University of Virginia Library Electronic Text Center.</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <p>All quotation marks retained as data.</p>
                <p>All unambiguous end-of-line hyphens have been removed, and the trailing part of a
                    word has been joined to the preceding line.</p>
                <p>The images exist as archived TIFF images, one or more JPEG versions for general
                    use, and thumbnail GIFs.</p>
                <p>Keywords in the header are a local Electronic Text Center scheme to aid in
                    establishing analytical groupings.</p>
            </editorialDecl>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <creation>
                <date value="1911">1911</date>
            </creation>
            <langUsage>
                <language id="eng" usage="main">English</language>
            </langUsage>
            <textClass>
                <keywords>
                    <term>fiction; prose</term>
                    <term>Women Writers</term>
                    <term>Young Readers</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords>
                    <term type="format">24-bit color; 400 dpi</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change>
                <date value="1996-10">October 1996</date>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>corrector</resp>
                    <name>Stephen Ramsay, Electronic Text Center</name>
                </respStmt>
                <item>Added TEI header and tags.</item>
            </change>
            <change>
                <date value="2005-07">July 2005</date>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Corrector</resp>
                    <name>John Ivor Carlson</name>
                </respStmt>
                <item>Converted SGML to XML. Fixed tagging.</item>
            </change>
            <change>
                <date value="2007-09">September 2007</date>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Migration</resp>
                    <name>Ethan Gruber, University of Virginia Library</name>
                </respStmt>
                <item>Converted XML markup from TEI Lite to uva-dl-tei (TEI P4 with local
                    customizations).</item>
            </change>
            <change>
                <date value="2008-01">January 2008</date>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Migration</resp>
                    <name>Greg Murray, University of Virginia Library</name>
                </respStmt>
                <item>Programmatically updated TEI header markup (but not header content) for
                    minimal compliance with current QA requirements.</item>
            </change>
<change>
<date value="2009-03">March 2009</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>Migration</resp>
<name>Scholarly Resources, University of Virginia Library</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Added and/or replaced the digital images accompanying the electronic text. Scanning of exterior and interior (ie. pages) of item was done only for items found in the University of Virginia Special Collections Library.</item>
</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text id="d1">

        <body id="d2">



            <div1 id="d3" type="story">
                <pb entity="DSSR_000002584_0001"/>
                <head>Edouard<lb/> ALICE DUNBAR</head>

                <p>PERE BOUTIN came down the sandy, pine-bordered walk with a knotted brow and a
                    gait that grew slower and slower. He was perplexed and his forehead knitted more
                    and more in a comical assumption of dignity. P&egrave;re Boutin thought that
                    he was dignified, but when one weighs two hundred pounds, and is short and rolls
                    in one's gait, is it reasonable to expect that the world will be impressed by
                    one's magnificence? </p>
                <p>Edouard was tall and lean and brown with a strength of muscle and length of limb
                    a little unusual in a boy still in his teens. He had followed the plow and rowed
                    his pirogue down the smooth river waters, and swung the axe into the fragrant,
                    resinous trees in the woods, until his physique was as that of a man's. A
                    sculptor would have posed him for a god, but no one knew about sculpture or art
                    in St. Tammany Parish, and the river's reflection meant nothing to Edouard's
                    eyes, accustomed to all the lavish beauty of a semi-tropical climate. </p>
                <p>He lived on the border of the Tchefuncta River in a wee house, far away from the
                    sleepy Covington City, which, after all, is only a town, vague and lonely and
                    forgotten. The small house leaned to one side, and rested in a caressing way
                    against a great mud chimney, as if seeking support in its old age. There was a
                    flower garden in front of it, with prim hollyhocks and larkspurs and crimson
                    poppies waving against a whitewashed picket fence. A crape myrtle stood in one
                    corner of the garden and a magnolia in the other. Edouard had been wont to
                    regard the latter with a sort of mystic awe. It had been planted by his
                    grandmother in her girlhood days, and when she had died, almost her last charge
                    had been about her favorite tree. He remembered how a great creamy blossom had
                    lain on her still breast on that awful, funereal day, and how a solemn
                    pilgrimage was made to the churchyard every spring to lay the first fragrant
                    bloom across her grave. </p>
                <p>"Ah, mon fils," began P&egrave;re Boutin, rubbing the wet red kerchief across
                    his face again, "but I have bad news fo' you." </p>
                <p>Edouard straightened his back and rested on his hoe. He was weeding out his
                    garden, not the one of poppies and hollyhocks and larkspurs, but the larger one
                    which kept the table supplied. </p>
                <p>"What?" he asked a little abruptly. </p>
                <p>"I have jus' been down to see you' Uncle Aristide, an' he t'inks to take you wid
                    him nex' week to the city, an' let you learn one trade." </p>
                <p>Edouard stood staring at his father with uncomprehending eyes. What could he
                    mean? To go away from the little brown house had <pb
                        entity="DSSR_000002584_0002" n="359"/> been a dream of
                    his for so long a time that it had become a part of his nature. But he had never
                    spoken it aloud. He had hidden it deep down in his heart, half ashamed, half
                    afraid of his treason against home. </p>
                <p>P&egrave;re Boutin mopped his face again, and raised his voice irritably. </p>
                <p>"Fo' w'y you stan' an' look at me lak dat? Cannot you understan'? You mus' go to
                    New Orleans to wo'k. We are po', an' you mus' learn one trade." </p>
                <p>"Oui, mon p&egrave;re," replied Edouard. He was slowly turning over the earth
                    with his hoe and trying to beat down the cries of joy that clamored for voice.
                    "I weel go w'enever Uncle Aristide wishes." </p>
                <p>It was an exciting time in the Boutin household, these days before Edouard's
                    leaving. People did not go away much in that district. M&egrave;re Boutin
                    had not gone to the city since that prehistoric time when she and the
                    P&egrave;re, but newly wed, had gone to see the Mardi Gras for a honeymoon
                    tour. The memory of that giddy time had served for a family legend ever since;
                    and little sister Jeanne had held her head above some other children in the
                    parish school because her maman had been to the city and could tell about the
                    Mardi Gras. </p>
                <p>"You mus' be ver' careful, mon fils," said M&egrave;re Boutin tearfully, for
                    the hundredth time, as she wiped her eyes on the clothes she was mending and
                    making for him. </p>
                <p>"I weel, ma m&egrave;re," Edouard would reply tenderly. He was still half
                    dazed at his good fortune, and knew but little of what went on about him. The
                    M&egrave;re Boutin would rock to and fro, her ample form shaking ponderously
                    in her grief. </p>
                <p>The day came at last, and M&egrave;re and P&egrave;re and sister Jeanne
                    were down at the bayou's edge to see Uncle Aristide's boat sail off with their
                    idol. Edouard was brave, and waved cheerily as they cast anchor and sailed
                    slowly down the lazy stream. He choked down a hard, salt something in his throat
                    as he saw M&egrave;re Boutin fall in her husband's arms, and Jeanne stoop
                    suspiciously low to pat Uno's head. The group vanished in a queer mist as he
                    stood gazing and swallowing that insistent something. Then a low hanging
                    oak-branch, laden with soft, gray moss that brushed his face, brought him back
                    to earth, and life had begun for Edouard. </p>
                <p>That was a wonderful journey. The quaint gray schooner, laden to the water's edge
                    with fragrant pine wood cut in the short lengths that housewives love for
                    kindling, sailed slowly down the shady bayou. Save when Uncle Aristide, who was
                    a gruff man with a child's heart, called him to do some task, Edouard lay on the
                    deck gazing into the water and wondering of the world he was soon to see. It was
                    full of dangers and temptations and disappointments, M&egrave;re Boutin had
                    said, and M&egrave;re Boutin knew, for had she not spent two whole weeks in
                    the city once? But Edouard was sure all would be well with him, for he was going
                    to work hard and go to mass every Sunday. <pb entity="DSSR_000002584_0003" n="360"/>
                </p>
                <p>Then the boat had reached the great blue waters of Lake Pontchartrain, and they
                    were skimming out on foam-crested waves, away from the sunset which glowed red
                    and glorious about them. The next morning, they had crawled into the Old Basin,
                    and were at rest up near the Rue Rampart. Edouard had watched with ever-widening
                    eyes, the transition from the Bayou St. John and its quaint villas, to the
                    artificial, brick-lined canal with its business blocks and old-fashioned
                    warehouses and grim draw-bridges, which opened grudgingly to let them pass with
                    a score of other lake craft, while the foot-passengers fumed at the delay, and
                    the car-drivers bantered each other from opposite sides. His head whirled at the
                    crowding of craft and the great houses, and the stir of the water side. He would
                    have paused and have taken it all in slowly, but that Uncle Aristide had him by
                    the arm, and was gruffly bidding him follow. </p>
                <p>He was to learn a trade. That was essentially the proper thing to do, and no
                    self-respecting young Creole would deem his life a success without such an
                    equipment. And Edouard was to learn to be a cigar maker, which is a good thing
                    to know, after all, since the world thinks it must have its cigars. The
                    head-man, to whom, all trembling and fear-shaken, came Edouard with Uncle
                    Aristide, was a small man, whose wrinkles set upon his parchment face like a
                    suit of ill-fitting clothes. </p>
                <p>"You' Uncle Aristide is a good man," he said by way of greeting. </p>
                <p>Edouard drew closer to his complimented relative and murmured an inarticulate
                    reply. </p>
                <p>"You weel mek a fine cigar-maker," continued the little man, musingly peering at
                    Edouard's hands. </p>
                <p>Edouard was embarrassed at this turn of compliments and looked to his uncle for
                    help. But Uncle Aristide was contemplating a pile of tobacco at the farther end
                    of the room. A sudden homesick awe had taken possession of the boy. </p>
                <p>"Ah," cried the cigar maker with sudden and startling enthusiasm. "Come, we weel
                    talk together. I have wo'k fo' you." </p>
                <p>It may have been that Edouard was homesick and heartsick too, in those first
                    weeks; but there was much to do and more to see. All day it was the shop, and in
                    the evenings back to Uncle Aristide's little home on Treme Street, where was
                    Tante Pauline, and petite Cousin Zora, who was such a tease. Then on Sundays, to
                    the Cathedral to mass, and long exploring tours through the wonderful city. So
                    Edouard's letters home were marvels to Jeanne; and M&egrave;re Boutin rocked
                    herself to and fro in her chair, and wondered to P&egrave;re how the city
                    had outgrown her memory. </p>
                <p>But of Emile Edouard said nothing. Emile was a fellow-worker in the shop. Emile
                    was light and graceful and dapper, and his ease and polish of manner made
                    Edouard blush more than once because he despaired to himself of ever being more
                    than a foolish country "Cajan." <pb entity="DSSR_000002584_0004" n="361"/> Edouard adored Emile as a superior
                    being, and his days and nights were given up many times in striving to emulate
                    this little Chesterfield. Emile would take him about and show him many things,
                    and Edouard humbly thanked him, and was grateful in his way for the contact. </p>
                <p>It was one day after the noon hour that he came into the shop breathlessly, for
                    he was late; and hanging up his coat, would have hastened to his bench. But
                    Frank Shelton, a great burly man, with a cruel underjaw, held him firmly back by
                    the arm. </p>
                <p>"Here he is, fellows," he growled. </p>
                <p>Edouard wrenched his arm free, and stood still with blazing eyes. </p>
                <p>"Fo' w'y&mdash;you stop now," he panted. "You git you' han's off me." </p>
                <p>"He's game, yes," remarked Rene, fondling a forbidden cigarette. </p>
                <p>"What's the matter?" asked Mr. Laporte, the wrinkled owner, hastening to the
                    group. </p>
                <p>"Oh, nothin' much," drawled Shelton, "only this young fellow's got away with my
                    watch." He spoke slowly and distinctly, and every word cut into Edouard's mind,
                    searing as it went. He gasped as the full import of it came to him. </p>
                <p>"Oh, but&mdash;but&mdash;oh, Mistare Laporte, you know I could not." He
                    was pleading to Mr. Laporte, but the little man looked hard at his
                    shame-reddened face, and twiddled his fingers with nervous haste. Edouard looked
                    wildly around the circle of grim men for one kindly glance, but he met only
                    lowering brows and unpitying looks bent upon him. </p>
                <p>"He took it," continued Shelton, "there's no doubt of that. He was seen rummaging
                    in my coat, and then he went out, and he's been down to Lowenstein's. You know
                    who that is?" </p>
                <p>There was a hard laugh from the men. There were some who had been to the
                    pawnbroker's on Orleans Street, and all knew Lowenstein's sign. </p>
                <p>"Ah," said the little Laporte, and he wrinkled his face more at Edouard. </p>
                <p>"But&mdash;but, I thought you' coat was mine. It was on my peg," cried
                    Edouard desperately, "an'&mdash;an'&mdash;I was only looking in the
                    windows at a guitar." </p>
                <p>The men laughed again, and Edouard turned helplessly to Emile. But he stood among
                    the rest, and there was a cold, supercilious smile on his face. </p>
                <p>"Where's the police?" queried one. </p>
                <p>"Oh, never min'," said Shelton. Something in the boy's pitiful face had touched
                    something within him, and he felt a momentary qualm of suspicion that he was not
                    guilty. "I won't arrest him," he growled, ashamed of his own weakness, "but I'd
                    like to kick him." </p>
                <p>"Where's the money he got?" cried Ren&eacute;. So they searched <pb
                    entity="DSSR_000002584_0005" n="362"/>
                    Edouard but there was no money to be found. </p>
                <p>"He mus' go, he mus' go," muttered Mr. Laporte, and he went his way nodding his
                    head. It was very annoying to stop work in this way, and the Uncle Aristide was
                    such a good man, too. </p>
                <p>Edouard's eyes were full of tears, and he went blindly to the row of pegs where
                    the men hung their coats. He took his own down and held it in his hand, and then
                    put it down for a minute while he searched for his lunch pail. Then, still
                    blinded and unseeing what he took, he picked up a coat, and putting it on,
                    turned from the shop with down-dropped head and a blazing anger and shame fast
                    growing in his face. In vain he sought to meet Emile's eye for a farewell
                    glance, but Emile's head was studiously averted, and Edouard went out the door
                    followed by a grim silence that was more cruel than hoots or jeers could have
                    been. </p>
                <p>Once out in the air, he gave himself up to bitterness. He had been wrongfully
                    accused, but evidence was against him, and the shame was as great as though he
                    were guilty. He felt that he could not meet Tante Pauline's gaze nor Zora's
                    laughter with this burden still upon him. The thought of M&egrave;re Boutin
                    and the brown house on the river cut still deeper, and involuntarily he
                    quickened his steps as he struck out in a direction which led far away from
                    Treme Street. They had called him a thief when he was striving his best to be
                    honest. He would go out and live to himself for there was no place for thieves
                    at his Uncle Aristide's. </p>
                <p>He plunged his hands deeply in his pockets and trudged rapidly along, he knew not
                    whither. The people in the streets looked curiously into his set face and
                    blazing eyes, and made way for him. He walked blindly, caring for nothing save
                    to get away from the scene of his humiliation, until he came to Tulane Avenue
                    across Canal Street. It was all unfamiliar ground to him, and he paused for an
                    instant to read the inscription on the gate of the Charity Hospital. Then he saw
                    the sewer-digging machine, and stood still to laugh. </p>
                <p>It was a queer thing to him, that sewer-digger. This was in the days when such
                    work was only an experiment, and it was all very clumsy and awkward. Such an
                    ungraceful iron work over the great open trench, and overhead, huge iron baskets
                    that slid along over their track to the puffing and wheezing of the machine,
                    until they came to a certain point, when they would tilt and empty their
                    hundreds of pounds of earth and mud and slime. Then they would glide back to the
                    starting point, there to be filled again. </p>
                <p>Edouard drew nearer to the machine work to watch the elaborate system of pulleys
                    and wheels, and so near did he stand that he could not notice how dangerously
                    close he was to the open trench and the heavy swinging baskets overhead. Two
                    little street gamins were playing near him. They laughed and pelted each other
                    with the mud and sand which they found. The smaller one shouted a triumphant
                    challenge to his playmate, stumbled, screamed, and was in the trench. <pb
                        entity="DSSR_000002584_0006" n="363"/>
                </p>
                <p>Edouard dropped on his knees and peered in after him. It was not deep, and the
                    little chap stood only waist high in muddy water, a good arm's length away from
                    Edouard. He was about to step in and hand the boy out to the street, when the
                    warning chug-chug and creak of machinery caused him to look up quickly. The
                    great iron basket with its mass of mud and slime was gliding overhead and was
                    pointed directly for the spot where the child stood sobbing. In a minute, it
                    would pour out its bulk, and woe to the one who stood beneath its force. The
                    engine was too far away to shout a warning to the men in charge, and the basket
                    too near for the stopping of the engine to have done any good. Its momentum
                    would have carried it on. Little as he knew of mechanics, Edouard realized all
                    this in a quick, intuitive flash. He threw himself flat on the ground, and
                    seizing the sides of the trench with one hand, reached the other down to grasp
                    the boy's arm. His reach was too short, and the boy trembling with fear, could
                    not understand how to reach up his hands. Edouard pulled himself farther over
                    the trench, until his head and shoulders and half his trunk hung over it. He
                    could feel the soft mud of the trench sides giving way under his hand. The
                    basket had glided directly over his head. He could hear the ominous click which
                    told that it was tilting. With an almost superhuman effort, he stretched out his
                    farthest, and grasping the child by the collar, he threw him over his shoulder,
                    and wriggled himself back from the sides of the trench. At the same instant, the
                    mass of dirt came rattling down into the water. </p>
                <p>Some passers-by had stopped to see the outcome of what promised a tragedy, and
                    the sewer workers, and some men from neighboring shops, came running up to
                    praise him and to offer him aid. Edouard was dazed and frightened and his only
                    clear thought was that in swinging the boy over his shoulder, he had heard the
                    sleeve of his coat rip out. </p>
                <p>And now he was a hero. For the first time he was tasting the sweets of adulation.
                    He was ashamed and would have run away and hid his face but that the little
                    woman who kept the millinery shop had noticed the ripped sleeve, and Edouard
                    must step into her parlor, hitherto undefiled by the clumsy feet of man, and
                    have his coat mended. Edouard blushed as he took it off, and was about to hand
                    it to her, when an unfamiliar look about it caused him to take it back suddenly,
                    and carry it to the window for closer inspection. It was Emile's. He had made a
                    mistake when he was leaving the shop. </p>
                <p>All the shame of the noon-hour came over him again, and he moodily handed the
                    garment back to the milliner, and gave himself up to bitterness. He had saved a
                    little boy's life, but&mdash;they called him a thief at the shop, and
                    nothing could wipe that away. </p>
                <p>The milliner's voice broke in on his musings. </p>
                <p>"There's a paper tucked in the lining somehow," she was saying, "shall I pull it
                    out for you?" </p>
                <p>"It is not mine," he replied. <pb entity="DSSR_000002584_0007" n="364"/>
                </p>
                <p>But she had already pulled it out and handed it to him. He glanced at it
                    abstractedly. Then he sat up suddenly and gasped. Could it be true? Could this
                    awful thing that confronted him be a fact and not a dream? It was but a little
                    yellow slip of paper. There was Lowenstein's name on it and Emile's, and a
                    number and something about a gold watch and twenty dollars. He took the mended
                    coat abruptly from the milliner, and murmuring scarcely audible thanks as he put
                    it on, plunged through the crowd waiting outside the door, and hastened down
                    town again. </p>
                <p>"Here he is again," called out Ren&eacute;, as Edouard entered the shop a
                    half hour later. </p>
                <p>"I&mdash;I&mdash;put on the wrong coat," he explained to Mr. Laporte. </p>
                <p>"Yes, yes," muttered the little man, "git you' own coat an' go. You' Uncle
                    Aristide is a good man&mdash;a good man," and he picked up a bunch of
                    tobacco strippings and looked at it sorrowfully. </p>
                <p>Edouard crossed over to Emile's bench. "Here is you' coat," he said shortly,
                    "an'&mdash;an'&mdash;this." Their eyes met, and Emile's face grew livid. </p>
                <p>"You won't tell?" he asked thickly. </p>
                <p>"No," Edouard spoke with difficulty. </p>
                <p>"I&mdash;I'll make it all right, you know." </p>
                <p>Edouard turned on him in a fury, "What do you tek me fo'?" he demanded, and
                    strode from the shop, taking his own coat from the peg as he went out. </p>
                <p>This time he went to Treme Street. It was easy now that he knew where the burden
                    of guilt lay. He told it all to Uncle Aristide and Tante Pauline, all, that is,
                    save the finding of the ticket. Deep down in his heart he locked Emile's secret,
                    and as the days and weeks went by, the sorrow of it grew a little less. Uncle
                    Aristide found other work for him to do, and he went his way and was happy. </p>
                <p>One Sunday Mr. Laporte came to the house. In his perplexity, he had wrinkled up
                    his face until it seemed that his skin must drop off. </p>
                <p>"I have come to mek reparation," he said to Edouard. "Dat man, Emile, we foun'
                    him out, yaas. Lowenstein, he tol' me, an' I tell the mens, an' dey give you
                    cheer." He held out his hand to Edouard. "You mus' come back," he said pumping
                    his arm vigorously. "An' you knew all dat time?" he queried, peering into
                    Edouard's face. </p>
                <p>But Edouard was silent. He had promised not to tell.</p>
            </div1>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI.2>
