<?xml version="1.0"?>

<?dlps id="DunLesi"?>
<?dlps page-images="color" figure-images="no"?>
<?dlps transcription="other"?>

<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/tei-p4/tei2.dtd" [
<!ENTITY % POSTKB "INCLUDE">
<!ENTITY % TEI.extensions.ent SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.ent">
<!ENTITY % TEI.extensions.dtd SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.dtd">
<!ENTITY % ISOpub SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/charent/iso-pub.ent"> %ISOpub;


<!ENTITY DSSR_000002585_0001 SYSTEM "000002585_0001" NDATA uvaHighRes>
<!ENTITY DSSR_000002585_0002 SYSTEM "000002585_0002" NDATA uvaHighRes>
<!ENTITY DSSR_000002585_0003 SYSTEM "000002585_0003" NDATA uvaHighRes>
<!ENTITY DSSR_000002585_0004 SYSTEM "000002585_0004" NDATA uvaHighRes>
<!ENTITY DSSR_000002585_0005 SYSTEM "000002585_0005" NDATA uvaHighRes>
]>
<TEI.2 id="DunLesi">
    <teiHeader creator="Etext" type="migrated">
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title type="main">Lesie, the Choir Boy</title>
                <title type="sort">lesie, the choir boy</title>
                <author>Dunbar, Alice</author>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Creation of machine-readable version:</resp>
                    <name>Judy Boss</name>
                    <resp>Creation of digital images:</resp>
                    <name>Stephen Ramsay, Electronic Text Center</name>
                    <resp>Conversion to TEI.2-conformant markup:</resp>
                    <name>University of Virginia Library Electronic Text Center.</name>
                </respStmt>
            </titleStmt>
            <extent>ca. <num type="kilobytes">18</num> kilobytes</extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>University of Virginia Library</publisher>
                <pubPlace>Charlottesville, Virginia</pubPlace>
                <idno type="ETC">DunLesi</idno>
                <date value="1996">1996</date>
                <availability status="public">
                    <p n="copyright">Copyright &#xa9; 1996 by the Rector and Visitors of the
                        University of Virginia</p>
                    <p n="access">Publicly accessible</p>
                </availability>
                <idno type="uva-pid">uva-lib:476916</idno>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title>University of Virginia Library, Text collection</title>
                <idno type="uva-set">UVA-LIB-Text</idno>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull>
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title type="main">Lesie, the Choir Boy</title>
                        <title level="j">The Southern Workman</title>
                        <title type="sort">lesie, the choir boy</title>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <extent>pp. 613-619</extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Hampton Institute</publisher>
                        <pubPlace>Hampton, VA</pubPlace>
                        <date value="1901-11">November 1901</date>
                        <idno type="callNo">Print copy consulted: Alderman Library, LC 2701
                        .S7</idno>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <notesStmt>
                        <note>
                            <p>Southern Workman, Vol. 30, No. 11, November 1901.</p>
                        </note>
                        <note>
                            <p>The following emendations were made to the text by Judy Boss:</p>
                            <list type="simple">
                                <item>p. 616, para. 7 -fer"? ] fer?";</item>
                                <item>p. 616, para. 11 -Stephen's". ] Stephen's.";</item>
                                <item>p. 617, para. 1 -go", ] go,";</item>
                                <item>p. 617, para. 2 -will", ] will,";</item>
                                <item>p. 617, para. 4 -"Co'se", ] "Co'se,";</item>
                                <item>p. 617, para. 5 -"say", ] "say,";</item>
                                <item>p. 617, para. 6 -is"? ] is?";</item>
                                <item>p. 617, para. 7 -Sanders", ] Sanders,";</item>
                                <item>p. 617, para. 8 -great", ] great,";</item>
                                <item>p. 617, para. 9 -Mr Sanders ] Mr. Sanders;</item>
                                <item>p. 617, para. 11 -out", ] out,";</item>
                                <item>p. 617, para. 11 -cried", as ] cried, "as;</item>
                                <item>p. 617, para. 4 -couldn't", ] couldn't,";</item>
                                <item>p. 618, para. 1 -goin'ter ] goin' ter;</item>
                                <item>p. 618, para. 1 -Sunday", ] Sunday,";</item>
                                <item>p. 618, para. 2 -dat", ] dat,";</item>
                                <item>p. 618, para. 5 -to-night", ] to-night,";</item>
                                <item>p. 618, para. 8 -"Well", ] "Well,";</item>
                                <item>p. 619, para. 4 -"more", ] more,";</item>
                                <item>p. 619, para. 6 -from", ] from,"</item>
                            </list>
                        </note>
                    </notesStmt>
                </biblFull>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>Prepared for the University of Virginia Library Electronic Text Center.</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <p>All quotation marks retained as data.</p>
                <p>All unambiguous end-of-line hyphens have been removed, and the trailing part of a
                    word has been joined to the preceding line.</p>
                <p>The images exist as archived TIFF images, one or more JPEG versions for general
                    use, and thumbnail GIFs.</p>
                <p>Keywords in the header are a local Electronic Text Center scheme to aid in
                    establishing analytical groupings.</p>
            </editorialDecl>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <creation>
                <date value="1901">1901</date>
            </creation>
            <langUsage>
                <language id="eng" usage="main">English</language>
            </langUsage>
            <textClass>
                <keywords>
                    <term>fiction; prose</term>
                    <term>Women Writers</term>
                    <term>Young Readers</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords>
                    <term type="format">24-bit color; 400 dpi</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change>
                <date value="1996-11">November 1996</date>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>corrector</resp>
                    <name>Stephen Ramsay, Electronic Text Center</name>
                </respStmt>
                <item>Added TEI header and tags.</item>
            </change>
            <change>
                <date value="2005-07">July 2005</date>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Corrector</resp>
                    <name>John Ivor Carlson</name>
                </respStmt>
                <item>Converted SGML to XML. Fixed tagging.</item>
            </change>
            <change>
                <date value="2007-09">September 2007</date>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Migration</resp>
                    <name>Ethan Gruber, University of Virginia Library</name>
                </respStmt>
                <item>Converted XML markup from TEI Lite to uva-dl-tei (TEI P4 with local
                    customizations).</item>
            </change>
            <change>
                <date value="2008-01">January 2008</date>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Migration</resp>
                    <name>Greg Murray, University of Virginia Library</name>
                </respStmt>
                <item>Programmatically updated TEI header markup (but not header content) for
                    minimal compliance with current QA requirements.</item>
            </change>
<change>
<date value="2009-03">March 2009</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>Migration</resp>
<name>Scholarly Resources, University of Virginia Library</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Added and/or replaced the digital images accompanying the electronic text. Scanning of exterior and interior (ie. pages) of item was done only for items found in the University of Virginia Special Collections Library.</item>
</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>

    <text id="d1">

        <body id="d2">



            <div1 id="d3" type="story">
                <pb entity="DSSR_000002585_0001"/>
                <head>Lesie, the Choir Boy<lb/> ALICE DUNBAR</head>

                <p>OVER and above all things nature had been lavish to Lesie Channing in the matter
                    of a voice. It was a full, clear soprano with rich tones in it that presaged a
                    marvel of tone in later years. He loved to sing. It was a pure joy to him to
                    fill the hall and room of his tenement home with the only tunes that he
                    knew&mdash;"coon" songs and music-hall ballads. But while he delighted in
                    the sounds that he made, no one had ever told Lesie that his voice was
                    marvellous. </p>
                <p>Besides this, he had a seraphic, olive-skinned face with masses of curly brown
                    hair that tossed about a broad forehead. His eyes were lustrous and innocent and
                    his mouth was small and tender. Had he lived on Fifth Avenue, he would have been
                    proud of his looks and have worn a velvet coat and wide lace collars. But in
                    "Steenth street, all this beauty was a sore trial to his spirit and a lasting
                    disgrace in the eyes of his companions. He had to be twice as aggressive as a
                    less prepossessing boy and was forced always to be doing something in order to
                    prove that his girl-like face did not belong to a girl-like spirit. He had made
                    his way into "de gang" by sheer determination, a bull-dog spirit and a very hard
                    pair of fists. When he was a small fellow he envied the bigger and more
                    masculine looking boys, but paid little attention to them, until one of them
                    called him "Molly" one day. Thereupon he arose, and tried to obliterate his
                    tormentor from the face of the earth. The elation of a good fight intoxicated
                    him, and having accomplished the annihilation in part of the aforesaid
                    tormentor, he turned his attention to two others&mdash;and his social
                    reputation was assured. </p>
                <p>When it became the pleasure of the aristocrats of 'Steenth street to honor the
                    newly opened "Pure in Heart" mission by their attendance, Lesie was first among
                    them. Although he would have died rather than confess it, he loved to go, not
                    because of the great scope for mischief, but because there was singing and
                    plenty of it. Mrs. Morton, the mission manager, would beam on him as he let his
                    voice out in full, and Lesie's joy knew no bounds. He was wont to relieve his
                    feelings by sticking a pin into his nearest neighbor. </p>
                <p>Then Sister Margaret came one day to a class of boys and heard him sing, and went
                    back to her place in St. Stephen's full of this seraphic looking boy's voice.
                    And the chorister, ever in search of fresh material for his choir, visited Mrs.
                    Channing. There were consultations, and Lesie was called in and made to warble a
                    verse from a hymn. The chorister was wild with delight. He was a rather
                    phlegmatic man, but his joy in this new find burst bounds, and he almost hugged
                    Mrs. Channing, baby and all. </p>
                <p>In the days which followed his good fortune, Lesie was strangely silent and
                    abstracted. He was sore afraid lest it should come to the <pb
                        entity="DSSR_000002585_0002" n="616" /> ears of
                    "de gang," for he feared what their opinion might be. So he played more freely
                    than usual, and had two wholly unnecessary fights with big boys on the next
                    street storing up an account, as it were, on which he could draw in the dark
                    days to come. </p>
                <p>He came home from his first morning service, and dropped into a chair without his
                    usual cheery greeting to the baby. Mrs. Channing eyed him narrowly, and her
                    maternal heart told her that something was not right. </p>
                <p>"Well?" she inquired, after waiting for a word. </p>
                <p>Lesie looked up and his gaze passed hers and sought the window. </p>
                <p>"Ain't you satisfied," continued Mrs. Channing, "how'd you like it?" </p>
                <p>"Aw, dey put me in a dress." </p>
                <p>"Mercy," cried the mother, then she grew indignant. </p>
                <p>"Wha'd dey take you fer?" she demanded. </p>
                <p>"All de guys had 'em, jes' like de minister's." </p>
                <p>Mrs. Channing stared at him with incredulous wonder and gravely considered the
                    idea of keeping him home in the future. She would not allow those people to make
                    a laughing stock of her son, no matter how much they wanted him. </p>
                <p>But it was not the gown altogether which had produced Lesie's abstraction,
                    although that was a great enough shock. He had heard the organist whisper to the
                    first tenor that he had a face like a little St. Cecelia, and he wondered what
                    it meant. </p>
                <p>It did not take the news long to go through the length and breadth of 'Steenth
                    street that Lesie was "doin' de heavy down at St. Stephen's." For a day, he was
                    regarded with scorn unspeakable, and he went his way alone, fierce and
                    contemptuous. Frank Smith, however, was unwise enough to groan and strike an
                    attitude as Lesie passed. The issue was short, sharp and decisive. There was a
                    celebration a half hour later at "Dago Joe's" expense, and his stock of peanuts
                    was materially reduced. </p>
                <p>Beyond the pleasure of raising his soul in song at service and rehearsals, the
                    choir life was an irksome one to Lesie. He was entirely out of sympathy with his
                    surroundings, and his fits of moodiness after an excursion down town grew longer
                    and longer. The boys of St. Stephen's looked down upon him, he felt that,
                    although the barrier which they drew was an intangible one. But the intangible
                    barriers are the ones that count. He was not of their creed nor of their kind.
                    They had traditions which he had not. They had clothes which he could never hope
                    to possess. Their speech was not his nor their talk. It was a different world in
                    which he moved, a lonely and dissatisfied guest. He would have met them singly
                    and in groups and have vanquished them by force, had it been possible, for this
                    was his only idea, his only knowledge of the way of asserting himself; but the
                    chorister was very strict and there was no chance. </p>
                <p>One Saturday night when they had gathered in groups in the <pb
                    entity="DSSR_000002585_0003" n="617"/>
                    choir-room awaiting the chorister, Fred Allen, an alto, accosted him with a
                    high-pitched note of triumph in his voice. </p>
                <p>"Bet you won't go," he said. </p>
                <p>"Bet I will," retorted Lesie. </p>
                <p>"Say, now, but will you?" </p>
                <p>"Co'se," said Lesie sternly. He did not know what it was but it behooved him to
                    affect an indifferent knowledge, for did not the honor of 'Steenth street depend
                    upon him? </p>
                <p>"Well, I say," put in another boy, but it's a big thing." </p>
                <p>"What is?" inquired Lesie forgetting his role. </p>
                <p>"Old man Sanders," said Fred, nodding his head at the church, "is going to take
                    us to the oratorio at Carnegie Hall, and give us a supper next week." </p>
                <p>"Oh, well, he thinks he's doing something great," said a melancholy youth, "I'm
                    not losing any sleep over it." </p>
                <p>Lesie was silent. He had not been in the choir long enough to know what an
                    oratorio was, and he felt strangely out of the whole affair. It was discussed
                    further, until Mr. Sanders came and made the matter more specific. They were to
                    meet him Wednesday night at the choir room and he would manage the rest. This
                    much Lesie understood, that he would hear music and good music, and that was
                    enough. </p>
                <p>Mrs. Channing was in a bad humor when Wednesday came. Her husband had failed to
                    give her a share of his wages on Saturday night, and the agent had been to the
                    house and threatened eviction if the rent was not paid in short order. When
                    Lesie approached her timidly with a request for a clean shirt and assistance
                    with his dressing, she turned on him fiercely and raised a hot iron
                    threateningly. </p>
                <p>"Get out," she cried, "as if I didn't have enough to do to keep food in your
                    mouth and a shelter over your head! Don't you dare to bother me wid your
                    high-toned mess. Want a clean shirt, do you? Next thing I know, you will be
                    wantin' a dress-suit to go to de opery." </p>
                <p>Lesie went down stairs and into the street without a word. Well, after all, he
                    would have a good time. He refused Dobson's invitation to go on First avenue,
                    after a rumored dog-fight, with such a gentle manner that it caused Dobson to
                    stare for an instant. Then he perched on the railing of the stoop and sang
                    softly to himself until it was time to go to bed. </p>
                <p>"Why didn't you come Wednesday?" he inquired. </p>
                <p>"I couldn't," said Lesie simply. </p>
                <p>The choir boys did not ask him why he was not with them at the oratorio. They had
                    not missed him. </p>
                <p>It was just at this time that he was assigned to a solo part to be sung at the
                    Easter service. There were only about twenty bars to be sung, but it was a sign
                    of great advancement, and some of the older boys looked at him with interest,
                    even envy. On the night that the parts were assigned, Lesie walked home with a
                    something tugging <pb entity="DSSR_000002585_0004" n="618"/> within him that made him whistle and pelt
                    pebbles at a passing cable car. </p>
                <p>"I'm goin' ter sing by myself Easter Sunday," he told his mother shyly. </p>
                <p>"Well, I don't see nuttin' in dat," she made reply. </p>
                <p>The sweetness of it had gone in an instant. He had intended offering to carry
                    home the basket of clothes that night. Instead, he had to be scolded to it, and
                    somehow, the burden never seemed so heavy nor the task so irksome. </p>
                <p>It was the last rehearsal before Easter, and Mr. Sanders was lecturing the boys
                    with more than wonted severity. </p>
                <p>"Keep in the house to-night," he was saying, "be careful to get sleep enough and
                    above all, don't come here in bad condition to-morrow." It was Mr. Sander's
                    first Easter at St. Stephen's, and he desired greatly to do himself credit. </p>
                <p>There was dissension in the Channing household that night. A difference of
                    opinion had arisen between the maternal and paternal members of the family. The
                    difference was of the violent and aggressive sort and there was an alcoholic
                    fume in the atmosphere of the kitchen. Lesie fled, with the other children,
                    supperless to the street for refuge. There was a great expedition on. "De gang"
                    had a business transaction down on 68th street, and Lesie joined in with a
                    joyous war-whoop, his good resolution to go to bed forgotten, the raw,
                    rain-laden east wind unheeded. </p>
                <p>It was far into the night when he crept into bed, flushed with success, for his
                    had been the voice that had led the boys on to victory in the raid against the
                    obnoxious 68th street crowd, and his had been the arms that had dealt the most
                    effective blows. He remembered faintly as he lay down that he should have been
                    asleep hours before. </p>
                <p>"Well," was his consoling reflection, "de ol' man an' de ol' woman was a
                    scrappin' an' I guess out-doors is de bes' place fer us kids when dey gits
                    togedder." </p>
                <p>The next morning, he woke with a headache, his mouth felt dry and parched and his
                    face was flushed. Mrs. Channing was sullen and paid no attention to him as he
                    pushed aside his coffee and bread untasted. She was irritable at the world in
                    general and was glad when Lesie left the house. He felt better when he was in
                    the street, and forgot the headache in the gold glint of the sun and the spring
                    freshness of the air. </p>
                <p>The atmosphere of the church was overpowering with the perfume of hundreds of
                    lilies and the close packing of the unwonted crowd. The sermon was long, and
                    Lesie found his head drooping, and his senses reeling with the odor of incense
                    and flowers. If he could only close his eyes for a minute, perhaps Sanders
                    wouldn't see, and he would feel better. He was going over in his mind the music
                    of his solo, and singing it mentally over and over until it mingled with the
                    sonorous voice of the rector and became inextricably entangled in the woof of
                    the sermon. <pb entity="DSSR_000002585_0005" n="619"/>
                </p>
                <p>Then he felt someone plucking wildly at his sleeve and started into
                    consciousness. The boy next to him had awakened him. The organ was pealing the
                    prelude to the anthem; Sanders was glaring at him with a savage fierceness that
                    made his heart stand still, and he distinctly heard the sallow, melancholy boy
                    titter behind him. He stood up with the rest, but sleep was in his eyes, and
                    fear in his soul, and the sheet of music trembled in his hand until the notes
                    ran together in a black, unreadable mass. He could not find his place, and he
                    dared not sing. Now, they were nearing his solo, he could hear the baritone
                    ending his part, and the boys turning their pages. Lesie's music was at the
                    beginning of the next leaf. He thumbed the music thickly, striving to turn it,
                    and there was the sound of many waters in his ears. He glanced up at Sanders and
                    caught a grim look in the chorister's eyes that nerved him to desperation. The
                    organ had played the first note of his solo, and the boys were looking at him
                    with expectancy. He parted his dry lips but no sound came forth, and the organ
                    had finished the first bar. He moistened his lips and tried again. This time a
                    note came forth. It was hoarse and cracked and false. Mr. Sanders finished the
                    solo. </p>
                <p>He rushed from the choir-room when the service was over, without waiting to hang
                    up his surplice. He could not stand the titters and giggles of the other boys.
                    He ran, rather than walked up to 'Steenth street. His heart was full of
                    bitterness and humiliation and his head was confused and wandering. Mrs.
                    Channing had remembered that he was to do something out of the ordinary to-day,
                    and she greeted him with renewed interest. </p>
                <p>"Well, how was it?" </p>
                <p>"Aw, I ain't goin' dere no more," he snapped, "dem guys make me tired." </p>
                <p>Thereafter, Lesie confined his musical accomplishments to the singing class of
                    the "Pure in Heart" Mission. </p>
                <p>"That boy will be heard from," said a visitor to the mission one evening as Lesie
                    was singing his very best. </p>
                <p>And so he was in after years, but that belongs to another time, and is for some
                    one else to tell.</p>

            </div1>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI.2>
