<?xml version="1.0"?>

<?dlps id="FreHumb"?>
<?dlps page-images="color" figure-images="yes"?>
<?dlps transcription="other"?>

<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/tei-p4/tei2.dtd" [
<!ENTITY % POSTKB "INCLUDE">
<!ENTITY % TEI.extensions.ent SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.ent">
<!ENTITY % TEI.extensions.dtd SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.dtd">
<!ENTITY % ISOpub SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/charent/iso-pub.ent"> %ISOpub;


<!ENTITY DSSR_000002603_0001 SYSTEM "000002603_0001" NDATA uvaHighRes>
<!ENTITY DSSR_000002603_0002 SYSTEM "000002603_0002" NDATA uvaHighRes>
<!ENTITY DSSR_000002603_0003 SYSTEM "000002603_0003" NDATA uvaHighRes>
<!ENTITY DSSR_000002603_0004 SYSTEM "000002603_0004" NDATA uvaHighRes>
<!ENTITY DSSR_000002603_0005 SYSTEM "000002603_0005" NDATA uvaHighRes>
<!ENTITY DSSR_000002603_0006 SYSTEM "000002603_0006" NDATA uvaHighRes>
<!ENTITY DSSR_000002603_0007 SYSTEM "000002603_0007" NDATA uvaHighRes>
<!ENTITY DSSR_000002603_0008 SYSTEM "000002603_0008" NDATA uvaHighRes>
]>
<TEI.2 id="FreHumb">
<teiHeader type="migrated" creator="Etext">
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title type="main">Humble Pie</title>
<title type="sort">humble pie</title>
<author>Freeman, Mary Eleanor Wilkins, 1852-1930</author>
<respStmt>
<resp>Creation of machine-readable version:</resp>
<name>Judy Boss</name>
<resp>Creation of digital images:</resp>
<name>Electronic Text Center</name>
<resp>Conversion to TEI.2-conformant markup:</resp>
<name>University of Virginia Library Electronic Text Center.</name>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt>
<extent>ca. <num type="kilobytes">33</num> kilobytes</extent>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>University of Virginia Library</publisher>
<pubPlace>Charlottesville, Virginia</pubPlace>
<idno type="ETC">FreHumb</idno>
<date value="1996">1996</date>
<availability status="public">
<p n="copyright">Copyright &#xa9; 1996 by the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia</p>
<p n="access">Publicly accessible</p>
</availability>
<idno type="uva-pid">uva-lib:476960</idno>
</publicationStmt>
<seriesStmt>
<title>University of Virginia Library, Text collection</title>
<idno type="uva-set">UVA-LIB-Text</idno>
</seriesStmt>
<notesStmt>
<note>
<p>Illustrations have been included from the print version.</p>
</note>
<note>
<p>The following emendations have been made to the text by Judy Boss: p. 478, para. 5 -"She's ] She ; p. 480, para. 6 -homliness. ] homeliness. ; p. 482, l. 26 -apear ] appear</p>
</note>
</notesStmt>
<sourceDesc>
<biblFull>
<titleStmt>
<title type="main">Humble Pie</title>
<title level="j">The Independent</title>
<title type="sort">humble pie</title>
<author>Mary E. Wilkins Freeman</author>
</titleStmt>
<extent>pp. 477-484</extent>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>S. W. Benedict</publisher>
<pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
<date value="1904">1904</date>
<idno type="callNo">Print copy consulted: Alderman Library, AP2.I53</idno>
</publicationStmt>
<notesStmt>
<note>
<p>The Independent, Vol 57, No. 2909, September 1, 1904.</p>
</note>
</notesStmt>
</biblFull>
</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc>
<encodingDesc>
<projectDesc>
<p>Prepared for the University of Virginia Library Electronic Text Center.</p>
</projectDesc>
<editorialDecl>
<p>All quotation marks retained as data.</p>
<p>All unambiguous end-of-line hyphens have been removed, and the trailing part of a word has been joined to the preceding line.</p>
<p>The images exist as archived TIFF images, one or more JPEG versions for general use, and thumbnail GIFs.</p>
<p>Keywords in the header are a local Electronic Text Center scheme to aid in establishing analytical groupings.</p>
</editorialDecl>
</encodingDesc>
<profileDesc>
<creation>
<date value="1904">1904</date>
</creation>
<langUsage>
<language id="eng" usage="main">English</language>
</langUsage>
<textClass>
<keywords>
<term>fiction; prose</term>
<term>Women Writers</term>
</keywords>
<keywords>
<term type="format">24-bit color; 400 dpi</term>
</keywords>
</textClass>
</profileDesc>
<revisionDesc>
<change>
<date value="1996-12">December 1996</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>corrector</resp>
<name>Stephen Ramsay, Electronic Text Center</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Added TEI header and tags.</item>
</change>
<change>
<date value="2005-07">July 2005</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>Corrector</resp>
<name>John Ivor Carlson</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Converted SGML to XML. Fixed tagging.</item>
</change>
<change>
<date value="2007-09">September 2007</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>Migration</resp>
<name>Ethan Gruber, University of Virginia Library</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Converted XML markup from TEI Lite to uva-dl-tei (TEI P4 with local customizations).</item>
</change>
<change>
<date value="2008-01">January 2008</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>Migration</resp>
<name>Greg Murray, University of Virginia Library</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Programmatically updated TEI header markup (but not header content) for minimal compliance with current QA requirements.</item>
</change>
<change>
<date value="2009-03">March 2009</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>Migration</resp>
<name>Scholarly Resources, University of Virginia Library</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Added and/or replaced the digital images accompanying the electronic text. Scanning of exterior and interior (ie. pages) of item was done only for items found in the University of Virginia Special Collections Library.</item>
</change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>
<text id="d1">
<body id="d2">




<div1 type="story" id="d3">
<pb entity="DSSR_000002603_0001" n="477"/>
<head>
<hi rend="bold">Humble Pie<lb/>

              BY MARY E. WILKINS FREEMAN<lb/>

      AUTHOR OF "THE PORTION OF LABOR," ETC.</hi></head>

<p>THERE are some people who never during their whole lives awake to a
consciousness of themselves, as they are recognized by others; there are
some who awake too early, to their undoing, and the flimsiness of their
characters; there are some who awake late with a shock, which does not
dethrone them from their individuality, but causes them agony, and is
possibly for their benefit.  Maria Gorham was one of the last, and for the
first time in her life she saw herself reflected mercilessly in the eyes of
her kind one summer in a great mountain hotel.  She had never been
aware that she was more conceited than others, that she had had on the
whole a better opinion of her external advantages at least, than she
deserved, but she discovered that her self-conceit had been something
which looked to her monstrous and insufferable.  She saw that she was
not on the surface what she had always thought herself to be, and she saw
that the surface has always its influence on the depths.
</p><p>Maria Gorham was an old young woman in her early thirties.  She
had taught school in her native village in one of the New England States
since she was seventeen.  She had been left quite alone in the world, five
years before, when her mother died.  She lived entirely alone in the house
in which she had been born.  It was one of the cottages prevalent in
certain localities.  She was entirely fearless.  So quietly poised was she in
her own self esteem that it had never occurred to her that anybody could
possibly have any ill will, or even any uncomplimentary feeling, toward
her.  She had always heard herself called good-looking, and it had not
occurred to her to doubt the opinion of others.  She had also heard herself
called industrious, capable and more than ordinarily clever, and she
acquiesced with that opinion also.  She had also heard her taste in dress
extolled, and she had packed her little trunk with entire confidence.
Dexter Ray's sister Emma had run across the street, and was watching
her.  "I thought I'd like to see you put all them pretty things in, I
suspected you was packin'," said Emma, with a gentle admiration, and
not a suspicion of jealousy.  Maria noted Emma's faulty English with a
superiority which gave her a certain pleasure.  "Poor Emma," she
thought, and replied all the more sweetly.  "Yes," said she, "I am going
on the eight o'clock train to-morrow morning, and I must have my trunk
all ready to-night."
</p><p>Emma watched Maria fold her blue foulard gown daintily.  "Well,"
she said, "I guess there won't be many to that hotel where you are goin'
that has any prettier things than you."
</p><p>Maria laughed.  "Nonsense," she replied, but in her heart she quite
agreed with Emma.  She had entire faith in her wardrobe, which she and
the village dressmaker had prepared.
</p><p>"I suppose you'll wear that handsome pink wrapper mornin's," said
Emma.
</p><p>"Yes, I have planned to," replied Maria.  Just as she spoke there
was a ring at the front door bell, and Emma started and blushed, altho she
had herself nothing for which to blush.  "I rather guess that must be
Dexter," said she.
</p><p>Maria frowned.
</p><p>"Dexter said he guessed mebbe he'd jest run in an' say good-by,"
said Emma, timidly, and with even more embarrassment.
</p><p>Maria herself blushed, but, as it seemed, with anger rather than
embarrassment.  However, she tried to speak politely.  Dexter Ray was
the only man who had ever wanted to marry her, and while she thought
herself too good for
    <pb entity="DSSR_000002603_0002" n="478"/>
him, she considered that he was to be
rewarded at least with politeness for his pretensions.
</p><p>"I really don't see how I can stop my packing," she said, "I wonder
if you wouldn't just run down stairs and tell your brother that I am real
sorry, but I am packing."
</p><p>Emma stood up with dignity.  She had at times a little sense of
injury on her brother's account.  "All right," said she.
</p><p>"I have been working very hard all day finishing up some sewing
and getting the house ready to leave, and, if I stop now, I don't know
when I would get to bed," Maria added, with more conciliation in her
tone.
</p><p>"All right," said Emma, and went out.  Maria heard her tell Dexter.
"She says she's real sorry; but she's awful tired, she's been workin' so
hard all day, and she's got to get her trunk packed to-night."  There was
more sorrow in Emma's voice than there had been in Maria's.  Maria stole
a glance out of the window, and saw Dexter going meekly down the path
between the flowering shrubs after his rebuff.  He was quite a tall man, a
little older than she, and there was an odd faithful bend in his shoulders.
Maria sighed, she could not have told why.  Sometimes she wished that
Dexter had been a more fitting match for her.
</p><p>Sometimes she had actually felt angry with Dexter Ray that he did
not try to make more of himself, but he spoke no better English than his
sister.  He also, in her opinion, had no ambition.  He kept the village drug
store, and several times he had had an opportunity to be selectman, and
once town clerk, but he seemed to have no interest except in measuring
out drugs and dispensing soda water.  It would have puzzled Maria had
she been required to mention by what right in view of her own
antecedents she regarded herself as on a higher social scale than Dexter
Ray.  Her father had been a small farmer, and his father before him.  On
her father's death she had sold all the farming land, and that made her
little nest egg in the savings bank.  She had never saved much from the
money which she earned teaching.  She had a weakness for pretty things,
both for her own person and for her house.  She had had a bay window
and a piazza put on the house since her father's death.  She had also a
very splendid carpet in the parlor and a set of plush furniture.  She had
never traveled.  There was in the depths of her soul a feminine timidity
about setting forth alone on strange paths, in spite of her steady egotism.
It was almost as if she feared lest her faith in herself would desert her, if
she were deprived of the accustomed support of admiring friends and
subjected to the cold scrutiny of strangers.  However, nothing could have
made her admit the slightest hesitation, and the next day she was to set
out alone to spend a whole month at a great mountain hotel.  "I declare,"
Emma Ray said, when she returned.  "I should think you'd sort of dread
startin' out all alone to-morrer, Maria."
</p><p>"I don't know why," replied Maria, calmly.
</p><p>"I should think you'd sort of dread goin' into the dinin'-room all
alone."
</p><p>"I don't know why."
</p><p>"Of course, I know you'll look as fine as anybody," said Emma in a
conciliatory tone.
</p><p>"I don't know why I should dread it, however I looked.  This is a
free country."
</p><p>"I suppose there's a lot of rich folks at that hotel."
</p><p>"Well, riches don't make any difference in a country like this, do
they?"
</p><p>"I don't know," replied Emma.
</p><p>"They ought not to, anyway," said Maria, firmly, substituting the
principle for the fact with a fairly great loyalty.
</p><p>"Mebbe they don't," said Emma.
</p><p>Presently Emma added.  "Of course, it ain't as tho you wasn't
educated.  Of course, you have been school-teachin' all your life, and I
s'pose lots of them rich folks couldn't teach school any more than they
could fly."
</p><p>"They haven't been obliged to," replied Maria.
</p><p>"They couldn't, anyway."
</p><p>Maria made no dissent to that.  In her heart she agreed with Emma.
She folded carefully a white lawn sacque trimmed with frills of
embroidery, and laid it in one of the top trays of her trunk.
</p><p>"That will be real pretty to wear with your black silk skirt," said
Emma.
</p><p>"Yes, I thought it would," said Maria.
    <pb entity="DSSR_000002603_0003" n="479"/>
</p>
<p>"It looks as if you might have a dreadful hot day to-morrow," said
Emma, glancing out of the window which faced the west.  The sun was
setting like an awful ball of fire for the ultimate consumption of the
world.
</p><p>"Yes, it seems as if it might be hot," assented Maria.
</p><p>"What are you going to wear travelin'?  You'll have quite a long
journey, most nine hours, Dexter said.  He studied it out on the time
table."
</p><p>"I'm going to wear my gray mohair I had last summer."
</p><p>"Well, that sheds the dust fine."
</p><p>"Yes, and I'm going to put my black silk skirt in the top of the trunk
where I can get at it easy, and put it on with this cambric sacque to go to
supper in, if it's a warm night," said Maria.
</p><p>"That will be a real good idea," said Emma, approvingly.  "It won't
be so much work as getting into a dress, and you'll feel tired."
</p><p>"That's what I thought.  I'll wear this cambric sacque to supper, and
then I suppose I shall sit in the parlor and listen to the music.  They say
there's music and dancing every night."
</p><p>"Well, there ought to be something when they ask such prices."
</p><p>"Yes, that is so," replied Maria.  She
    <pb entity="DSSR_000002603_0004" n="480"/>
was herself secretly
dazed at the wild extravagance into which she was about to launch, but a
spirit of defiance had suddenly seized her.  It was a hot electric summer,
prone to burst forth in fierce storms, and Maria, in spite of her great self
poise, had an irritable, high-strung nervous temperament.  All at once it
had seemed to her that she could no longer remain where she was and go
her daily rounds.  She hated the very sight of all the old articles of
furniture, which had heretofore been to her almost like members of her
family.  She had acquired the habit of sitting in the front parlor, a room
which had never been used unless there was company in the house.  She
also slept in the front chamber instead of her own for weeks.  From these
rooms she could look across the street and see Dexter Ray coming and
going, and sometimes she was conscious of a distinct anger against fate
which had not provided her with a better lover.  She had an
unacknowledged humiliation because of her single estate.  She was afraid
that people would think nobody had ever wanted to marry her.  She took
a pleasure of which she was ashamed in having Emma Ray run in often
and in her apparently unappreciated hints concerning her brother.  Emma
had been almost aghast when Maria told her of her resolution to go to the
mountains and spend a month.
</p><p>"Why don't you wait and go on one of them fifteen-dollar
excursions?" said she.  "There will be time enough before your school
begins."
</p><p>"I am not going with a rabble.  I would rather stay at home," replied
Maria, firmly.
</p><p>"But it must cost an awful sight at that hotel."
</p><p>"I don't care.  I'm going to take the money out of the bank, and I am
going.  I need a change.  I have been getting nervous lately, and, if I go at
all, I am going the way I want to go.  I don't care if it does cost.  I have
made up my mind."
</p><p>Dexter was almost as much aghast as his sister when she told him
of the proposed flitting, but after a minute he said: "Well, I guess she's
right.  She'd better go the way that's a-goin' to do her good, if she goes at
all.  I'm glad she's goin' to have a little vacation.  She has worked hard all
her life."  The expression of Dexter Ray's face as he said that was gentle,
almost noble.  The tears sprang into his sister's eyes.  "I don't know as
she has worked any harder than lots of other folks," said she, and she
spoke almost crossly to cover her pity for her brother.  "Go right up an'
down the street here," she added.  "How many women or men have ever
had a real vacation?"
</p><p>"That don't alter it any," replied Dexter, still with the same gentle,
noble expression.  "I'm real glad <hi rend="italic">she's</hi> goin' to
have one, anyway."
The emphasis which he put upon the she was like a benediction.  It
almost transfigured the face of the man, which was homely with a
commonplace homeliness.  He was a good druggist, and the village
people held him, after all, in esteem, altho he had always been, in a
measure, a butt, because of his awkwardness and shyness.  He stumbled
on all the thresholds of social intercourse with his kind, but he never
made an error in putting up a prescription.  The night they were talking
about Maria's going away he proposed timidly to his sister that perhaps
Maria would like to have him carry her to the railroad station in his
buggy.  "There'd be plenty of room in front for her trunk tipped up on
end, and it would save her fifty cents," he said.
</p><p>"Land, she'd turn up her nose at the bare idea," replied Emma.
</p><p>"Well, maybe she would ruther have the stage come for her,"
returned Dexter, meekly.  "I was only thinkin' of savin' her some money."
</p><p>"It would make no end of talk," Emma said, with more leniency
toward Maria.
</p><p>"Well, I s'pose you are right," responded Dexter, with a sigh.
</p><p>However, Emma was so sorry for him that the night before Maria
left, when the trunk was packed, and she was about to go home across
the street, she said, timidly, "I s'pose you've got the stage ordered to take
you to the station in the mornin'."
</p><p>"Of course," replied Maria.  "It isn't very likely I would leave that
until after nine o'clock at night, when the train left in the morning."  She
spoke with some
    <pb entity="DSSR_000002603_0005" n="481"/>
asperity.  She seemed to have a glimpse of
Emma's meaning in putting the question, "Why?" she demanded further.
</p><p>"Nothin'," replied Emma, meekly.  She felt cowed, and as if she had
done her brother's cause great harm.  "Only&mdash;"
</p><p>"Only what?"
</p><p>"Oh, it wasn't nothin', only Dexter, he said he'd jest as lief take you
and your trunk down to the train, and save you the expense."
</p><p>Maria's face flushed.  "Well, I rather think I wouldn't go down to
the station with Dexter Ray right in the face an' eyes of all the people,
with my trunk tilted up in front," said she.  "I should think your brother
would have known better than to propose such a thing."
</p><p>Emma Ray was almost in tears.  She was capable of evanescent
spurts of assertion, especially on her brother's account, but she was easily
intimidated, especially by Maria, to whom she looked up with the
greatest admiration and love.  However, she also loved her brother, and
she made a feeble feint in his defense.  He didn't mean nothin' but
kindness," she said, and Maria's heart smote her.
</p><p>"Oh, I know it!" she replied, "and I'm much obliged to him, but you
know, Emma, yourself, it wouldn't do."
</p><p>"Maybe it wouldn't," said Emma, "but Dexter he didn't think of that.
Men ain't apt to.  He jest meant to be kind, and save you expense."  There
was something almost piteous in her tone.
</p><p>"Well," said Maria, "when I started out planning this trip I made up
my mind to spend some money, and not worry about the expense, but I'm
just as much obliged to your brother."  Maria always said, "your brother"
instead of Dexter.
</p><p>That night after she had gone to bed she thought about it all, and
she felt almost angry again with fate, or with Dexter himself, she could
scarcely have told which, that the one man who had fallen in love with
her had been Dexter Ray and not some one whom she could consider as
her equal, and who spoke better English.  The position, socially speaking,
she did not think of at all.  A druggist was as good as anybody in her
little village; in fact, it was considered a decidedly genteel calling.  It was
only Dexter's own personal drawbacks which she considered.
</p><p>The next morning she started on her trip, and a queer little qualm of
something like self-pity smote her when she saw one of the village
women being driven to the station by her husband in his buggy, with a
small trunk tilted up in front.  She herself clambered out of the village
stage coach, which was a relic preserved with pride, and she tripped a
little and a bit of the braid ripped off the hem of her gray mohair.  She
was obliged to pin it up when she got on the train.  The thought came to
her that a woman was better off with a husband to take her to the station,
and assist her out, and check her baggage.  Then she straightened herself,
and realized with pride that she was going to the mountains to stay a
month in a great hotel at an enormous price, and the other woman was
only going to pay a visit to her sister in Maine, and going on an excursion
at that.  It was almost dark when Maria arrived at her destination, then
she had a drive of a mile through the woods, which rose and sank and
beetled on mountain sides.  The air was cooler, and she was conscious of
a strange vigor in it.  She rode in a mountain wagon which was filled
with passengers, altho Maria could not remember seeing one of them on
the train.  They had all been on Pullman coaches.  It had never occurred
to Maria to take a Pullman coach.  On the seat with Maria was a
corpulent woman in a long black silk traveling cloak, and a hat draped
with a chiffon veil.  She cast one glance at Maria, then looked away, and
it was as if she had not seen her at all.  With this woman were her two
young daughters in tailor-made suits and a young son carrying golf sticks.
The two daughters were nearly of an age, and very pretty with pert tilts to
their chins, and they carried themselves like princesses.  They talked but
little, but what they said was as the language of an unknown world to
Maria.  Both of the girls glanced at Maria very much as their mother had
done, only they gave each other an almost imperceptible glance of
amusement afterward.  Maria wondered why.  She caught the glance, as
any self-centered person would have done.  She shortly afterward raised
her
    <pb entity="DSSR_000002603_0006" n="482"/>
hands and straightened her bonnet.  She wore a bonnet with
strings tied under the chin, altho she was not nearly so old as the girls'
mother.  She also wore a nice little brown and white checked shawl over
her shoulders.  The shawl had belonged to her mother, and Maria always
used it for an extra wrap on a journey, without a thought that its day as
regarded fashion has passed.  When she had seated herself in the
mountain wagon she put the shawl over her shoulders and sat up straight
with her school teacher air, which was almost majestic.  She did not
dream that the combination of majesty, and little checked shawl, and
bonnet, and face, which was almost too young for such head gear, could
possibly afford any amusement to the girls beside her.  When she heard a
soft subdued chuckle she did not dream that she was the cause of it.
"Two silly girls," she said to herself, and eyed the mountains, and
realized her own superiority, inasmuch as she was intent upon those
majestic slopes, while the girls were chattering over their own petty
little affairs.  She made up her mind that she would write Emma Ray
while she was away, it would please her so much, and she thought
of a fine sentiment to put in the letter.  She would say that she had never
realized her own littleness so much as when she had her first glimpse of
the mountains, and she did not know that in reality she realized her own
superiority instead of her littleness.  They reached the hotel, and she was
shown to her room.  She felt a slight inward tremor, because she had
never been in a hotel before, but she fairly strutted across the office,
holding her bonneted head high, with her little checked shawl still over
her shoulders.  And she carried out her intention of slipping on her black
silk skirt and her white cambric sacque, in which to appear at supper.
But for the first time in her life Maria Gorham had an awed sensation as
she saw the other women sweep into the dining-room in evening gowns.
She looked around furtively, and she saw not another woman in a sacque.
But she was not easily daunted, not even when some other ladies in low
neck gowns seated themselves at her table, and she saw them looking
askance at her sacque.
</p><p>She ordered her supper with dignity, and ate it, and when she had
finished she marched stiffly the whole length of the dining-room.  They
had placed her at a table at the extreme end.  She heard furtive chuckles,
but she did not admit that they were laughing at her, Maria Gorham, and
that she did not still believe in her sacque and its entire appropriateness
to the occasion, and she would not weaken.  She went into the
music-room, and seated herself composedly and listened to the orchestra
and watched the young people dance.  When at last she went up to her
room, and divested herself of the sacque, she did not own that she would
not wear it again to supper while she was in the hotel.  Instead she hung
it up carefully with a little defiant air, under the cretonne curtain which
served in lieu of a closet on one side of the room.  "I don't care what
other folks wear, I rather think I have a right to wear anything I choose
which is tidy and comfortable," she told herself.  The next morning she
attired herself in the pink wrapper and went down to breakfast, and she
was soon aware that not another woman in the dining-room wore a
wrapper.  She became aware that furtive fun was made of her.  The
people in the hotel were, on the whole, a well bred and good-natured lot,
and were incapable of downright ridicule.  But now Maria Gorham's
spirit was up. Out on the verandah she went and walked up and down
holding up her wrapper daintily.  Then she sat down in one of the
verandah chairs, and watched people pass her with furtive stares at her
wrapper, and she felt fairly warlike.  She said to herself that she would
not persist in wearing the white cambric sacque to supper, since she had
not planned that, altho if there came a warm night when she did not feel
like putting on a tight dress she would wear it, but as for the wrapper she
would not give in one whit.  It was a pretty wrapper, and nicely made,
trimly belted with a pink ribbon.  She had intended to wear it mornings
during her stay at the hotel, and she would wear it.  And she did, but as
the time went on she suffered tortures.  Ridicule was the hardest thing in
the world for one of her kind to endure.  Open warfare would have been
more to her liking, but ridicule it was that she
    <pb entity="DSSR_000002603_0007" n="483"/>
had to prepare
herself for every morning, and ridicule the worse because it was covert
and could not be met with open resentment.  Several times in the evening
when she was wearing one of her best dresses, which somehow seemed
not so fine as she had thought them, she heard herself alluded to as the
woman who wore the wrapper mornings.  She knew that was the name
she went by, but the more she suffered the more obstinate she grew.  She
walked the verandah in her wrapper.  She even climbed a mountain, a
small one, marching to the summit as grimly and unflinchingly as the
youth in "Excelsior," holding up the wrapper carefully above her starched
petticoat.  She wore on that expedition her little bonnet with a small
black lace veil, and the black flies crawled under the veil and bit her
cruelly.  The next day her face was so swollen that she was obliged to
call in the hotel physician, and it was on that day that Mrs. Evans came in
the afternoon.  There was a gentle knock at Maria's door, and Maria said,
"Come in," and a woman as gentle as the knock entered, and asked if she
could not do something for her.  She had heard that she was ill.  Maria
answered her gratefully at first, then she caught a swift glance of the
other woman's eye at the pink wrapper, a fold of which obtruded from
behind the calico curtain, and she understood that this woman, sweet and
gentle and kind-hearted as she was, had looked upon her in the wrapper
as the others had.  Then she spoke grimly, altho grimness only lent
renewed absurdity to her distorted face.  "There is nothing you can do,
thank you," she said.  "I have had medical advice.  The "medical advice"
alone would have proclaimed her the school teacher.  The other woman
was rather persistent in her kindness, she offered to read to her, but Maria
refused more and more brusquely.  The woman went away, but soon she
sent by a bell boy a plate of grapes, having selected the choicest from
some which had been sent to her from New York.  "Now, she'll be
coming again," Maria said to herself, and she was right.  Next day Maria
was better, still her face was too badly swollen for her to leave her room,
and the woman came again. Even after she had quite recovered Maria
was liable to a call from her, altho she never encouraged it.  In fact, the
woman, who had an obtrusively benevolent heart, had set herself the task
of quietly leading up to the wrapper.  She had talked it over with some
other ladies, and they had agreed that it was a shame that a woman as
good as Maria seemed to be should make herself so ridiculous.  But the
other ladies had not the spirit of this one.  "I am going to tell her," said
she, and she did about a week after she had first spoken to her.  The
woman was calling upon Maria one morning and Maria was wearing the
wrapper, and the woman spoke out with exceeding sweetness, which still
had a sting in it.  "What a lovely wrapper that is you are wearing," said
the woman.
</p><p>Maria's face changed.  She looked at her suspiciously, altho she
answered with dignity.  "Thank you!" she said.
</p><p>"What a pity it is that wrappers, no matter how pretty they are, are
not worn in large hotels," said the woman.  Then her face colored
piteously before the indignation in Maria's.  "It does not make the
slightest difference to me what is worn in hotels, or is not worn in
hotels," said Maria, sternly.  "I wear whatever I please as long as it is tidy
and respectable."
</p><p>Tears actually sprang into the other woman's eyes.  "Oh, dear, I am
so sorry you take it so!" said she.  "I meant well.  It was only because I
hated to have&mdash;" She paused.
</p><p>"Hated to have what?" asked Maria, pitilessly.
</p><p>"Hated to have you made fun of," almost sobbed the other woman.
</p><p>"If I am not made fun of for anything worse than wearing a wrapper
in the morning, it does not worry me at all," said Maria, with her head up
in the air.
</p><p>The other woman rose.  "Well, I meant it kindly, and I am going
away in the morning," said she.
</p><p>"Oh, I am not at all offended!" said Maria, in a somewhat softer
voice, "and I thank you for your interest, but I do not allow even my
dearest friends to interfere in matters so purely personal as my attire."
</p><p>The next morning Maria in her wrapper shook hands with the other
woman,
    <pb entity="DSSR_000002603_0008" n="484"/>
as she went out of the hotel on her way to the train.  "I
do hope you don't lay up anything against me," said the other woman.
</p><p>"Not at all," said Maria, briskly and kindly.  Then the woman went
her way.  She was the only one of the guests who had spoken to Maria,
and she had been in the hotel two weeks.  Nobody at all spoke to her
during the remaining two weeks of her stay.  Maria was, on the whole,
more lonely than she had ever been in her life, and she did more thinking.
She thought a good deal about Dexter Ray.  She thought how if she had a
husband with her like many of the other women she would not have felt
so defenseless and isolated in her wrapper, which she had begun to
regard as a matter of principle.  She felt sure that Dexter would admire
the wrapper.  She could see just the kindly, worshipful expression that
would come into his brown eyes at the sight of her in it.  She recalled
how Emma had believed in the wrapper.  She began to reflect as she had
never done on the pettiness and worthlessness of externals.  She wished
she could see Emma, and hear her talk in her bad English.  She began to
understand that the bad English might be very much like the wrapper,
something beneath a loving soul to notice, if the heart of the speaker
were right.  She remembered how very plain Dexter Ray was, and how
clumsy, and how he talked just as Emma did, and it all seemed to her
like the wrapper and the cambric sacque, something for people who had
not love and appreciation in their hearts to make fun of, but nothing of
any consequence to those who could see what was underneath; the
honesty, and the affection, and the faithfulness.  Two days before Maria
went home she wrote to Emma Ray, and told her when she was coming,
and asked her and her brother to come in and spend the next evening
with her.  Maria was pale when she posted the letter in the little hotel
office.  She had never asked Dexter to spend the evening with her before,
and she knew what it would mean.  Emma Ray, when she got the letter
the day before Maria's return, read it aloud to Dexter.  When Emma read
that Maria would like to have them both come in and spend the evening
the brother and sister looked at each other.  Dexter's homely, faithful face
flushed, then turned very pale.  Emma gazed at him with the sympathy of
a mother, rather than of a sister.  Nobody knew how she had pitied him,
and how hard she had tried to help him.  She smiled with the loveliest
unselfishness, then she looked again at the letter in her hand.  "Guess
Maria has been eatin' humble pie," she thought to herself, then she
reflected how much she thought of Maria, and her brother, and how
glad she was.  "Well, I guess Maria thinks that the old friends that have
always set store by her are the best after all," she said, and a moral
perfume, as of the sweetness of humility itself, seemed to come in her
face from the letter.</p>

<closer>
<dateline>METUCHEN, N. J.</dateline>
</closer>


</div1>
</body>
</text>
</TEI.2>


