<?xml version="1.0"?>

<?dlps id="JewDark"?>
<?dlps page-images="color" figure-images="yes"?>
<?dlps transcription="other"?>

<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/tei-p4/tei2.dtd" [
<!ENTITY % POSTKB "INCLUDE">
<!ENTITY % TEI.extensions.ent SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.ent">
<!ENTITY % TEI.extensions.dtd SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.dtd">
<!ENTITY % ISOpub SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/charent/iso-pub.ent"> %ISOpub;



<!ENTITY DSSR_000002647_0001 SYSTEM "000002647_0001" NDATA uvaHighRes>
<!ENTITY DSSR_000002647_0002 SYSTEM "000002647_0002" NDATA uvaHighRes>
<!ENTITY DSSR_000002647_0003 SYSTEM "000002647_0003" NDATA uvaHighRes>
<!ENTITY DSSR_000002647_0004 SYSTEM "000002647_0004" NDATA uvaHighRes>
<!ENTITY DSSR_000002647_0005 SYSTEM "000002647_0005" NDATA uvaHighRes>
<!ENTITY DSSR_000002647_0006 SYSTEM "000002647_0006" NDATA uvaHighRes>
<!ENTITY DSSR_000002647_0007 SYSTEM "000002647_0007" NDATA uvaHighRes>
<!ENTITY DSSR_000002647_0008 SYSTEM "000002647_0008" NDATA uvaHighRes>
<!ENTITY DSSR_000002647_0009 SYSTEM "000002647_0009" NDATA uvaHighRes>
<!ENTITY DSSR_000002647_0010 SYSTEM "000002647_0010" NDATA uvaHighRes>
]>


<TEI.2 id="JewDark">
<teiHeader type="migrated" creator="Etext">
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title type="main">In Dark New England Days</title>
<title type="sort">in dark new england days</title>
<author>Jewett, Sarah Orne</author>
<respStmt>
<resp>Creation of machine-readable version</resp>
<name>Judy Boss, University of Omaha</name>
<resp>Conversion to TEI-conformant markup</resp>
<name>University of Virginia Library Electronic Text Center</name>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt>
<extent>ca. <num type="kilobytes">46</num> kilobytes</extent>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>University of Virginia Library</publisher>
<pubPlace>Charlottesville, Virginia</pubPlace>
<idno type="ETC">JewDark</idno>
<date value="1994">1994</date>
<availability status="public">
<p n="copyright">Copyright &#xa9; 1994 by the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia</p>
<p n="access">Publicly accessible</p>
</availability>
<idno type="uva-pid">uva-lib:477082</idno>
</publicationStmt>
<seriesStmt>
<title>University of Virginia Library, Text collection</title>
<idno type="uva-set">UVA-LIB-Text</idno>
</seriesStmt>
<notesStmt>
<note>
<p>Illustrations have been included from the print version</p>
</note>
</notesStmt>
<sourceDesc>
<biblFull>
<titleStmt>
<title type="main">In Dark New England Days</title>
<title type="sort">in dark new england days</title>
<author>Sarah Orne Jewett</author>
<respStmt>
<resp>Illustrator</resp>
<name>E. W. Kemble</name>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>The Century Company</publisher>
<pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
<date value="1890-10">October 1890</date>
</publicationStmt>
<seriesStmt>
<p>Century Illustrated Monthly Magazine, XL, No. 6</p>
</seriesStmt>
</biblFull>
</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc>
<encodingDesc>
<projectDesc>
<p>Prepared for the University of Virginia Library ElectronicText Center</p>
</projectDesc>
<editorialDecl>
<p>All quotation marks retained as data</p>
<p>All unambiguous end-of-line hyphens have been removed, and the
trailing part of a word has been joined to the preceding
line.</p>
<p id="ETC">Keywords in the header are a local Electronic Text
Center scheme to aid in establishing analytical groupings</p>
</editorialDecl>
<refsDecl>
<p>ID elements are given for each page element and are composedof the text's
unique cryptogram and the given page number, as in SpeFQue1 for page one of
Spenser's Faerie Queene.</p>
</refsDecl>
</encodingDesc>
<profileDesc>
<creation>
<date value="1890-10">October 1890</date>
</creation>
<langUsage>
<language id="eng" usage="main">English</language>
</langUsage>
<textClass>
<keywords>
<term>fiction; prose</term>
</keywords>
</textClass>
</profileDesc>
<revisionDesc>
<change>
<date value="1994-10">October 1994</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>corrector</resp>
<name>Bryson Clevenger Jr.</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Created header.  Paginated according to printed text.
Scanned images from printed text. Spellchecked against original
printed text. Cleaned ambiguous end of line hyphens. Retagged
italics.</item>
</change>
<change>
<date value="2005-07">July 2005</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>Corrector</resp>
<name>John Ivor Carlson</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Converted to XML and/or checked tags.</item>
</change>
<change>
<date value="2007-09">September 2007</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>Migration</resp>
<name>Ethan Gruber, University of Virginia Library</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Converted XML markup from TEI Lite to uva-dl-tei (TEI P4 with local customizations).</item>
</change>
<change>
<date value="2008-01">January 2008</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>Migration</resp>
<name>Greg Murray, University of Virginia Library</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Programmatically updated TEI header markup (but not header content) for minimal compliance with current QA requirements.</item>
</change>
<change>
<date value="2009-03">March 2009</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>Migration</resp>
<name>Scholarly Resources, University of Virginia Library</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Added and/or replaced the digital images accompanying the electronic text. Scanning of exterior and interior (ie. pages) of item was done only for items found in the University of Virginia Special Collections Library.</item>
</change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

 <text id="d1">
<body id="d2">
<div1 type="section" n="1" id="d3">
 <pb entity="DSSR_000002647_0001" n="911"/>
<head>IN DARK NEW ENGLAND DAYS.</head>
<p>
THE last of the neighbors was going home; officious Mrs. Peter
Downs had lingered late and sought for additional housework with
which to prolong her stay.  She had talked incessantly, and
buzzed like a busy bee as she helped to put away the best
crockery after the funeral supper, while the sisters Betsey and
Hannah Knowles grew every moment more forbidding and unwilling to
speak.  They lighted a solitary small oil lamp at last as if for
Sunday evening idleness, and put it on the side table in the
kitchen.
</p><p>"We ain't intending to make a late evening of it,"
announced Betsey, the elder, standing before Mrs. Downs in an
expectant,
final way, making an irresistible opportunity for saying
goodnight.  "I'm sure we're more
than obleeged to ye,&mdash;ain't we, Hannah?&mdash;but I don't feel 's if
we ought to keep ye longer.
We
ain't going to do no more to-night, but set down a spell and kind
of collect ourselves, and then make for bed."
</p><p>Susan Downs offered one more plea.  "I'd stop all night
with
ye an' welcome; 'tis gettin' late&mdash;an' dark," she added
plaintively; but the sisters shook their heads quickly, and
Hannah
said that they might as well get used to staying alone, since
they
would have to do it first or last.  In spite of herself Mrs.
Downs
was obliged to put on her funeral best bonnet and shawl and start
on her homeward way.
</p><p>"Close-mouthed old maids!" she grumbled as the door shut
behind her all too soon and denied her the light of the lamp
along
the footpath.  Suddenly there was a bright ray from the window,
as
if some one had pushed back the curtain and stood with the lamp
close to the sash.  "That's Hannah," said the retreating guest.
"She'd told me somethin' about things, I know, if it hadn't 'a'
been for Betsey.  Catch me workin' myself to pieces again for
'em."
But, however grudgingly this was said, Mrs. Downs's conscience
told
her that the industry of the past two days had been somewhat
selfish on her part; she had hoped that in the excitement of this
unexpected funeral season she might for once be taken into the
sisters' confidence.  More than this, she knew that they were
certain of her motive, and had 
 
 <pb entity="DSSR_000002647_0002" n="912"/>  
 deliberately refused the expected satisfaction.  "'Tain't as if I was one o' them curious
busybodies anyway," she said to herself pityingly; "they might
'a'
neighbored with somebody for once, I do believe."  Everybody
would
have a question ready for her the next day, for it was known that
she had been slaving herself devotedly since the news had come of
old Captain Knowles's sudden death in his bed from a stroke, the
last of three which had in the course of a year or two changed
him
from a strong old man to a feeble, chair-bound cripple.
</p><p>Mrs. Downs stepped bravely along the dark country road;
she
could see a light in her own kitchen window half a mile away, and
did not stop to notice either the penetrating dampness or the
shadowy woods at her right.  It was a cloudy night, but there was
a dim light over the open fields.  She had a disposition of mind
towards the exciting circumstances of death and burial, and was
in
request at such times among her neighbors; in this she was like a
city person who prefers tragedy to comedy, but not having the
semblance within her reach, she made the most of looking on at
real
griefs and departures.
</p><p>Some one was walking towards her in the road; suddenly she
heard footsteps.  The figure stopped, then came forward again.
</p><p>"Oh, 'tis you, ain't it?" with a tone of disappointment.
"I
cal'lated you'd stop all night, 't had got to be so late, an' I
was
just going over to the Knowles gals'; well, to kind o' ask how
they
be, an'&mdash;"  Mr. Peter Downs was evidently counting on his visit.
</p><p>"They never passed me the compliment," replied his wife.
"I
declare I didn't covet the walk home; I'm 'most beat out, bein'
on
foot so much.  I was 'most put out with 'em for lettin' of me see
quite so plain that my room was better than my company.  But I
don'
know's I blame 'em; they want to look an' see what they've got,
an'
kind of git by their selves, I expect.  'Twas natural."
</p><p>"Mrs. Downs knew that her husband would resent her first
statements, being a sensitive and grumbling man.  She had formed
a
pacific habit of suiting her remarks to his point of view to save
an outburst.  He contented himself with calling the Knowles girls
hoggish, and put a direct question as to whether they had let
fall
any words about their situation, but Martha Downs was obliged to
answer in the negative.
</p><p>"Was Enoch Holt there after the folks come back from the
grave?"
</p><p>"He wa'n't; they never give him no encouragement neither."
</p><p>"He appeared well, I must say," continued Peter Downs.
"He
took his place next but one behind us in the procession, 'long of
Melinda Dutch, an' walked to an' from with her, give her his arm,
and then I never see him after we got back; but I thought he
might
be somewhere in the house, an' I was out about the barn an' so
on."
</p><p>"They was civil to him.  I was by when he come, just
steppin'
out of the bedroom after we'd finished layin' the old Cap'n into
his coffin.  Hannah looked real pleased when she see Enoch, as if
she hadn't reelly expected him, but Betsey stuck out her hand 's
if
'twas an eend o' board, an' drawed her face solemner 'n ever.
There, they had natural feelin's.  He was their own father when
all
was said, the Cap'n was, an' I don't know but he was clever to
'em
in his way, 'ceptin' when he disappointed Hannah about her
marryin'
Jake Good'in.  She l'arned to respect the old Cap'n's foresight,
too."
</p><p>"Sakes alive, Marthy, how you do knock folks down with one
hand an' set 'em up with t'other," chuckled Mr. Downs.  They next
discussed the Captain's appearance as he lay in state in the
front
room, a subject which, with its endless ramifications, would keep
the whole neighborhood interested for weeks to come.
</p><p>An hour later the twinkling light in the Downs house
suddenly
disappeared.  As Martha Downs took a last look out of doors
through
her bedroom window she could see no other light; the neighbors
had
all gone to bed.  It was a little past nine, and the night was
damp
and still.</p>
</div1>
<div1 type="section" n="2" id="d4">
<head>II.</head>

<p>THE Captain Knowles place was eastward from the Downs', and a
short turn in the road and the piece of hard-wood growth hid one
house from the other.  At this unwontedly late hour the elderly
sisters were still sitting in their warm kitchen; there were
bright
coals under the singing tea-kettle which hung from the crane by
three or four long pothooks.  Betsey Knowles objected when her
sister offered to put on more wood.
</p><p>"Father never liked to leave no great of a fire, even
though
he slept right here in the bedroom.  He said this floor was one
that would light an' catch easy, you r'member."
</p><p>"Another winter we can move down and take the bedroom
ourselves&mdash;'twill be warmer for us," suggested Hannah; but Betsey
shook her head doubtfully.  The thought of their old father's
grave, unwatched and undefended in the outermost dark field,
filled
their hearts with a strange tenderness.  They had been his
dutiful,
patient slaves, and it seemed like disloyalty to have abandoned
the
poor shape, to be sitting there disregarding the thousand
requirements
 
 <pb entity="DSSR_000002647_0003" n="913"/>
and services of the past.  More than all, they were facing a free
future; they were their own
mistresses at last, though past sixty years of age.  Hannah was
still a child at heart.
She chased away a dread suspicion, when Betsey forbade the wood,
lest this elder sister, who favored their father's looks, might
take his place as stern ruler of the household.
</p><p>"Betsey," said the younger sister suddenly, "we'll have us
a
cook stove, won't we, next winter?  I expect we're going to have
something to do with?"
</p><p>Betsey did not answer; it was impossible to say whether
she
truly felt grief or only assumed it.  She had been sober and
silent
for the most part since she routed neighbor Downs, though she
answered her sister's prattling questions with patience and
sympathy.  Now she rose from her chair and went to one of the
windows, and, pushing back the sash curtain, pulled the wooden
shutter across and hasped it.
</p><p>"I ain't going to bed just yet," she explained.  "I've
been a-waiting to make sure
nobody
was coming in.  I don't
know 's there'll be any better time to look in the chest and see
what we've
got to depend on.  We never'll get no chance to do it by day."
</p><p>Hannah looked frightened for a moment, then nodded, and
turned
to the opposite window and pulled that shutter with much
difficulty; it had always caught and hitched and been
provoking&mdash;a
warped piece of red oak, when even-grained white pine would have
saved strength and patience to three generations of the Knowles
race.  Then the sisters crossed the kitchen and opened the
bedroom
door.  Hannah shivered a little as the colder air struck her, and
her heart beat loudly.  Perhaps it was the same with Betsey.
</p><p>The bedroom was clean and orderly for the funeral guests.
Instead of the blue homespun there was a beautifully quilted
white
coverlet which had been part of their mother's wedding
furnishing,
and this made the bedstead with its four low posts look
unfamiliar
and awesome.  The lamplight shone through the kitchen door behind
them, not very bright at best, but Betsey reached under the bed,
and with all the strength she could muster pulled out the end of
a
great sea chest.  The sisters tugged together and pushed, and
made
the most of their strength before they finally brought it through
the narrow door into the kitchen.  The solemnity of the deed made
them both whisper as they talked, and Hannah did not dare say
what
was in her timid heart&mdash;that she would rather brave discovery by
daylight than such a feeling of being disapprovingly watched now
in
the dead of night.  There came a slight sound outside the house
which made her look anxiously at Betsey, but Betsey remained
tranquil.
</p><p>"It's nothing but a stick falling down the woodpile," she
answered in a contemptuous whisper, and the younger woman was
reassured.
</p><p>Betsey reached deep into her pocket and found a great key
which was worn smooth and bright like silver, and never had been
trusted willingly into even her own safe hands.  Hannah held the
lamp, and the two thin figures bent eagerly over the lid as it
opened.  Their shadows were waving about the low walls, and
looked
like strange shapes bowing and dancing behind them.
</p><p>The chest was stoutly timbered, as if it was built in some
ship-yard, and there were heavy wrought-iron hinges and a large
escutcheon for the keyhole that the ship's blacksmith might have
hammered out.  On the top somebody had scratched deeply the
crossed
lines for a game of fox and geese, and this had a trivial,
irreverent look, and might have been the unforgiven fault of some
idle ship's boy.  The sisters had hardly dared look at the chest
or
to signify their knowledge of its existence at unwary times.
They
had swept carefully about it year after year, and wondered if it
was indeed full of gold as the neighbors used to hint; but no
matter how much found a way in, little had found the way out.
They
had been hampered all their lives for money, and in consequence
had
developed a wonderful facility for spinning and weaving, mending
and making.  Their small farm was an early example of intensive
farming; they were allowed to use its products in a niggardly
way,
but the money that was paid for wool, for hay, for wood, and for
summer crops had all gone into the chest.  The old captain was a
hard master; he rarely commended and often blamed.  Hannah
trembled
before him, but Betsey faced him sturdily, being amazingly like
him, with a feminine difference; as like as a ruled person can be
to a ruler, for the discipline of life had taught the man to
aggress, the woman only to defend.  In the chest was a fabled sum
of prize-money, besides these slender earnings of many years; all
the sisters' hard work and self-sacrifice were there in money and
a mysterious largess besides.  All their lives they had been
looking forward to this hour of ownership.
</p><p>There was a solemn hush in the house; the two sisters were
safe from their neighbors, and there was no fear of interruption
at
such an hour in that hard-working community, tired with a day's
work that had been early begun.  If any one came knocking at the
door, both door and windows were securely fastened.
</p><p>The eager sisters bent above the chest, they held their
breath
and talked in softest whispers.
 <pb entity="DSSR_000002647_0004" n="914"/>   
 With stealthy tread a man came out of the woods near by.
</p><p>He stopped to listen, came nearer, stopped again, and then
crept close to the old house.  He stepped up on the banking, next
the window with the warped shutter; there was a knothole in it
high
above the women's heads, towards the top.  As they leaned over
the
chest an eager eye watched them.  If they had turned that way
suspiciously the eye might have caught the flicker of the lamp
and
betrayed itself.  No, they were too busy: the eye at the shutter
watched and watched.
</p><p>There was a certain feeling of relief in the sisters'
minds
because the contents of the chest were so commonplace at first
sight.  There were some old belongings dating back to their
father's early days of seafaring.  They unfolded a waistcoat
pattern or two of figured stuff which they had seen him fold and
put away again and again.  Once he had given Betsey a gay China
silk handkerchief, and here were two more like it.  They had not
known what a store of treasures might be waiting for them, but
the
reality so far was disappointing; there was much spare room to
begin with, and the wares within looked pinched and few.  There
were bundles of papers, old receipts, some letters in two not
very
thick bundles, some old account books with worn edges, and a
blackened silver can which looked very small in comparison with
their anticipation, being an heirloom and jealously hoarded and
secreted by the old man.  The women began to feel as if his lean,
angry figure were bending with them over the sea chest.
</p><p>They opened a package done up in many layers of old soft
paper&mdash;a worked piece of Indian muslin, and an embroidered scarf
which they had never seen before.  "He must have brought them
home
to mother," said Betsey with a great outburst of feeling.  "He
never was the same man again; he never would let nobody else have
them when he found she was dead, poor old father!"
</p><p>Hannah looked wistfully at the treasures.  She rebuked
herself
for selfishness, but she thought of her pinched girlhood and the
delight these things would have been.  Ah yes! it was too late
now
for many things besides the sprigged muslin.  "If I was young as
I
was once there's lots o' things I'd like to do now I'm free,"
said
Hannah with a gentle sigh; but her sister checked her
anxiously&mdash;it
was fitting that they should preserve a semblance of mourning
even
to themselves.
</p><p>The lamp stood in a kitchen chair at the chest's end and
shone
full across their faces.  Betsey looked intent and sober as she
turned over the old man's treasures.  Under the India mull was an
antique pair of buff trousers, a waistcoat of strange
old-fashioned
foreign stuff, and a blue coat with brass buttons, brought home
from over seas, as the women knew, for their father's wedding
clothes.  They had seen him carry them out at long intervals to
hang them in the spring sunshine; he had been very feeble the
last
time, and Hannah remembered that she had longed to take them from
his shaking hands.
</p><p>"I declare for 't, I wish't we had laid him out in 'em,
'stead
o' the robe," she whispered; but Betsey made no answer.  She was
kneeling still, but held herself upright and looked away.  It was
evident that she was lost in her own thoughts.
</p><p>"I can't find nothing else by eyesight," she muttered.
"This
chest never'd be so heavy with them old clothes.  Stop!  Hold
that
light down, Hannah; there's a place underneath here.  Them papers
in the till takes a shallow part.  Oh, my gracious!  See here,
will
ye?  Hold the light, hold the light!"
</p><p>There was a hidden drawer in the chest's side&mdash;a long,
deep
place, and it was full of gold pieces.  Hannah had seated herself
in the chair to be out of her sister's way.  She held the lamp
with
one hand and gathered her apron on her lap with the other, while
Betsey, exultant and hawk-eyed, took out handful after handful of
heavy coins, letting them jingle and chink, letting them shine in
the lamp's rays, letting them roll across the floor&mdash;guineas,
dollars, doubloons, old French and Spanish and English gold!
</p><p><hi rend="italic">Now, now!  Look!  The eye at the window!</hi>
</p><p>At last they have found it all; the bag of silver, the
great
roll of bank bills, and the heavy weight of gold&mdash;the prize-money
that had been like Robinson Crusoe's in the cave.  They were rich
women that night; their faces grew young again as they sat side
by
side and exulted while the old kitchen grew cold.  There was
nothing they might not do within the range of their timid
ambitions; they were women of fortune now and their own
mistresses.
They were beginning at last to live.
</p><p>The watcher outside was cramped and chilled.  He let
himself
down softly from the high step of the winter banking and crept
towards the barn, where he might bury himself in the hay and
think.
His fingers were quick to find the peg that opened the little
barn
door; the beasts within were startled and stumbled to their feet,
then went back to their slumbers.  The night wore on; the light
spring rain began to fall, and the sound of it on the house roof
close down upon the sisters' bed lulled them quickly to sleep.
Twelve, one, two o'clock passed by.
</p><p>They had put back the money and the clothes and the minor
goods and treasures 
 <pb entity="DSSR_000002647_0005" n="915"/>  
 and pulled the chest back into the
bedroom so that it was out of sight from the kitchen; the bedroom
door was always shut by day.  The younger sister wished to carry
the money to their own room, but Betsey disdained such
precaution.
The money had always been safe in the old chest, and there it
should stay.  The next week they would go to Riverport and put it
into the bank; it was no use to lose the interest any longer.
Because their father had lost some invested money in his early
youth it did not follow that every bank was faithless.  Betsey's
self-assertion was amazing, but they still whispered to each
other
as they got ready for bed.  With strange forgetfulness Betsey had
laid the chest key on the white coverlet in the bedroom and left
it
there.</p></div1>
<div1 type="section" n="3" id="d5">
<head>III.</head>

<p>IN August of that year the whole country side turned out to go
to court.
</p><p>The sisters had been rich for one night; in the morning
they
waked to find themselves poor with a bitter pang of poverty of
which they had never dreamed.  They had said little, but they
grew
suddenly pinched and old.  They could not tell how much money
they
had lost, except that Hannah's lap was full of gold, a weight she
could not lift nor carry.  After a few days of stolid misery they
had gone to the chief lawyer of their neighborhood to accuse
Enoch
Holt of the robbery.  They dressed in their best and walked
solemnly side by side across the fields and along the road, the
shortest way to the man of law.  Enoch Holt's daughter saw them
go
as she stood in her doorway and felt a cold shiver run through
her
frame as if in foreboding.  Her father was not at home; he had
left
for Boston late on the afternoon of Captain Knowles's funeral.
He
had had notice the day before of the coming in of a ship in which
he owned a thirty-second; there was talk of selling the ship, and
the owners' agent had summoned him.  He had taken pains to go to
the funeral because he and the old captain had been on bad terms
ever since they had bought a piece of woodland together and the
captain declared himself wronged at the settling of accounts.  He
was growing feeble even then, and had left the business to the
younger man.  Enoch Holt was not a trusted man, yet he had never
before been openly accused of dishonesty.  He was not a professor
of religion, but foremost on the secular side of church matters.
Most of the men in that region were hard men; it was difficult to
get money, and there was little real comfort in a community where
the sterner, stingier, forbidding side of New England life was
well
exemplified.
</p><p>The proper steps had been taken by the officers of the
law,
and in answer to the writ Enoch Holt appeared, much shocked and
very indignant, and was released on bail which covered the sum
his
shipping interest had brought him.  The weeks had dragged by,
June
and July were long in passing, and here was court day at last,
and
all the townsfolk hastening by high-roads and by-roads to the
court-house.  The Knowles girls themselves had risen at break of
day and walked the distance steadfastly, like two of the three
Fates: who would make the third, to cut the thread for their
enemy's disaster?  Public opinion was divided.  There were many
voices ready to speak on the accused man's side; a sharp-looking
acquaintance left his business in Boston to swear that Holt was
in
his office before noon on the day following the robbery, and that
he had spent most of the night in Boston, as proved by several
minor details of their interview.  As for Holt's young married
daughter, she was a favorite with the townsfolk, and her husband
was away at sea overdue these last few weeks.  She sat on one of
the hard court benches with a young child in her arms, born since
its father sailed; they had been more or less unlucky, the Holt
family, though Enoch himself was a man of brag and bluster.
</p><p>All the hot August morning until the noon recess, and all
the
hot August afternoon, fly teased and wretched with the heavy air,
the crowd of neighbors listened to the trial.  There was not much
evidence brought; everybody knew that Enoch Holt left the funeral
procession hurriedly and went away on horseback towards Boston.
His daughter knew no more than this.  The Boston man gave his
testimony impatiently, and one or two persons insisted that they
saw the accused on his way at nightfall several miles from home.
</p><p>As the testimony came out it all tended to prove his
innocence, though public opinion was to the contrary.  The
Knowles
sisters looked more stern and gray hour by hour; their vengeance
was not to be satisfied; their accusation had been listened to
and
found wanting, but their instinctive knowledge of the matter
counted for nothing.  They must have been watched through the
knothole of the shutter; nobody had noticed it until some years
before Enoch Holt himself had spoken of the light's shining
through
on a winter's night as he came towards the house.  The chief
proof
was that nobody else could have done the deed.  But why linger
over
<hi rend="italic">pros</hi> and <hi rend="italic">cons?</hi>  The jury returned directly with a
verdict
of "not proven," and the tired audience left the court-house.
</p><p>But not until Hannah Knowles with angry eyes had risen to
her feet. 
 
 <pb entity="DSSR_000002647_0006" n="916"/>
</p><p>The sterner elder sister tried to pull her back; every one
said that they should have looked to Betsey to say the awful
words
that followed, not to her gentler companion.  It was Hannah,
broken
and disappointed, who cried in a strange high voice as Enoch Holt
was passing by without a look:
</p><p>"You stole it, you thief!  You know it in your heart!"
</p><p>The startled man faltered, then he faced the women.  The
people who stood near seemed made of eyes as they stared to see
what he would say.
</p><p>"I swear by my right hand I never touched it."
</p><p>"Curse your right hand then!" cried Hannah Knowles,
growing
tall and thin like a white flame drawing upward.  "Curse your
right
hand, yours and all your folks' that follow you!  May I live to
see
the day!"
</p><p>The people drew back while for a moment accused and
accuser
stood face to face.  Then Holt's flushed face turned white, and
he
shrank from the fire in those wild eyes, and walked away clumsily
down the court-room.  Nobody followed him, nobody shook hands
with
him or told the acquitted man that they were glad of his release.

Half an hour later Betsey and Hannah Knowles took their homeward
way, to begin their hard round of work again.  The horizon that
had
widened with such glory for one night had closed round them again
like an iron wall.
</p><p>Betsey was alarmed and excited by her sister's
uncharacteristic behavior, and she looked at her anxiously from
time to time.  Hannah had become the harder-faced of the two.
Her
disappointment was the keener, for she had kept more of the
unsatisfied desires of her girlhood until that dreary morning
when
they found the sea chest rifled and the treasure gone.
</p><p>Betsey said inconsequently that it was a pity she did not
have
that black silk gown that would stand alone.  They had planned
for
it over the open chest, and Hannah's was to be a handsome green.
They might have worn them to court.  But even the pathetic
facetiousness of her elder sister did not bring a smile to Hannah
Knowles's face, and the next day one was at the loom and the
other
at the wheel again.  The neighbors talked about the curse with
horror; in their minds a fabric of sad fate was spun from the
bitter words.
</p><p>The Knowles sisters never had worn silk gowns and they
never
would.  Sometimes Hannah or Betsey would stealthily look over the
chest in one or the other's absence.  One day when Betsey was
very
old and her mind had grown feeble she tied her own India silk
handkerchief about her neck, but they never used the other two.
They aired the wedding suit once every spring as long as they
lived.  They were both too old and forlorn to make up the India
mull.  Nobody knows how many times they took everything out of
the
heavy old clamped box and peered into every nook and corner to
see
if there was not a single gold piece left.  They never answered
any
one who made bold to speak of their misfortune.
</p></div1>
<div1 type="section" n="4" id="d6">
<head>IV.</head>

<p>ENOCH HOLT had been a seafaring man in his early days, and
there was news that the owners of a Salem ship in which he held a
small interest wished him to go out as supercargo.  He was brisk
and well in health, and his son-in-law, an honest but an unlucky
fellow, had done less well than usual, so that nobody was
surprised
when Enoch made ready for his voyage.  It was nearly a year after
the theft, and nothing had come so near to restoring him to
public
favor as his apparent lack of ready money.  He openly said that
he
put great hope in his adventure to the Spice Islands, and when he
said farewell one Sunday to some members of the dispersing
congregation more than one person wished him heartily a pleasant
voyage and safe return.  He had an insinuating tone of voice and
an
imploring look that day, and this fact, with his probable long
absence and the dangers of the deep, won him much sympathy.  It
is
a shameful thing to accuse a man wrongfully, and Enoch Holt had
behaved well since the trial; and, what is more, had shown no
accession to his means of living.  So away he went with a far
amount of good wishes, though one or two persons assured
remonstrating listeners that they thought it likely Enoch would
make a good voyage, better than common, and show himself
forwarded
when he came to port.  Soon after his departure Mrs. Peter Downs
and an intimate acquaintance discussed the ever-exciting subject
of
the Knowles robbery over a friendly cup of tea.
</p><p>They were in the Downs kitchen and quite by themselves.
Peter
Downs himself had been drawn as a juror, and had been for two
days
at the county town.  Mrs. Downs was giving herself to social
interests in his absence, and Mrs. Forder, an asthmatic but very
companionable person, had arrived by two o'clock that afternoon
with her knitting work, sure of being welcome.  The two old
friends
had first talked over varied subjects of immediate concern, but
when supper was nearly finished they fell back upon the lost
Knowles gold, as has been already said.
</p><p>"They got a dreadful blow, poor gals," wheezed Mrs. Forder
with compassion.  "'Twas harder for them than for most folks;

<pb entity="DSSR_000002647_0007" n="917"/> 
 they'd had a long stent with the ol' gentleman; very
arbitrary, very arbitrary."
</p><p>"Yes," answered Mrs. Downs, pushing back her tea-cup, then
lifting it again to see if it was quite empty.  "Yes, it took
holt
o' Hannah the most.  I should 'a' said Betsey was a good deal the
most set in her ways an' would 'a' been most tore up, but
'twa'n't
so."
</p><p>"Lucky that Holt's folks sets on the other aisle in the
meetin' house, I do consider, so 't they needn't face each other
sure as Sabbath comes round."
</p><p>"I see Hannah an' him come face to face two Sabbaths afore
Enoch left.  So happened he dallied to have a word 'long o'
Deacon
Good'in, an' him an' Hannah stepped front of each other 'fore
they
knowed what they's about.  I sh'd thought her eyes'd looked right
through him.  No one of 'em took the word; Enoch he slinked off
pretty quick."
</p><p>"I see 'em too," said Mrs. Forder; "made my blood run
cold."
</p><p>"Nothin' ain't come of the curse yit,"&mdash;Mrs. Downs lowered
the
tone of her voice,&mdash;"least, folks says so.  It kind o' worries
pore
Phoebe Holt&mdash;Miss Dow, I would say.  She was narved all up at the
time o' the trial, an' when her next baby come into the world
first
thin' she made out t' ask me was whether it seemed likely, an'
she
gived me a pleadin' look as if I'd got to tell her what she
hadn't
heart to ask.  'Yes, dear,' says I, 'put up his little hands to
me
kind of wonted'; an' she turned a look on me like another
creatur',
so pleased an' contented."
</p><p>"I s'pose you don't see no great of the Knowles gals?"
inquired Mrs. Forder, who lived two miles away in the other
direction.
</p><p>"They stepped to the door yisterday when I was passin' by,
and
I went in an' set a spell long of 'em," replied the hostess.
"They'd got pestered with that ol' loom o' theirn.  'Fore I
thought, says I, ''Tis all worn out, Betsey,' says I; 'why on
airth
don't ye git somebody to git some o' your own wood an' season it
well so 'twon't warp, same's mine done, an' build ye a new one?'
But Betsey muttered an' twitched away; 'twa'n't like her, but
they're dis'p'inted at every turn, I s'pose, an' feel poor where
they've got the same 's ever to do with.  Hannah's a-coughin'
this
spring 's if somethin' ailed her.  I asked her if she had bad
feelin's in her pipes, an' she said yis, she had, but not to
speak
of 't before Betsey.  I'm goin' to fix her up some hoarhound an'
elecampane quick 's the ground's nice an' warm an' roots livens
up
a grain more.  They're limp an' wizened 'long to the fust of the
spring.  Them would be service'ble, simmered away to a syrup
'long
o' molasses; now don't you think so, Miss Forder?"
</p><p>"Excellent," replied the wheezing dame.  "I covet a
portion
myself, now you speak.  Nothin' cures my complaint, but a new
remedy takes holt clever sometimes, an' eases me for a spell."
And
she gave a plaintive sigh, and began to knit again.
</p><p>Mrs. Downs rose and pushed the supper table to the wall
and
drew her chair nearer to the stove.  The April nights were
chilly.
</p><p>"The folks is late comin' after me," said Mrs. Forder,
ostentatiously.  "I may's well confess that I told 'em if they
was
late with the work they might let go o' fetchin' o' me an' I'd
walk
home in the mornin'; take it easy when I was fresh.  Course I
mean
ef 'twouldn't put you out: I knowed you was all alone, an' I kind
o' wanted a change."
</p><p>"Them words was in my mind to utter while we was to
table,"
avowed Mrs. Downs, hospitably.  "I ain't reelly afeared, but 'tis
sort o' creepy fastenin' up an' goin' to bed alone.  Nobody can't
help hearkin', an' every common noise starts you.  I never used
to
give nothin' a thought till the Knowleses was robbed, though."
</p><p>"'Twas mysterious, I do maintain," acknowledged Mrs.
Forder.
"Comes over me 
 <pb entity="DSSR_000002647_0008" n="918"/>  
 sometimes p'raps 'twasn't Enoch; he'd 'a'
branched out more in course o' time.  I'm waitin' to see if he
does extry well to sea 'fore I let my mind come to bear on his bein'
clean-handed."
</p><p>"Plenty thought 'twas the old Cap'n come back for it an'
sperited it away.  Enough said that 'twasn't no honest gains;
most
on't was prize-money o' slave ships, an' all kinds o' devil's
gold
was mixed in.  I s'pose you've heard that said?"
</p><p>"Time an' again," responded Mrs. Forder; "an' the worst
on't
was simple ole Pappy Flanders went an' told the Knowles gals
themselves that folks thought the old Cap'n come back an' got it,
and Hannah done wrong to cuss Enoch Holt an' his ginerations
after
him the way she done."
</p><p>"I think it took holt on her ter'ble after all she'd gone
through," said Mrs. Downs, compassionately.  "He ain't near so
simple as he is ugly, Pappy Flanders ain't.  I've seen him set
here
an' read the paper sober 's anybody when I've been goin' about my
mornin's work in the shed-room, an' when I'd come in to look
about
he'd twist it with his hands an' roll his eyes an' begin to git
off
some o' his gabble.  I think them wanderin' cheap-wits likes the
fun on't an' 'scapes stiddy work, an' gits the rovin' habit so
fixed it sp'iles 'em."
</p><p>"My gran'ther was to the South Seas in his young days,"
related Mrs. Forder, impressively, "an' he said cussin' was
common
there.  I mean sober spitin' with a cuss.  He seen one o' them
black folks git a gredge against another an' go an' set down an'
look stiddy at him in his hut an' cuss him in his mind an' set
there an' watch, watch, until the other kind o' took sick an'
died,
all in a fortnight, I believe he said; 'twould make your blood
run
cold to hear gran'ther describe it, 'twould so.  He never done
nothin' but set an' look, an' folks would give him somethin' to
eat
now an' then, as if they thought 'twas all right, an' the other
one'd try to go an' come, an' at last he hived away altogether
an'
died.  I don't know what you'd call it that ailed him.  There's
suthin' in cussin' that's bad for folks, now I tell ye, Miss
Downs."
</p><p>"Hannah's eyes always makes me creepy now," Mrs. Downs
confessed uneasily.  "They don't look pleadin' an' childish same
's
they used to.  Seems to me as if she'd had the worst on't."
</p><p>"We ain't seen the end on't yit," said Mrs. Forder,
impressively.  "I feel it within me, Marthy Downs, an' it's a
terrible thing to have happened right amon'st us in Christian
times.  If we live long enough we're goin' to have plenty to talk
over in our old age that's come o' that cuss.  Some seed's shy o'
sproutin' till a spring when the s'ile's jist right to breed it."
</p><p>"There's lobeely now," agreed Mrs. Downs, pleased to
descend
to prosaic and familiar levels.  "They ain't a good crop one year
in six, and then you find it in a place where you never observed
none to grow afore, like 's not; ain't it so, reelly?"  And she
rose to clear the table, pleased with the certainty of a guest
that
night.  Their conversation was not reassuring to the heart of a
timid woman alone in an isolated farm-house on a dark spring
evening, especially so near the anniversary of old Captain
Knowles's death.</p></div1>
<div1 type="section" n="5" id="d7"><head>V.</head>

<p>LATER in these rural lives by many years two aged women were
crossing a wide field together, following a foot-path such as one
often finds between widely separated homes of the New England
country.  Along these lightly traced thoroughfares the children
go
to play, and lovers to plead, and older people to companion one
another in work and pleasure,
 <pb entity="DSSR_000002647_0009" n="919"/>  
 in sickness and sorrow;
generation after generation comes and goes again by these country
by-ways.
</p><p>The foot-path led from Mrs. Forder's to another farm-house
half a mile beyond, where there had been a wedding.  Mrs. Downs
was
there, and in the June Weather she had been easily persuaded to
go
home to tea with Mrs. Forder with the promise of being driven
home
later in the evening.  Mrs. Downs's husband had been dead three
years, and her friend's large family was scattered from the old
nest; they were lonely at times in their later years, these old
friends, and found it very pleasant now to have a walk together.
Thin little Mrs. Forder, with all her wheezing, was the stronger
and more active of the two; Mrs. Downs had grown heavier and
weaker
with advancing years.
</p><p>They paced along the foot-path slowly, Mrs. Downs rolling
in
her gait like a sailor, and availing herself of every pretext to
stop and look at herbs in the pasture ground they crossed, and at
the growing grass in the mowing fields.  They discussed the
wedding
minutely, and then where the way grew wider they walked side by
side instead of following each other, and their voices sank to
the
low tone that betokens confidence.
</p><p>"You don't say that you really put faith in all them old
stories?"
</p><p>"It ain't accident altogether, noways you can fix it in
your
mind," maintained Mrs. Downs.  "Needn't tell me that cussin'
don't
do neither good nor harm.  I shouldn't want to marry amon'st the
Holts if I was young ag'in!  I r'member when this young man was
born that's married to-day, an' the fust thing his poor mother
wanted to know was about his hands bein' right.  I said yes they
was, but las' year he was twenty year old and come home from the
frontier with one o' them hands&mdash;his right one&mdash;shot off in a
fight.  They say 't happened to sights o' other fellows, an'
their
laigs gone too, but I count 'em over on my fingers, them Holts,
an'
he's the third.  May say that 'twas all an accident his mother's
gittin' throwed out o' her waggin comin' home from meetin', an'
her
wrist not bein' set good, an' she, bein' run down at the time,
'most lost it altogether, but thar' it is stiffened up an' no
good
to her.  There was the second.  An' Enoch Holt hisself come home
from the Chiny seas, made a good passage an' a sight o' money in
the pepper trade, jest 's we expected, an' goin' to build him a
new
house, an' the frame gives a kind o' lurch when they was raisin'
of
it an' surges over on to him an' nips him under.  'Which arm?'
says
everybody along the road when they was comin' an' goin' with the
doctor.  'Right one&mdash;got to lose it,' says the doctor to 'em an'
next time Enoch Holt got out to meetin' he stood up in the house
o'
God with the hymn-book in his left hand, an' no right hand to
turn
his leaf with.  He knowed what we was all a'thinkin'."
</p><p>"Well," said Mrs. Forder, very short-breathed with
climbing
the long slope of the pasture hill, "I don't know but I'd as soon
be them as the Knowles gals.  Hannah never knowed no peace again
after she spoke them words in the co't-house.  They come back an'
harnted her, an' you know, Miss Downs, better'n I do, being
door-neighbors as one may say, how they lived their lives out
like wild beasts into a lair."
</p><p>"They used to go out some by night to git the air,"
pursued
Mrs. Downs with interest.  "I used to open the door an' step
right
in, an' I used to take their yarn an' stuff 'long o' mine an'
sell
'em, an' do for the poor stray creatur's long 's they'd let me.
They'd be grateful for a mess o' early pease or potatoes as ever
you see, an' Peter he allays favored 'em with pork, fresh an'
salt,
when we slaughtered.
 <pb entity="DSSR_000002647_0010" n="920"/> .  
 The old Cap'n kept 'em child'n long
as he lived, an' then they was too old to l'arn different.  I
allays liked Hannah the best till that change struck her.  Betsey
she held out to the last jest about the same.  I don't know, now
I
come to think of it, but what she felt it the most o' the two."
</p><p>"They'd never let me s'much as git a look at 'em,"
complained
Mrs. Forder.  "Folks got awful stories a-goin' one time.  I've
heard it said, an' it allays creeped me cold all over, that there
was somethin' come an' lived with 'em&mdash;a kind o' black shadder, a
cobweb kind o' a man-shape that followed 'em about the house an'
made a third to them; but they got hardened to it theirselves,
only
they was afraid 'twould follow if they went anywheres from home.
You don't believe no such a piece o' nonsense?&mdash;  But there, I've
asked ye times enough before."
</p><p>"They'd got shadders enough, poor cretur's," said Mrs.
Downs
with reserve.  "Wasn't no kind o' need to make 'em up no spooks,
as
I know on.  Well, here's these young folks a-startin'; I wish 'em
well, I'm sure.  She likes him with his one hand better than most
gals likes them as has a good sound pair.  They looked prime
happy;
I hope no curse won't foller 'em."
</p><p>The friends stopped again&mdash;poor, short-winded bodies&mdash;on
the
crest of the low hill and turned to look at the wide landscape,
bewildered by the marvelous beauty and the sudden flood of golden
sunset light that poured out of the western sky.  They could not
remember that they had ever observed the wide view before; it was
like a revelation or an outlook towards the celestial country,
the
sight of their own green farms and the country-side that bounded
them.  It was a pleasant country indeed, their own New England:
their petty thoughts and vain imaginings seemed futile and
unrelated to so fair a scene of things.  But the figure of a man
who was crossing the meadow below looked like a malicious black
insect.  It was an old man, it was Enoch Holt; time had worn and
bent him enough to have satisfied his bitterest foe.  The women
could see his empty coat-sleeve flutter as he walked slowly and
unexpectantly in that glorious evening light.
</p>
<trailer>
                       <hi rend="italic">Sarah Orne Jewett.</hi></trailer>

</div1>
</body>
</text>
</TEI.2>
