<?xml version="1.0"?>

<?dlps id="KroMaxi"?>
<?dlps page-images="color" figure-images="yes"?>
<?dlps transcription="other"?>

<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/tei-p4/tei2.dtd" [
<!ENTITY % POSTKB "INCLUDE">
<!ENTITY % TEI.extensions.ent SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.ent">
<!ENTITY % TEI.extensions.dtd SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.dtd">
<!ENTITY % ISOlat1 SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/charent/iso-lat1.ent"> %ISOlat1;
<!ENTITY % ISOpub SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/charent/iso-pub.ent"> %ISOpub;


<!ENTITY DSSR_000002607_0001 SYSTEM "000002607_0001" NDATA uvaHighRes>
<!ENTITY DSSR_000002607_0002 SYSTEM "000002607_0002" NDATA uvaHighRes>
<!ENTITY DSSR_000002607_0003 SYSTEM "000002607_0003" NDATA uvaHighRes>
<!ENTITY DSSR_000002607_0004 SYSTEM "000002607_0004" NDATA uvaHighRes>
]>
<TEI.2 id="KroMaxi">
<teiHeader type="migrated" creator="Etext">
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title type="main">Max&#xed;m G&#xf3;rky</title>
<title type="sort">maxim gorky</title>
<author>Kropotkin, Peter</author>
<respStmt>
<resp>Creation of machine-readable version:</resp>
<name>Judy Boss</name>
<resp>Creation of digital images:</resp>
<name>Stephen Ramsay, Electronic Text Center</name>
<resp>Conversion to TEI.2-conformant markup:</resp>
<name>University of Virginia Library Electronic Text Center.</name>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt>
<extent>ca. <num type="kilobytes">21</num> kilobytes</extent>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>University of Virginia Library</publisher>
<pubPlace>Charlottesville, Virginia</pubPlace>
<idno type="ETC">KroMaxi</idno>
<date value="1996">1996</date>
<availability status="public">
<p n="copyright">Copyright &#xa9; 1996 by the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia</p>
<p n="access">Publicly accessible</p>
</availability>
<idno type="uva-pid">uva-lib:477107</idno>
</publicationStmt>
<seriesStmt>
<title>University of Virginia Library, Text collection</title>
<idno type="uva-set">UVA-LIB-Text</idno>
</seriesStmt>
<notesStmt>
<note>
<p>Illustrations have been included from the print version.</p>
</note>
</notesStmt>
<sourceDesc>
<biblFull>
<titleStmt>
<title type="main">Max&#xed;m G&#xf3;rk</title>
<title level="j">The Independent</title>
<title type="sort">maxim gork</title>
<author>Prince Peter Kropotkin</author>
</titleStmt>
<extent>pp. 1378-1371</extent>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>W. S. Benedict</publisher>
<pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
<date value="1904-12-15">December 15, 1904</date>
<idno type="callNo">Print copy consulted: Alderman Library AP2 .I53</idno>
</publicationStmt>
<notesStmt>
<note>
<p>The Independent, Vol. 57, No. 2924, December 15, 1904.</p>
</note>
</notesStmt>
</biblFull>
</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc>
<encodingDesc>
<projectDesc>
<p>Prepared for the University of Virginia Library Electronic Text Center.</p>
</projectDesc>
<editorialDecl>
<p>All quotation marks retained as data.</p>
<p>All unambiguous end-of-line hyphens have been removed, and the trailing part of a word has been joined to the preceding line.</p>
<p>The images exist as archived TIFF images, one or more JPEG versions for general use, and thumbnail GIFs.</p>
<p>Keywords in the header are a local Electronic Text Center scheme to aid in establishing analytical groupings.</p>
</editorialDecl>
</encodingDesc>
<profileDesc>
<creation>
<date value="1904">1904</date>
</creation>
<langUsage>
<language id="eng" usage="main">English</language>
</langUsage>
<textClass>
<keywords>
<term>nonfiction; prose</term>
</keywords>
<keywords>
<term type="format">24-bit color; 400 dpi</term>
</keywords>
</textClass>
</profileDesc>
<revisionDesc>
<change>
<date value="1996-11">November 1996</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>corrector</resp>
<name>Stephen Ramsay, Electronic Text Center</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Added TEI header and tags.</item>
</change>
<change>
<date value="2005-07">July 2005</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>Corrector</resp>
<name>John Ivor Carlson</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Converted to XML and/or checked tags.</item>
</change>
<change>
<date value="2007-09">September 2007</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>Migration</resp>
<name>Ethan Gruber, University of Virginia Library</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Converted XML markup from TEI Lite to uva-dl-tei (TEI P4 with local customizations).</item>
</change>
<change>
<date value="2008-01">January 2008</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>Migration</resp>
<name>Greg Murray, University of Virginia Library</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Programmatically updated TEI header markup (but not header content) for minimal compliance with current QA requirements.</item>
</change>
<change>
<date value="2009-03">March 2009</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>Migration</resp>
<name>Scholarly Resources, University of Virginia Library</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Added and/or replaced the digital images accompanying the electronic text. Scanning of exterior and interior (ie. pages) of item was done only for items found in the University of Virginia Special Collections Library.</item>
</change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>
<text id="d1">

<body id="d2">



<div1 type="bio" id="d3">
            <pb entity="DSSR_000002607_0001" n="1378"/>
<head type="main">Max&iacute;m G&oacute;rky</head>
 <head type="sub" >BY PRINCE PETER KROPOTKIN<lb/></head>

<head type="desc">AUTHOR OF "FIELDS, FACTORIES AND WORKSHOPS," "MUTUAL AID," ETC.</head>
<p>FEW writers have established their reputation so rapidly as
Max&iacute;m G&oacute;rky.  His first sketches (1892-95), were
published in an obscure provincial paper of the Caucasus, and were
totally unknown to the literary world, but when a short tale of his
appeared in a widely-read [illustration omitted] review, edited by
Korol&eacute;nko, it at once attracted general attention.  The
beauty of its form, its artistic finish, and the new note of strength
and courage which rang through it, brought the young writer
immediately into prominence.  It became known that
Max&iacute;m G&oacute;rky was the pen-name of quite a young
man, A. Pyeshkoff, who was born in 1868 in Nizhni Novgorod, a
large town on the Volga; that his father was a merchant, or an
artisan, his mother a remarkable peasant woman, who died soon
after the birth of her son, and that the boy, orphaned when only
nine, was brought up in a family of his father's relatives.  The
childhood of G&oacute;rky must have been anything but happy, for
one day he ran away and entered into service on a Volga River
steamer.  Later he lived and wandered on foot with the tramps in
South Russia, and during these wanderings he wrote a number of
short stories which were published in a newspaper of Northern
Caucasia.  The stories proved to be remarkably fine, and when a
collection of all that he had hitherto written was published in 1900,
in four small volumes, the whole of a large edition was sold in a
very short time, and the name of G&oacute;rky took its place&mdash;to
speak of living novelists only&mdash;by the side of those of
Korol&eacute;nko and Tch&eacute;hoff, immediately after the
name of Leo Tolst&oacute;y.  In Western Europe and America his
reputation was made with the same rapidity, as soon as a couple of
his sketches were translated into French and German, and
retranslated into English.
</p><p>It is sufficient to read a few of G&oacute;rky's short stories,
for instance, "M&aacute;lva," or "Tehelk&aacute;sh," or "The Ex-Men," or "Twenty-six Men and One Girl," to realize at once the
causes of his rapidly won popularity.  The men and women he
describes are not heroes; they are the most ordinary tramps or slum-dwellers; and what he writes are not novels in the proper sense of
the word, merely sketches of life.  And yet, in the literature of all
nations, including the short stories of Guy de Maupassant and Bret
Harte, there are few things in which such a fine analysis of
complicated and struggling human feelings is given, such
interesting, original, and new characters are so well depicted, and
human psychology is so admirably interwoven with a background
of nature&mdash;a calm sea, menacing waves, or endless, sun-burnt
prairies.  In the first-named story, you really <hi rend="italic">see</hi> the
promontory that juts out into "the laughing waters," that promontory
upon
            <pb entity="DSSR_000002607_0002" n="1379"/>
which the fisherman has pitched his hut; and you
understand why M&aacute;lva, the woman who loves him and
comes to see him every Sunday, loves that spot as much as she does
the fisherman himself.  And then, at every page, you are struck by
the quite unexpected variety of fine touches with which the love of
that strange and complicated nature, M&aacute;lva, is depicted, or
by the unforeseen aspects under which both the ex-peasant
fisherman and his peasant son appear in the short space of a few
days.  The variety of strokes, refined and brutal, tender and terribly
harsh, with which G&oacute;rky pictures human feelings, is such
that in comparison with his heroes the heroes and heroines of our
best novelists seem so simple&mdash;so simplified, like a flower in
European decorative art in comparison with a real flower.
</p><p>G&oacute;rky is a great artist; he is a poet; but he is also a
child of all that long series of folk-novelists whom Russia has had
for the last half century, and he has utilized their experience: he has
found at last that happy combination of realism with idealism, for
which the Russian folk-novelists have been striving for so many
years.  Ryesh&eacute;tnikoff and his school had tried to write
novels of an ultra-realistic character, without any trace of
idealization.  They restrained themselves whenever they felt
inclined to generalize, to create, to idealize.  They tried to write
mere diaries, in which events, great and small, important and
insignificant, were related with an equal exactitude, without even
changing the tone of the narrative.  In this way, by dint of their
talent, they were able to obtain the most poignant effects; but, like
the historian who vainly tries to be "impartial," yet always remains
a party man, they had not avoided the idealization which they so
much dreaded.
</p><p>The stratum of society from which G&oacute;rky took the
heroes of his first short stories&mdash;and in short stories he appears at his
best&mdash;is that of the tramps of Southern Russia: men who have
broken with regular society, who never accept the yoke of
permanent work, laboring only as long as they want to, as "casuals"
in the seaports on the Black Sea; who sleep in dosshouses or in
ravines on the outskirts of the cities, and tramp in the summer from
Odessa to the Crimea, and from the Crimea to the prairies of
Northern Caucasia, where they are always welcome at harvest time.
</p><p>Far from his whining and complaining about the hard lot of his
tramps, a refreshing note of energy and courage, which is quite
unique in Russian literature sounds through the stories of
G&oacute;rky.  His tramps are miserably poor, but they "don't
care."  They drink, but there is nothing among them nearly
approaching the dark drunkenness of despair which we see in
Lev&iacute;toff.  Even the most "down-trodden" one of them, far
from making a virtue of his helplessness, as Dostoy&eacute;vsky's
heroes always did,&mdash;dreams of reforming the world and making it
rich.  He dreams of the moment when "we, once 'the poor,' shall
vanish, after having enriched the Croesuses with the richness of the
spirit and the power of life."  ("A Mistake," I, 170.)
</p><p>G&oacute;rky cannot stand whining; he cannot bear that self-castigation in which other Russian writers so much delight, which
Turgueneff's <hi rend="italic">sub</hi>-Hamlets used to express so
poetically, of
which Dostoy&eacute;vsky has made a virtue, and of which Russia
offers such an infinite variety of examples.  G&oacute;rky knows
the type, but he has no pity for such men.  "What's all this talk about
circumstances?" he makes "Old Izerghil" say.

</p><p>"Every one makes his own circumstances!  I see all sorts of
men&mdash;but the strong ones&mdash;where are they?  There are fewer and
fewer noble men!"

</p><p>In "V&aacute;re&ntilde;ka Ol&eacute;sova," G&oacute;rky
expresses all his contempt for the average "intellectual" of our own
days.  He introduces to us the interesting type of a girl, full of
vitality; a most primitive creature, absolutely untouched by any
ideals of liberty and equality, but so full of an intense life, so
independent, so much herself, that one cannot but feel greatly
interested in her.  She meets with one of those "intellectuals" who
know and admire higher ideals, but are weaklings, utterly devoid of
the nerve of life.  Of course, V&aacute;re&ntilde;ka laughs at the
very idea of such a man's falling in love with her; and these are the
expressions in which G&oacute;rky makes her define the usual hero
of Russian novels:

</p><p>"The Russian hero is always silly and stupid, he is always sick
of something; always
            <pb entity="DSSR_000002607_0003" n="1380"/>
thinking about something that
cannot be understood, and is himself so miserable, so mi-i-serable!
He will think, think, then talk, then he will go and make a
declaration of love, and after that he thinks and thinks again, till he
marries. . . .  And when he is married, he talks all sorts of nonsense
to his wife, and then abandons her."  ("V&aacute;re&ntilde;ka
Ol&eacute;sova," II, 281.)

</p><p>G&oacute;rky's favorite type is the "rebel"&mdash;the man in full
revolt against society, but at the same time a strong man, a power;
and as he has found among the tramps with whom he has lived, at
least the type in embryo, it is from this stratum of society that he
takes his most interesting heroes.

</p><p>Some of G&oacute;rky's tramps are, of course, philosophers.
They think about human life, and have had opportunities to know
what it is.  He remarks somewhere:

</p><p>"Every one who has had a struggle to sustain in his life, and
has been defeated by life, and now feels cruelly imprisoned amidst
its squalor, is more of a philosopher than Schopenhauer himself; for
abstract thought can never be cast into such a correct and vivid
plastic form as that in which is expressed the thought born directly
out of suffering." (31.)

</p><p>Love of nature is, of course, another characteristic feature of
ythe tramp,&mdash;

"Konov&aacute;loff loved Nature with a deep, inarticulate love,
which was betrayed only by a glitter in his eyes.  Every time he was
in the fields, or on the river bank, he became permeated with a sort
of peace and love which made him still more like to a child.
Sometimes he would say with a deep sigh, looking at the sky,
'Good!' and in this exclamation there was more sense and feeling
than in the rhetoric of many poets. . . .  Like all the rest, poetry loses
its holy simplicity and spontaneity, when it becomes a profession."
(II, 33-4.)

</p><p>However, G&oacute;rky's rebel-tramp, is not a Nietzscheite
who ignores everything beyond his narrow egotism, or imagines
himself an "over-man" the "diseased ambition" of "an intellectual"
is required to create the true Nietzscheite type.  In G&oacute;rky's
tramps, as in his women of the lowest class, there are flashes of
greatness of character, and a simplicity which is incompatible with
the superman's self-conceit.  He does not idealize them so as to
make of them real heroes; that would be too untrue to life: the tramp
is still a defeated being.  But he shows how, among these men,
owing to an inner consciousness of strength, there are moments of
greatness, even tho that inner force be not strong enough to make
out of Orl&oacute;ff (in "The Orl&oacute;ffs") or Iliy&aacute; (in
"The Three") a real power, a real hero&mdash;the man who fights against
those much stronger than himself.  He seems to say: Why are not
you, intellectuals, as truly "individual," as frankly rebellious against
the society you criticise, and as strong as some of these submerged
ones are?
</p><p>In his short stories, G&oacute;rky is great; but like his two
great contemporaries, Korol&eacute;nko and Tch&eacute;hoff,
whenever he has tried to write a longer novel, with a full
development of characters, he has not succeeded.  Taken as a
whole, "Thomas Gord&eacute;eff," notwithstanding several
beautiful and deeply impressive scenes, is weaker than most of
G&oacute;rky's short stories; and while the first portion of "The
Three," the idyllic life of the three young people, and the tragical
issues foreshadowed in it, make us expect to find in this novel one
of the finest productions in Russian literature, its end is
disappointing.  The French translator of "The Three" has even
preferred to terminate it abruptly, at the point where Iliy&aacute;
stands on the grave of the man whom he has killed, rather than to
give G&oacute;rky's end of the novel.
</p><p>Over and over again G&oacute;rky returns to the idea of the
necessity of an ideal in the work of the novel-writer.  He says:

</p><p>"The cause of the present opinion (in Russian society) is the
neglect of idealism.  Those who have exiled from life all
romanticism have stripped us so as to leave us quite naked: this is
why we are so uninteresting to one another, and so disgusted with
one another."  ("A Mistake.")

</p><p>And in "The Reader" he develops his &aelig;sthetic canons in
full.  He tells how one of his earliest productions, on its appearance
in print, is read one night before a circle of friends.  He receives
many compliments for it, and after leaving the house, is tramping
along a deserted street, feeling for the first time in his existence the
happiness of life, when a person, unknown to him, and whom he
had not noticed among those present at the reading, overtakes
            <pb entity="DSSR_000002607_0004" n="1381"/>
him and begins to talk about the duties of the author.  Says
the stranger:

</p><p>"You will agree with me that the duty of literature is to aid
man in understanding himself, to raise his faith in himself, to
develop his longing for truth; to combat what is bad in men; to find
what is good in them, and to wake up in their souls shame, anger,
courage&mdash;to do everything, in short, to render men strong in a noble
sense of the word, and capable of inspiring their lives with the holy
spirit of beauty.  It seems to me, we need once more to have dreams,
pretty creations of our fancy and visions, because the life we have
built up is poor in color, is dim and dull. . . .  Well, let us try&mdash;perhaps imagination will help a man to rise above the earth and find
his true place on it, which he has lost."
</p><p>"Can you," the "Reader" goes on to ask, "create for men ever
so small an illusion that has the power to raise them?  No!"  "All of
you teachers of the day take more than you give, because you speak
only about faults&mdash;you see only those.  But there must also be good
qualities in men; you possess some, don't you? . . .  Don't you notice
that, owing to your continual efforts to define and to classify them,
the virtues and the vices have been entangled like two balls of black
and white thread which have become gray by taking color from
each other?" . . .  "I doubt whether God has sent you on earth.  If he
had sent messengers, he would have chosen stronger men than you
are.  He would have lighted in them the fire of a passionate love of
life, of truth, of men."
</p><p>"Nothing but everyday life, everyday life, only everyday
people, everyday thoughts and events.  When will you, then, speak
of 'the rebel spirit,' of the necessity of a new birth of the spirit?
Where is, then, the calling to the creation of a new life? the lessons
of courage? the words which give wings to the soul?'"
</p><p>"Confess you don't know how to represent life so that your
pictures of it shall provoke in man a redemptive spirit of shame and
a burning desire of creating new forms of life. . . .  Can you
accelerate the pulsation of life?  Can you inspire it with energy, as
others have done?"
</p><p>"I see many intelligent men round about me, but few noble
ones among them, and these few are broken and suffering souls.  I
don't know why it should be so, but so it is; the better the man, the
cleaner and the more honest his soul, the less energy he has; the
more he suffers and the harder is his life. . . .  But altho they suffer
so much from feeling the want of something better they have not the
force to create it."
</p><p>"One thing more.  Can you awake in man a laughter full of the
joy of life, and at the same time elevating to the soul?  Look&mdash;men
have quite forgotten good wholesome laughter!"
</p><p>"The sense of life is not in self-satisfaction after all, man is
better than that.  The sense of life is in the beauty and the force of
striving toward some aim; every moment of being ought to have its
higher aim.  Wrath, hatred, shame, loathing, and finally a grim
despair&mdash;these are the levers by means of which you may destroy
everything on earth.  What can you do to awake a thirst for life,
when you only whine, sigh, moan or coolly point out to man that he
is nothing but dust?"
</p><p>"Oh, for a man, firm and loving, with a burning heart and a
powerful all-embracing mind.  In the stuffy atmosphere of shameful
silence, his prophetic words would resound like a tocsin, and
perhaps the mean souls of the living dead would shiver!" (253.)

</p><p>These ideas of G&oacute;rky about the necessity of something
better than everyday life&mdash;something which shall elevate the soul,
fully explain also his last drama, "At the Bottom," which has had
such a success at Moscow, but played by the very same artists at St.
Petersburg, met with but little enthusiasm.  The idea is the same as
that of Ibsen's "Wild Duck."  The inhabitants of a dosshouse, all of
them, maintain their ability to live only as long as they cherish some
illusion: the drunkard actor dreams of recovery in some special
retreat; a fallen girl takes refuge in her illusion of real love, and so
on.  And the dramatic situation of these beings with already so little
to retain them in life, is only the more poignant when the illusions
are destroyed.  The drama is powerful.  It must lose, tho, on the
stage on account of some technical mistakes (a useless fourth act,
the unnecessary person of a woman introduced in the first scene and
then disappearing; but apart from these mistakes it is eminently
dramatic.  The positions are really tragical, the action is rapid, and
as to the conversations of the inhabitants of the dosshouse and their
philosophy of life, both are above all praise.  Altogether one feels
that G&oacute;rky is very far yet from having said his last word.
The question is only whether in the classes of society he now
frequents he will be able to discover the further developments&mdash;undoubtedly existing&mdash;of the types which he understands best.  Will
he find among them further materials responding to the
&aelig;sthetic canons whose following has hitherto been the source
of his power?</p>

<closer>
<dateline>BROMLEY, KENT, ENGLAND.</dateline>
</closer>


</div1>
</body>
</text>
</TEI.2>
