<?xml version="1.0"?>

<?dlps id="LaFStor"?>
<?dlps page-images="color" figure-images="no"?>
<?dlps transcription="other"?>

<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/tei-p4/tei2.dtd" [
<!ENTITY % POSTKB "INCLUDE">
<!ENTITY % TEI.extensions.ent SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.ent">
<!ENTITY % TEI.extensions.dtd SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.dtd">
<!ENTITY % ISOpub SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/charent/iso-pub.ent"> %ISOpub;


<!ENTITY DSSR_000002586_0001 SYSTEM "000002586_0001" NDATA uvaHighRes>
<!ENTITY DSSR_000002586_0002 SYSTEM "000002586_0002" NDATA uvaHighRes>
<!ENTITY DSSR_000002586_0003 SYSTEM "000002586_0003" NDATA uvaHighRes>
<!ENTITY DSSR_000002586_0004 SYSTEM "000002586_0004" NDATA uvaHighRes>
]>
 
 
<TEI.2 id="LaFStor">
    <teiHeader creator="Etext" type="migrated">
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title type="main">The Story of a Vision</title>
                <title type="sort">story of a vision</title>
                <author>La Flesche, Francis</author>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Creation of machine-readable version:</resp>
                    <name>Judy Boss</name>
                    <resp>Creation of digital images:</resp>
                    <name>Catherine Tousignant, Electronic Text Center</name>
                    <resp>Conversion to TEI.2-conformant markup:</resp>
                    <name>University of Virginia Library Electronic Text Center.</name>
                </respStmt>
            </titleStmt>
            <extent>ca. <num type="kilobytes">14</num> kilobytes</extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>University of Virginia Library</publisher>
                <pubPlace>Charlottesville, Virginia</pubPlace>
                <idno type="ETC">LaFStor</idno>
                <date value="1996">1996</date>
                <availability status="public">
                    <p n="copyright">Copyright &#xa9; 1996 by the Rector and Visitors of the
                        University of Virginia</p>
                    <p n="access">Publicly accessible</p>
                </availability>
                <idno type="uva-pid">uva-lib:477109</idno>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title>University of Virginia Library, Text collection</title>
                <idno type="uva-set">UVA-LIB-Text</idno>
            </seriesStmt>
            <notesStmt>
                <note>
                    <p>Judy Boss has made the following changes to the text: page 106: on",] on,";
                        down"] down,"; come over] came over.</p>
                </note>
            </notesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull>
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title type="main">The Story of Vision</title>
                        <title level="j">The Southern Workman</title>
                        <title type="sort">story of vision</title>
                        <author>Francis La Flesche</author>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <extent>pp. 106-109.</extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Hampton Normal and Agricultural Institute</publisher>
                        <pubPlace>Hampton, Va</pubPlace>
                        <date value="1901-02">February, 1901</date>
                        <idno type="callNo">Print copy consulted: UVa Library call number LC 2701
                            .S7</idno>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <notesStmt>
                        <note>
                            <p>Southern Workman 30 (Feb. 1901): 106-109.</p>
                        </note>
                    </notesStmt>
                </biblFull>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>Prepared for the University of Virginia Library Electronic Text Center.</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <p>All quotation marks retained as data.</p>
                <p>All unambiguous end-of-line hyphens have been removed, and the trailing part of a
                    word has been joined to the preceding line.</p>
                <p>The images exist as archived TIFF images, one or more JPEG versions for general
                    use, and thumbnail GIFs.</p>
                <p>Keywords in the header are a local Electronic Text Center scheme to aid in
                    establishing analytical groupings.</p>
            </editorialDecl>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <creation>
                <date value="1901">1901</date>
            </creation>
            <langUsage>
                <language id="eng" usage="main">English</language>
            </langUsage>
            <textClass>
                <keywords>
                    <term>fiction; prose</term>
                    <term>Native American</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords>
                    <term type="format">24-bit color; 400 dpi</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change>
                <date value="1996-11">November, 1996</date>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>corrector</resp>
                    <name>Catherine Tousignant, Electronic Text Center</name>
                </respStmt>
                <item>Added TEI header and tags.</item>
            </change>
            <change>
                <date value="2005-07">July 2005</date>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Corrector</resp>
                    <name>John Ivor Carlson</name>
                </respStmt>
                <item>Converted SGML to XML and/or corrected tagging.</item>
            </change>
            <change>
                <date value="2007-09">September 2007</date>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Migration</resp>
                    <name>Ethan Gruber, University of Virginia Library</name>
                </respStmt>
                <item>Converted XML markup from TEI Lite to uva-dl-tei (TEI P4 with local
                    customizations).</item>
            </change>
            <change>
                <date value="2008-01">January 2008</date>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Migration</resp>
                    <name>Greg Murray, University of Virginia Library</name>
                </respStmt>
                <item>Programmatically updated TEI header markup (but not header content) for
                    minimal compliance with current QA requirements.</item>
            </change>
<change>
<date value="2009-03">March 2009</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>Migration</resp>
<name>Scholarly Resources, University of Virginia Library</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Added and/or replaced the digital images accompanying the electronic text. Scanning of exterior and interior (ie. pages) of item was done only for items found in the University of Virginia Special Collections Library.</item>
</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>

    <text id="d1">


        <body id="d2">
            <div1 id="d3" type="story">
                <pb entity="DSSR_000002586_0001" n="106"/>
                <head>The Story of a Vision<lb/> FRANCIS LA FLESCHE</head>

                <p>EACH of us, as we gathered at the lodge of our story teller at dusk, picked up an
                    armful of wood and entered. The old man who was sitting alone, his wife having
                    gone on a visit, welcomed us with a pleasant word as we threw the wood down by
                    the fire-place and busied ourselves rekindling the fire. </p>
                <p> Ja-bae-ka and Ne-ne-ba, having nothing to do at this moment, fell to scuffling.
                    "You will be fighting if you keep on", warned the old man. </p>
                <p>"Stop your fooling and come and sit down", scolded Wa-du-pa; you're not in your
                    own house." </p>
                <p>The flames livened up cheerily and cast a ruddy glow about us, when Wa-du-pa
                    said, "Grandfather, the last time we were here you told us the myth of the eagle
                    and the wren; we liked it, but now we want a true story, something that really
                    happened, something you saw yourself." </p>
                <p>"How thirsty I am!" said the old man irrelevantly, "I wonder what makes me so
                    dry." </p>
                <p>"Quick!" said Wa-du-pa, motioning to Ja-bae-ka, "Get some water!" </p>
                <p> The lad peered into one kettle, squinted into another and then said, "There
                    isn't any." </p>
                <p> "Then go, get some!" arose a number of voices. </p>
                <p> "Why don't some of you go?" Ja-bae-ka retorted, picking up one of the kettles. </p>
                <p> "Take both!" some one shouted. </p>
                <p> Ja-bae-ka approached the door grumbling. As he grasped the heavy skin portier to
                    make his way out, he turned and said, "Don't begin until I come back." </p>
                <p> We soon heard his heavy breathing in the long entrance way. "It's moonlight,
                    just like day!" he exclaimed, as he set the kettles <pb
                        entity="DSSR_000002586_0002" n="107"/> down and
                    thrust his cold hands into the flames with a twisting motion. "The boys and
                    girls are having lots of fun sliding on the ice." </p>
                <p> "Let them slide, we don't care!" ejaculated Wa-du-pa as he dipped a cup into the
                    water and handed it to the old man, who put it to his lips and made a gulping
                    sound as he drank, the lump in his throat leaping up and down at each swallow.
                    At the last draught he expelled his pent-up breath with something like a groan,
                    set the cup down, wiped his lips with the back of his hand, and asked, "A real
                    true story&mdash;something that I saw myself; that's what you want, is it?" </p>
                <p> "Yes, grandfather," we sang out in chorus, "a story that has you in it!" </p>
                <p> His face brightened with a smile and he broke into a gentle laugh, nodding his
                    head to its rhythm. </p>
                <p> After a few moments' musing, and when we boys had settled down, the old man
                    began: "Many, many winters ago, long before any of you were born, our people
                    went on a winter hunt, away out among the sand hills where even now we sometimes
                    go. There was a misunderstanding between the leaders, so that just as we reached
                    the hunting grounds the tribe separated into two parties, each going in a
                    different direction. </p>
                <p> The weather was pleasant enough while on the journey, but a few days after the
                    departure of our friends a heavy storm came upon us. For days and nights the
                    wind howled and roared, threatening to carry away our tents and the snow fell
                    thick and fast, so that we could not see an arm's length; it was waist deep and
                    yet it kept falling. No hunting could be done; food grew scarcer and scarcer and
                    the older people became alarmed. </p>
                <p> One afternoon as my father, mother and I were sitting in our tent eating from
                    our last kettle of corn, there came a lull and we heard with startling
                    distinctness a man singing a song of augury. We paused to listen, but the wind
                    swept down again and drowned the voice. </p>
                <p> "A holy man seeking for a sign," said my father. "Son, go and hear if he will
                    give us words of courage." </p>
                <p> My father was lame and could not go himself, so I waded through the heavy drifts
                    and with much difficulty reached the man's tent, where many were already
                    gathered to hear the predictions. I held my breath in awe as I heard the holy
                    man say: </p>
                <p> "For a moment the wind ceased to blow, the clouds parted, and in the rift I saw
                    standing, in mid air against the blue sky, the spirit of the man who was
                    murdered last summer. His head was bowed in grief and although he spoke not, I
                    know from the vision that the anger of the storm gods was moved against us for
                    not punishing the murderer. Silently the spirit lifted an arm and pointed beyond
                    the hills. Then I found that I too was in mid air. I looked over the hilltops
                    and beheld a forest, where shadowy forms like those of large animals moved among
                    the trees. I turned once more to the spirit, but the clouds had come together
                    again. <pb entity="DSSR_000002586_0003" n="108"/>
                </p>
                <p> "Before dawn to-morrow the storm will pass away, then let the runners go to the
                    forest that I saw and tell us whether or not there is truth in the words that I
                    have spoken." </p>
                <p> As predicted, the wind ceased to blow and the snow to fall. Runners were hastily
                    sent to the forest and the sun was hardly risen when one of them returned with
                    the good news that the shadowy forms the holy man had seen were truly those of
                    buffalo. </p>
                <p> The effect of the news upon the camp was like magic, faces brightened, the
                    gloomy forebodings that clouded the minds of the older people fled as did the
                    storm, and laughter and pleasantries enlivened the place. The hunters and boys
                    were soon plodding through the snow toward the forest and before dark every one
                    returned heavily laden, tired and hungry, but none the less happy. The fires
                    burned brightly that night and men told stories until it was nearly morning. </p>
                <p> The forest of the vision was a bag of game; every few days the hunters went
                    there and returned with buffalo, elk, or deer, so that even the poorest man had
                    plenty for his wife and children to eat. </p>
                <p> All this time nothing had been heard from the party that separated from us
                    before the storm. One night when I came home from a rabbit hunt, I found my
                    mother and father packing up pemican and jerked meat as though for a journey. I
                    looked inquiringly at the pack as I ate my supper; bye and bye my mother told me
                    that a man had just come from the other camp with the news that the people had
                    exhausted their supplies and, as they could find no game, they were suffering
                    for want of food. My sister and her husband were in that camp, and I was told to
                    carry the pack to them. </p>
                <p> My father had arranged with a young man bound on a similar errand to call for me
                    early in the morning, so I went to bed as soon as I had finished eating, to get
                    as much sleep and rest as possible. It was well that I did, for long before dawn
                    creaking footsteps approached our tent and the man called out, "Are you ready?"
                    I quickly slipped on my leggings and moccasins, put on my robe, slung the pack
                    over my shoulders and we started. </p>
                <p> To avoid the drifts we followed the ridges, but even there the snow lay deep and
                    we were continually breaking through the hard crust. My friend turned every
                    mishap into a joke and broke the monotony of our travel with humorous tales and
                    incidents. Late at night we camped in the bend of a small, wooded stream. We
                    gathered a big pile of dry branches, kindled a roaring fire and roasted some of
                    the jerked meat. When supper was over we dried our moccasins, then piling more
                    wood on the fire we wrapped ourselves up in our robes and went to sleep. </p>
                <p> I do not know how long we might have slept had we not been wakened by the
                    howling of hundreds of wolves not far away from us. "They're singing to the
                    morning star!" said my friend. "It is near day, so we must be up and going." </p>
                <p> We ate a little of the pemican, helped each other to load, and again <pb
                    entity="DSSR_000002586_0004" n="109"
                    /> we started. Before night we were overtaken by other men and boys who were
                    also going to the relief of their friends in the other camp, where we arrived
                    just in time to save many of the people from starving. </p>
                <p> How curious it was that the predictions of the holy man should come
                    true&mdash;the stopping of the storm before morning, the forest, and the
                    shadowy forms of animals. Stranger still was the death of the murderer. This
                    took place, we were told by the people we had rescued, on the very night of the
                    augury in our camp. They said, as the man was sitting in his tent that night,
                    the wind suddenly blew the door flap violently aside, an expression of terror
                    came over his face, he fell backward, and he was dead. </p>
                <p> In the old days, many strange things came to pass in the life of our people, but
                    now we are getting to be different." </p>
                <p> Wa-du-pa thanked the story teller, and we were about to go when Ne-ne-ba,
                    pointing to Ja-bae-ka, whispered, "He's gone to sleep! Let's scare him." </p>
                <p> The old man fell into the spirit of the fun, so we all tip-toed to the back part
                    of the lodge where it was dark and watched, as the flames died down to a blue
                    flickering. We could see the boy's head drop lower and lower until his nose
                    nearly touched his knee. Just then a log on the fire suddenly tumbled from its
                    place, broke in two, sent up a shower of crackling sparks and Ja-bae-ka awoke
                    with a start. He threw up his head, looked all around and thinking he was left
                    alone in the darkened lodge, took fright and rushed to the door with a cry of
                    terror. We ran out of our hiding places with shouts of laughter and overtook
                    Ja-bae-ka outside the door, where we teased him about going to sleep and being
                    afraid in the dark. </p>
                <p> Suddenly he turned upon Ne-ne-ba and said, "You did that, you rascal! I'll pay
                    you back sometime."</p>

            </div1>
        </body>

    </text>
</TEI.2>
