<?xml version="1.0"?>

<?dlps id="LonPurp"?>
<?dlps page-images="color" figure-images="yes"?>
<?dlps transcription="other"?>

<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/tei-p4/tei2.dtd" [
<!ENTITY % POSTKB "INCLUDE">
<!ENTITY % TEI.extensions.ent SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.ent">
<!ENTITY % TEI.extensions.dtd SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.dtd">


<!ENTITY DSSR_000002634_0001 SYSTEM "000002634_0001" NDATA uvaHighRes>
<!ENTITY DSSR_000002634_0002 SYSTEM "000002634_0002" NDATA uvaHighRes>
<!ENTITY DSSR_000002634_0003 SYSTEM "000002634_0003" NDATA uvaHighRes>
<!ENTITY DSSR_000002634_0004 SYSTEM "000002634_0004" NDATA uvaHighRes>
<!ENTITY DSSR_000002634_0005 SYSTEM "000002634_0005" NDATA uvaHighRes>
<!ENTITY DSSR_000002634_0006 SYSTEM "000002634_0006" NDATA uvaHighRes>
<!ENTITY DSSR_000002634_0007 SYSTEM "000002634_0007" NDATA uvaHighRes>
<!ENTITY DSSR_000002634_0008 SYSTEM "000002634_0008" NDATA uvaHighRes>
<!ENTITY DSSR_000002634_0009 SYSTEM "000002634_0009" NDATA uvaHighRes>
<!ENTITY DSSR_000002634_0010 SYSTEM "000002634_0010" NDATA uvaHighRes>
<!ENTITY DSSR_000002634_0011 SYSTEM "000002634_0011" NDATA uvaHighRes>
<!ENTITY DSSR_000002634_0012 SYSTEM "000002634_0012" NDATA uvaHighRes>
<!ENTITY DSSR_000002634_0013 SYSTEM "000002634_0013" NDATA uvaHighRes>
<!ENTITY DSSR_000002634_0014 SYSTEM "000002634_0014" NDATA uvaHighRes>
<!ENTITY DSSR_000002634_0015 SYSTEM "000002634_0015" NDATA uvaHighRes>
<!ENTITY DSSR_000002634_0016 SYSTEM "000002634_0016" NDATA uvaHighRes>
<!ENTITY DSSR_000002634_0017 SYSTEM "000002634_0017" NDATA uvaHighRes>
<!ENTITY DSSR_000002634_0018 SYSTEM "000002634_0018" NDATA uvaHighRes>
<!ENTITY DSSR_000002634_0019 SYSTEM "000002634_0019" NDATA uvaHighRes>
<!ENTITY DSSR_000002634_0020 SYSTEM "000002634_0020" NDATA uvaHighRes>
<!ENTITY DSSR_000002634_0021 SYSTEM "000002634_0021" NDATA uvaHighRes>
<!ENTITY DSSR_000002634_0022 SYSTEM "000002634_0022" NDATA uvaHighRes>
<!ENTITY DSSR_000002634_0023 SYSTEM "000002634_0023" NDATA uvaHighRes>
<!ENTITY DSSR_000002634_0024 SYSTEM "000002634_0024" NDATA uvaHighRes>
<!ENTITY DSSR_000002634_0025 SYSTEM "000002634_0025" NDATA uvaHighRes>
<!ENTITY DSSR_000002634_0026 SYSTEM "000002634_0026" NDATA uvaHighRes>
<!ENTITY DSSR_000002634_0027 SYSTEM "000002634_0027" NDATA uvaHighRes>
<!ENTITY DSSR_000002634_0028 SYSTEM "000002634_0028" NDATA uvaHighRes>
<!ENTITY DSSR_000002634_0029 SYSTEM "000002634_0029" NDATA uvaHighRes>
<!ENTITY DSSR_000002634_0030 SYSTEM "000002634_0030" NDATA uvaHighRes>
<!ENTITY DSSR_000002634_0031 SYSTEM "000002634_0031" NDATA uvaHighRes>
<!ENTITY DSSR_000002634_0032 SYSTEM "000002634_0032" NDATA uvaHighRes>
<!ENTITY DSSR_000002634_0033 SYSTEM "000002634_0033" NDATA uvaHighRes>
<!ENTITY DSSR_000002634_0034 SYSTEM "000002634_0034" NDATA uvaHighRes>
<!ENTITY DSSR_000002634_0035 SYSTEM "000002634_0035" NDATA uvaHighRes>
<!ENTITY DSSR_000002634_0036 SYSTEM "000002634_0036" NDATA uvaHighRes>
<!ENTITY DSSR_000002634_0037 SYSTEM "000002634_0037" NDATA uvaHighRes>
<!ENTITY DSSR_000002634_0038 SYSTEM "000002634_0038" NDATA uvaHighRes>
<!ENTITY DSSR_000002634_0039 SYSTEM "000002634_0039" NDATA uvaHighRes>
<!ENTITY DSSR_000002634_0040 SYSTEM "000002634_0040" NDATA uvaHighRes>
<!ENTITY DSSR_000002634_0041 SYSTEM "000002634_0041" NDATA uvaHighRes>
<!ENTITY DSSR_000002634_0042 SYSTEM "000002634_0042" NDATA uvaHighRes>
<!ENTITY DSSR_000002634_0043 SYSTEM "000002634_0043" NDATA uvaHighRes>
<!ENTITY DSSR_000002634_0044 SYSTEM "000002634_0044" NDATA uvaHighRes>
<!ENTITY DSSR_000002634_0045 SYSTEM "000002634_0045" NDATA uvaHighRes>
<!ENTITY DSSR_000002634_0046 SYSTEM "000002634_0046" NDATA uvaHighRes>
<!ENTITY DSSR_000002634_0047 SYSTEM "000002634_0047" NDATA uvaHighRes>
<!ENTITY DSSR_000002634_0048 SYSTEM "000002634_0048" NDATA uvaHighRes>
<!ENTITY DSSR_000002634_0049 SYSTEM "000002634_0049" NDATA uvaHighRes>
<!ENTITY DSSR_000002634_0050 SYSTEM "000002634_0050" NDATA uvaHighRes>
]>
<TEI.2 id="LonPurp"> 
<teiHeader type="migrated" creator="Etext">
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title type="main">Purple-Eyes</title>
<title type="sort">purple eyes</title>
<author>Long, John Luther, 1861-1927</author>
<respStmt> 
<resp>Creation of machine-readable version:</resp> 
<name>Naked Word</name> 
<resp>Conversion to TEI.2-conformant markup:</resp> 
<name>University of Virginia Library Electronic Text Center.</name>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt> 
<extent>ca. <num type="kilobytes">49</num> kilobytes</extent> 
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>University of Virginia Library</publisher>
<pubPlace>Charlottesville, Virginia</pubPlace> 
<idno type="ETC">LonPurp</idno> 
<date value="2000">2000</date>
<availability status="public">
<p n="copyright">Copyright &#xa9; 2000 by the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia</p>
<p n="access">Publicly accessible</p>
</availability>
<idno type="uva-pid">uva-lib:477153</idno>
</publicationStmt>
<seriesStmt>
<title>University of Virginia Library, Text collection</title>
<idno type="uva-set">UVA-LIB-Text</idno>
</seriesStmt> 
<sourceDesc>
<biblFull>
<titleStmt>
<title type="main">Purple-Eyes</title>
<title type="sort">purple eyes</title>
<author>John Luther Long</author>
</titleStmt> 
<extent>224 p. front. 18 cm</extent> 
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>Century Co.</publisher> 
<pubPlace>New York</pubPlace> 
<date value="1898">1898</date> 
<idno type="callNo">Alderman Special Collections, Taylor 1898 .L65 m3</idno>
</publicationStmt> 
<notesStmt>
<note>
<p>This story came from Madame Butterfly</p>
</note>
</notesStmt>
</biblFull>
</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc> 
<encodingDesc>
<projectDesc>
<p>Prepared for the University of Virginia Library Electronic Text Center.</p>
</projectDesc> 
<editorialDecl>
<p>All unambiguous end-of-line hyphens have been removed, and the  trailing part of a word has been joined to the preceding line.</p> 
<p id="ETC">Some keywords in the header are a local Electronic Text Center scheme  to aid in establishing analytical groupings.</p>
</editorialDecl> 
</encodingDesc> 
<profileDesc>
<creation>
<date value="1898">1898</date>
</creation> 
<langUsage>
<language id="eng" usage="main">English</language>
</langUsage> 
<textClass>
<keywords>
<term>fiction</term> 
<term>poetry</term> 
<term>masculine</term> 
<term>Special Collections</term>
</keywords> 
</textClass>
</profileDesc> 
<revisionDesc>
<change>
<date value="2000-10">October, 2000</date> 
<respStmt>
<resp>corrector</resp> 
<name>Jill Phillips, the Electronic Text Center</name>
</respStmt> 
<item>Added TEI header and tags</item>
</change> 
<change>
<date value="2005-07">July 2005</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>Corrector</resp>
<name>John Ivor Carlson</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Converted SGML to XML and/or corrected tagging.</item>
</change>
<change>
<date value="2007-09">September 2007</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>Migration</resp>
<name>Ethan Gruber, University of Virginia Library</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Converted XML markup from TEI Lite to uva-dl-tei (TEI P4 with local customizations).</item>
</change>
<change>
<date value="2008-01">January 2008</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>Migration</resp>
<name>Greg Murray, University of Virginia Library</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Programmatically updated TEI header markup (but not header content) for minimal compliance with current QA requirements.</item>
</change>
<change>
<date value="2009-03">March 2009</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>Migration</resp>
<name>Scholarly Resources, University of Virginia Library</name>
</respStmt> 
<item>Added and/or replaced the digital images accompanying the electronic text. Scanning of exterior and interior (ie. pages) of item was done only for items found in the Unversity of Virginia Special Collections Library.</item>
</change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader> 
 

<text id="d1"> 
  <front id="d2">
    <pb entity="DSSR_000002634_0001" n="Spine"/>
    <pb entity="DSSR_000002634_0002" n="Cover"/>
    <pb entity="DSSR_000002634_0003" n="Back"/>
    <pb entity="DSSR_000002634_0004" n="Head"/>
    <pb entity="DSSR_000002634_0005" n="Tail"/>
    <pb entity="DSSR_000002634_0006" n="Foredge"/>
    
    <div1 type="half-title" id="d3">
    <pb entity="DSSR_000002634_0007" n="Half Title"/><p/>
      <pb entity="DSSR_000002634_0008"/>
      </div1>
    </front>
    
<body id="d4"> 
<div1 type="story" id="d5"> 
  <pb entity="DSSR_000002634_0009" n="89"/>
<head>Purple-Eyes</head> 
 

 
<div2 type="section" id="d6"> 

  <head>I <lb/>THE FEVER JAPONICA </head> 
 
 
<p> 
GARLAND was charmed with his reception. Before he could open his head (in 
his own perhaps too picturesque phrase) the two girls had buried their delightful 
noses in the mats, and were bobbing vividly up and down, sibilating honorifics 
at him in the voice and manner used only to personages. The mother joined 
them an instant later, making a phalanx, and she was nearly as beautiful, 
and quite as graceful, as her daughters. So that at one moment he would have 
presented to him the napes of 
  <pb entity="DSSR_000002634_0010" n="90"/>

three pretty necks, and at the next, with a 
conjurer's quick change, three pairs of eyes that smiled always, and three 
mouths that did their best (which was very well indeed) to assist the eyes. 
At first, I say, he was charmed, then a little bewildered, then bewitched. 
And perhaps it was well that his conversation-book was the only thing about 
him that spoke Japanese; for Garland's vocabulary, even when it was fairly 
accurate, had grown indiscreet since coming to Japan. 
</p><p> 
He perceived, however, by a surreptitious glance at the conversation-book 
when the napes of the necks were in view, that they were addressing him as 
"Augustness" and "Excellency," and that the mother was insisting that he 
should take immediate possession of her "miserable" house and its contents. 
He wondered dreamily and he drifted into dreams with the most curious 
ease whether the girls would be included. 
</p><p> 
Finally he began to feel it his duty to be tired of this fawning, as his 
refluent American democracy insisted upon naming it though, personally, 
he liked it and all the clever pretences of the Japanese. He sat bolt 
upright and frowned. But the charming 
  <pb entity="DSSR_000002634_0011" n="91"/>
kotowing did not in the least abate. 
He had heard somewhere that the only way to stop this sort of thing short 
of apoplexy was to compete in it. 
</p><p> 
He tried to reach the mats with his own nose. It seemed easy, but it was 
a disaster. There is a trick in it. He plunged forward helplessly almost 
into the lap of one of his hostesses. Garland sat up, with their joint 
assistance, very red in the face, but quite cheerful; for though the mother 
looked greatly pained, the girls were smiling like two Japanese angels. (The 
phrase is again Garland's: there are no Japanese angels.) Garland had the 
instant intelligence to perceive that this had at once stopped the kotowing, 
and precipitated a piquant intimacy. 
</p><p> 
"I say," said he, idiomatically, "I nearly broke my neck trying to say howdy-do 
in your way. Now won't you kindly say it in mine, without the least danger 
to life and limb?" 
</p><p> 
He held out his hand invitingly, and the one on his right went into debate 
as to which one to give him. She knew there was some foreign etiquette in 
the matter. 
</p><p> 
"In doubt, shake both," said Garland, doing it. 
</p>
  
  <pb entity="DSSR_000002634_0012" n="92"/>
  <p> 
The one on his left emulated her sister to the last particular (the mother 
had retired for refreshments), but he noticed that the hands she gave him 
were long and white. He glanced up, and found himself looking into a pair 
of blue eyes. He followed the forehead to the brassy hair above. Then he 
began furiously to turn the leaves of the conversation-book. The one on his 
right laughed a little, and said: 
</p><p> 
"What you lig as', please?" 
</p><p> 
Garland closed the book, and stared. He did not ask what he had meant to, 
because of something he saw in the questioner's face. 
</p><p> 
"Ah, if you lig more bedder for do so, speak the English," she said, with 
a quiet flourish that was lost upon Garland. 
</p><p> 
He flung the conversation-book into a corner. Black-Eyes, as he had mentally 
named her, in despair of her Japanese name, which was Meadowsweet, smiled 
ecstatically. 
</p><p> 
"Ah-h-h! You lig those those English?" 
</p><p> 
"Like it? It's heavenly! I say, fancy, if you can  but you 
can't depending upon a dictionary for your most sacred sentiments for 
three months." 
</p>
  
  <pb entity="DSSR_000002634_0013" n="93"/>
  <p> 
Wherein it will be perceived that Garland had learned the whole art of Japanese 
politeness gentle prevarication. 
</p><p> 
<hi rend="italic">"How</hi> that is nize!" breathed the blue-eyed one, fervently. 
</p><p> 
Garland turned suddenly upon her, then questioned her with his eyes. She 
understood. 
</p><p> 
"Those thing you speak-ing," she barely breathed once more, 
in explanation. 
</p><p> 
"Oh!" said Garland. But it meant more than print can express. "Tell me, if 
you please, what your name is." 
</p><p> 
It was Miss Purple-Wistaria; but the Japanese of this was quite as impossible 
as the other. 
</p><p> 
"Do you mind me calling you Blue-Eyes?" asked Garland. "When it comes to 
Japanese proper names I have already taken the liberty of mentally calling 
your sister Black-Eyes, and if you don't mind " 
</p><p> 
"You call those blue-eye?" asked Miss Meadowsweet. 
</p><p> 
"Why, yes," said Garland. "What do you call them?" 
</p><p> 
"Purple-eye." 
</p><p> 
"Well, I like that better, anyhow. It shall be Purple-Eyes." 
</p>
  
  <pb entity="DSSR_000002634_0014" n="94"/>
  <p> 
"She got other already English name," confided Black-Eyes, with the manner 
for her sister he did not like. 
</p><p> 
"Oh! What is it?" 
</p><p> 
"Sarann," laughed the dark one. "Tha' 's jus' joke her fadder. He all times 
joke upon her." 
</p><p> 
Garland did not quite understand. He decided that he did not wish to, for 
the blue-eyed one looked very uncomfortable. 
</p><p> 
"I shall call her Purple-Eyes," he said. 
</p><p> 
The disagreeableness of the other continued. 
</p><p> 
"Yaes; tha' 's good name for her," she added, with an intention that 
was distinctly odious. 
</p><p> 
"In America that would be the most beautiful name a man could give a beautiful 
woman," said Garland, severely. 
</p><p> 
The dark one looked a bit frightened. The blonde one gave him the merest 
horizon of her eyes as she raised her head. Gratitude was in them. 
</p><p> 
"Now, won't you go on, and tell me how you knew me before I opened my blooming 
head?" 
</p><p> 
He had again addressed himself to Purple-Eyes, but Black-Eyes answered: 
</p>
  
  <pb entity="DSSR_000002634_0015" n="95"/>
  <p> 
"What is that open you' head, an' blooming you' head?" 
</p><p> 
Garland informed her. 
</p><p> 
"Oh-h-h!" laughed the dark one. <hi rend="italic">"Tha' 's</hi> way know yo' 'fore open you' 
<hi rend="italic">bloom</hi>-ing head!" 
</p><p> 
She suddenly reached into the bosom of the kimono of the blue-eyed one, and 
brought forth a photograph of Garland; whereat Garland got red again, and 
again the blue-eyed one drooped her head, 
</p><p> 
"Oh, I say," Garland began, without a very distinct idea of what he was going 
to say, "Brownie sent you that aha, ha, ha!" he had happily drifted 
into the very thing "and wrote you that I would arrive with a letter 
from him; so that you would know me you know; and of course when I 
arrived of course when I arrived why, of <hi rend="italic">course</hi> oh, 
hang it!" 
</p><p> 
They both waited breathlessly upon his words. 
</p><p> 
"Of course," echoed Black-Eyes, sympathetically "of course tha' 
's correc', an' tha' 's also <hi rend="italic">nize</hi>. Of course you arrive 
when you arrive." 
</p><p> 
Garland wondered whether she was guying him. 
</p>
  <pb entity="DSSR_000002634_0016" n="96"/>
  <p> 
"Yes  why, of course," said he once more, and a laugh <hi rend="italic">en masse</hi> 
cleared the air. 
</p><p> 
Garland, in a panic, was searching his pockets. 
</p><p> 
"What lot pockets!" sighed Black-Eyes, insidiously desiring to compose his 
nerves. 
</p><p> 
"Sixteen," admitted Garland. "I wish they were only one, just now. By Jove, 
I've lost that letter!" 
</p><p> 
The graceful mother arrived with the tobacco <hi rend="italic">bon</hi> (there appeared to 
be no servant), and Garland, professing an ignorance which seems problematical 
after three months in Japan, desired to be initiated into the art and mystery 
of the Japanese pipe. The tender was made to Purple-Eyes, but Black-Eyes 
undertook it. 
</p><p> 
<hi rend="italic">"So</hi>," she said, rolling a pellet of the tobacco, and putting it into 
the pipe; "an' <hi rend="italic">so</hi>," as she fearlessly put a live coal upon it with 
her fingers; <hi rend="italic">"so</hi>," as she put it to her own lips and sent out a tiny 
puff; "an' an' an' <hi rend="italic">so!"</hi> as she laughed and put it to his. 
And yet Garland found himself wishing that the other one had done it, and 
believing that she could do it better! And this, you perceive, was already 
perilous business. 
</p><p> 
It was afternoon when Garland arrived, 

  <pb entity="DSSR_000002634_0017" n="97"/>
and the mother's actions, though covered 
by diplomatic entrances and exits, with a view to impressing him to the contrary, 
indicated to him that she was cooking. And presently Purple-Eyes got up and 
lighted the <hi rend="italic">andon</hi>. Garland, who delighted in her grace of motion, 
had not yet learned that each movement was the result of much study and the 
practice of many stoical rules of decorum. However, he rose as far as his 
knees, and said he must go. A glance of alarm passed between the girls, and 
both stiffened in consternation. 
</p><p> 
"Sa-ay tha' 's not nize for us," accused the dark one, with valor. "Brownie 
he write unto us that you so kine with him, you give him you' las' pair boots, 
an' go naked on you' both feet. Tha' 's way we got do you. 
<hi rend="italic">But</hi> account you go'n' go 'way, we can not. Hence we got be always 
'shamed 'fore Brownie an' <hi rend="italic">aevery</hi>body. Tha' 's not nize for 
us." Garland had not risen above his knees, and she came hopefully forward. 
"Please don' go 'way!" She turned to Purple-Eyes in the peremptory way that 
Garland resented. "Sa-ay why <hi rend="italic">you</hi> don' as' him stay among us? 
Sa-ay don' you wish?" 
</p>
  
  <pb entity="DSSR_000002634_0018" n="98"/>
  <p> 
Garland's eyes followed. Unconsciously they besought her. 
</p><p> 
"We <hi rend="italic">lig</hi> if you stay among us," said Purple-Eyes, haltingly. 
</p><p> 
But there was something else just the timid lifting of an eyelid. Garland 
answered this with a rift of pleasure which shot across his face. 
</p><p> 
"Me? <hi rend="italic">I</hi> lig also if you stay among us I." 
</p><p> 
But now it was spoken to the mats. There was the edge of a smile visible, 
nevertheless, and Garland felt the courage it took for this. 
</p><p> 
"Well, if <hi rend="italic">you</hi> like," said Garland he laughed 
suddenly <hi rend="italic">"I</hi> like too." 
</p><p> 
"Thangs!" 
</p><p> 
They both said it at once; but some splendid reward passed from Purple-Eyes 
to Garland. 
</p><p> 
So presently they had a feast, in which four little tables stood in a 
circle one for each. There would have been only three had not Garland 
insisted that the mother should dine with them. He had not the least idea 
how fearfully he had disarranged domestic matters, for the mother, of course, 
instantly did as he requested. And then the 

  <pb entity="DSSR_000002634_0019" n="99"/>
three of them served him, and 
cunningly joined in engaging him while one or the other prepared the viands. 
But finally it was a very joyous meal; and only when the Osaka beer came 
on did Garland at all suspect how much out of the ordinary it was for them. 
They had forgotten to be taught how to open the bottles! 
</p></div2><div2 type="section" id="d7"> 
  <head>II THE SHADOW OF THE SHOJI </head> 
 
<p> 
And he went to sleep that night, when sleep came, on a floor that was as 
dainty as any bed, in a huge wadded overcoat called a <hi rend="italic">futon</hi>, on a 
wooden pillow that rocked and screeched a little (as if afraid to screech 
more) when he turned. An <hi rend="italic">andon</hi> burned dimly behind a screen, and he 
was aware of the slumberous aroma Japonica, as he characterized it. But he 
could not sleep of course not. For, less than six feet away, behind 
the translucent walls of paper, he could hear the melodious dithyrambics 
of the three voices. He could catch a sleepy word now and then, which he 
knew came from 

  <pb entity="DSSR_000002634_0020" n="100"/>
the blue-eyed one. They were much fewer than those of the 
other two. Some vague picture of those eyes, patiently sad, as he had conceived 
them, kept itself between him and sleep, until finally it was sudden morning, 
and the splendid light of Japan, subdued by the <hi rend="italic">shoji</hi>, was shining 
in his face. 
</p><p> 
He lay indolently awake for a long time, Presently a noise not much greater 
than the alighting of a fly upon a stretched screen drew his attention. He 
perceived a dampened finger slowly working against the other side of the 
<hi rend="italic">shoji</hi>, until presently the paper parted, and the finger came through. 
It was very pink at the tip. Slowly it reamed the hole larger, then disappeared, 
to be replaced by an eye. And the eye was blue. Garland nearly laughed aloud, 
until he remembered that he was the objective of the eye. Then unconsciously 
he arranged his hair a little, and began to pose. But the humor of it came 
down upon him again, and he laughed. The eyes instantly disappeared, and 
he could see the shadow of its owner gliding away. In a panic of regret, 
Garland called out: 
</p><p> 
"Don't go, Purple-Eyes!" 
</p><p> 
The shadow hesitated, and then returned. 
</p><p> 
"How you know tha' 's Purple-Eyes?" 
</p>
  <pb entity="DSSR_000002634_0021" n="101"/>
  <p> 
"By her own confession now." 
</p><p> 
Her pretty laugh sifted through the <hi rend="italic">shoji</hi>. 
</p><p> 
"You want me come unto you?" asked the voice beyond. "Tha' 's what I dunno." 
</p><p> 
Garland was (in his own phrase again) quite paralyzed. He might have thought, 
but he did not, that she was only tendering the offices of the servant they 
did not have; but he called out, with a mixture of bravado and trembling 
which alarmed them both: 
</p><p> 
"Yes; come in!" 
</p><p> 
The damaged <hi rend="italic">shoji</hi> slid haltingly aside, and she entered very slowly 
and softly; and he thought of the pictures of the returning Sun-Goddess as 
she came through the opening and down the burst of light it let in. As she 
prostrated herself Garland noticed that her hair had been newly dressed (an 
operation of several hours), and that she wore a dainty blue kimono, too 
gay for any but a geisha to wear. But it became her royally. 
</p><p> 
"You look more than ever like a picture on a fan," greeted Garland, with 
even more admiration in his eyes than in his voice. 
</p><p> 
Instead of being pleased, as any other Japanese girl would have been, Purple-Eyes 
slowly shook her head. 
</p>
  
  <pb entity="DSSR_000002634_0022" n="102"/>
  <p> 
"Alas! you naever see no picture on fan lig unto me." 
</p><p> 
"But I have," insisted Garland. 
</p><p> 
She shook her head again. 
</p><p> 
"Well, then, if not, why not?" 
</p><p> 
"They got not those purple eye an' pink face an' flaming hair " 
</p><p> 
She sighed, and looked askance at Garland. He seemed fully to agree with 
her. She changed her tone to one of resigned solicitude and ceremony. 
</p><p> 
"You sleeping well all those night?" 
</p><p> 
"Well, by the great Jehovah and the Continental Congress, if I were a Japanese 
artist, that is the kind of eyes and face and hair they should all have! 
Yes, sir! every blamed one of them!" 
</p><p> 
The girl caught her breath, and something flamed up her face and lighted 
her splendid eyes anew. She dared to look at him. It had all sounded quite 
true. Wistfully she dissembled this at least was truly Japanese. 
</p><p> 
"You sleeping well all" she lost her purpose for a moment "all 
those night all?" 
</p><p> 
"Blue eyes for me, every day in the week." 
</p>
  <pb entity="DSSR_000002634_0023" n="103"/>
  <p> 
"You sleeping well?" Joy was all too plainly in her voice now irrepressible 
joy. 
</p><p> 
He laughed, and caught her hands rapturously. She did not deny him, and he 
kissed them. 
</p><p> 
"Oh, you are delightful!" said he. 
</p><p> 
"Me? <hi rend="italic">I</hi> don' sleep moach." 
</p><p> 
"You look as fresh as new porcelain." 
</p><p> 
"Yaes; I been fix up," 
</p><p> 
She consciously let him look her over. 
</p><p> 
"No; I didn't sleep at first. I was listening to your voice," Garland confessed, 
quite without reservation. 
</p><p> 
The girl was confused a little. 
</p><p> 
"You don' lig be annoy with those voice?" 
</p><p> 
"Why, it is divine!" 
</p><p> 
A white shaft of fear crossed her face. 
</p><p> 
"Tha' 's jus' fun I egspeg?" 
</p><p> 
"Tha' 's ver' earnest," he gayly mocked. 
</p><p> 
He was pleasing her now. She even went with his mood a little way. Joy was 
such a beautiful and tempting and elusive thing! 
</p><p> 
"Lig goddess, mebby?" 
</p><p> 
Garland nodded seriously. 
</p><p> 
"Tha' 's nize for <hi rend="italic">me</hi>." 
</p><p> 
"An' for <hi rend="italic">me"</hi> in quite her own manner. 
</p>
  
  <pb entity="DSSR_000002634_0024" n="104"/>
  <p> 
"But not the goddesses?" 
</p><p> 
They laughed together, and she drew confidently a little closer to him. 
</p><p> 
"Listen; I go 'n' tell you a thing. You <hi rend="italic">not</hi> in fun <hi rend="italic">not?"</hi> 
</p><p> 
"I mean every word," declared Garland, "and more than I have words to mean." 
</p><p> 
"An' you lig be tell?" 
</p><p> 
"That is what I am waiting so impatiently for to be tell." 
</p><p> 
"Tha' 's nize. Eijinsan 'most always fun. Nobody but you aever lig those 
hair an' eye. Aeverybody hate me. <hi rend="italic">Why?</hi> Account they say I b'long pink-face 
people. Account my fadder he sei yo jin a west-ocean mans. <hi rend="italic">I</hi> 
di'n' do so unto those hair an' eye! I can <hi rend="italic">not</hi> help. <hi rend="italic">Me?</hi> When 
I see you got those purple eye lig unto me, an' also those yellow hairs, 
an' all pink in the face, I thing mebby you go'n' lig me liddle lig 
I was brodder an' fadder with you. Also, I thing mebby you go'n' take me 
away with you beyond those west-ocean, where pink-face people live. 
<hi rend="italic">Me?</hi> Don' you thing those pink-face people lig me liddle if I come 
unto them?" 
</p><p> 
"God bless you yes," said Garland, with something suspiciously tender 
in voice and 

  <pb entity="DSSR_000002634_0025" n="105"/>
eyes. He still had her hands, delighting in them, caressing 
them. The girl's face was irradiated. She poured out all her soul for him. 
</p><p> 
<hi rend="italic">"Me?</hi> Listen 'nother time. Before I know you' eyes purple an' you' 
hair yellow lig unto me, I lig you? <hi rend="italic">Me?</hi> Sa-ay I lig jus' your 
<hi rend="italic">picture!"</hi> She laughed, confused, and shifted a little closer. "You 
don' hate me account I doing those?" 
</p><p> 
"No," said Garland, guiltily "no, I don't hate you." 
</p><p> 
"Sa-ay you go'n' take me at those pink-face people?" 
</p><p> 
Garland was silent. 
</p><p> 
<hi rend="italic">"If</hi> you don', I got go myself. <hi rend="italic">Me?</hi> I <hi rend="italic">got</hi> go!" 
</p><p> 
Garland nodded, and she understood him to have assented. This was wrong. 
But her joy was superb, and Garland had a very soft heart. 
</p><p> 
"Oh <hi rend="italic">how</hi> that is nize! <hi rend="italic">Me?</hi> I got so. I dunno  all 
times seem lig I b'long 'cross west-ocean. Seem lig I different from 
<hi rend="italic">aevery</hi>body else. <hi rend="italic">Me?</hi> I got have somebody <hi rend="italic">lig</hi> 
me somebody <hi rend="italic">touch</hi> me  hole my 
hands <hi rend="italic">so so so!"</hi> She illustrated fervidly. 
</p>
  
  <pb entity="DSSR_000002634_0026" n="106"/>
  <p> 
Garland, alarmed at her dynamic emotion, released them. She returned them 
to him. 
</p><p> 
<hi rend="italic">"But</hi> nobody don' <hi rend="italic">wish</hi>. Others Japan people they 
don' lig be ligued. But me? I <hi rend="italic">got</hi> be  else I got pain in my heart 
an' am ill. You aever have those pain at you' heart lig you all times 
falling down down down? Tha' 's mos' tarrible. Tha' 's lone-some-ness. 
<hi rend="italic">Me?</hi> I thing I go'n' die sometime account that. Tha' 's lone-some-ness 
to cross west-ocean to pink-face people. Yaes; tha' 's why I <hi rend="italic">got</hi> do 
those. Oku-Sama tha' 's my modder she saying 'most all times, 'Jus' 
lig pink-face people. Always got be lig by 'nother touch by 
'nother speak sof' by 'nother.' An' tha' 's <hi rend="italic">you</hi>  yaes! You 
lig me, an' you touch me, an' you speak sof' unto me the ver' first time 
I seeing you. <hi rend="italic">Me?</hi> I <hi rend="italic">know</hi>, those time I first seeing you, that 
you don' hate me account I got those pink face upon me." 
</p><p> 
"No," admitted Garland, seriously. 
</p><p> 
<hi rend="italic">"How</hi> that is nize! It make something rest go 'sleep inside me. 
I got that peace. Jus' when you touch my hand at first I got some happiness. 
But <hi rend="italic">now</hi> I got that peace." 
</p><p> 
She began regretfully to detach herself. 

  <pb entity="DSSR_000002634_0027" n="107"/>
Garland detained her. She was very 
dainty and very confiding very wise. She had unconsciously got very 
close to him. And Garland had vanquished his alarm of her. 
</p><p> 
<hi rend="italic">"Me?</hi> I don' wish; but I got git you somethings eat. Soon you starve. 
I <hi rend="italic">got</hi>." 
</p><p> 
But Garland would not let her go and she was a willing captive, though 
she dissembled an urgent necessity. 
</p><p> 
"Where is Black-Eyes and your mother?" asked Garland. 
</p><p> 
The girl seemed reluctant, but told him that they all worked in the neighboring 
silk-mill, the pulsations of which he had heard in the night. 
</p><p> 
"Never mind. I'd rather famish," said the impulsive Garland, with a strange 
remorse. "Will you assist?" 
</p><p> 
"Yaes," laughed the girl. <hi rend="italic">"Me?</hi> I been famish  many times." 
</p><p> 
"Heavens!" breathed Garland, inventorying all her daintiness once more. "How 
much do your mother and sister earn?" 
</p><p> 
The girl seemed quite indifferent as to this. 
</p><p> 
"Sometime fi' sen; sometime ten fifteen; one times, twenty-two." 
</p><p> 
"And you?" 
</p>
  <pb entity="DSSR_000002634_0028" n="108"/>
  <p> 
"Me? Oh, jus' liddle." 
</p><p> 
She earned more than the other two. 
</p><p> 
"And what does it cost you to live?" 
</p><p> 
"Live? Half those fi' ten fifteen sen." 
</p><p> 
"And you save the rest? That is very prudent." 
</p><p> 
The girl looked bewildered; then she explained: 
</p><p> 
"Other half sen' Brownie." 
</p><p> 
He suddenly let her go. She leaned over him bewitchingly. 
</p><p> 
"Firs' some breakfas'; then I go'n' help you famish all day! What you 
thing?" 
</p><p> 
She came back in a moment. The sleeves of her kimono were tucked out of the 
way, and there was rice-flour on her pretty arms. 
</p><p> 
"You go'n' to naever tell 'bout those fi' ten  fifteen sen, 
an' all those?" 
</p><p> 
"No," said Garland; "I will never tell." 
</p><p> 
"Else they go'n' kill me," she threatened gayly. 
</p><p> 
"I prefer to have you live," he laughed, as brightly as he could. 
</p><p> 
"Tha' 's secret among jus' you an' me?" 
</p><p> 
"Yes," said Garland. 
</p><p> 
She started away, then came back. 
</p><p> 
<hi rend="italic">"Me?</hi> I lig I <hi rend="italic">lig</hi> have secret among jus' you an' me." 
With a radiant face she fled. 
</p>
  <pb entity="DSSR_000002634_0029" n="109"/>
  <p> 
And here was Brownie's poor little skeleton stripped naked. He had lived 
at the university like a gentleman. He was still living in Philadelphia like 
a gentleman. Garland wondered whether it would make any difference in 
Philadelphia if it were known that it was the pitiful 
"fi' ten fifteen sen'" that his mother and sisters earned each 
day that supported him. A great disgust for Brownie and a great pity for 
Purple-Eyes were the immediate postulates. And is not pity akin to love? 
  </p>
</div2>
  
  <div2 type="section" id="d8"> 
  <head>III THE DANCE OF THE RED MAPLE-LEAVES </head> 
 
<p> 
The question of making one's toilet in the interior of Japan is still a serious 
one for the American who lives behind closed doors and cherishes his divine 
right of privacy. Garland had solved the vexation for all his contemporaries 
(according to Garland) by making his toilet as to half or quarter of his 
sacred person at a time (depending somewhat upon the danger of surprise), 
thus reducing the chances of exposure by one-half 

  <pb entity="DSSR_000002634_0030" n="110"/>
or three-quarters. Purple-Eyes 
brought him the requisites for his toilet, and the moment she was gone he 
bared his shoulders and chest, and plunged into the delightful water, perfumed, 
like everything else, with the aroma Japonica. But his pretty hostess reappeared 
through the movable walls at an unwatched place. 
</p><p> 
He abandoned a momentary impulse to scuttle behind the screen because of 
the admiration he saw in her eyes, and then he half turned that she might 
see the muscles of his back. 
</p><p> 
<hi rend="italic">"How</hi> you are beau-ti-ful!" she said slowly, as her eyes traveled, 
quite without embarrassment, over his athletic uppers. 
</p><p> 
"Thanks," he laughed, with pleasure in the little incident. 
</p><p> 
Garland turned a little further, and raised his arms above his head in the 
way of athletes. 
</p><p> 
She handed him a towel he had dropped. 
</p><p> 
"I thing I come tell you we got large tub for bath," she said then. 
</p><p> 
"Where is it?" asked Garland, suspiciously. 
</p><p> 
"There." 
</p><p> 
She pointed. 
</p>
    
    <pb entity="DSSR_000002634_0031" n="111"/>
    <p> 
"That's what I thought. You must excuse me. I can't perform that sacred rite 
in the fierce light that beats upon a front porch." 
</p><p> 
"Yaes? Eijinsan don' lig?" She did not understand. 
</p><p> 
"No," admitted Garland. 
</p><p> 
"Also, you lig for me go 'way liddle?" 
</p><p> 
Garland said yes, and she went. 
</p><p> 
When she returned, it was with a delightful breakfast of fish, rice, and 
persimmons. She put the little table between them, and on her knees, on the 
other side, taught him how to eat as a Japanese should. This is really not 
difficult, except the chopsticks; and with these she had to help him so often 
that their fingers were in almost constant contact. Alas! Garland made it 
as difficult as possible. And, alas! Garland was glad of the chopsticks! 
</p><p> 
Her joy overflowed the mouth and eyes which it seemed should know nothing 
but tears. 
</p><p> 
Afterward he helped her, with masculine joy of his own ineptitude, to reform 
the apartment, and secrete the things which had made it successively a 
reception-room, sleeping-chamber, and breakfast-room. You may 

  <pb entity="DSSR_000002634_0032" n="112"/>
judge whether 
or not this was delightful to a fellow like Garland, and also whether it 
was perilous. 
</p><p> 
It is not often that one has the felicity of ending one's breakfast with 
a song, and then of ending the song with a dance. Purple-Eyes brought her 
samisen quite without suggestion from Garland, and said with naivete: 
</p><p> 
"I go'n' sing you a song. You lig me sing?" 
</p><p> 
"Try me!" challenged Garland, with an admiration in his eyes which pleased 
her greatly. 
</p><p> 
"Long down behine the Suwanee River" was the curious song she sang, in Japanese 
English. 
</p><p> 
Garland laughed. 
</p><p> 
"Don' you lig those?" she pouted. "I learn it for you.'" 
</p><p> 
He said it was lovely, and begged her to go on. 
</p><p> 
But his eyes wandered from the fingers on the strings to those on the plectrum, 
and then away to the lips above; and when she turned into the chorus he joined 
her with his inconstant eyes still there. It was only an 

  <pb entity="DSSR_000002634_0033" n="113"/>
indifferent tenor, 
but the girl thought it full of fervor. It was only that it joined and mingled 
with hers as she fancied their spirits doing and might always do. 
</p><p> 
<hi rend="italic">"How</hi> that is nize!" she breathed in frank ecstasy. "You got voice 
lig lig " 
</p><p> 
But there was nothing at hand to compare it with, and she laughed confessingly. 
</p><p> 
"Nothing," said Garland. "It's original." 
</p><p> 
"Yaes nothing original," she admitted. 
</p><p> 
"Sing another," begged Garland, with enthusiasm. 
</p><p> 
She did "When the swallows flying home"; and then still another "'Tis 
the last rosebud summer." 
</p><p> 
"Where did you learn them?" asked he. 
</p><p> 
"That day when I got you' picture. <hi rend="italic">Me?</hi> I thing you lig me sing, mebby. 
Well, I git those song; I make them United States' language, so you comprehend." 
</p><p> 
"God bless you!" said Garland. 
</p><p> 
The girl leaned forward with dewy eyes. 
</p><p> 
"Sa-ay you lig me also dance jus' 
one liddle dance for <hi rend="italic">you?"</hi> 
</p><p> 
She came bewitchingly nearer. Garland glanced again at her geisha-like costume. 


  <pb entity="DSSR_000002634_0034" n="114"/>
Had she thought all this out for his entertainment, he wondered. 
</p><p> 
"Yes," he said. 
</p><p> 
"But you naev <hi rend="italic">naever</hi> go'n' tell?" 
</p><p> 
She raised her brows, and held up a finger archly. 
</p><p> 
"On my sacred honor!" laughed Garland. 
</p><p> 
"No one?" 
</p><p> 
"Not a soul." 
</p><p> 
"Tha' 's go'n' be 'nother secret among jus' you an' me foraever an' aever?" 
</p><p> 
"Forever and ever," announced Garland, as if it were the Service. 
</p><p> 
"Account if you aever do, they go'n' kill me!" 
</p><p> 
"What! Kill you?" 
</p><p> 
"Dade!" She nodded ominously. 
</p><p> 
"Who?" 
</p><p> 
"Black-Eyes an' those modder." 
</p><p> 
"Oh!" said Garland. He understood. 
</p><p> 
He was left to guess that this dainty flower had been taught the arts of 
a geisha to assist also in keeping up Brownie's state. 
</p><p> 
"I lig dance for <hi rend="italic">you</hi>," confessed the girl, joyously. "Others? No; 
I do not lig. They as' me, 'Where you got those pink face?' <hi rend="italic">Me?</hi>' I 
don' lig those. I rather work in those mill. My modder an' my 
  <pb entity="DSSR_000002634_0035" n="115"/>
sister getting 
all times an-gery account I don' dance. <hi rend="italic">But</hi> tha' 's in-sult 
upon me! I don't <hi rend="italic">lig</hi> be insult. So! <hi rend="italic">Me?</hi> I jus' don' dance for 
no one  but but but jus' <hi rend="italic">you!"</hi> 
</p><p> 
She vanished through the <hi rend="italic">shoji</hi>, and presently returned, a symphony 
in autumnal reds and browns. 
</p><p> 
"I go'n' dance for you that red maple-leaf dance. Me? I am that leaf." 
</p><p> 
"You look it," said Garland, more tenderly than he knew. 
</p><p> 
The girl spread her garments that he might inspect her. 
</p><p> 
"This is a forest," she went on; "an' you sa-ay  you a <hi rend="italic">tree!</hi> 
Aha, ha, ha!" 
</p><p> 
She laughed, made him a noble courtesy, and murmured a little tune to which 
she floated down from the top of a maple-tree. For a while she lay quite 
still, shivering a little. Then the wind stirred her, and she rose, and swept 
down upon Garland, then back and into a whirl of other leaves. Then hither 
and thither, merrily, like an autumn leaf, until she shivered down at his 
feet, with bowed head. 
</p><p> 
She was making it more and more perilous for Garland. 
</p></div2>
  
  <div2 type="section" id="d9"> 
    <pb entity="DSSR_000002634_0036" n="116"/>
  <head>IV <hi rend="italic">"HOW THAT IS NIZE!"</hi></head> 
 
<p> 
That night they had a gay little supper, with a tiny servant, who, Garland 
guessed, with entire accuracy, had been borrowed for the occasion. 
</p><p> 
"You got nize day?" asked Black-Eyes. 
</p><p> 
Garland caught a startled glance from Purple-Eyes, and answered discreetly 
that he had had oh, yes; a very pleasant day, giving no damaging 
particulars. 
</p><p> 
But Black-Eyes fancied from the blankness of his countenance that he was 
indulging in the same kind of prevarication with which she would have met 
such a question. She devoted herself to him all the rest of the evening. 
As he retired for the night, the last thing she said to him, with a reproachful 
glance at Purple-Eyes, was: 
</p><p> 
"To-morrow you go'n' have mos' bes' nize times. <hi rend="italic">I</hi> go'n' stay home 
with you!" 
</p><p> 
And she did, making it a very dreary day for Garland. He could not help thinking 
of Purple-Eyes at the factory, with her dainty hands begrimed. 
</p>
    
    <pb entity="DSSR_000002634_0037" n="117"/>
    <p> 
But presently, when she returned, there was no grime upon her hands. She 
was dainty and smiling. 
</p><p> 
"You got nize day?" she asked, with her head coyly down. She knew he had 
not. And she purposely quoted her sister. 
</p><p> 
"No," he said savagely. "I'm glad it's over." 
</p><p> 
The flame was in her face again. But she kept it down. 
</p><p> 
"I thing Black-Eyes ver' be-witch-ing." 
</p><p> 
"But she is not <hi rend="italic">you</hi>," he said. 
</p><p> 
She looked slowly up. The little weariness which had been limned upon her 
face by the day's drudgery was gone, and in its stead was a vague glory rejected 
from within. 
</p><p> 
<hi rend="italic">"How</hi> that is nize," she whispered "for <hi rend="italic">me!"</hi> 
</p><p> 
"For me," said Garland, approaching her threateningly. She did not retreat. 
She subsided a little toward him just a little that he might know 
she would never retreat from him. Her eyes smiled confidently. 
</p><p> 
He stopped where he was. 
</p><p> 
"Who is to be chatelaine to-morrow?" 
</p><p> 
"What is that chat ?" she asked. 
</p><p> 
"Who is to keep the house?" 
</p>
    
    <pb entity="DSSR_000002634_0038" n="118"/>
    <p> 
"Me. Me one day, Black-Eyes next." 
</p><p> 
She saw his face lighten. 
</p><p> 
"You lig that?" 
</p><p> 
"I like half of it." 
</p><p> 
She thought a moment until she understood; then she lifted her shining face. 
</p><p> 
"Ah, Eijinsan, how be-witch-ing <hi rend="italic">you</hi> are!" 
</p></div2><div2 type="section" id="d10"> 
  <head>V THE PLAINTIVE TEMPLE BELLS </head> 
 
<p> 
The next day they went up to the temple on the mountain-side, the plaintive 
bells of which Garland had heard. Purple-Eyes was tall, and walked with less 
difficulty than most Japanese girls, so they walked. It was a day of dreams. 
Garland remembered afterward the smell of the incense, the voices of the 
chanting <hi rend="italic">bonzes</hi>, that the tea-house on the mountain-side where they 
rested called itself the House of the Seven Golden Crystals; the rest was 
Purple-Eyes and happiness. Japan had been growing upon him for three 
months, and now unhappiness made but little impression. 
</p>
  
  <pb entity="DSSR_000002634_0039" n="119"/>
  <p> 
The day remained in his mind with the sum of his dreams this lotus-eating, 
nectar-drinking, happy-go-lucky Garland! 
</p><p> 
Thus it curiously went on. One day it was Black-Eyes, and the true Japan, 
and the real Garland. The next it was Purple-Eyes, and the ideal Japan, and 
the lotus-eating Garland. What is more like lotus-eating than being adored? 
At first Garland used to smile at the strange dual life which circumstances 
had wrought out for him. Then he used to wonder which was better. Later he 
tried to decide only which he liked better. Now he no longer differentiated 
at all. His analytical edge was quite dulled. Still, he had heard that this 
fever of Japan always wore off. Some said it lasted as long as two years, 
some said five; no one had said ten. And what then? 
</p><p> 
"Why, then? <hi rend="italic">Me!"</hi> 
</p><p> 
He had spoken the last three words aloud, and they had been answered by the 
laughing, dewy-eyed subject of them. 
</p><p> 
He looked at her. 
</p><p> 
"Well, one ought to be content," he laughed. 
</p><p> 
"An' you content?" she smiled back. 
</p><p> 
He did not answer at once. 
</p>
  
  <pb entity="DSSR_000002634_0040" n="120"/>
  <p> 
"Do you know that you have been growing more bewitching every day since " 
</p><p> 
"Sinze <hi rend="italic">you</hi> an' <hi rend="italic">joy</hi> came at Japan?" 
</p><p> 
From the opened <hi rend="italic">shoji</hi> she flung him the gay greeting he had taught 
her, and disappeared; for it was Black-Eyes' day, and she had yet to dress 
for her work. 
</p><p> 
That day he harbored madly the notion of marriage with Purple-Eyes and a 
residence in Japan. It had quite infected him before night, and was distinctly, 
but less and less strongly, in his mind for several days. But then came a 
letter from his elder brother, in answer to his own of a rather confessional 
and emotional sort, asking him what he meant by living upon three working-women. 
It told him to go away to the devil anywhere but away from 
there. It was like a cold douche. The fever Japonica, as every one had said, 
was at last gone. So small a thing as his brother's letter had cured it. 
Now he smiled. He had meant to write to Miss Warburton, offering to release 
her. 
</p></div2><div2 type="section" id="d11"> 
  <pb entity="DSSR_000002634_0041" n="121"/>
  <head>VI "SAYONARA?" </head> 
 
<p> 
I know not what he said to Purple-Eyes, but with her tears there was a certain 
buoyancy that had not been there but for some hope. And why not? For Garland 
was a very sweet and gentle fellow, who abhorred pain. The three went to 
see him off, and he tried desperately to be gay; but something was pulling 
at his heart-strings, and there were tears perilously near his eyes. Black-Eyes 
did not marvel at this. She had always understood that it was the way of 
west-ocean men. But they were only too evidently ready to be answered by 
other tears in the dewy eyes that were blue. And <hi rend="italic">this</hi> was annoying 
to Black-Eyes. She made her sister tremble by a look. So she of the blue 
eyes could only grasp and hold Garland's big hand in both her own exquisite 
ones when the others looked away. When their eyes returned hers looked off 
to the big funnels of the ship, though she still held the hand. But when 
she looked at Garland again he had his handkerchief to his eyes; something 

  <pb entity="DSSR_000002634_0042" n="122"/>
inside had given way. Then hers came from her sleeve, too. So at last it 
was quite a little tragedy. 
</p><p> 
Sad it is that one forgets that one has eaten of the lotus; but thus it is 
with the lotus, and thus did Garland. 
</p><p> 
That night, in bed, Black-Eyes undertook some criticism of Garland. Her sister 
flared up in a way that was new and superb. 
</p><p> 
"Tha' 's a lie! He's the mos' bes' nize gent in the whole worl'." And she 
fell to sobbing. 
</p><p> 
"What is the matter?" asked the mother, who was kinder than Black-Eyes. 
</p><p> 
"I got that lone-some-ness," sobbed the girl, in answer. 
</p><p> 
"Poor little pink-face!" said the mother, touching her cheek. "Always must 
be touch by some one!" 
</p><p> 
<hi rend="italic">"Me?"</hi> said Purple-Eyes, with a power and assurance which were startling. 
"I am glad I have that pink face!" She laughed. "And I am glad I have 
<hi rend="italic">not</hi> that brown face! Aha!" 
</p><p> 
The mother asked in alarm: 
</p><p> 
"Has the Eijinsan told you strange things?" 
</p><p> 
"The strangest and most beautiful things in all the world!" breathed Purple-Eyes. 


  <pb entity="DSSR_000002634_0043" n="123"/>
"Not <hi rend="italic">told</hi> them, but looked them thought them to me." 
</p><p> 
"And you believed?" 
</p><p> 
"I believed." 
</p><p> 
"That is very sad," said the mother. "It is the way of the west-ocean men." 
</p><p> 
"Ah, it <hi rend="italic">is</hi> his way, thank Shaka! and it is <hi rend="italic">not</hi> sad. It is very 
joyous." 
</p><p> 
"Shaka grant that it is not, my daughter. To the Eijinsan you are only a 
plaything, I fear." 
</p><p> 
"He may have me for a plaything," said the girl, defiantly. "Who has not 
playthings?" 
</p><p> 
"When a plaything becomes shabby " 
</p><p> 
"But I am not, and I never shall be." 
</p><p> 
"In a little while we shall know," said the mother, finally. 
</p><p> 
"In a little while we shall know," repeated the girl, joyously. 
</p></div2><div2 type="section" id="d12"> 
  <head>VII "WHAT YOU BED?" </head> 
 
<p> 
Later they found the letter in the discarded conversation-book. It said 
that Garland was having his final outing before becoming a 

  <pb entity="DSSR_000002634_0044" n="124"/>
Benedick; and 
the missionary on the hill told them that that meant that he was to be married 
upon his return to America. Purple-Eyes drew a sharp breath, then faced the 
other two savagely. She was able to laugh presently; but it was a very piteous 
laugh. 
</p><p> 
"Tha' 's what I know! Aha, ha, ha! He he tell me all those." But 
the pitiful lie stuck in her throat, and her lips were dry. "He tell me 
<hi rend="italic">aevery</hi>-thing! Yaes" to a look of doubt from Black-Eyes  
"he go'n' marry that other for jus' liddle " 
</p><p> 
"Speak Japanese," said her mother, who was not so clever at English as her 
daughters; but the request fell like a lash upon Purple-Eyes' heart. 
</p><p> 
"I will not!" she flamed forth, "I will speak his language. He will come 
for me. If he do not come, I shall go to him. He go'n' marry that 
other <hi rend="italic">if</hi> he marry her <hi rend="italic">if</hi> jus' 
liddle <hi rend="italic">Me?</hi> He go'n' marry me las' an' foraever!" 
</p><p> 
Suddenly she became aware that she had betrayed her secret. 
</p><p> 
"Oh, all the gods in the sky!" she cried in anguish. "Tha' 's lie. He 
<hi rend="italic">not</hi> go'n' marry me. He <hi rend="italic">don'</hi> say. Jus' I thing so jus' 
I " She had to debase herself still 

  <pb entity="DSSR_000002634_0045" n="125"/>
further, if she would be shriven. 
"He <hi rend="italic">not</hi> go'n' come for me. I <hi rend="italic">not</hi> go'n' go at him. <hi rend="italic">Me?</hi> 
Tha' 's correc', Oku-San; I jus' his liddle plaything. He don' say nawthing. 
Jus' <hi rend="italic">I</hi> thing so." 
</p><p> 
Her mother nodded. 
</p><p> 
"And when he tires of the plaything " 
</p><p> 
She threw an imaginary something into the air. 
</p><p> 
"Yaes," whispered Purple-Eyes, humbly bowing her head; but when her face 
was down she smiled. It was all very sure to her. As she looked up she saw 
something like malevolence upon the face of her sister. 
</p><p> 
<hi rend="italic">"But</hi> also he not <hi rend="italic">go'n'</hi> marry that other foraever!" 
</p><p> 
Her sister smiled unbelievingly, 
</p><p> 
"I bed you don'!" 
</p><p> 
"Ah! <hi rend="italic">what</hi> you bed?" challenged Black-Eyes. 
</p><p> 
"That heart in my bosom!" answered Purple-Eyes. 
</p></div2><div2 type="section" id="d13"> 
  <head>VIII LONE-SOME-NESS </head> 
 
<p> 
Garland did not reach the end of his ante-Benedick wanderings until a year 
later. 

  <pb entity="DSSR_000002634_0046" n="126"/>
Then he found, among other letters awaiting him, one in a long, dainty 
envelope addressed in English and Japanese. He knew it was from Purple-Eyes 
before he opened it. It was seven months old. 
</p><p> 
As he read, all her little tricks of inflection came back upon him. He knew 
that her long white hands were waving emphases at him very gently. The 
questioning which her eyes had learned after his coming as if she were 
not quite sure of something was upon him out of the shadows beyond the 
lamp. The subtle aromas which always exhaled from her garments were distinct 
enough to startle him. He looked quickly back and about the room. Then he 
laughed softly. But his face had flushed, and gladness had lit his eyes. 
The fever Japonica was once more in his veins and it was his own 
room and America with only her pictured face (fallen from the envelope) 
before him herself on the other side of the world. Unconsciously he 
read aloud in her voice and manner: 
</p><p> 
"That is ledder from me, Miss Purple-Eyes, unto you, Mister J. F. Garland. 
That is nize day in Japan. I lig if you hoarry soon coming at Japan 'nother 
time. You 

  <pb entity="DSSR_000002634_0047" n="127"/>
been 'way ver' long time. I lig if you hoarry account aeverybody 
hating me more an' more. I got those feeling again 'bout somethings I want 
an' have not got it, That is lone-some-ness. That is to cross west-ocean. 
You have also got those? Me? I been that sad aever sinze you gone me away 
from. I been that ill. I thing mebby I go'n' die soon. <hi rend="italic">Aexcep'</hi> you 
come? Say you go'n' come, that I don' die? Black-Eye she all times make amusement 
'bout you don' come. That is a liar. She don' know you who you are. She don' 
know you that you go'n' come soon as you kin. Mebby you go'n' marry with 
those pink-face for liddle while? Me? I study those conversation-book so 
I kin write unto you. Also, I fine those ledder you lose when you first arrive 
among us at Japan. You desire those ledder? Me? I keep it upon my bosom among 
those photograph of you. Mister J. F. Garland, I don' keer you do marry those 
other for liddle while. Then you go'n' marry me las' an' foraever. Jus' hoarry. 
Yit I am not gay. I can not be gay until you come again. That is sad for 
me. Also, you do not lig for me be gay, but lig unto widow till you come. 
Then, Mister J. F. Garland, 

  <pb entity="DSSR_000002634_0048" n="128"/>
I shall be that happy. Mebby you ill an' can 
not come unto me? Then I come unto you, if you wish me. What you thing? That 
is a picture of me lig I promise. I fix up same lig those day you hol' my 
hands. How that was nize! That is first time I aever been my hands hol' so 
nize so sof'. Mister J. F. Garland, that is you hol' my hands that sof'. 
Me? I don' let no one else do those unto my hands lig you wishing, mebby. 
Jus' you. Mister J. F. Garland, you go'n' hol' my hands all times this 
after-while? Say, don' stay marry with that other so ver' long. Account those 
lone-some-ness. Please sen' me picture of those other you marry unto. If 
you marry unto them. I lig see how she is that beautiful. Please write me 
letter aevery day. Please come back that soon. So I kin be joyous. It is 
that sad for me." 
</p><p> 
Every laboriously formed letter, printed like the first copy of a child at 
school, told him what this had cost her; and the little flourishes at the 
end, where she had grown more certain, what pride she had in them! The picture 
was exquisitely colored, as only the Japanese can color them, and had been 
very costly to her. He set it before him, and 

  <pb entity="DSSR_000002634_0049" n="129"/>
with his head in his hands 
studied it. The eyes were very blue, but no bluer than her own. They looked 
into his half sadly, half gayly, tempting him again. The Japan fever had 
its way with him, and for a moment ten he lived that lotus life 
with her over again. Then came a great upheaval inside which was yearning. 
He was tired. He had been tired ever since leaving Japan. In those eyes he 
saw again the invitation to rest. The hair, with its brassy lustre he 
could see the sun on it again smell its perfume  feel it under 
his hands. The lips were parted a little, as they nearly always were, and 
within showed the brilliant teeth. 
</p><p> 
"Oh," he cried out, as he rose, "get thee behind me moon-goddess get 
thee behind me!" He laughed wofully, and took up the picture again. "I thought 
it gone the fever the dreaming the lotus-eating." 
</p><p> 
There was a knock on the door, and a messenger-boy handed in the answer to 
a note. 
</p><p> 
"Yes," it ran; "I shall be home at eight <hi rend="italic">and so glad!"</hi> 
</p><p> 
It was twenty minutes to eight. 
</p><p> 
Garland hurried into his evening clothes and hastened away, leaving the rest 
of the 

  <pb entity="DSSR_000002634_0050" n="130"/>
letters unopened. But he came back, from down the stairs, and again 
set the picture up before him. Then he strode softly up and down the apartment, 
a smile half sad, half gay, upon his face. The little clock chimed the few 
notes which told him it was a quarter past eight. He smiled another 
kind of smile. He had forgotten that she would be at home at eight and 
would be glad! He looked again briefly at the picture of Purple-Eyes. There 
was moisture in his own. Then softly, as if it were sentient, he turned it 
face down and went out. 
</p> 
</div2> 
</div1>  
</body> 
</text> 
</TEI.2> 
