<?xml version="1.0"?>

<?dlps id="OskProb"?>
<?dlps page-images="color" figure-images="no"?>
<?dlps transcription="other"?>

<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/tei-p4/tei2.dtd" [
<!ENTITY % POSTKB "INCLUDE">
<!ENTITY % TEI.extensions.ent SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.ent">
<!ENTITY % TEI.extensions.dtd SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.dtd">
<!ENTITY % ISOpub SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/charent/iso-pub.ent"> %ISOpub;


<!ENTITY DSSR_000002588_0001 SYSTEM "000002588_0001" NDATA uvaHighRes>
<!ENTITY DSSR_000002588_0002 SYSTEM "000002588_0002" NDATA uvaHighRes>
<!ENTITY DSSR_000002588_0003 SYSTEM "000002588_0003" NDATA uvaHighRes>
<!ENTITY DSSR_000002588_0004 SYSTEM "000002588_0004" NDATA uvaHighRes>
<!ENTITY DSSR_000002588_0005 SYSTEM "000002588_0005" NDATA uvaHighRes>
<!ENTITY DSSR_000002588_0006 SYSTEM "000002588_0006" NDATA uvaHighRes>
<!ENTITY DSSR_000002588_0007 SYSTEM "000002588_0007" NDATA uvaHighRes>
]>
<TEI.2 id="OskProb">
    <teiHeader creator="Etext" type="migrated">
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title type="main">The Problem of Old Harjo</title>
                <title type="sort">problem of old harjo</title>
                <author>Oskison, John M.</author>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Creation of machine-readable version:</resp>
                    <name>Judy Boss</name>
                    <resp>Creation of digital images:</resp>
                    <name>Craig Simmons</name>
                    <resp>Conversion to TEI.2-conformant markup:</resp>
                    <name>University of Virginia Library Electronic Text Center.</name>
                </respStmt>
            </titleStmt>
            <extent>ca. <num type="kilobytes">20</num> kilobytes</extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>University of Virginia Library</publisher>
                <pubPlace>Charlottesville, Virginia</pubPlace>
                <idno type="ETC">OskProb</idno>
                <date value="1996-12">December 1996</date>
                <availability status="public">
                    <p n="copyright">Copyright &#xa9; 1996 by the Rector and Visitors of the
                        University of Virginia</p>
                    <p n="access">Publicly accessible</p>
                </availability>
                <idno type="uva-pid">uva-lib:477234</idno>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title>University of Virginia Library, Text collection</title>
                <idno type="uva-set">UVA-LIB-Text</idno>
            </seriesStmt>
            <notesStmt>
                <note>
                    <p>Judy Boss made the following editorial changes to the print version: page
                        236, paragraph 2, line 2, "and&#x2014;" to "and&#x2014;""; page 236,
                        paragraph 9, line 3, "an order" to "in order"; page 240, paragraph 5, line
                        4, "grevious" to "grievous".</p>
                </note>
            </notesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull>
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title type="main">The Problem of Old Harjo</title>
                        <title level="j">The Southern Workman</title>
                        <title type="sort">problem of old harjo</title>
                        <author>John M. Oskison</author>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <p>1st Edition</p>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent>pp.235 -241</extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Hampton Institute Press</publisher>
                        <pubPlace>Hampton, Virginia</pubPlace>
                        <date value="1907-04">April 1907</date>
                        <idno type="callNo">Print copy consulted: UVa Library Call Number: LC2701
                            .S7</idno>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <notesStmt>
                        <note>
                            <p>The Southern Workman, Vol. 36 (April 1907): pp. 235-241.</p>
                        </note>
                    </notesStmt>
                </biblFull>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>Prepared for the University of Virginia Library Electronic Text Center.</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <p>All quotation marks retained as data.</p>
                <p>All unambiguous end-of-line hyphens have been removed, and the trailing part of a
                    word has been joined to the preceding line.</p>
                <p>The images exist as archived TIFF images, one or more JPEG versions for general
                    use, and thumbnail GIFs.</p>
                <p>Keywords in the header are a local Electronic Text Center scheme to aid in
                    establishing analytical groupings.</p>
            </editorialDecl>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <creation>
                <date value="1907-04">April 1907</date>
            </creation>
            <langUsage>
                <language id="eng" usage="main">English</language>
            </langUsage>
            <textClass>
                <keywords>
                    <term>fiction; prose</term>
                    <term>Native American</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change>
                <date value="1996-12">December 1996</date>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>corrector</resp>
                    <name>Craig Simmons; Electronic Text Center at The University of Virginia</name>
                </respStmt>
                <item>Added TEI header and tags. Scanned images. Checked and parsed SGML
                tagging.</item>
            </change>
            <change>
                <date value="2005-07">July 2005</date>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Corrector</resp>
                    <name>John Ivor Carlson</name>
                </respStmt>
                <item>Converted to XML and/or checked tags.</item>
            </change>
            <change>
                <date value="2007-09">September 2007</date>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Migration</resp>
                    <name>Ethan Gruber, University of Virginia Library</name>
                </respStmt>
                <item>Converted XML markup from TEI Lite to uva-dl-tei (TEI P4 with local
                    customizations).</item>
            </change>
            <change>
                <date value="2008-01">January 2008</date>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Migration</resp>
                    <name>Greg Murray, University of Virginia Library</name>
                </respStmt>
                <item>Programmatically updated TEI header markup (but not header content) for
                    minimal compliance with current QA requirements.</item>
            </change>
<change>
<date value="2009-03">March 2009</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>Migration</resp>
<name>Scholarly Resources, University of Virginia Library</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Added and/or replaced the digital images accompanying the electronic text. Scanning of exterior and interior (ie. pages) of item was done only for items found in the University of Virginia Special Collections Library.</item>
</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text id="d1">
        <body id="d2">

            <div1 id="d3" type="story">
                <pb entity="DSSR_000002588_0001" n="235"/>
                <head>THE PROBLEM OF OLD HARJO <lb/><lb/>JOHN M. OSKISON </head>
                <p> THE Spirit of the Lord had descended upon old Harjo. From the new missionary,
                    just out from New York, he had learned that he was a sinner. The fire in the new
                    missionary's eyes and her gracious appeal had convinced old Harjo that this was
                    the time to repent and be saved. He was very much in earnest, and he assured
                    Miss Evans that he wanted to be baptized and received into the church at once.
                    Miss Evans was enthusiastic and went to Mrs. Rowell with the news. It was Mrs.
                    Rowell who had said that it was no use to try to convert the older Indians, and
                    she, after fifteen years of work in Indian Territory missions, should have
                    known. Miss Evans was pardonably proud of her conquest. </p>
                <pb entity="DSSR_000002588_0002" n="236"/>

                <p>"Old Harjo converted!" exclaimed Mrs. Rowell. "Dear Miss Evans, do you know that
                    old Harjo has two wives?" To the older woman it was as if some one had said to
                    her "Madame, the Sultan of Turkey wishes to teach one of your mission Sabbath
                    school classes." </p>
                <p>"But," protested the younger woman, "he is really sincere, and&mdash;" </p>
                <p>"Then ask him," Mrs. Rowell interrupted a bit sternly, "if he will put away one
                    of his wives. Ask him, before he comes into the presence of the Lord, if he is
                    willing to conform to the laws of the country in which he lives, the country
                    that guarantees his idle existence. Miss Evans, your work is not even begun." No
                    one who knew Mrs. Rowell would say that she lacked sincerity and patriotism. Her
                    own cousin was an earnest crusader against Mormonism, and had gathered a goodly
                    share of that wagonload of protests that the Senate had been asked to read when
                    it was considering whether a certain statesman of Utah should be allowed to
                    represent his state at Washington. </p>
                <p>In her practical, tactful way, Mrs. Rowell had kept clear of such embarrassments.
                    At first, she had written letters of indignant protest to the Indian Office
                    against the toleration of bigamy amongst the tribes. A wise inspector had been
                    sent to the mission, and this man had pointed out that it was better to ignore
                    certain things, "deplorable, to be sure," than to attempt to make over the
                    habits of the old men. Of course, the young Indians would not be permitted to
                    take more than one wife each." </p>
                <p>So Mrs. Rowell had discreetly limited her missionary efforts to the young, and
                    had exercised toward the old and bigamous only that strict charity which even a
                    hopeless sinner might claim. </p>
                <p>Miss Evans, it was to be regretted, had only the vaguest notions about
                    "expediency;" so weak on matters of doctrine was she that the news that Harjo
                    was living with two wives didn't startle her. She was young and possessed of but
                    one enthusiasm&mdash;that for saving souls. </p>
                <p>"I suppose," she ventured, "that old Harjo <hi rend="italic">must</hi> put away
                    one wife before he can join the church?" </p>
                <p>"There can be no question about it, Miss Evans." </p>
                <p>"Then I shall have to ask him to do it." Miss Evans regretted the necessity for
                    forcing this sacrifice, but had no doubt that the Indian would make it in order
                    to accept the gift of salvation which she was commissioned to bear to him. </p>
                <p>Harjo lived in a "double" log cabin three miles from the mission. His ten acres
                    of corn had been gathered into its fence-rail crib; four hogs that were to
                    furnish his winter's bacon had been brought in from the woods and penned
                    conveniently near to the crib; out in a corner of the garden, a fat mound of
                    dirt rose where the crop of turnips and potatoes had been buried against the
                    corrupting frost; and in the hayloft of his log stable were stored many
                    pumpkins, dried corn, <pb entity="DSSR_000002588_0003" n="237"/> onions (suspended in bunches from the
                    rafters) and the varied forage that Mrs. Harjo number one and Mrs. Harjo number
                    two had thriftily provided. Three cows, three young heifers, two colts, and two
                    patient, capable mares bore the Harjo brand, a fantastic <hi rend="bold">"H-|"</hi>
                    <ref n="1" target="n1" type="ed">*</ref> that the old man had designed.
                    Materially, Harjo was solvent; and if the Government had ever come to his aid he
                    could not recall the date. </p>
                <p>This attempt to rehabilitate old Harjo morally, Miss Evans felt, was not one to
                    be made at the mission; it should be undertaken in the Creek's own home where
                    the evidences of his sin should confront him as she explained. </p>
                <p>When Miss Evans rode up to the block in front of Harjo's cabin, the old Indian
                    came out, slowly and with a broadening smile of welcome on his face. A clean
                    gray flannel shirt had taken the place of the white collarless garment, with
                    crackling stiff bosom, that he had worn to the mission meetings. Comfortable,
                    well-patched moccasins had been substituted for creaking boots, and brown
                    corduroys, belted in at the waist, for tight black trousers. His abundant gray
                    hair fell down on his shoulders. In his eyes, clear and large and black, glowed
                    the light of true hospitality. Miss Evans thought of the patriarchs as she saw
                    him lead her horse out to the stable; thus Abraham might have looked and lived. </p>
                <p>"Harjo," began Miss Evans before following the old man to the covered passageway
                    between the disconnected cabins, "is it true that you have two wives?" Her tone
                    was neither stern nor accusatory. The Creek had heard that question before, from
                    scandalized missionaries and perplexed registry clerks when he went to Muscogee
                    to enroll himself and his family in one of the many "final" records ordered to
                    be made by the Government preparatory to dividing the Creek lands among the
                    individual citizens. </p>
                <p>For answer, Harjo called, first into the cabin that was used as a kitchen and
                    then, in a loud, clear voice, toward the small field, where Miss Evans saw a
                    flock of half-grown turkeys running about in the corn stubble. From the kitchen
                    emerged a tall, thin Indian woman of fifty-five, with a red handkerchief bound
                    severely over her head. She spoke to Miss Evans and sat down in the passageway.
                    Presently, a clear, sweet voice was heard in the field; a stout, handsome woman,
                    about the same age as the other, climbed the rail fence and came up to the
                    house. She, also, greeted Miss Evans briefly. Then she carried a tin basin to
                    the well near by, where she filled it to the brim. Setting it down on the horse
                    block, she rolled back her sleeves, tucked in the collar of her gray blouse, and
                    plunged her face in the water. In a minute she came out of the kitchen freshened
                    and smiling. 'Liza Harjo had been pulling dried bean stalks at one end of the
                    field, and it was dirty work. At last old Harjo turned to Miss Evans and said,
                    "These two my wife&mdash;this one 'Liza, this one Jennie." </p>
                <p>It was done with simple dignity. Miss Evans bowed and stammered. <pb
                    entity="DSSR_000002588_0004" n="238"/>
                    Three pairs of eyes were turned upon her in patient, courteous inquiry. </p>
                <p>It was hard to state the case. The old man was so evidently proud of his women,
                    and so flattered by Miss Evans' interest in them, that he would find it hard to
                    understand. Still, it had to be done, and Miss Evans took the plunge. </p>
                <p>"Harjo, you want to come into our church?" The old man's face lighted. </p>
                <p>"Oh, yes, I would come to Jesus, please, my friend." </p>
                <p>"Do you know, Harjo, that the Lord commanded that one man should mate with but
                    one woman? The question was stated again in simpler terms, and the Indian
                    replied, "Me know that now, my friend. Long time ago"&mdash;Harjo plainly
                    meant the whole period previous to his conversion&mdash;"me did not know.
                    The Lord Jesus did not speak to me in that time and so I was blind. I do what
                    blind man do." </p>
                <p>"Harjo, you must have only one wife when you come into our church. Can't you give
                    up one of these women?" Miss Evans glanced at the two, sitting by with smiles of
                    polite interest on their faces, understanding nothing. They had not shared
                    Harjo's enthusiasm either for the white man's God or his language. </p>
                <p>"Give up my wife?" A sly smile stole over his face. He leaned closer to Miss
                    Evans. "You tell me, my friend, which one I give up." He glanced from 'Liza to
                    Jennie as if to weigh their attractions, and the two rewarded him with their
                    pleasantest smiles. "You tell me which one," he urged. </p>
                <p>"Why, Harjo, how can I tell you!" Miss Evans had little sense of humor; she had
                    taken the old man seriously. </p>
                <p>"Then," Harjo sighed, continuing the comedy, for surely the missionary was
                    jesting with him, "'Liza and Jennie must say." He talked to the Indian women for
                    a time, and they laughed heartily. 'Liza, pointing to the other, shook her head.
                    At length Harjo explained, "My friend, they cannot say. Jennie, she would run a
                    race to see which one stay, but 'Liza, she say no, she is fat and cannot run." </p>
                <p>Miss Evans comprehended at last. She flushed angrily, and protested, "Harjo, you
                    are making a mock of a sacred subject; I cannot allow you to talk like this." </p>
                <p>"But did you not speak in fun, my friend?" Harjo queried, sobering. "Surely you
                    have just said what your friend, the white woman at the mission (he meant Mrs.
                    Rowell) would say, and you do not mean what you say." </p>
                <p>"Yes, Harjo, I mean it. It is true that Mrs. Rowell raised the point first, but I
                    agree with her. The church cannot be defiled by receiving a bigamist into its
                    membership." Harjo saw that the young woman was serious, distressingly serious.
                    He was silent for a long time, but at last he raised his head and spoke quietly,
                    "It is not good to talk like that if it is not in fun." </p>

                <pb entity="DSSR_000002588_0005" n="239"/>
                <p> He rose and went to the stable. As he led Miss Evans' horse up to the block it
                    was champing a mouthful of corn, the last of a generous portion that Harjo had
                    put before it. The Indian held the bridle and waited for Miss Evans to mount.
                    She was embarrassed, humiliated, angry. It was absurd to be dismissed in this
                    way by&mdash; "by an ignorant old bigamist!" Then the humor of it burst upon
                    her, and its human aspect. In her anxiety concerning the spiritual welfare of
                    the sinner Harjo, she had insulted the man Harjo. She began to understand why
                    Mrs. Rowell had said that the old Indians were hopeless. </p>
                <p>"Harjo," she begged, coming out of the passageway, "please forgive me. I do not
                    want you to give up one of your wives. Just tell me why you took them." </p>
                <p>"I will tell you that, my friend." The old Creek looped the reins over his arm
                    and sat down on the block. "For thirty years Jennie has lived with me as my
                    wife. She is of the Bear people, and she came to me when I was thirty-five and
                    she was twenty-five. She could not come before, for her mother was old, very
                    old, and Jennie, she stay with her and feed her. </p>
                <p>"So, when I was thirty years old I took 'Liza for my woman. She is of the Crow
                    people. She help me make this little farm here when there was no farm for many
                    miles around. </p>
                <p>"Well, five years 'Liza and me, we live here and work hard. But there was no
                    child. Then the old mother of Jennie she died, and Jennie got no family left in
                    this part of the country. So 'Liza say to me, 'Why don't you take Jennie in
                    here?' I say, 'You don't care?' and she say, 'No, maybe we have children here
                    then.' But we have no children&mdash;never have children. We do not like
                    that, but God He would not let it be. So, we have lived here thirty years very
                    happy. Only just now you make me sad." </p>
                <p>"Harjo," cried Miss Evans, "forget what I said. Forget that you wanted to join
                    the church." For a young mission worker with a single purpose always before her,
                    Miss Evans was saying a strange thing. Yet she couldn't help saying it; all of
                    her zeal seemed to have been dissipated by a simple statement of the old man. </p>
                <p>"I cannot forget to love Jesus, and I want to be saved." Old Harjo spoke with
                    solemn earnestness. The situation was distracting. On one side stood a convert
                    eager for the protection of the church, asking only that he be allowed to
                    fulfill the obligations of humanity and on the other stood the church,
                    represented by Mrs. Rowell, that set an impossible condition on receiving old
                    Harjo to itself. Miss Evans wanted to cry; prayer, she felt, would be entirely
                    inadequate as a means of expression. </p>
                <p>"Oh! Harjo," she cried out, "I don't know what to do. I must think it over and
                    talk with Mrs. Rowell again." </p>
                <p>But Mrs. Rowell could suggest no way out; Miss Evans' talk with her only gave the
                    older woman another opportunity to preach <pb entity="DSSR_000002588_0006" n="240"/> the folly of wasting
                    time on the old and "unreasonable" Indians. Certainly the church could not
                    listen even to a hint of a compromise in this case. If Harjo wanted to be saved
                    there was one way and only one&mdash;unless&mdash; </p>
                <p>"Is either of the two women old? I mean, so old that she is&mdash;
                    an&mdash;" </p>
                <p>"Not at all," answered Miss Evans. "They're both strong and&mdash; yes,
                    happy." I think they will outlive Harjo." </p>
                <p>"Can't you appeal to one of the women to go away? I dare say we could provide for
                    her." Miss Evans, incongruously, remembered Jennie's jesting proposal to race
                    for the right to stay with Harjo. What could the mission provide as a substitute
                    for the little home that 'Liza had helped to create there in the edge of the
                    woods? What other home would satisfy Jennie? </p>
                <p>"Mrs. Rowell, are you sure that we ought to try to take one of Harjo's women from
                    him? I'm not sure that it would in the least advance morality amongst the tribe,
                    but I'm certain that it would make three gentle people unhappy for the rest of
                    their lives." </p>
                <p>"You may be right, Miss Evans." Mrs. Rowell was not seeking to create
                    unhappiness, for enough of it inevitably came to be pictured in the little
                    mission building. "You may be right," she repeated, "but it is a grievous
                    misfortune that old Harjo should wish to unite with the church." </p>
                <p>No one was more regular in his attendance at the mission meetings than old Harjo.
                    Sitting well forward, he was always in plain view of Miss Evans at the organ.
                    Before the service began, and after it was over, the old man greeted the young
                    woman. There was never a spoken question, but in the Creek's eyes was always a
                    mute inquiry. </p>
                <p>Once Miss Evans ventured to write to her old pastor in New York, and explain her
                    trouble. This was what he wrote in reply: "I am surprised that you are troubled,
                    for I should have expected you to rejoice, as I do, over this new and wonderful
                    evidence of the Lord's reforming power. Though the church cannot receive the old
                    man so long as he is confessedly a bigamist and violator of his country's just
                    laws, you should be greatly strengthened in your work through bringing him to
                    desire salvation." </p>
                <p>"Oh! it's easy to talk when you're free from responsibility!" cried out Miss
                    Evans. "But I woke him up to a desire for this water of salvation that he cannot
                    take. I have seen Harjo's home, and I know how cruel and useless it would be to
                    urge him to give up what he loves&mdash;for he does love those two women who
                    have spent half their lives and more with him. What, what can be done!" </p>
                <p>Month after month, as old Harjo continued to occupy his seat in the mission
                    meetings, with that mute appeal in his eyes and a persistent light of hope on
                    his face, Miss Evans repeated the question, "What can be done?" If she was
                    sometimes tempted to say to the <pb entity="DSSR_000002588_0007" n="241"/> old man, "Stop worrying about your
                    soul; you'll get to Heaven as surely as any of us," there was always Mrs. Rowell
                    to remind her that she was not a Mormon missionary. She could not run away from
                    her perplexity. If she should secure a transfer to another station, she felt
                    that Harjo would give up coming to the meetings, and in his despair become a
                    positive influence for evil amongst his people. Mrs. Rowell would not waste her
                    energy on an obstinate old man. No, Harjo was her creation, her impossible
                    convert, and throughout the years, until death&mdash;the great solvent which
                    is not always a solvent&mdash;came to one of them, would continue to haunt
                    her. </p>
                <p>And meanwhile, what? </p>

                <note id="n1" n="1">
                    <p>Image of the Harjo brand.</p>
                </note>
            </div1>
        </body>



    </text>
</TEI.2>
