<?xml version="1.0"?>

<?dlps id="PagMars"?>
<?dlps page-images="color" figure-images="yes"?>
<?dlps transcription="other"?>

<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/tei-p4/tei2.dtd" [
<!ENTITY % POSTKB "INCLUDE">
<!ENTITY % TEI.extensions.ent SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.ent">
<!ENTITY % TEI.extensions.dtd SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.dtd">
<!ENTITY % ISOpub SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/charent/iso-pub.ent"> %ISOpub;







 
 

<!ENTITY DSSR_000002677_0001 SYSTEM "000002677_0001" NDATA uvaHighRes>
<!ENTITY DSSR_000002677_0002 SYSTEM "000002677_0002" NDATA uvaHighRes>
<!ENTITY DSSR_000002677_0003 SYSTEM "000002677_0003" NDATA uvaHighRes>
<!ENTITY DSSR_000002677_0004 SYSTEM "000002677_0004" NDATA uvaHighRes>
<!ENTITY DSSR_000002677_0005 SYSTEM "000002677_0005" NDATA uvaHighRes>
<!ENTITY DSSR_000002677_0006 SYSTEM "000002677_0006" NDATA uvaHighRes>
<!ENTITY DSSR_000002677_0007 SYSTEM "000002677_0007" NDATA uvaHighRes>
<!ENTITY DSSR_000002677_0008 SYSTEM "000002677_0008" NDATA uvaHighRes>
<!ENTITY DSSR_000002677_0009 SYSTEM "000002677_0009" NDATA uvaHighRes>
<!ENTITY DSSR_000002677_0010 SYSTEM "000002677_0010" NDATA uvaHighRes>
<!ENTITY DSSR_000002677_0011 SYSTEM "000002677_0011" NDATA uvaHighRes>
<!ENTITY DSSR_000002677_0012 SYSTEM "000002677_0012" NDATA uvaHighRes>
<!ENTITY DSSR_000002677_0013 SYSTEM "000002677_0013" NDATA uvaHighRes>
<!ENTITY DSSR_000002677_0014 SYSTEM "000002677_0014" NDATA uvaHighRes>
<!ENTITY DSSR_000002677_0015 SYSTEM "000002677_0015" NDATA uvaHighRes>
<!ENTITY DSSR_000002677_0016 SYSTEM "000002677_0016" NDATA uvaHighRes>
<!ENTITY DSSR_000002677_0017 SYSTEM "000002677_0017" NDATA uvaHighRes>
<!ENTITY DSSR_000002677_0018 SYSTEM "000002677_0018" NDATA uvaHighRes>
<!ENTITY DSSR_000002677_0019 SYSTEM "000002677_0019" NDATA uvaHighRes>
<!ENTITY DSSR_000002677_0020 SYSTEM "000002677_0020" NDATA uvaHighRes>
<!ENTITY DSSR_000002677_0021 SYSTEM "000002677_0021" NDATA uvaHighRes>
<!ENTITY DSSR_000002677_0022 SYSTEM "000002677_0022" NDATA uvaHighRes>
<!ENTITY DSSR_000002677_0023 SYSTEM "000002677_0023" NDATA uvaHighRes>
<!ENTITY DSSR_000002677_0024 SYSTEM "000002677_0024" NDATA uvaHighRes>
<!ENTITY DSSR_000002677_0025 SYSTEM "000002677_0025" NDATA uvaHighRes>
<!ENTITY DSSR_000002677_0026 SYSTEM "000002677_0026" NDATA uvaHighRes>
<!ENTITY DSSR_000002677_0027 SYSTEM "000002677_0027" NDATA uvaHighRes>
<!ENTITY DSSR_000002677_0028 SYSTEM "000002677_0028" NDATA uvaHighRes>
<!ENTITY DSSR_000002677_0029 SYSTEM "000002677_0029" NDATA uvaHighRes>
<!ENTITY DSSR_000002677_0030 SYSTEM "000002677_0030" NDATA uvaHighRes>
<!ENTITY DSSR_000002677_0031 SYSTEM "000002677_0031" NDATA uvaHighRes>
<!ENTITY DSSR_000002677_0032 SYSTEM "000002677_0032" NDATA uvaHighRes>
<!ENTITY DSSR_000002677_0033 SYSTEM "000002677_0033" NDATA uvaHighRes>
<!ENTITY DSSR_000002677_0034 SYSTEM "000002677_0034" NDATA uvaHighRes>
<!ENTITY DSSR_000002677_0035 SYSTEM "000002677_0035" NDATA uvaHighRes>
<!ENTITY DSSR_000002677_0036 SYSTEM "000002677_0036" NDATA uvaHighRes>
<!ENTITY DSSR_000002677_0037 SYSTEM "000002677_0037" NDATA uvaHighRes>
<!ENTITY DSSR_000002677_0038 SYSTEM "000002677_0038" NDATA uvaHighRes>
]>
<TEI.2 id="PagMars">
   <teiHeader type="migrated" creator="Etext">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Marse Chan; A Tale of Old Virginia</title>
            <title type="sort">marse chan a tale of old virginia</title>
            <author>Page, Thomas Nelson</author>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Creation of machine-readable version:</resp>
               <name>Stephen Railton</name>
               <resp>Creation of digital images:</resp>
               <name>Stephen Railton</name>
               <resp>Conversion to TEI.2-conformant markup:</resp>
               <name>University of Virginia Library Electronic Text Center.</name>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <extent>ca. <num type="kilobytes">62</num> kilobytes</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>University of Virginia Library</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Charlottesville, Virginia</pubPlace>
            <idno type="ETC">PagMars</idno>
            <date value="1997">1997</date>
            <availability status="public">
               <p n="copyright">Copyright &#xa9; 1997 by the Rector and Visitors of the
                  University of Virginia</p>
               <p n="access">Publicly accessible</p>
            </availability>
            <idno type="uva-pid">uva-lib:477239</idno>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>University of Virginia Library, Text collection</title>
            <idno type="uva-set">UVA-LIB-Text</idno>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>
               <p>Illustrations have been included from Marse Chan; A Tale of Old Virginia,
                  published by Charles Scribner's Sons in New York in 1892 (UVA Library call number
                  PS 2514 .M3 1892)</p>
            </note>
            <note>
               <p>The electronic text of Marse Chan is preceded by a prefatory note written by
                  Professor Stephen Railton of the University of Virginia.</p>
            </note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title type="main">Marse Chan; A Tale of Old Virginia</title>
                  <title level="m">In Ole Virginia</title>
                  <title type="sort">marse chan a tale of old virginia</title>
                  <author>Thomas Nelson Page</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>pp. 1-47</extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Charles Scribner's Sons</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                  <date value="1896">1896</date>
                  <idno type="callNo">Print copy consulted: UVA Library call number PS 2512 .I5 1887
                     copy 2</idno>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>
                     <p>Written in 1881, Marse Chan first appeared in The Century in April 1884, and
                        then became part of the collection, In Ole Virginia, in 1887. This
                        electronic text is taken from the 1887 version of this collection.</p>
                  </note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Prepared for the University of Virginia Library Electronic Text Center.</p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>All quotation marks retained as data.</p>
            <p>All unambiguous end-of-line hyphens have been removed, and the trailing part of a
               word has been joined to the preceding line.</p>
            <p>The images exist as archived TIFF images, one or more JPEG versions for general use,
               and thumbnail GIFs.</p>
            <p>Keywords in the header are a local Electronic Text Center scheme to aid in
               establishing analytical groupings.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <creation>
            <date value="1881">1881</date>
         </creation>
         <langUsage>
            <language id="eng" usage="main">English</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords>
               <term>prose; fiction</term>
               <term>American Civil War</term>
            </keywords>
            <keywords>
               <term type="artist">W. T. Smedley</term>
               <term type="format">24-bit color; 400 dpi</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date value="1997-06">June 1997</date>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>corrector</resp>
               <name>Carol Osborne, Electronic Text Center</name>
            </respStmt>
            <item>Added TEI header and tags</item>
         </change>
         <change>
            <date value="2005-07">July 2005</date>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Corrector</resp>
               <name>John Ivor Carlson</name>
            </respStmt>
            <item>Converted SGML to XML and/or corrected tagging.</item>
         </change>
         <change>
            <date value="2007-09">September 2007</date>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Migration</resp>
               <name>Ethan Gruber, University of Virginia Library</name>
            </respStmt>
            <item>Converted XML markup from TEI Lite to uva-dl-tei (TEI P4 with local
               customizations).</item>
         </change>
         <change>
            <date value="2008-01">January 2008</date>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Migration</resp>
               <name>Greg Murray, University of Virginia Library</name>
            </respStmt>
            <item>Programmatically updated TEI header markup (but not header content) for minimal
               compliance with current QA requirements.</item>
         </change>
<change>
<date value="2009-03">March 2009</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>Migration</resp>
<name>Scholarly Resources, University of Virginia Library</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Added and/or replaced the digital images accompanying the electronic text. Scanning of exterior and interior (ie. pages) of item was done only for items found in the University of Virginia Special Collections Library.</item>
</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>

   <text id="d1">
      <front id="d2">
         <div1 type="note" id="d3">
            <head>Constructing an Old South</head>
            <p>Tom Sawyer <hi rend="italic">(1876) was one of the first fictions to depict a
                  slave-owning community nostalgically, although in it slaves are only glimpsed at
                  the narrative margins, and the community is identified as "western" rather than
                  "southern." By the time</hi> Huck Finn <hi rend="italic">appeared in the
                  mid-1880's, as Jay Hubbel puts it, "Southern stories were becomingly
                  extraordinarily popular. The Northern magazines were full of them."</hi></p>

            <p><hi rend="italic">Among the magazines most hospitable to sentimental or nostalgic
                  treatments of the days "befo' de war" was</hi> The Century<hi rend="italic">,
                  which also published a lot of MT's work, including pre-publication installments
               of</hi> Huck Finn<hi rend="italic">,</hi> Connecticut Yankee<hi rend="italic">,
               and</hi> Pudd'nhead Wilson<hi rend="italic">. It was</hi> The Century <hi
                  rend="italic">that published "Marse Chan," the first fiction by Thomas Nelson
                  Page. Written in 1881, this story appeared in</hi> The Century <hi rend="italic">
                  in April, 1884, just eight months before the magazine published its first excerpt
                  from</hi> Huck Finn <hi rend="italic">&mdash; chapters 17 and 18, the account
                  of the Shepherdson-Grangerford feud (see Prepublishing Huck). There are great
                  differences between Page's and MT's accounts of the Southern "aristocracy," of
                  course, but Huck himself admires the Grangerfords as much as Sam, Page's
                  reminiscing slave, admires his white masters.</hi></p>

            <p><hi rend="italic">Page's plantation tales remained extremely popular throughout the
                  1880's and 1890's, both in magazines and when reprinted in collections like</hi>
               In Ole Virginia<hi rend="italic"> (1887). How contemporary readers saw MT's accounts
                  of the "Old South" in relation to the works of apologists like Page is not clear.
                  In 1889, for example, MT filled in when Page was unable to deliver a lecture in
                  Baltimore. And E.W. Kemble, the artist MT hired to illustrate</hi> Huck Finn<hi
                  rend="italic">, spent the rest of his career illustrating plantation tales (see
                  Representations of Jim). The illustrations below, however, are by W.T.
               Smedley.</hi></p>
         </div1>
      </front>

      <body id="d4">

         <div1 type="story" id="d5">
            <pb entity="DSSR_000002677_0001" n="1"/>
            <head>From <hi rend="italic">In Ole Virginia</hi>, by Thomas Nelson Page<lb/> MARSE
               CHAN<lb/> A TALE OF OLD VIRGINIA </head>


            <p>ONE afternoon, in the autumn of 1872, I was riding leisurely down the sandy road that
               winds along the top of the water-shed between two of the smaller rivers of eastern
               Virginia. The road I was travelling, following "the ridge" for miles, had just struck
               me as most significant of the character of the race whose only avenue of
               communication with the outside world it had formerly been. Their once splendid
               mansions, now fast falling to decay, appeared to view from time to time, set back far
               from the road, in proud seclusion, among groves of oak and hickory, now scarlet and
               gold with the early frost. Distance was nothing to this people; time was of no
               consequence to them. They desired but a level path in life, and that they had, though
               the way was longer, and the outer world strode by them as they dreamed.</p>

            <p>I was aroused from my reflections by hearing some one ahead of me calling,
               "Heah!&mdash;heah&mdash;whoo-oop, heah!"</p>

            <p>Turning the curve in the road, I saw just before me a negro standing, with a hoe and
               a watering-pot <pb entity="DSSR_000002677_0002" n="2"/> in his hand. He had evidently just gotten over the
               "worm-fence" into the road, out of the path which led zigzag across the "old field"
               and was lost to sight in the dense growth of sassafras. When I rode up, he was
               looking anxiously back down this path for his dog. So engrossed was he that he did
               not even hear my horse, and I reined in to wait until he should turn around and
               satisfy my curiosity as to the handsome old place half a mile off from the road.</p>

            <p>The numerous out-buildings and the large barns and stables told that it had once been
               the seat of wealth, and the wild waste of sassafras that covered the broad fields
               gave it an air of desolation that greatly excited my interest. Entirely oblivious of
               my proximity, the negro went on calling "Whoo-oop, heah!" until along the path,
               walking very slowly and with great dignity, appeared a noble-looking old orange and
               white setter, gray with age, and corpulent with excessive feeding. As soon as he came
               in sight, his master began:</p>

            <p>"Yes, dat you! You gittin' deaf as well as bline, I s'pose! Kyarnt heah me callin', I
               reckon? Whyn't yo' come on, dawg?"</p>

            <p>The setter sauntered slowly up to the fence and stopped, without even deigning a look
               at the speaker, who immediately proceeded to take the rails down, talking meanwhile:</p>

            <p>"Now, I got to pull down de gap, I s'pose! Yo' <pb entity="DSSR_000002677_0003" n="3"/> so sp'ilt yo' kyahn hardly
               walk. Jes' ez able to git over it as I is! Jes' like white folks&mdash;think 'cuz
               you's white and I's black, I got to wait on yo' all de time. Ne'm mine, I ain' gwi'
               do it!"</p>

            <p>The fence having been pulled down sufficiently low to suit his dogship, he marched
               sedately through, and, with a hardly perceptible lateral movement of his tail, walked
               on down the road. Putting up the rails carefully, the negro turned and saw me.</p>

            <p>"Sarvent, marster," he said, taking his hat off. Then, as if apologetically for
               having permitted a stranger to witness what was merely a family affair, he added: "He
               know I don' mean nothin' by what I sez. He's Marse Chan's dawg, an' he's so ole he
               kyahn git long no pearter. He know I'se jes' prodjickin' wid 'im."</p>

            <p>"Who is Marse Chan?" I asked; "and whose place is that over there, and the one a mile
               or two back&mdash;the place with the big gate and the carved stone pillars?"</p>

            <p>"Marse Chan," said the darky, "he's Marse Channin'&mdash;my young marster; an'
               dem places&mdash;dis one's Weall's, an' de one back dyar wid de rock gate-pos's
               is ole Cun'l Chahmb'lin's. Dey don' nobody live dyar now, 'cep' niggers. Arfter de
               war some one or nurr bought our place, but his name done kind o' slipped me. I nuver
               hearn on 'im befo'; I think dey's half-strainers. I don' ax none on 'em no odds. I
               lives down de road heah, a little <pb entity="DSSR_000002677_0004" n="4"/> piece, an' I jes' steps down of a
               evenin' and looks arfter de graves."</p>

            <p>"Well, where is Marse Chan?" I asked.</p>

            <p>"Hi! don' you know? Marse Chan, he went in de army. I was wid 'im. Yo' know he warn'
               gwine an' lef' Sam."</p>

            <p>"Will you tell me all about it," I said, dismounting.</p>

            <p>Instantly, and as if by instinct, the darky stepped forward and took my bridle. I
               demurred a little; but with a bow that would have honored old Sir Roger, he shortened
               the reins, and taking my horse from me, led him along.</p>

            <p>"Now tell me about Marse Chan," I said.</p>

            <p>"Lawd, marster, hit's so long ago, I'd a'most forgit all about it, ef I hedn' been
               wid him ever sence he wuz born. Ez 'tis, I remembers it jes' like 'twuz yistiddy. Yo'
               know Marse Chan an' me&mdash;we wuz boys togerr. I wuz older'n he wuz, jes' de
               same ez he wuz whiter 'n me. I wuz born plantin' corn time, de spring arfter big Jim
               an' de six steers got washed away at de upper ford right down dyar b'low de quarters
               ez he wuz a bringin' de Chris'mas things home; an' Marse Chan, he warn' born tell
               mos' to de harves' arfter my sister Nancy married Cun'l Chahmb'lin's Torm, 'bout
               eight years arfterwoods.</p>

            <p>"Well, when Marse Chan wuz born, dey wuz de grettes' doin's at home you ever did see.
               De folks <pb entity="DSSR_000002677_0005" n="5"/> all hed holiday, jes' like in de Chris'mas. Ole marster (we
               didn' call 'im <hi rend="italic">ole</hi> marster tell arfter Marster Chan wuz
               born&mdash;befo' dat he wuz jes' de marster, so)&mdash;well, ole marster, his
               face fyar shine wid pleasure, an' all de folks wuz mighty glad, too, 'cause dey all
               loved ole marster, and aldo' dey did step aroun' right peart when ole marster was
               lookin' at 'em, dyar warn' nyar han' on de place but what, ef he wanted anythin',
               would walk up to de back poach, an' say he warn' to see de marster. An' ev'ybody wuz
               talkin' 'bout de young marster, an' de maids an' de wimmens 'bout de kitchen wuz
               sayin' how 'twuz de purties' chile dey ever see; an' at dinner-time de mens (all on
               'em hed holiday) come roun' de poach an' ax how de missis an' de young marster wuz,
               an' ole marster come out on de poach an' smile wus'n a 'possum, an' sez, 'Thankee!
               Bofe coin' fust rate, boys;' an' den he stepped back in de house, sort o' laughin' to
               hisse'f, an' in a minute he come out ag'in wid de baby in he arms, all wrapped up in
               flannens an' things, an' sez, 'Heah he is, boys.' All de folks den, dey went up on de
               poach to look at 'im, drappin' dey hats on de steps, an' scrapin' dey feets ez dey
               went up. An' pres'n'y ole marster, lookin' down at we all chil'en all packed togerr
               down dyah like a parecel o' sheep-burrs, cotch sight o' me (he knowed my name, 'cause
               I use' to hole he hoss fur 'im sometimes; but he didn' know all de chile'n by name,
               dey wuz so <pb entity="DSSR_000002677_0006" n="6"/> many on 'em), an' he sez, 'Come up heah!' So up I goes
               tippin', skeered like, an' old marster sez, 'Ain' you Mymie's son?' 'Yass, seh,' sez
               I. 'Well,' sez he, 'I'm gwine to give you to yo' young Marse Channin' to be his
               body-servant,' an' he put de baby right in my arms (it's de truth I'm tellin' yo'!),
               an' yo' jes' ought to a-heard de folks sayin', 'Lawd! marster, dat boy'll drap dat'
               chile!' 'Naw, he won't,' sez marster; 'I kin trust 'im.' And den he sez: 'Now, Sam,
               from dis time you belong to yo' young Marse Channin'; I wan' you to tek keer on 'im
               ez long ez he lives. You are to be his boy from dis time. An' now,' he sez, 'carry
               'im in de house.' An' he walks arfter me an' opens de do's fur me, an' I kyars 'im in
               my arms, an' lays 'im down on de bed. An' from dat time I was tooken in de house to
               be Marse Channin's body-servant.</p>

            <p>"Well, you nuver see a chile grow so. Pres'n'y he growed up right big, an' ole
               marster sez he must have some edication. So he sont 'im to school to ole Miss Lawry
               down dyar, dis side o' Cun'l Chahmb'lin's, an' I use' to go 'long wid 'im an' tote he
               books an' we all's snacks; an' when he larnt to read an' spell right good, an' got
               'bout so-o big, ole Miss Lawry she died, an' ole marster said he mus' have a man to
               teach 'im an' trounce 'im. So we all went to Mr. Hall, whar kep' de school-house
               beyant de creek, an' dyar we went ev'y day, 'cep <pb entity="DSSR_000002677_0007" n="7"/> Sat'd'ys of co'se, an'
               sich days ez Marse Chan din' warn' go, an' ole missis begged 'im off.</p>



            <p>"Hit wuz down dyar Marse Chan fust took notice o' Miss Anne. Mr. Hall, he taught gals
               ez well ez boys, an' Cun'l Chahmb'lin he sont his daughter (dat's Miss Anne I'm
               talkin' about). She wuz a leetle bit o' gal when she fust come. Yo' see, her ma wuz
               dead, an' ole Miss Lucy Chahmb'lin, she lived wid her brurr an' kep' house for 'im;
               an' he wuz so busy wid politics, he didn' have much time to spyar, so he sont Miss
               Anne to Mr. Hall's by a 'ooman wid a note. When she come dat day in de school-house,
               an' all de chil'en looked at her so hard, she tu'n right red, an' tried to pull her
               long curls over her eyes, an' den put bofe de backs of her little han's in her two
               eyes, an' begin to cry to herse'f. Marse Chan he was settin' on de een' o' de bench
               nigh de do', an' he jes' reached out an' put he arm roun' her an' drawed her up to
               'im. An' he kep' whisperin' to her, an' callin' her name, an' coddlin' her; an'
               pres'n'y she took her han's down an' begin to laugh.</p>

            <p>"Well, dey 'peared to tek' a gre't fancy to each urr from dat time. Miss Anne she
               warn' nuthin' but a baby hardly, an' Marse Chan he wuz a good big boy 'bout mos'
               thirteen years ole, I reckon. Hows'ever, dey sut'n'y wuz sot on each urr an' (yo'
               heah me!) ole marster an' Cun'l Chahmb'lin dey 'peared to like it 'bout well ez de
               chil'en. Yo' <pb entity="DSSR_000002677_0008" n="8"/> see, Cun'l Chahmb'lin's place j'ined ourn, an' it looked
               jes' ez natural fur dem two chil'en to marry an' mek it one plantation, ez it did fur
               de creek to run down de bottom from our place into Cun'l Chahmb'lin's. I don' rightly
               think de chil'en thought 'bout gittin' <hi rend="italic">married</hi>, not den, no
               mo'n I thought 'bout marryin' Judy when she wuz a little gal at Cun'l Chahmb'lin's,
               runnin' 'bout de house, huntin' fur Miss Lucy's spectacles; but dey wuz good frien's
               from de start. Marse Chan he use' to kyar Miss Anne's books fur her ev'y day, an' ef
               de road wuz muddy or she wuz tired, he use' to tote her; an' 'twarn' hardly a day
               passed dat he didn' kyar her some'n' to school-apples or hick'y nuts, or some'n. He
               wouldn' let none o' de chil'en tease her, nurr. Heh! One day, one o' de boys poked he
               finger at Miss Anne, and arfter school Marse Chan he axed 'im 'roun' hine de
               school-house out o' sight, an' ef he didn' whop 'im!</p>

            <p>"Marse Chan, he wuz de peartes' scholar ole Mr. Hall hed, an' Mr. Hall he wuz mighty
               proud o' 'im. I don' think he use' to beat 'im ez much ez he did de urrs, aldo' he
               wuz de head in all debilment dat went on, jes' ez he wuz in sayin' he lessons.</p>

            <p>"Heh! one day in summer, jes' fo' de school broke up, dyah come up a storm right
               sudden, an' riz de creek (dat one yo' cross' back yonder), an' Marse Chan he toted
               Miss Anne home on he back. He ve'y off'n did dat when de parf wuz muddy. <pb entity="DSSR_000002677_0009" n="9"/>
               But dis day when dey come to de creek, it had done washed all de logs 'way. 'Twuz
               still mighty high, so Marse Chan he put Miss Anne down, an' he took a pole an' waded
               right in. Hit took 'im long up to de shoulders. Den he waded back, an' took Miss Anne
               up on his head an' kyared her right over. At fust she wuz skeered; but he tol' her he
               could swim an' wouldn' let her git hu't, an' den she let 'im kyar her 'cross, she
               hol'in' his han's. I warn' 'long dat day, but he sut'n'y did dat thing.</p>

            <p>"Ole marster he wuz so pleased 'bout it, he giv' Marse Chan a pony; an' Marse Chan
               rode 'im to school de day arfter he come, so proud, an' sayin' how he wuz gwine to
               let Anne ride behine 'im; an' when he come home dat evenin' he wuz walkin'. 'Hi!
               where's yo' pony?' said ole marster. 'I give 'im to Anne,' says Marse Chan. 'She
               liked 'im, an'&mdash;I kin walk. ' 'Yes,' sez ole marster, laughin', 'I s'pose
               you's already done giv' her yo'se'f, an' nex' thing I know you'll be givin' her this
               plantation and all my niggers.'</p>

            <p>"Well, about a fortnight or sich a matter arfter dat, Cun'l Chahmb'lin sont over an'
               invited all o' we all over to dinner, an' Marse Chan wuz 'spressly named in de note
               whar Ned brought; an' arfter dinner he made ole Phil, whar wuz his ker'ige-driver,
               bring roun' Marse Chan's pony wid a little side-saddle on 'im, an' a beautiful little
               hoss wid a bran'-new saddle an' bridle on 'im; an' he gits up <pb entity="DSSR_000002677_0010" n="10"/> an' meks
               Marse Chan a gre't speech, an' presents 'im de little hoss; an' den he calls Miss
               Anne, an' she comes out on de poach in a little ridin' frock, an' dey puts her on her
               pony, an' Marse Chan mounts his hoss, an' dey goes to ride, while de grown folks is
               a-laughin' an' chattin' an' smokin' dey cigars.</p>

            <p>"Dem wuz good ole times, marster&mdash;de bes' Sam ever see! Dey wuz, in fac'!
               Niggers didn' hed nothin' 't all to do&mdash;jes' hed to 'ten' to de feedin' an'
               cleanin' de hosses, an' doin' what de marster tell 'em to do; an' when dey wuz sick,
               dey had things sont 'em out de house, an' de same doctor come to see 'em whar 'ten'
               to de white folks when dey wuz po'ly. Dyar warn' no trouble nor nothin'.</p>

            <p>"Well, things tuk a change arfter dat. Marse Chan he went to de bo'din' school, whar
               he use' to write to me constant. Ole missis use' to read me de letters, an' den I'd
               git Miss Anne to read 'em ag'in to me when I'd see her. He use' to write to her too,
               an' she use' to write to him too. Den Miss Anne she wuz sont off to school too. An'
               in de summer time dey'd bofe come home, an' yo' hardly knowed whether Marse Chan
               lived at home or over at Cun'l Chahmb'lin's. He wuz over dyah constant. 'Twuz always
               ridin' or fishin' down dyah in de river; or sometimes he' go over dyah, an' 'im an'
               she'd go out an' set in de yard onder de trees; she settin' up mekin' out she wuz
               knittin' some sort o' <pb entity="DSSR_000002677_0011" n="11"/> bright-cullored some'n', wid de grarss growin' all
               up 'g'inst her, an' her hat th'owed back on her neck, an' he readin' to her out
               books; an' sometimes dey'd bofe read out de same book, fust one an' den todder. I
               use' to see 'em! Dat wuz when dey wuz growin' up like.</p>

            <p>"Den ole marster he run for Congress, an' ole Cun'l Chahmb'lin he wuz put up to run
               'g'inst ole marster by de Dimicrats; but ole marster he beat 'im. Yo' know he wuz
               gwine do dat! Co'se he wuz! Dat made ole Cun'l Chahmb'lin mighty mad, and dey stopt
               visitin' each urr reg'lar, like dey had been doin' all 'long. Den Cun'l Chahmb'lin he
               sort o' got in debt, an' sell some o' he niggers, an' dat's de way de fuss begun.
               Dat's whar de lawsuit cum from. Ole marster he didn' like nobody to sell niggers, an'
               knowin' dat Cun'l Chahmb'lin wuz sellin' o' his, he writ an' offered to buy his M'ria
               an' all her chil'en, 'cause she hed married our Zeek'yel. An' don' yo' think, Cun 'l
               Chahmb'lin axed ole marster mo' 'n th'ee niggers wuz wuth fur M'ria! Befo' old
               marster bought her, dough, de sheriff cum an' levelled on M'ria an' a whole parecel
               o' urr niggers. Ole marster he went to de sale, an' bid for 'em; but Cun'l Chahmb'lin
               he got some one to bid 'g'inst ole marster. Dey wuz knocked out to ole marster dough,
               an' den dey hed a big lawsuit, an' ole marster wuz agwine to co't, off an' on, fur
               some years, till at lars' de co't decided dat M'ria belonged <pb entity="DSSR_000002677_0012" n="12"/> to ole
               marster. Ole Cun'l Chahmb'lin den wuz so mad he sued ole marster for a little strip
               o' lan' down dyah on de line fence, whar he said belonged to 'im. Evy'body knowed hit
               belonged to ole marster. Ef yo' go down dyah now, I kin show it to yo', inside de
               line fence, whar it hed done bin ever since long befo' Cun'l Chahmb'lin wuz born. But
               Cun 'l Chahmb'lin wuz a mons'us perseverin' man, an' ole marster he wouldn' let
               nobody run over 'im. No, dat he wouldn'! So dey wuz agwine down to co't about dat,
               fur I don' know how long, till ole marster beat 'im.</p>

            <p>"All dis time, yo' know, Marse Chan wuz agoin' back'ads an' for'ads to college, an'
               wuz growed up a ve'y fine young man. He wuz a ve'y likely gent'men! Miss Anne she hed
               done mos' growed up too&mdash;wuz puttin' her hyar up like ole missis use' to put
               hers up, an' 'twuz jes' ez bright ez de sorrel's mane when de sun cotch on it, an'
               her eyes wuz gre't big dark eyes, like her pa's, on'y bigger an' not so fierce, an'
               'twarn' none o' de young ladies ez purty ez she wuz. She an' Marse Chan still set a
               heap o' sto' by one 'nurr, but I don' think dey wuz easy wid each urr ez when he used
               to tote her home from school on his back. Marse Chan he use' to love de ve'y groun'
               she walked on, dough, in my 'pinion. Heh! His face 'twould light up whenever she come
               into chu'ch, or anywhere, jes' like de sun hed come th'oo a chink on it suddenly.</p>
            <pb entity="DSSR_000002677_0013" n="13"/>
            <p>"Den' ole marster lost he eyes. D' yo' ever heah 'bout dat? Heish! Didn' yo'? Well,
               one night de big barn cotch fire. De stables, yo' know, wuz under de big barn, an'
               all de hosses wuz in dyah. Hit 'peared to me like 'twarn' no time befo' all de folks
               an' de neighbors dey come, an' dey wuz a-totin' water, an' a-tryin' to save de po'
               critters, and dey got a heap on 'em out; but de ker'ige-hosses dey wouldn' come out,
               an' dey wuz a-runnin' back'ads an' for'ads inside de stalls, a-nikerin' an'
               a-screamin', like dey knowed dey time hed come. Yo' could heah 'em so pitiful, an'
               pres'n'y old marster said to Ham Fisher (he wuz de ker'ige-driver), 'Go in dyah an'
               try to save 'em; don' let 'em bu'n to death.' An' Ham he went right in. An' jest
               arfter he got in, de shed whar it hed fus' cotch fell in, an' de sparks shot 'way up
               in de air; an' Ham didn' come back, an' de fire begun to lick out under de eaves over
               whar de ker'ige hosses' stalls wuz, an' all of a sudden ole marster tu'ned an' kissed
               ole missis, who wuz standin' nigh him, wid her face jes' ez white ez a sperit's, an',
               befo' anybody knowed what he wuz gwine do, jumped right in de do', an' de smoke come
               po'in' out behine 'im. Well, seh, I nuver 'spects to heah tell Judgment sich a soun'
               ez de folks set up! Ole missis she jes' drapt down on her knees in de mud an' prayed
               out loud. Hit 'peared like her pra'r wuz heard; for in a minit, right out de same
               do', kyarin' Ham Fisher in his arms, come <pb entity="DSSR_000002677_0014" n="14"/> ole marster, wid his clo's all
               blazin'. Dey flung water on 'im, an' put 'im out; an', ef you b'lieve me, yo' wouldn'
               a-knowed 'twuz ole marster. Yo' see, he hed find Ham Fisher done fall down in de
               smoke right by the ker'ige-hoss' stalls, whar he sont him, an' he hed to tote 'im
               back in his arms th'oo de fire what hed done cotch de front part o' de stable, and to
               keep de flame from gittin' down Ham Fisher's th'ote he hed tuk off his own hat and
               mashed it all over Ham Fisher's face, an' he hed kep' Ham Fisher from bein' so much
               bu'nt; but <hi rend="italic">he</hi> wuz bu'nt dreadful! His beard an' hyar wuz all
               nyawed off, an' his face an' han's an' neck wuz scorified terrible. Well, he jes'
               laid Ham Fisher down, an' then he kind o' staggered for'ad, an' ole missis ketch' 'im
               in her arms. Ham Fisher, he warn' bu'nt so bad, an' he got out in a month to two; an'
               arfter a long time, ole marster he got well, too; but he wuz always stone blind
               arfter that. He nuver could see none from dat night.</p>

            <p>"Marse Chan he comed home from college toreckly, an' he sut'n'y did nuss ole marster
               faithful&mdash;jes' like a 'ooman. Den he took charge of de plantation arfter
               dat; an' I use' to wait on 'im jes' like when we wuz boys togedder; an' sometimes
               we'd slip off an' have a fox-hunt, an' he'd be jes' like he wuz in ole times, befo'
               ole marster got bline, an' Miss Anne Chahmb'lin stopt comin' over to our house, an'
               settin' onder de trees, readin' out de same book.</p>
            <pb entity="DSSR_000002677_0015" n="15"/>
            <p>"He sut'n'y wuz good to me. Nothin' nuver made no diffunce 'bout dat. He nuver hit me
               a lick in his life&mdash;an' nuver let nobody else do it, nurr.</p>



            <p>"I 'members one day, when he wuz a leetle bit o' boy, ole marster hed done tole we
               all chil'en not to slide on de straw-stacks; an' one day me an' Marse Chan thought
               ole marster hed done gone 'way from home. We watched him git on he hoss an' ride up
               de road out o' sight, an' we wuz out in de field a-slidin' an' a-slidin', when up
               comes ole marster. We started to run; but he hed done see us, an' he called us to
               come back; an' sich a whuppin' ez he did gi' us!</p>


            <p>"Fust he took Marse Chan, an' den he teched me up. He nuver hu't me, but in co'se I
               wuz a-hollerin' ez hard ez I could stave it, 'cause I knowed dat wuz gwine mek him
               stop. Marse Chan he hed'n open he mouf long ez ole marster wuz tunin' 'im; but soon
               ez he commence warmin' me an' I begin to holler, Marse Chan he bu'st out cryin', an'
               stept right in befo' ole marster an' ketchin' de whup, sed:</p>

            <p>" 'Stop, seh! Yo' sha'n't whup 'im; he b'longs to me, an' ef you hit 'im another lick
               I'll set 'im free!'</p>

            <p>"I wish yo' hed see ole marster. Marse Chan he warn' mo'n eight years ole, an' dyah
               dey wuz&mdash;old marster stan'in' wid he whup raised up, an' Marse <pb entity="DSSR_000002677_0016" n="16"/>
               Chan red an' cryin', hol'in' on to it, an' sayin' I b'longst to 'im.</p>

            <p>"Ole marster, he raise' de whup, an' den he drapt it, an' broke out in a smile over
               he face, an' he chuck' Marse Chan onder de chin, an' tu'n right roun' an' went away,
               laughin' to hisse'f, an' I heah 'im tellin' ole missis dat evenin', an' laughin'
               'bout it.</p>

            <p>" 'Twan' so mighty long arfter dat when dey fust got to talkin' 'bout de war. Dey wuz
               a-dictatin' back'ads an' for'ads 'bout it fur two or th'ee years 'fo' it come sho'
               nuff, you know. Ole marster, he was a Whig, an' of co'se Marse Chan he tuk after he
               pa. Cun'l Chahmb'lin, he wuz a Dimicrat. He wuz in favor of de war, an' ole marster
               and Marse Chan dey wuz agin' it. Dey wuz a-talkin' 'bout it all de time, an' purty
               soon Cun'l Chahmb'lin he went about ev'vywhar speakin' an' noratin' 'bout Ferginia
               ought to secede; an' Marse Chan he wuz picked up to talk agin' 'im. Dat wuz de way
               dey come to fight de duil. I sut'n'y wuz skeered fur Marse Chan dat mawnin', an' he
               was jes' ez cool! Yo' see, it happen so: Marse Chan he wuz a-speakin' down at de Deep
               Creek Tavern, an' he kind o' got de bes' of ole Cun'l Chahmb'lin. All de white folks
               laughed an' hoorawed, an' ole Cun'l Chahmb'lin&mdash;my Lawd! I t'ought he'd 'a'
               bu'st, he was so mad. Well, when it come to his time to speak, he jes' light into
               Marse Chan. IIe call 'im a traitor, an' a ab'litionis', an' I don' know what all.
               Marse Chan, he jes' kep' cool <pb entity="DSSR_000002677_0017" n="17"/> till de ole Cun'l light into he pa. Ez
               soon ez he name ole marster, I seen Marse Chan sort o' lif' up he head. D' yo' ever
               see a hoss rar he head up right sudden at night when he see somethin' comin' to'ds
               'im from de side an' he don' know what 'tis? Ole Cun'l Chahmb'lin he went right on.
               He said ole marster hed taught Marse Chan; dat ole marster wuz a wuss ab'litionis'
               den he son. I looked at Marse Chan, an' sez to myse'f: 'Fo' Gord! old Cun'l
               Chahmb'lin better min', an' I hedn' got de wuds out, when ole Cun'l Chahmb'lin 'cuse'
               old marster o' cheatin' 'im out o' he niggers, an' stealin' piece o' he
               lan'&mdash;dat's de lan' I tole you 'bout. Well, seh, nex' thing I knowed, I
               heahed Marse Chan&mdash;hit all happen right 'long togerr, like lightnin' and
               thunder when they hit right at you&mdash;I heah 'im say:</p>

            <p>" 'Cun'l Chahmb'lin, what you say is false, an' yo' know it to be so. You have
               wilfully slandered one of de pures' an' nobles' men Gord ever made, an' nothin' but
               yo' gray hyars protects you.'</p>

            <p>"Well, ole Cun'l Chahmb'lin, he ra'd an' he pitch'd. He said he wan' too ole, an'
               he'd show 'im so.</p>

            <p>" 'Ve'y well,' says Marse Chan.</p>

            <p>"De meetin' broke up den. I wuz hol'in' de hosses out dyar in de road by dee een' o'
               de poach, an' I see Marse Chan talkin' an' talkin' to Mr. Gordon an' anudder
               gent'man, and den he come out an' got on de sorrel an' galloped off. Soon ez he got
                  <pb entity="DSSR_000002677_0018" n="18"/> out o' sight he pulled up, an' we walked along tell we come to de
               road whar leads off to'ds Mr. Barbour's. He wuz de big lawyer o' de country. Dar he
               tu'ned off. All dis time he hedn' sed a wud, 'cep' to kind o' mumble to hisse'f now
               and den. When we got to Mr. Barbour's, he got down an' went in. Dat wuz in de late
               winter; de folks wuz jes' beginnin' to plough fur corn. He stayed dyar 'bout two
               hours, an' when he come out Mr. Barbour come out to de gate wid 'im an' shake han's
               arfter he got up in de saddle. Den we all rode off. 'Twuz late den&mdash;good
               dark; an' we rid ez hard ez we could, tell we come to de ole school-house at ole
               Cun'l Chahmb'lin's gate. When we got dar, Marse Chan got down an' walked right slow
               'roun' de house. After lookin' roun' a little while an' tryin' de do' to see ef it
               wuz shet, he walked down de road tell he got to de creek. He stop' dyar a little
               while an' picked up two or three little rocks an' frowed 'em in, an' pres'n'y he got
               up an' we come on home. Ez he got down, he tu'ned to me an', rubbin' de sorrel's
               nose, said: 'Have 'em well fed, Sam; I'll want 'em early in de mawnin'.'</p>

            <p>"Dat night at supper he laugh an' talk, an' he set at de table a long time. Arfter
               ole marster went to bed, he went in de charmber an' set on de bed by 'im talkin' to
               'im an' tellin' 'im 'bout de meetin' an' e'vything; but he nuver mention ole Cun'l
               Chahmb'lin's name. When he got up to come out to de office in <pb entity="DSSR_000002677_0019" n="19"/> de yard,
               whar he slept, he stooped down an' kissed 'im jes' like he wuz a baby layin' dyar in
               de bed, an' he'd hardly let ole missis go at all. I knowed some'n wuz up, an' nex'
               mawnin' I called 'im early befo' light, like he tole me, an' he dressed an' come out
               pres'n'y jes' like he wuz goin' to church. I had de hosses ready, an' we went out de
               back way to'ds de river. Ez we rode along, he said:</p>

            <p>" 'Sam, you an' I wuz boys togedder, wa'n't we?'</p>

            <p>" 'Yes,' sez I, 'Marse Chan, dat we wuz.'</p>

            <p>" 'You have been ve'y faithful to me,' sez he, 'an' I have seen to it that you are
               well provided fur. You want to marry Judy, I know, an' you'll be able to buy her ef
               you want to.'</p>

            <p>"Den he tole me he wuz goin' to fight a duil, an' in case he should git shot, he had
               set me free an' giv' me nuff to tek keer o' me an' my wife ez long ez we lived. He
               said he'd like me to stay an' tek keer o' ole marster an' ole missis ez long ez dey
               lived, an' he said it wouldn' be very long, he reckoned. Dat wuz de on'y time he
               voice broke&mdash;when he said dat; an' I couldn' speak a wud, my th'oat choked
               me so.</p>

            <p>"When we come to de river, we tu'ned right up de bank, an' arfter ridin' 'bout a mile
               or sich a matter, we stopped whar dey wuz a little clearin' wid elder bushes on one
               side an' two big gum-trees on de urr, an' de sky wuz all red, an' de water down to'ds
               whar the sun wuz comin' wuz jes' like de sky.</p>
            <pb entity="DSSR_000002677_0020" n="20"/>
            <p>"Pres'n'y Mr. Gordon he come, wid a 'hogany box 'bout so big 'fore 'im, an' he got
               down, an' Marse Chan tole me to tek all de hosses an' go 'roun' behine de bushes whar
               I tell you 'bout&mdash;off to one side; an' 'fore I got 'roun' dar, ole Cun'l
               Chahmb'lin an' Mr. Hennin an' Dr. Call come ridin' from t'urr way, to'ds ole Cun'l
               Chahmb'lin's. When dey hed tied dey hosses, de urr gent'mens went up to whar Mr.
               Gordon wuz, an' arfter some chattin' Mr. Hennin step' off 'bout fur ez 'cross dis
               road, or mebbe it mout be a little furder; an' den I seed 'em th'oo de bushes loadin'
               de pistils, an' talk a little while; an' den Marse Chan an' ole Cun'l Chahmb'lin
               walked up wid de pistils in dey han's, an' Marse Chan he stood wid his face right
               to'ds de sun. I seen it shine on him jes' ez it come up over de low groun's, an' he
               look like he did sometimes when he come out of church. I wuz so skeered I couldn' say
               nothin'. Ole Cun'l Chahmb'lin could shoot fust rate, an' Marse Chan he never missed.</p>

            <p>"Den I heared Mr. Gordon say, 'Gent'mens, is yo' ready?' and bofe of 'em sez,
               'Ready,' jes' so.</p>

            <p>"An' he sez, 'Fire, one, two'&mdash;an' ez he said 'one,' ole Cun'l Chahmb'lin
               raised he pistil an' shot right at Marse Chan. De ball went th'oo his hat. I seen he
               hat sort o' settle on he head ez de bullit hit it, an' <hi rend="italic">he</hi> jes'
               tilted his pistil up in de a'r an' <pb entity="DSSR_000002677_0021" n="21"/> shot&mdash;<hi rend="italic"
               >bang</hi>; an' ez de pistil went bang, he sez to Cun'l Chahmb'lin, 'I mek you a
               present to yo' fam'ly, seh!'</p>

            <p>"Well, dey had some talkin' arfter dat. I didn't git rightly what it wuz; but it
               'peared like Cun'l Chahmb'lin he warn't satisfied, an' wanted to have anurr shot. De
               seconds dey wuz talkin', an' pres'n'y dey put de pistils up, an' Marse Chan an' Mr.
               Gordon shook han's wid Mr. Hennin an' Dr. Call, an' come an' got on dey hosses. An'
               Cun'l Chahmb'lin he got on his horse an' rode away wid de urr gent'mens, lookin' like
               he did de day befo' when all de people laughed at 'im.</p>

            <p>"I b'lieve ole Cun'l Chahmb'lin wan' to shoot Marse Chan, anyway!</p>

            <p>"We come on home to breakfast, I totin' de box wid de pistils befo' me on de roan.
               Would you b'lieve me, seh, Marse Chan he nuver said a wud 'bout it to ole marster or
               nobody. Ole missis didn' fin' out 'bout it for mo'n a month, an' den, Lawd! how she
               did cry and kiss Marse Chan; an' ole marster, aldo' he never say much, he wuz jes' ez
               please' ez ole missis. He call me in de room an' made me tole 'im all 'bout it, an'
               when I got th'oo he gi' me five dollars an' a pyar of breeches.</p>

            <p>"But ole Cun'l Chahmb'lin he nuver did furgive Marse Chan, an' Miss Anne she got mad
               too. Wimmens is mons'us onreasonable nohow. Dey's jes' like a catfish: you can n' tek
               hole on 'em like <pb entity="DSSR_000002677_0022" n="22"/> udder folks, an' when you gits 'm yo' can n' always
               hole 'em.</p>

            <p>"What meks me think so? Heaps o' things&mdash;dis: Marse Chan he done gi' Miss
               Anne her pa jes' ez good ez I gi' Marse Chan's dawg sweet 'taters, an' she git mad
               wid 'im ez if he hed kill 'im 'stid o' sen'in' 'im back to her dat mawnin' whole an'
               soun'. B'lieve me! she wouldn' even speak to him arfter dat!</p>

            <p>"Don' I 'member dat mawnin'!</p>

            <p>"We wuz gwine fox-huntin', 'bout six weeks or sich a matter after de duil, an' we met
               Miss Anne ridin' 'long wid anurr lady an' two gent'mens whar wuz stayin' at her
               house. Dyar wuz always some one or nurr dyar co'ting her. Well, dat mawnin' we meet
               'em right in de road. 'Twuz de fust time Marse Chan had see her sence de duil, an' he
               raises he hat ez he pahss, an' she looks right at 'im wid her head up in de yair like
               she nuver see 'im befo' in her born days; an' when she comes by me, she sez,
               'Good-mawnin', Sam!' Gord! I nuver see nuthin' like de look dat come on Marse Chan's
               face when she pahss 'im like dat. He gi' de sorrel a pull dat fotch 'im back settin'
               down in de san' on he hanches. He ve'y lips wuz white. I tried to keep up wid 'im,
               but 'twarn' no use. He sont me back home pres'n'y, an' he rid on. I sez to myself,
               'Cun'l Chahmb'lin, don' yo' meet Marse Chan dis mawnin'. He ain' bin lookin' 'roun'
               de ole <pb entity="DSSR_000002677_0023" n="23"/> school-house, whar he an' Miss Anne use' to go to school to ole
               Mr. Hall together, fur nuffin'. He won' stan' no prodjickin' to-day.'</p>

            <p>"He nuver come home dat night tell 'way late, an' ef he'd been fox-huntin' it mus'
               ha' been de ole red whar lives down in de greenscum mashes he'd been chasin'. De way
               de sorrel wuz gormed up wid sweat an' mire sut'n'y did hu't me. He walked up to de
               stable wid he head down all de way, an' I'se seen 'im go eighty miles of a winter
               day, an' prance into de stable at night ez fresh ez if he hed jes' cantered over to
               ole Cun'l Chahmb'lin's to supper. I nuver seen a hoss beat so sence I knowed de
               fetlock from de fo'rock, an' bad ez he wuz he wan' ez bad ez Marse Chan.</p>

            <p>"Whew! he didn' git over dat thing, seh&mdash;he nuver did git over it.</p>

            <p>"De war come on jes' den, an Marse Chan wuz elected cap'n; but he wouldn' tek it. He
               said Firginia hadn' seceded, an' he wuz gwine stan' by her. Den dey 'lected Mr.
               Gordon cap'n.</p>

            <p>"I sut'n'y did wan' Marse Chan to tek de place, cuz I knowed he wuz gwine tek me wid
               'ini. He wan' gwine widout Sam. An' beside, he look so po' an' thin, I thought he wuz
               gwine die.</p>

            <p>"Of co'se, ole missis she heared 'bout it, an' she met Miss Anne in de road, an' cut
               her jes' like Miss Anne cut Marse Chan.</p>

            <p>"Ole missis, she wuz proud ez anybody! So we <pb entity="DSSR_000002677_0024" n="24"/> wuz mo' strangers den ef we
               hadn' live' in a hundred miles of each urr. An' Marse Chan he wuz gittin' thinner an'
               thinner, an' Firginia she come out, an' den Marse Chan he went to Richmond an'
               listed, an' come back an' sey he wuz a private, an' he didn' know whe'r he could tek
               me or not. He writ to Mr. Gordon, hows'ever, an' 'twuz 'cided dat when he went I wuz
               to go 'long an' wait on him an' de cap'n too. I didn' min' dat, yo' know, long ez I
               could go wid Marse Chan, an' I like' Mr. Gordon, anyways.</p>

            <p>" Well, one night Marse Chan come back from de offis wid a telegram dat say, 'Come at
               once,' so he woz to start nex' mawnin'. He uniform wuz all ready, gray wid yaller
               trimmin's, an' mine wuz ready too, an' he had ole marster's sword, whar de State gi'
               'im in de Mexikin war; an' he trunks wuz all packed wid ev'rything in 'em, an' my
               chist was packed too, an' Jim Rasher he druv 'em over to de depo' in de waggin, an'
               we wuz to start nex' mawnin' 'bout light. Dis wuz 'bout de las' o' spring, you know.
               Dat night ole missis made Marse Chan dress up in he uniform, an' he sut'n'y did look
               splendid, wid he long mustache an' he wavin' hyar an' he tall figger.</p>

            <p>"Arfter supper he come down an' sez: 'Sam, I wan' you to tek dis note an' kyar it
               over to Cun'l Chahmb'lin's, an' gi' it to Miss Anne wid yo' own han's, an' bring me
               wud what she sez. Don' let <pb entity="DSSR_000002677_0025" n="25"/> any one know 'bout it, or know why you've
               gone.' 'Yes, seh,' sez I.</p>

            <p>"Yo' see, I knowed Miss Anne's maid over at ole Cun'l Chahmb'lins&mdash;dat wuz
               Judy whar is my wife now&mdash;an' I knowed I could wuk it. So I tuk de roan an'
               rid over, an' tied 'im down de hill in de cedars, an' I wen' 'roun' to de back yard.
               'Twuz a right blowy sort o' night; de moon wuz jes' risin', but de clouds wuz so big
               it didn' shine 'cep' th'oo a crack now an' den. I soon foun' my gal, an' arfter
               tellin' her two or three lies 'bout herse'f, I got her to go in an' ax Miss Anne to
               come to de do'. When she come, I gi' her de note, an' arfter a little while she bro't
               me anurr, an' I tole her good-by, an' she gi' me a dollar, an' I come home an' gi' de
               letter to Marse Chan. He read it, an' tole me to have de hosses ready at twenty
               minits to twelve at de corner of de garden. An' jes' befo' dat he come out ez ef he
               wuz gwine to bed, but instid he come, an' we all struck out to'ds Cun'l Chahmb'lin's.
               When we got mos' to de gate, de hosses got sort o' skeered, an' I see dey wuz some'n
               or somebody standin' jes' inside; an' Marse Chan he jumpt off de sorrel an' flung me
               de bridle an' he walked up.</p>

            <p>"She spoke fust ('twuz Miss Anne had done come out dyar to meet Marse Chan), an' she
               sez, jes' ez cold ez a chill, 'Well, seh, I granted your favor. I wished to relieve
               myse'f of de obligations you placed me under a few months ago, when you made me a <pb entity="DSSR_000002677_0026"
                  n="26"/> present of my father, whom you fust insulted an' then prevented from
               gittin' satisfaction.'</p>

            <p>"Marse Chan he didn' speak fur a minit, an' den he said: 'Who is with you?' (Dat wuz
               ev'y wud.)</p>

            <p>" 'No one,' sez she; 'I came alone.'</p>

            <p>" 'My God!' sez he, 'you didn' come all through those woods by yourse'f at this time
               o' night?'</p>

            <p>" 'Yes, I'm not afraid,' sez she. (An' heah dis nigger! I don' b'lieve she wuz.)</p>


            <p>"De moon come out, an' I cotch sight o' her stan'in' dyar in her white dress, wid de
               cloak she had wrapped herse'f up in drapped off on de groun', an' she didn' look like
               she wuz 'feared o' nuthin'. She wuz mons'us purty ez she stood dyar wid de green
               bushes behine her, an' she hed jes' a few flowers in her breas'&mdash;right
               hyah&mdash;and some leaves in her sorrel hyar; an' de moon come out an' shined
               down on her hyar an' her frock, an' 'peared like de light wuz jes' stan'in' off it ez
               she stood dyar lookin' at Marse Chan wid her head tho'd back, jes' like dat mawnin'
               when she pahss Marse Chan in de road widout speakin' to 'im, an sez to me,
               'Good-mawnin', Sam.'</p>

            <p>"Marse Chan, he den tole her he hed come to say good-by to her, ez he wuz gwine 'way
               to de war nex' mawnin'. I wuz watchin' on her, an' I tho't, when Marse Chan tole her
               dat, she sort o' started an' looked up at 'im like she wuz mighty sorry, an' 'peared
               like she didn' stan' quite so straight arfter <pb entity="DSSR_000002677_0027" n="27"/> dat. Den Marse Chan he
               went on talkin' right fars' to her; an' he tole her how he had loved her ever sence
               she wuz a little bit o' baby mos', an' how he nuver 'membered de time when he hedn'
               'spected to marry her. He tole her it wuz his love for her dat hed made 'im stan'
               fust at school an' collige, an' hed kep' 'im good an' pure; an' now he wuz gwine
               'way, wouldn' she let it be like 'twuz in ole times, an' ef he come back from de war
               wouldn' she try to think on him ez she use' to do when she wuz a little guirl?</p>

            <p>"Marse Chan he had done been talkin' so serious, he hed done tuk Miss Anne's han',
               an' wuz lookin' down in her face like he wuz list'nin' wid his eyes.</p>

            <p>"Arfter a minit Miss Anne she said somethin', an' Marse Chan he cotch her urr han'
               an' sez:</p>

            <p>" 'But if you love me, Anne?'</p>

            <p>"When he said dat, she tu'ned her head 'way from 'im, an' wait' a minit, an' den she
               said&mdash;right clear:</p>

            <p>" 'But I don' love yo'.' (Jes' dem th'ee wuds!) De wuds fall right
               slow&mdash;like dirt falls out a spade on a coffin when yo's buryin' anybody, an'
               seys, 'Uth to uth.' Marse Chan he jes' let her hand drap, an' he stiddy hisse'f
               'g'inst de gate-pos', an' he didn' speak torekly. When he did speak, all he sez wuz:</p>

            <p>" 'I mus' see you home safe.'</p>

            <p>"I 'clar, marster, I didn' know 'twuz Marse <pb entity="DSSR_000002677_0028" n="28"/> Chan's voice tell I look at
               'im right good. Well, she wouldn' let 'im go wid her. She jes' wrap' her cloak 'roun'
               her shoulders, an' wen' 'long back by herse'f, widout doin' more'n jes' look up once
               at Marse Chan leanin' dyah 'g'inst de gate-pos' in he sodger clo's, wid he eyes on de
               groun'. She said 'Good-by' sort o' sorf, an' Marse Chan, widout lookin' up, shake
               han's wid her, an' she wuz done gone down de road. Soon ez she got 'mos' 'roun' de
               curve, Marse Chan he followed her, keepin' under de trees so ez not to be seen, an' I
               led de hosses on down de road behine 'im. He kep' 'long behine her tell she wuz safe
               in de house, an' den he come an' got on he hoss, an' we all come home.</p>

            <p>"Nex' mawnin' we all come off to j'ine de army. An' dey wuz a-drillin' an' a-drillin'
               all 'bout for a while an' dey went 'long wid all de res' o' de army, an' I went wid
               Marse Chan an' clean he boots, an' look arfter de tent, an' tek keer o' him an' de
               hosses. An' Marse Chan, he wan' a bit like he use' to be. He wuz so solumn an'
               moanful all de time, at leas' 'cep' when dyah wuz gwine to be a fight. Den he'd
               peartin' up, an' he alwuz rode at de head o' de company, 'cause he wuz tall; an' hit
               wan' on'y in battles whar all his company wuz dat <hi rend="italic">he</hi> went, but
               he use' to volunteer whenever de cun'l wanted anybody to fine out anythin', an' 'twuz
               so dangersome he didn' like to mek one man go no sooner'n anurr, yo' know, an' ax'd
               who'd volunteer. <hi rend="italic">He</hi> 'peared to like <pb entity="DSSR_000002677_0029" n="29"/> to go
               prowlin' aroun' 'mong dem Yankees, an' he use' to tek me wid 'im whenever he could.
               Yes, seh, he sut'n'y wuz a good sodger! He didn' mine bullets no more'n he did so
               many draps o' rain. But I use' to be pow'ful skeered sometimes. It jes' use' to 'pear
               like fun to 'im. In camp he use' to be so sorrerful he'd hardly open he mouf. You'd
               'a' tho't he wuz seekin', he used to look so moanful; but jes' le' 'im git into
               danger, an' he use' to be like ole times&mdash;jolly an' laughin' like when he
               wuz a boy.</p>

            <p>"When Cap'n Gordon got he leg shot off, dey mek Marse Chan cap'n on de spot, 'cause
               one o' de lieutenants got kilt de same day, an' turr one (named Mr. Ronny) wan' no
               'count, an' all de company said Marse Chan wuz de man.</p>

            <p>"An' Marse Chan he wuz jes' de same. He didn' never mention Miss Anne's name, but I
               knowed he wuz thinkin' on her constant. One night he wuz settin' by de fire in camp,
               an' Mr. Ronny&mdash;he wuz de secon' lieutenant&mdash;got to talkin' 'bout
               ladies, an' he say all sorts o' things 'bout 'em, an' I see Marse Chan kinder lookin'
               mad; an' de lieutenant mention Miss Anne's name. He hed been courtin' Miss Anne 'bout
               de time Marse Chan fit de duil wid her pa, an' Miss Anne hed kicked 'im dough he wuz
               mighty rich, 'cause he warn' nuthin' but a half-strainer, an' 'cause she like Marse
               Chan, I believe, dough she didn' speak to 'im; an' Mr. Ronny he got <pb entity="DSSR_000002677_0030" n="30"/>
               drunk, an' 'cause Cun'l Chahmb'lin tole 'im not to come dyah no more, he got mighty
               mad. An' dat evenin' I'se tellin' yo' 'bout, he wuz talkin', an' he mention' Miss
               Anne's name. I see Marse Chan tu'n he eye 'roun' on 'im an' keep it on he face, and
               pres'n'y Mr. Ronny said he wuz gwine hev some fun dyah yit. He didn' mention her name
               dat time; but he said dey wuz all on 'em a parecel of stuck-up 'risticrats, an' her
               pa wan' no gent'men anyway, an'&mdash;I don' know what he wuz gwine say (he nuver
               said it), fur ez he got dat far Marse Chan riz up an' hit 'im a crack, an' he fall
               like he hed been hit wid a fence-rail. He challenged Marse Chan to fight a duil, an'
               Marse Chan he excepted de challenge, an' dey wuz gwine fight; but some on 'em tole
               'im Marse Chan wan' gwine mek a present o' him to his fam'ly, an' he got somebody to
               bre'k up de duil; twan' nuthin' dough, but he wuz 'fred to fight Marse Chan. An'
               purty soon he lef' de comp'ny.</p>


            <p>"Well, I got one o' de gent'mens to write Judy a letter for me, an' I tole her all
               'bout de fight, an' how Marse Chan knock Mr. Ronny over fur speakin' discontemptuous
               o' Cun'l Chahmb'lin, an' I tole her how Marse Chan wuz a-dyin' fur love o' Miss Anne.
               An' Judy she gits Miss Anne to read de letter fur her. Den Miss Anne she tells her
               pa, an'&mdash;you mind, Judy tells me all dis arfterwards, an' she say when Cun'l
               Chahmb'lin hear 'bout it, he wuz settin' <pb entity="DSSR_000002677_0031" n="31"/> on de poach, an' he set still a
               good while, an' den he sey to hisse'f:</p>

            <p>" 'Well, he carn' he'p bein' a Whig.'</p>

            <p>"An' den he gits up an' walks up to Miss Anne an' looks at her right hard; an' Miss
               Anne she hed done tu'n away her haid an' wuz makin' out she wuz fixin' a rose-bush
               'g'inst de poach; an' when her pa kep' lookin' at her, her face got jes' de color o'
               de roses on de bush, and pres'n'y her pa sez:</p>

            <p>" 'Anne!'</p>

            <p>"An' she tu'ned roun', an' he sez:</p>

            <p>" 'Do yo' want 'im?'</p>

            <p>"An' she sez, 'Yes,' an' put her head on he shoulder an' begin to cry; an' he sez:</p>

            <p>" 'Well, I won' stan' between yo' no longer. Write to 'im an' say so.'</p>

            <p>"We didn' know nuthin' 'bout dis den. We wuz a-fightin' an' a-fightin' all dat time;
               an' come one day a letter to Marse Chan, an' I see 'im start to read it in his tent,
               an' he face hit look so cu'ious, an' he hen's trembled so I couldn' mek out what wuz
               de matter wid 'im. An' he fol' de letter up an' wen' out an' wen' way down 'hine de
               camp, an' stayed dyah 'bout nigh an hour. Well, seh, I wuz on de lookout for 'im when
               he come back, an', fo' Gord, ef he face didn' shine like a angel's! I say to myse'f,
               'Um'm! ef de glory o' Gord ain' done shine on 'im!' An' what yo' 'spose 'twuz?</p>


            <p>"He tuk me wid 'im dat evenin', an' he tell me <pb entity="DSSR_000002677_0032" n="32"/> he hed done git a letter
               from Miss Anne, an' Marse Chan he eyes look like gre't big stars, an' he face wuz
               jes' like 'twuz dat mawnin' when de sun riz up over de low groun', an' I see 'im
               stan'in' dyah wid de pistil in he han', lookin' at it, an' not knowin' but what it
               mout be de lars' time, an' he done mek up he mine not to shoot ole Cun'l Chahmb'lin
               fur Miss Anne's sake, what writ 'im de letter.</p>

            <p>"He fol' de letter wha' was in his han' up, an' put it in he inside
               pocket&mdash;right dyar on de lef' side; an' den he tole me he tho't mebbe we wuz
               gwine hev some warm wuk in de nex' two or th'ee days, an' arfter dat ef Gord speared
               'im he'd git a leave o' absence fur a few days, an' we'd go home.</p>

            <p>"Well, dat night de orders come, an' we all hed to git over to'ds Romney; an' we rid
               all night till 'bout light; an' we halted right on a little creek, an' we stayed dyah
               till mos' breakfas' time, an' I see Marse Chan set down on de groun' 'hine a bush an'
               read dat letter over an' over. I watch 'im, an' de battle wuz a-goin' on, but we had
               orders to stay 'hine de hill, an' ev'y now an' den de bullets would cut de limbs o'
               de trees right over us, an' one o' dem big shells what goes <hi rend="italic"
                  >'Awhar-awhar-awhar!'</hi> would fall right 'mong us; but Marse Chan he didn' mine
               it no mo'n nuthin'! Den it 'peared to git closer an' thicker, and Marse Chan he calls
               me, an' I crep' up, an' he sez:</p>

            <p>" 'Sam, we'se goin' to win in dis battle, an' den <pb entity="DSSR_000002677_0033" n="33"/> we'll go home an' git
               married; an' I'se goin' home wid a star on my collar.' An' den he sez, 'Ef I'm
               wounded, kyar me home, yo' hear?' An' I sez, 'Yes, Marse Chan.'</p>

            <p>"Well, jes' den dey blowed boots an' saddles, an' we mounted; an' de orders come to
               ride 'roun' de slope, an' Marse Chan's comp'ny wuz de secon', an' when we got 'roun'
               dyah, we wuz right in it. Hit wuz de wust place ever dis nigger got in. An' dey said,
               ' Charge 'em !' an' my king! ef ever you see bullets fly, dey did dat day. Hit wuz
               jes' like hail; an' we wen' down de slope (I long wid de res') an' up de hill right
               to'ds de cannons, an' de fire wuz so strong dyar (dey hed a whole rigiment o'
               infintrys layin' down dyar onder de cannons) our lines sort o' broke an' stop; de
               cun'l was kilt, an' I b'lieve dey wuz jes' 'bout to bre'k all to pieces, when Marse
               Chan rid up an' cotch hol' de fleg an' hollers, 'Foller me!' an' rid strainin' up de
               hill 'mong de cannons. I seen 'im when he went, de sorrel four good lengths ahead o'
               ev'y urr hoss, jest like he use' to be in a fox-hunt, an' de whole rigiment right
               arfter 'im. Yo' ain' nuver hear thunder! Fust thing I knowed, de roan roll' head over
               heels an' flung me up 'g'inst de bank, like yo' chuck a nubbin over 'g'inst de foot
               o' de corn pile. An dat's what kep' me from bein' kilt, I 'spects. Judy she say she
               think 'twuz Providence, but I think 'twuz de bank. O' co'se, Providence put de bank
               dyah, but how <pb entity="DSSR_000002677_0034" n="34"/> come Providence never saved Marse Chan? When I look'
               'roun', de roan wuz layin' dyah by me, stone dead, wid a cannon-ball gone 'mos' th'oo
               him, an' our men hed done swep' dem on t'urr side from de top o' de hill. 'Twan' mo'n
               a minit, de sorrel come gallupin' back wid his mane flyin', an' de rein hangin' down
               on one side to his knee. 'Dyar!' says I, 'fo' Gord! I 'specks dey done kill Marse
               Chan, an' I promised to tek care on him.'</p>

            <p>"I jumped up an' run over de bank, an' dyar, wid a whole lot o' dead men, an' some
               not dead yit, onder one o' de guns wid de fleg still in he han', an' a bullet right
               th'oo he body, lay Marse Chan. I tu'n 'im over an' call 'im, 'Marse Chan!' but 'twan'
               no use, he wuz done gone home, sho' 'nuff. I pick' 'im up in my arms wid de fleg
               still in he han's, an' toted 'im back jes' like I did dat day when he wuz a baby, an'
               ole marster gin 'im to me in my arms, an' sez he could trus' me, an' tell me to tek
               keer on 'im long ez he lived. I kyar'd 'im 'way off de battlefiel' out de way o' de
               balls, an' I laid 'im down onder a big tree till I could git somebody to ketch de
               sorrel for me. He wuz cotched arfter a while, an' I hed some money, so I got some
               pine plank an' made a coffin dat evenin', an' wrapt Marse Chan's body up in de fleg,
               an' put 'im in de coffin; but I didn' nail de top on strong, 'cause I knowed ole
               missis wan' see 'im; an' I got a' ambulance an' set out for home dat night. We
               reached dyar de nex' <pb entity="DSSR_000002677_0035" n="35"/> evein', arfter travellin' all dat night an' all
               nex' day.</p>

            <p>" Hit 'peared like somethin' hed tole ole missis we wuz comin' so; for when we got
               home she wuz waitin' for us&mdash;done drest up in her best Sunday-clo'es, an'
               stan'n' at de head o' de big steps, an' ole marster settin' in his big
               cheer&mdash;ez we druv up de hill to'ds de house, I drivin' de ambulance an' de
               sorrel leadin' 'long behine wid de stirrups crost over de saddle.</p>

            <p>"She come down to de gate to meet us. We took de coffin out de ambulance an' kyar'd
               it right into de big parlor wid de pictures in it, whar dey use' to dance in ole
               times when Marse Chan wuz a school-boy, an' Miss Anne Chahmb'lin use' to come over,
               an' go wid ole missis into her chamber an' tek her things off. In dyar we laid de
               coffin on two o' de cheers, an' ole missis nuver said a wud; she jes' looked so ole
               an' white.</p>

            <p>"When I had tell 'em all 'bout it, I tu'ned right 'roun' an' rid over to Cun'l
               Chahmb'lin's, 'cause I knowed dat wuz what Marse Chan he'd 'a' wanted me to do. I
               didn' tell nobody whar I wuz gwine, 'cause yo' know none on 'em hadn' nuver speak to
               Miss Anne, not sence de duil, an' dey didn' know 'bout de letter.</p>

            <p>"When I rid up in de yard, dyar wuz Miss Anne a-stan'in' on de poach watchin' me ez I
               rid up. I tied my hoss to de fence, an' walked up de parf. <pb entity="DSSR_000002677_0036" n="36"/> She knowed by
               de way I walked dyar wuz somethin' de motter, an' she wuz mighty pale. I drapt my cap
               down on de een' o' de steps an' went up. She nuver opened her mouf; jes' stan' right
               still an' keep her eyes on my face. Fust, I couldn' speak; den I cotch my voice, an'
               I say, 'Marse Chan, he done got he furlough.'</p>

            <p>"Her face was mighty ashy, an' she sort o' shook, but she didn' fall. She tu'ned
               'roun' an' said, 'Git me de ker'ige !' Dat wuz all.</p>

            <p>"When de ker'ige come 'roun', she hed put on her bonnet, an' wuz ready. Ez she got
               in, she sey to me, 'Hev yo' brought him home?' an' we drove 'long, I ridin' behine.</p>

            <p>"When we got home, she got out, an' walked up de big walk&mdash;up to de poach by
               herse'f. Ole missis hed done fin' de letter in Marse Chan's pocket, wid de love in
               it, while I wuz 'way, an' she wuz a-waitin' on de poach. Dey sey dat wuz de fust time
               ole missis cry when she find de letter, an' dat she sut'n'y did cry over it,
               pintedly.</p>

            <p>"Well, seh, Miss Anne she walks right up de steps, mos' up to ole missis stan'in'
               dyar on de poach, an' jes' falls right down mos' to her, on her knees fust, an' den
               fiat on her face right on de flo', ketchin' at ole missis' dress wid her two
               han's&mdash;so.</p>

            <p>"Ole missis stood for 'bout a minit lookin' down at her, an' den she drapt down on de
               flo' by her, an' took her in bofe her arms.</p>
            <pb entity="DSSR_000002677_0037" n="37"/>
            <p>"I couldn' see, I wuz cryin' so myse'f, an' ev'ybody wuz cryin'. But dey went in
               arfter a while in de parlor, an' shet de do'; an' I heahd 'em say, Miss Anne she tuk
               de coffin in her arms an' kissed it, an' kissed Marse Chan, an' call 'im by his name,
               an' her darlin', an' ole missis lef' her cryin' in dyar tell some on 'em went in, an'
               found her done faint on de flo'.</p>

            <p>"Judy (she's my wife) she tell me she heah Miss Anne when she axed ole missis mout
               she wear mo'nin' fur 'im. I don' know how dat is; but when we buried 'im nex' day,
               she wuz de one whar walked arfter de coffin, holdin' ole marster, an' ole missis she
               walked next to 'em.</p>

            <p>"Well, we buried Marse Chan dyar in de ole grabeyard, wid de fleg wrapped roun' 'im,
               an' he face lookin' like it did dat mawnin' down in de low groun's, wid de new sun
               shinin' on it so peaceful.</p>

            <p>"Miss Anne she nuver went home to stay arfter dat; she stay wid ole marster an' ole
               missis ez long ez dey lived. Dat warn' so mighty long, 'cause ole marster he died dat
               fall, when dey wuz fallerin' fur wheat&mdash;I had jes' married Judy
               den&mdash;an' ole missis she warn' long behine him. We buried her by him next
               summer. Miss Anne she went in de hospitals toreckly arfter ole missis died; an' jes'
               fo' Richmond fell she come home sick wid de fever. Yo' nuver would 'a' knowed her fur
               de same ole Miss Anne. She wuz light ez a piece o' peth, an' so white, 'cep' her eyes
               an' her sorrel hyar, an' she kep' on gittin' <pb entity="DSSR_000002677_0038" n="38"/> whiter an' weaker. Judy she
               sut'n'y did nuss her faithful. But she nuver got no betterment! De fever an' Marse
               Chan's bein' kilt hed done strain her, an' she died jes' fo' de folks wuz sot free.</p>

            <p>"So we buried Miss Anne right by Marse Chan, in a place whar ole missis hed tole us
               to leave, an' dey's bofe on 'em sleep side by side over in de ole grabeyard at home.</p>

            <p>"An' will yo' please tell me, marster? Dey tells me dat de Bible sey dyar won' be
               marryin' nor givin' in marriage in heaven, but I don' b'lieve it signifies
               dat&mdash;does you?"</p>

            <p>I gave him the comfort of my earnest belief in some other interpretation, together
               with several spare "eighteen-pences," as he called them, for which he seemed humbly
               grateful. And as I rode away I heard him calling across the fence to his wife, who
               was standing in the door of a small whitewashed cabin, near which we had been
               standing for some time:</p>

            <p>"Judy, have Marse Chan's dawg got home?"</p>

         </div1>

      </body>
   </text>
</TEI.2>
