<?xml version="1.0"?>

<?dlps id="PeaGriz"?>
<?dlps page-images="none" figure-images="yes"?>
<?dlps transcription="other"?>

<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/tei-p4/tei2.dtd" [
<!ENTITY % POSTKB "INCLUDE">
<!ENTITY % TEI.extensions.ent SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.ent">
<!ENTITY % TEI.extensions.dtd SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.dtd">
<!ENTITY % ISOpub SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/charent/iso-pub.ent"> %ISOpub;

<!ENTITY DSSR_000002646_0001 SYSTEM "000002646_0001" NDATA uvaHighRes>
<!ENTITY DSSR_000002646_0002 SYSTEM "000002646_0002" NDATA uvaHighRes>
<!ENTITY DSSR_000002646_0003 SYSTEM "000002646_0003" NDATA uvaHighRes>
<!ENTITY DSSR_000002646_0004 SYSTEM "000002646_0004" NDATA uvaHighRes>
<!ENTITY DSSR_000002646_0005 SYSTEM "000002646_0005" NDATA uvaHighRes>
<!ENTITY DSSR_000002646_0006 SYSTEM "000002646_0006" NDATA uvaHighRes>
<!ENTITY DSSR_000002646_0007 SYSTEM "000002646_0007" NDATA uvaHighRes>
<!ENTITY DSSR_000002646_0008 SYSTEM "000002646_0008" NDATA uvaHighRes>
]>
<TEI.2 id="PeaGriz"> 
<teiHeader type="migrated" creator="Etext">
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title type="main">Grizel Cochrane's Ride</title>
<title type="sort">grizel cochranes ride</title>
<author>Peattie, Elia Wilkinson, 1862-1935</author>
<respStmt>
<resp>Illustrator</resp> 
<name>R. B. Birch</name> 
<resp>Creation of machine-readable version:</resp> 
<name>Judy Boss</name> 
<resp>Conversion to TEI.2-conformant markup:</resp> 
<name>Tom Palombi, University of Virginia Library Electronic Text Center.</name>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt> 
<extent>ca. <num type="kilobytes">30</num> kilobytes</extent> 
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>University of Virginia Library</publisher>
<pubPlace>Charlottesville, Virginia</pubPlace> 
<idno type="ETC">PeaGriz</idno> 
<date value="1999">1999</date>
<availability status="public">
<p n="copyright">Copyright &#xa9; 1999 by the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia</p>
<p n="access">Publicly accessible</p>
</availability>
<idno type="uva-pid">uva-lib:477246</idno>
</publicationStmt>
<seriesStmt>
<title>University of Virginia Library, Text collection</title>
<idno type="uva-set">UVA-LIB-Text</idno>
</seriesStmt> 
<notesStmt>
<note>
<p>Illustrations have been included from the original source.</p>
</note>
</notesStmt> 
<sourceDesc>
<biblFull>
<titleStmt>
<title type="main">Grizel Cochrane's Ride</title>
<title level="j">St. Nicholas</title>
<title type="sort">grizel cochranes ride</title>
<author>Peattie, Elia Wilkinson, 1862-1935</author>
</titleStmt> 
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>The Century Co.</publisher> 
<pubPlace>New York</pubPlace> 
<date value="1887">1873-1943</date> 
<idno type="callNo">Source copy consulted: UVa Library, AP 201 .S3 v.14</idno>
</publicationStmt> 
<notesStmt>
<note>
<p>This story appeared in v. 14, no. 4 (Feb. 1887), p. 271-278.</p>
</note>
</notesStmt>
</biblFull>
</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc> 
<encodingDesc>
<projectDesc>
<p>Prepared for the University of Virginia Library Electronic Text Center.</p>
</projectDesc> 
<editorialDecl>
<p>All unambiguous end-of-line hyphens have been removed, and the  trailing part of a word has been joined to the preceding line.</p> 
<p id="ETC">Some keywords in the header are a local Electronic Text Center scheme  to aid in establishing analytical groupings.</p>
</editorialDecl> 
</encodingDesc> 
<profileDesc>
<creation>
<date value="1887">1887</date>
</creation> 
<langUsage>
<language id="eng" usage="main">English</language>
</langUsage> 
<textClass>
<keywords>
<term>fiction</term> 
<term>poetry</term> 
<term>feminine</term> 
<term>Women Writers</term>
</keywords> 
</textClass>
</profileDesc> 
<revisionDesc>
<change>
<date value="1999-02">February 1999</date> 
<respStmt>
<resp>corrector</resp> 
<name>Tom Palombi, Electronic Text Center</name>
</respStmt> 
<item>Added TEI header and tags.</item>
</change> 
<change>
<date value="2005-07">July 2005</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>Corrector</resp>
<name>John Ivor Carlson</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Converted SGML to XML and/or corrected tagging.</item>
</change>
<change>
<date value="2007-09">September 2007</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>Migration</resp>
<name>Ethan Gruber, University of Virginia Library</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Converted XML markup from TEI Lite to uva-dl-tei (TEI P4 with local customizations).</item>
</change>
<change>
<date value="2008-01">January 2008</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>Migration</resp>
<name>Greg Murray, University of Virginia Library</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Programmatically updated TEI header markup (but not header content) for minimal compliance with current QA requirements.</item>
</change>
<change>
<date value="2009-03">March 2009</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>Migration</resp>
<name>Scholarly Resources, University of Virginia Library</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Added and/or replaced the digital images accompanying the electronic text. Scanning of exterior and interior (ie. pages) of item was done only for items found in the University of Virginia Special Collections Library.</item>
</change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader> 
<text id="d1">  
 
<body id="d2"> 
 

 
<div1 type="story" id="d3"> 
    <pb entity="DSSR_000002646_0001" n="271"/> 
<head> 
Grizel Cochrane's Ride<lb/> 
<hi rend="italic">(Founded on an incident of the Monmouth Rebellion)</hi><lb/> 
BY ELIA W. PEATTIE 
</head> 
 
<p>IN the midsummer of 1685, the hearts of the people of old Edinburgh 
were filled with trouble and excitement.  King Charles the Second, of 
England, was dead, and his brother, the Duke of York, reigned in his 
stead to the dissatisfaction of a great number of the people. 
 
</p><p>The hopes of this class lay with the young Duke of Monmouth, the 
ambitious and disinherited son of Charles the Second, who, on account of 
the King's displeasure, had been living for some time at foreign courts. 
On hearing of the accession of his uncle, the Duke of York, to the 
throne, Monmouth yielded to the plans of the English and Scottish lords 
who favored his own pretensions, and prepared to invade England with a 
small but enthusiastic force of men. 
 
</p><p>The Duke of Argyle, the noblest lord of Scotland, who also was an 
exile, undertook to conduct the invasion at the north, while Monmouth 
should enter England at the west, gather the yeomanry about him and form 
a triumphant conjunction with Argyle in London, and force the "usurper," 
as they called King James the Second, from his throne. 
 
</p><p>Both landings were duly made. The power of Monmouth's name and 
rank rallied to his banner at first a large number of adherents; but 
their defeat at Sedgemoor put an end to his invasion. And the Duke of 
Argyle, a few days after his landing in Scotland, was met by a superior 
force of the King's troops. Retreating into a morass, his soldiers were 
scattered and dispersed. Many of his officers deserted him in a panic of 
fear. The brave old nobleman himself was taken prisoner, and be-headed 
at Edinburgh, while all the people secretly mourned. He died without 
betraying his friends, 
 
    <pb entity="DSSR_000002646_0002" n="272"/> 
 
though the relentless King of England threatened to compel him to do so, 
by the torture of the thumb-screw and the rack. 
 
</p><p>Many of his officers and followers underwent the same fate; and 
among those imprisoned to await execution was a certain nobleman, Sir 
John Cochrane, who had been made famous by other political intrigues. 
His friends used all the influence that their high position accorded 
them to procure his pardon, but without success; and the unfortunate 
baronet, a moody and impulsive man by nature, felt that there was no 
escape from the terrible destiny, and prepared to meet it in a manner 
worthy of a follower of the brave old duke. But he had one friend on 
whose help he had not counted. 
 
</p><p>In an upper chamber of an irregular, many-storied mansion far 
down the Canon gate, Grizel Cochrane, the imprisoned man's daughter, sat 
through the dread hours waiting to learn her father's sentence. There 
was too little doubt as to what it would be. The King and his generals 
meant to make merciless examples of the leaders of the rebellion. Even 
the royal blood that flowed in the veins of Monmouth had not saved his 
head from the block. This proud prince, fleeing from the defeat of 
Sedgemoor, had been found hiding in a ditch, covered over with the ferns 
that flourished at the bottom. Grizel wept as she thought of the young 
duke's horrible fate. She remembered when she had last seen him about 
the court at Holland, where she had shared her father's exile.  Gay, 
generous, and handsome, he seemed a creature born to live and rule. What 
a contrast was the abject, weeping coward covered with mud and slime, 
who had been carried in triumph to the grim Tower of London to meet his 
doom! The girl had been taught to believe in Monmouth's rights, and she 
walked the floor trembling with shame and impatience as she thought of 
his bitter defeat.  She walked to the little dormer window and leaned 
out to look at the gray castle, far up the street, with its dull and 
lichen-covered walls. She knew that her father looked down from the 
barred windows of one of the upper apartments accorded to prisoners of 
state. She wondered if a thought of his little daughter crept in his 
mind amid his ruined hopes. The grim castle frowning at her from its 
rocky height filled her with dread; and shuddering, she turned from it 
toward the street below to let her eyes follow absently the passers-by. 
They whispered together as they passed the house, and when now and then 
some person caught a glimpse of her face in the ivy-sheltered window, 
she only met a look of commiseration. No one offered her a happy 
greeting. 
 
</p><p>"They all think him doomed," she cried to herself. "No one hath 
the grace to feign hope."  Bitter tears filled her eyes, until suddenly 
through the mist she was conscious that some one below was lifting a 
plumed hat to her. It was a stately gentleman with a girdled vest and 
gorgeous coat and jeweled sword-hilt. 
 
</p><p>"Mistress Cochrane," said he, in that hushed voice we use when we 
wish to direct a remark to one person, which no one else shall overhear, 
"I have that to tell thee which is most important." 
 
</p><p>"Is it secret?" asked Grizel, in the same 
guarded tone that he had used. 
 
</p><p>"Yes," he replied, without looking up, and continuing slowly in 
his walk, as if he had merely exchanged a morning salutation. 
 
</p><p>"Then," she returned, hastily, "I will tell Mother; and we will 
meet thee in the twilight, at the side door under the balcony." She 
continued to look from the window, and the man sauntered on as if he had 
no care in the world but to keep the scarlet heels of his shoes from the 
dust.  After a time Grizel arose, changed her loose robe for a more 
ceremonious dress, bound her brown braids into a prim gilded net, and 
descended into the drawing-room. 
 
</p><p>Her mother sat in mournful state at the end of the lofty 
apartment. About her were two ladies and several gentlemen, all 
conversing in low tones such as they might use, Grizel thought to 
herself, if her father were dead in the house. They all stopped talking 
as she entered, and looked at her in surprise. In those days it was 
thought very improper and forward for a young girl to enter a 
drawing-room uninvited, if guests were present. Grizel's eyes fell 
before the embarrassing scrutiny, and she dropped a timid courtesy, 
lifting her green silken skirts daintily, like a high-born little 
maiden, as she was. Lady Cochrane made a dignified apology to her guests 
and then turned to Grizel. 
 
</p><p>"Well, my daughter?" she said, questioningly. 
 
</p><p>"I pray thy pardon, Mother," said Grizel, in a trembling voice, 
speaking low, that only her mother might hear; "but within a few moments 
Sir Thomas Hanford will be secretly below the balcony, with news for 
us." 
 
</p><p>The lady half rose from her seat, trembling. 
 
</p><p>"Is he commissioned by the governor?" she 
asked. 
 
</p><p>"I can not tell," said the little girl; but here her voice broke, 
and regardless of the strangers, she flung herself into her mother's 
lap, weeping:  "I am sure it is bad news of Father!" Lady Cochrane wound 
her arm about her daughter's waist, and, with a gesture of apology, led 
her from the room. Half an hour later she re-entered it hurriedly, 
followed by Grizel, who sank unnoticed in the deep embrasure of a 
window, and shivered there behind the heavy folds of the velvet 
hangings. </p>
 
    <pb entity="DSSR_000002646_0003" n="273"/> 

 
    <pb entity="DSSR_000002646_0004" n="274"/> 
 
<p>"I have just received terrible intelligence, my friends," 
announced Lady Cochrane, standing, tall and pale, in the midst of her 
guests. "The governor has been informally notified that the next post 
from London will bring Sir John's sentence.  He is to be hanged at the 
Cross."There was a perfect silence in the dim room; then one of the 
ladies broke into loud sobbing, and a gentleman led Lady Cochrane to a 
chair, while the others talked apart in earnest whispers. 
 
</p><p>"Who brought the information?" asked one of 
the gentlemen, at length. "Is there not hope 
that it is a false report?" 
 
</p><p>"I am not at liberty," said Lady Cochrane, "to tell who brought 
me this terrible news; but it was a friend of the governor, from whom I 
would not have expected a service. Oh, is it too late," she cried, 
rising from her chair and pacing the room, "to make another attempt at 
intercession? Surely something can be done!" 
 
</p><p>The gentleman who had stood by her chair &mdash; a 
gray-headed, sober-visaged man &mdash; returned answer: 
 
</p><p>"Do not count on any remedy now, dear Lady Cochrane. I know this 
new King. He will be relentless toward any one who has questioned his 
right to reign. Besides, the post has already left London several days, 
and will doubtless be here by to-morrow noon." 
 
</p><p>"I am sure," said a gentleman who had not yet spoken, "that if we 
had a few days more he might be saved. They say King James will do 
anything for money, and the wars have emptied his treasury.  Might we 
not delay the post?" he suggested, in a low voice. 
 
</p><p>"No," said the gray-headed gentleman; "that 
is utterly impossible." 
 
</p><p>Grizel, shivering behind the curtain, listened with eager ears. 
Then she saw her mother throw herself into the arms of one of the ladies 
and break into ungoverned sobs. The poor girl could stand no more, but 
glided from the room unnoticed and crept up to her dark chamber, where 
she sat, repeating aimlessly to herself the words that by chance had 
fixed themselves strongest in her memory: "Delay the post &mdash; delay the 
post!" 
 
</p><p>The moon arose and shone in through the panes, making a wavering 
mosaic on the floor as it glimmered through the wind-blown ivy at the 
window.  Like a flash, a definite resolution sprang into Grizel's mind. 
If, by delaying the post, time for intercession with the King could be 
gained, and her father's life so saved, then the post <hi rend="italic">must</hi> be 
delayed!  But how?  She had heard the gentleman say that it would be 
impossible. She knew that the postboy went heavily armed, to guard 
against the highwaymen who frequented the roads in search of plunder. 
This made her think of the wild stories of masked men who sprung from 
some secluded spot upon the postboys, and carried off the letters and 
money with which they were intrusted. 
 
</p><p>Suddenly she bounded from her seat, stood still a moment with her 
hands pressed to her head, ran from her room, and up the stairs which 
led to the servants' sleeping apartments. She listened at a door, and 
then, satisfied that the room was empty, entered, and went straight to 
the oaken wardrobe.  By the light of the moon she selected a jacket and 
a pair of trousers. She looked about her for a hat and found one hanging 
on a peg near the window; then she searched for some time before she 
found a pair of boots. They were worn and coated with mud. 
 
</p><p>"They are all the better," she said to herself, and hurried on 
tiptoe down the corridor.  She went next to the anteroom of her father's 
chamber. It was full of fond associations, and the hot tears sprung into 
her eyes as she looked about it.  She took up a brace of pistols, 
examined them awkwardly, her hands trembling under their weight as she 
found at once to her delight and her terror that they were loaded.  Then 
she hurried with them to her room. 
 
</p><p>Half an hour later, the butler saw a figure which he took to be 
that of Allen, the stable-boy, creeping down the back stairs, boots in 
hand. 
 
</p><p>"Whaur noo, me laddie?" he asked, "It's 
gey late for ye to gang oot the nicht." 
 
</p><p>"I hae forgot to bar the stable door," replied 
Grizel in a low and trembling voice, imitating as 
well as she could the broad dialect of the boy. 
 
</p><p>"Hech!" said the butler. "I ne'er hear ye 
mak sae little hammer in a' yer days." 
 
</p><p>She fled on. The great kitchen was deserted.  She gathered up all 
the keys from their pegs by the door, let herself quietly out, and sped 
across the yard to the stable. With trembling hands she fitted first one 
key and then another to the door until she found the right one. Once 
inside the stable, she stood irresolute. She patted Bay Bess, her own 
little pony. 
 
</p><p>"Thou wouldst never do, Bess," she said.  "Thou art such a lazy 
little creature." The round, fat carriage-horses stood there. "You are 
just holiday horses, too," said Grizel to them, "and would be winded 
after an hour of the work I want you for to-night." But in the shadow of 
the high stall stood Black Ronald, Sir John Cochrane's great, dark 
battle-horse, that riderless, covered with dust and foam, had dashed 
down the Canongate after the terrible rout of Argyle in the bogs of 
Leven-side, while all the people stood and stared at the familiar steed, 
carrying, as he did, the first silent message of disaster. Him Grizel 
unfastened and led out. 
 
    <pb entity="DSSR_000002646_0005" n="275"/> 
 
</p><p>"Thou art a true hero," she said, rubbing his nose with the 
experienced touch of a horsewoman; "and I'll give thee a chance to-night 
to show that thou art as loyal as ever." Her hands were cold with 
excitement, but she managed to buckle the saddle and bridle upon him, 
while the huge animal stood in restless expectancy, anxious to be gone. 
She drew on the boots without any trouble, and slipped the pistols into 
the holsters. 
 
</p><p>"I believe thou knowest what I would have of thee," said Grizel 
as she led the horse out into the yard and on toward the gateway. 
Frightened, as he half circled about her in his impatience, she undid 
the fastening of the great gates, but her strength was not sufficient to 
swing them open. 
 
</p><p>"Ronald," she said in despair, "I can not open 
the gates!" Ronald turned his head about and 
looked at her with his beautiful eyes. He seemed 
to be trying to say, "I can." 
 
</p><p>"All right," said Grizel, as if he had spoken.  She mounted the 
black steed, laughed nervously as she climbed into the saddle. "Now," 
she said, "go on!" The horse made a dash at the gates, burst them open, 
and leaped out into the road. He curveted about for a moment, his hoofs 
striking fire from the cobble-stones. Then Grizel turned his head down 
the Canongate, away from the castle.  She knew the point at which she 
intended to leave the city, and toward that point she headed Black 
Ronald. The horse seemed to know he was doing his old master a service, 
as he took his monstrous strides forward. Only once did Grizel look 
backward, and then a little shudder, half terror, half remorse, struck 
her, for she saw her home ablaze with light, and heard cries of 
excitement borne faintly to her on the rushing night wind. They had 
discovered her flight. Once she thought she heard hoof-beats behind her, 
but she knew she could not be overtaken. 
 
</p><p>Through the streets, now narrow, now broad.  now straight, now 
crooked, dashed Black Ronald and his mistress. Once he nearly ran down a 
drowsy watchman who stood nodding at a sharp corner, but horse and rider 
were three hundred yards away before the frightened guardian regained 
his composure and sprang his discordant rattle. 
 
</p><p>Now the houses grew scarcer, and presently the battlements of the 
town wall loomed up ahead, and Grizel's heart sank, for there were 
lights in the road. She heard shouts, and knew she was to be challenged. 
She firmly set her teeth, said a little prayer, and leaned far forward 
upon Black Ronald's neck. The horse gave a snort of defiance, shied 
violently away from a soldier who stood by the way, and then went 
through the gateway like a shot. Grizel clung tightly to her saddle-bow, 
and urged her steed on. On, on they went down the firm roadway lined on 
either side by rows of noble oaks &mdash; on, on, out into the country-side, 
where the sweet odor of the heather arose gracious and fragrant to the 
trembling girl.  There was little chance of her taking a wrong path. 
The road over which the postboy came was the King's highway, always kept 
in a state of repair. 
 
</p><p>She gave herself no time to notice the green upland farms, or the 
stately residences which stood out on either hand in the moonlight. She 
concentrated her strength and mind on urging her horse forward.  She was 
too excited to form a definite plan, and her only clear idea was to meet 
the postboy before daylight, for she knew it would not be safe to trust 
too much to her disguise. Now and then a feeling of terror flashed over 
her, and she turned sick with dread; but her firm purpose upheld her. 
 
</p><p>It was almost four in the morning, and the wind 
was blowing chill from the sea, when she entered 
the rolling woodlands about the Tweed. Grizel 
was shivering with the cold, and was so tired that 
she with difficulty kept her place in the saddle. 
 
</p><p>"We can not hold out much longer, Ronald," she said; "and if we 
fail, we can never hold up our heads again." Ronald, the sure-footed, 
stumbled and nearly fell. "It is no use," sighed Grizel; "we must rest." 
She dismounted, but it was some moments before her tired limbs could 
obey her will. Beside the roadway was a ditch filled with running water, 
and Grizel managed to lead Ronald down the incline to its brink, and let 
him drink. She scooped up a little in her hand and moistened her tongue; 
then, realizing that Ronald must not be allowed to stand still, she, 
with great difficulty, mounted upon his back again, and, heartsick, 
fearful, yet not daring to turn back, coaxed him gently forward. 
 
</p><p>The moon had set long before this, and in the misty east the sky 
began to blanch with the first gleam of morning. Suddenly, around the 
curve of the road where it leaves the banks of the Tweed, came a dark 
object. Grizel's heart leaped wildly.  Thirty seconds later she saw that 
it was indeed a horseman. He broke into a song: 
 
</p><lg type="verse"> 
<l>"The Lord o' Argyle cam' wi' plumes and wi' spears, 
</l><l>And Monmouth he landed wi' gay cavaliers! 
</l><l>The pibroch has caa'd every tartan thegither, 
</l><l>B' thoosans their footsteps a' pressing the heather; 
</l><l>Th' North and the Sooth sent their bravest ones out, 
</l><l>But a joust wi' Kirke's Lambs put them all to the rout." 
</l></lg> 
 
<p>By this time, the horseman was so close that Grizel could distinguish 
objects hanging upon the horse in front of the rider. They were the 
mail-bags! For the first time she realized her weakness and saw how 
unlikely it was that she would be 
 
    <pb entity="DSSR_000002646_0006" n="276"/> 
 
able to cope with an armed man. The blood rushed to her head, and a 
courage that was the inspiration of the moment took possession of her. 
She struck Black Ronald a lash with her whip. 
 
</p><p>"Go!" she said to him shrilly, while her heart-beats hammered in 
her ears, "Go!" 
 
</p><p>The astonished and excited horse leaped down the road. As she met 
the postboy, she drew Black Ronald, with a sudden strength that was born 
of the danger, back upon his haunches. His huge body blocked the way. 
 
</p><p>"Dismount!" she cried to the other rider.  Her voice was hoarse 
from fright, and sounded strangely in her own ears. But a wild courage 
nerved her, and the hand that drew and held the pistol was as firm as a 
man's. Black Ronald was rearing wildly, and in grasping the reins 
tighter, her other hand mechanically altered its position about the 
pistol. 
 
</p><p>She had not meant to fire, she had only thought to aim and 
threaten, but suddenly there was a flash of light in the gray 
atmosphere, a dull reverberation, and to the girl's horrified amazement 
she saw the horse in front of her stagger and fall heavily to the 
ground. The rider, thrown from his saddle, was pinned to the earth by 
his horse and stunned by the fall. Dizzy with pain and confused by the 
rapidity of the assault, he made no effort to draw his weapon. 
 
</p><p>The mail-bags had swung by their own momentum quite clear of the 
horse in its fall, and now lay loosely over its back, joined by the 
heavy strap. 
 
</p><p>It was a painful task for the exhausted girl to dismount, but she 
did so, and, lifting the cumbersome leathern bags, she threw them over 
Black Ronald's neck. It was yet more painful to her tender heart to 
leave the poor fellow she had injured lying in so pitiable a condition, 
but her father's life was in danger, and that, to her, was of more 
moment than the postboy's hurts. 
 
</p><p>"Heaven forgive me," she said, bending over him. "I pray this may 
not be his death!" She clambered over the fallen horse and mounted 
Ronald, who was calm again. Then she turned his head toward Edinboro' 
Town and hurriedly urged him forward. But as she sped away from the 
scene of the encounter, she kept looking back, with an awe-struck face, 
to the fallen postboy. In the excitement of the meeting and in her one 
great resolve to obtain her father's death-warrant, she had lost all 
thought of the risks she ran or of the injuries she might inflict; and 
it was with unspeakable relief, therefore, that she at last saw the 
post-boy struggle to his feet, and stand gazing after her.  "Thank 
Heaven, he is not killed!" she exclaimed again and again, as she now 
joyfully pressed Ronald into a gallop. Throughout the homeward journey, 
Grizel made it a point to urge him to greater speed when nearing a 
farmhouse, so that there would be less risk of discovery. Once or twice 
she was accosted by laborers in the field, and once by the driver of a 
cart, but their remarks were lost upon the wind as the faithful Ronald 
thundered on. She did not feel the need of sleep, for she had forgotten 
it in all her excitement, but she was greatly exhausted and suffering 
from the effects of her rough ride. 
 
</p><p>Soon the smoke in the distance showed Grizel that her native town 
lay an hour's journey ahead. She set her teeth and said an encouraging 
word to the horse. He seemed to understand, for he redoubled his 
energies. Now the roofs became visible, and now, grim and sullen, the 
turrets of the castle loomed up. Grizel felt a great lump in her throat 
as she thought of her father in his lonely despair. 
 
</p><p>She turned Ronald from the road again and cut through a clump of 
elms. She came out in a few minutes and rode more slowly toward a 
smaller gate than the one by which she had left the city.  A stout 
soldier looked at her carelessly and then turned to his tankard of ale, 
after he had noticed the mail-bags. Grizel turned into a crooked, narrow 
street lined on each side with toppling, frowning buildings. She drew 
rein before a humble house, and slipped wearily from her saddle and 
knocked at the door. An old woman opened the heavy oaken door and Grizel 
fell into her arms. 
 
</p><p>"The bags &mdash; the mail," she gasped, and fainted.  When she 
recovered consciousness, she found herself on a low, rough bed. The old 
woman was bending over her. 
 
</p><p>"Losh keep me!" said the dame. "I did na ken ye! Ma puir bairnie! 
Hoo cam' ye by these?" and she pointed to the clothes of Allen. 
 
</p><p>"The bags?" said Grizel, sitting bolt upright &mdash; 
 
</p><p>"Are under the hearth," said the old woman. 
 
</p><p>"And Ronald?" continued Grizel. 
 
</p><p>"Is in the byre wi' the coos," said the other with a knowing 
leer. "Not a soul kens it. Ne'er a body saw ye come." 
 
</p><p>Breathlessly Grizel explained all to her old nurse, and then 
sprung off the bed. At her request the old dame locked the door and 
brought her the bags.  By the aid of a sharp knife the pair slashed open 
the leathern covering, and the inclosed packets fell upon the floor. 
With trembling hands Grizel fumbled them all over, tossing one after 
another impatiently aside as she read the addresses. At last she came 
upon a large one addressed to the governor. With beating heart she 
hesitated a moment, and then tore the packet open with shaking fingers. 
She easily read the bold handwriting.  Suddenly everything swam before 
her, and again she nearly fell into her companion's arms. 
 
</p><p>It was too true. What she read was a formal 
 
    <pb entity="DSSR_000002646_0007" n="277"/> 


 
    <pb entity="DSSR_000002646_0008" n="278"/> 
 
warrant of the King, signed by his majesty, and stamped and sealed with 
red wax. It ordered the governor to hang Sir John Cochrane of Ochiltree 
at the Cross in Edinburgh at ten o'clock in the morning, on the third 
day of the following week.  She clutched the paper and hid it in her 
dress. 
 
</p><p>The disposition of the rest of the mail was soon decided upon. 
The old lady's son Jock &mdash; a wild fellow &mdash; was to put the sacks on the 
back of a donkey and turn it loose outside the gates, at his earliest 
opportunity. And then Grizel, clad in some rough garments the old lady 
procured, slipped out of the house, and painfully made her way toward 
the Canongate. 
 
</p><p>It was four o'clock in the afternoon when she reached her home. 
The porter at the gate could scarcely be made to understand that the 
uncouth figure before him was his young mistress. But a moment later her 
mother was embracing her, with tears of joy, 
 
</p><p>All the male friends of Sir John were hastily summoned, and 
Grizel related her adventure, and displayed the death-warrant of her 
father. The hated document was consigned to the flames, a consultation 
was held, and that night three of the gentlemen left for London. 
 
</p><p>The next day, the donkey and the mail-sacks were found by a 
sentry, and some little excitement was occasioned; but when the postboy 
came in later, and related how he had been attacked by six stalwart 
robbers, and how he had slain two of them and was then overpowered and 
forced to surrender the bags, all wonderment was set at rest. 
 
</p><p>The Cochrane family passed a week of great anxiety, but when it 
was ended, the three friends returned from London with joyful news. The 
King had listened to their petition, and had ordered the removal of Sir 
John to the Tower of London, until his case could be reconsidered. So to 
London Sir John went; and after a time the payment of five thousand 
pounds to some of the King's advisers secured an absolute pardon. His 
lands, which had been confiscated, were restored to him; and on his 
arrival at his Scottish home, he was warmly welcomed by a great 
concourse of his friends. He thanked them in a speech, taking care, 
however, not to tell who was so greatly instrumental in making his 
liberation possible.  But we may be sure that he was secretly proud of 
the pluck and devotion of his daughter Grizel. 

 
</p> 
</div1> 
</body>  
</text>  
</TEI.2> 
