<?xml version="1.0"?>

<?dlps id="romlitt"?>
<?dlps page-images="color" figure-images="no"?>
<?dlps transcription="other"?>

<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/tei-p4/tei2.dtd" [
<!ENTITY % POSTKB "INCLUDE">
<!ENTITY % TEI.extensions.ent SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.ent">
<!ENTITY % TEI.extensions.dtd SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.dtd">
<!ENTITY % ISOlat1 SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/charent/iso-lat1.ent"> %ISOlat1;
<!ENTITY % ISOpub SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/charent/iso-pub.ent"> %ISOpub;
<!ENTITY RomLitCo SYSTEM "uva-lib:490982" NDATA uvaHighRes>  

<!ENTITY DSSR_000001484_0001 SYSTEM "uva-lib:510506" NDATA uvaHighRes>
<!ENTITY DSSR_000001484_0002 SYSTEM "uva-lib:510507" NDATA uvaHighRes>
<!ENTITY DSSR_000001484_0003 SYSTEM "uva-lib:510508" NDATA uvaHighRes>
<!ENTITY DSSR_000001484_0004 SYSTEM "uva-lib:510509" NDATA uvaHighRes>
]>
<TEI.2 id="romlitt">
    <teiHeader creator="Etext" type="migrated">
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title type="main">'Little Africa': The Last Slave Cargo Landed in the United States</title>
                <title type="sort">little africa the last slave cargo landed in the united states</title>
                <author>Romeyn, Henry</author>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Creation of machine-readable version:</resp>
                    <name>Judy Boss</name>
                    <resp>Creation of digital images:</resp>
                    <name>Lisa Goldberg</name>
                    <resp>Conversion to TEI.2-conformant markup:</resp>
                    <name>Lisa Goldberg, University of Virginia Library Electronic Text
                    Center.</name>
                </respStmt>
            </titleStmt>
            <extent>ca. <num type="kilobytes">28</num> kilobytes</extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>University of Virginia Library</publisher>
                <pubPlace>Charlottesville, Virginia</pubPlace>
                <idno type="ETC">romlitt</idno>
                <date value="1996">1996</date>
                <availability status="public">
                    <p n="copyright">Copyright &#xa9; 1996 by the Rector and Visitors of the
                        University of Virginia</p>
                    <p n="access">Publicly accessible</p>
                </availability>
                <idno type="uva-pid">uva-lib:477343</idno>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title>University of Virginia Library, Text collection</title>
                <idno type="uva-set">UVA-LIB-Text</idno>
            </seriesStmt>
            <notesStmt>
                <note>
                    <p>Image of cover has been included from the print version.</p>
                </note>
                <note>
                    <p>Judy Boss has made the following changes: pg. 14, para. 1: institution,']
                        institution,"; pg. 14, para. 7: some-time,] some time,; pg. 15, para. 7:
                        occured.] occurred.; pg. 16, para. 6: it] it.; pg. 16, para. 6: 'Africans."]
                        "Africans."; pg. 16, para. 9: of Dahomy] of Dahomey; pg. 16, para. 10:
                        Da-homah lan'] Da-ho-mah lan'; pg. 16, para. 10: Dah-ho-mah"!] Dah-ho-mah!;
                        pg. 16, para. 10: Do ho-mah!] Da-ho-mah!"; pg. 16, para. 13: incl sure]
                        inclosure; pg. 17, continuing para. from pg. 16: Ghos.'] Ghos'.; pg. 17,
                        para. 1: rites] rites.</p>
                </note>
            </notesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull>
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title type="main">'Little Africa': The Last Slave Cargo Landed in the
                            United States.</title>
                        <title level="j">Southern Workman</title>
                        <title type="sort">little africa the last slave cargo landed in the united
                            states</title>
                        <author>Henry Romeyn</author>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <extent>pp. 14-17</extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Hampton Normal and Agricultural Institute</publisher>
                        <pubPlace>Hampton, VA</pubPlace>
                        <date value="1897-01">January 1897</date>
                        <idno type="callNo">Print copy consulted: University of Virginia library
                            call no. LC 2701 .S7</idno>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <notesStmt>
                        <note>
                            <p>Southern Workman, Vol. 26, No. 1 (Jan. 1897): pp. 14-17.</p>
                        </note>
                    </notesStmt>
                </biblFull>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>Prepared for the University of Virginia Library Electronic Text Center.</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <p>All quotation marks retained as data.</p>
                <p>All unambiguous end-of-line hyphens have been removed, and the trailing part of a
                    word has been joined to the preceding line.</p>
                <p>The images exist as archived TIFF images, one or more JPEG versions for general
                    use, and thumbnail GIFs.</p>
                <p>Keywords in the header are a local Electronic Text Center scheme to aid in
                    establishing analytical groupings.</p>
            </editorialDecl>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <creation>
                <date value="1897">1897</date>
            </creation>
            <langUsage>
                <language id="eng" usage="main">English</language>
            </langUsage>
            <textClass>
                <keywords>
                    <term>African American</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords>
                    <term>non-fiction; prose</term>
                    <term type="format">24-bit color, 400 dpi</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change>
                <date value="1996-11">November 1996</date>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>corrector</resp>
                    <name>Lisa Goldberg</name>
                </respStmt>
                <item>Added TEI header and tags</item>
            </change>
            <change>
                <date value="2005-07">July 2005</date>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Corrector</resp>
                    <name>John Ivor Carlson</name>
                </respStmt>
                <item>Converted SGML to XML and/or corrected tagging.</item>
            </change>
            <change>
                <date value="2007-09">September 2007</date>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Migration</resp>
                    <name>Ethan Gruber, University of Virginia Library</name>
                </respStmt>
                <item>Converted XML markup from TEI Lite to uva-dl-tei (TEI P4 with local
                    customizations).</item>
            </change>
            <change>
                <date value="2008-01">January 2008</date>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Migration</resp>
                    <name>Greg Murray, University of Virginia Library</name>
                </respStmt>
                <item>Programmatically updated TEI header markup (but not header content) for
                    minimal compliance with current QA requirements.</item>
            </change>
<change>
<date value="2009-03">March 2009</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>Migration</resp>
<name>Scholarly Resources, University of Virginia Library</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Added and/or replaced the digital images accompanying the electronic text. Scanning of exterior and interior (ie. pages) of item was done only for items found in the University of Virginia Special Collections Library.</item>
</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text id="d1">

        <body id="d3">

            <div1 id="d4" type="story">
                <pb entity="DSSR_000001484_0001" n="14" pid="uva-lib:510506"/>
                <head> "LITTLE AFRICA." <lb/> The Last Slave Cargo Landed in the United States. </head>

                <p>Among the passengers of the "Roger B. Taney," Captain Timothy Meaher, plying
                    between Mobile and Montgomery, Ala. in April, 1858, were a number of Northern
                    gentlemen returning to their homes after a winter spent in the South. The trip
                    occupied several days, and as might have been expected, the slavery question was
                    a fruitful theme of discussion. Captain Meaher, though born in Gardiner, Maine,
                    had removed, when a mere lad, to the Gulf States, and accumulated quite a
                    fortune for those days; a large portion of which was in "chattels" employed on
                    his half dozen steamboats, or on cotton plantations in the interior of the
                    state, and in lumbering among the pines and cypress lands near the coast. Of
                    course he was a defender of "the institution," and, in reply to the expressed
                    belief of one of his passengers that "with the supply by importation from Africa
                    cut off and any further spread in the Territories denied, the thing was doomed,"
                    he declared that, despite the stringent measures taken by most of the civilized
                    powers to crush out the over-sea traffic, it could be still carried on
                    successfully. In response to the disbelief expressed by his opponent, he offered
                    to wager any amount of money that he would "import a cargo in less than two
                    years, and no one be hanged for it." </p>
                <p>He was not a man to be daunted by difficulties, or deterred by danger. Having
                    made his boast, he prepared to make it good; and proceeded to sound some of his
                    friends on whom he thought he could rely, upon the subject of a market for a
                    cargo. He found but little trouble in engaging places for one hundred or more,
                    and decided to hold about thirty for his own use. The next thing to consider was
                    a suitable vessel. Preferring to build rather than buy,&mdash;as attracting
                    less attention, he engaged the services of a young Canadian shipwright, and the
                    keel of the schooner "Clotilde," of three hundred and twenty-seven tons, was
                    laid in the Mobile River, a short distance above the city. She was built with a
                    view to speed, and was claimed by her builder to be the fastest vessel ever
                    built in Gulf waters. Work was pushed on her, and in November she was ready for
                    sea. Lying where she did, her loading attracted no attention although when she
                    cleared "for St. Thomas and a market," ostensibly with a cargo of lumber, her
                    "ground-tier" was composed of filled water-casks, topped with barrels of meal,
                    farina, grits, and salt meats with a covering of lumber sufficient to hide from
                    casual inspection all below it, and make temporary decks and partitions for
                    stowing the expected live cargo. Duplicate papers were prepared for use on the
                    African Coast if overhauled by cruisers; also others making a fictitious
                    transfer of the vessel at Loando, on that shore. </p>
                <p>For the capital on which to trade, she carried ninety casks of rum, twenty cases
                    of cotton cloth, and about $12,000 in gold. Her builder went in her as
                    supercargo, and none of her crew, picked up at random in the city, knew of their
                    destination till at sea, and even then supposed they were on a legal trading
                    voyage. </p>
                <p>Caught in a terrific storm, which came near sending all to the bottom, the
                    Captain was forced to put into Porto Praya, Azore Islands, to repair damages;
                    but was soon again under weigh and in forty days from date of sailing was off
                    Loando. This coast was too closely watched for any trade to be effected, but the
                    fictitious change of ownership was gone through with, and the vessel sailed for
                    Whydah on the Guinea Coast, north and west of the mouth of the Niger. </p>
                <p>This was the seaport,&mdash;if port it could be called&mdash;for his
                    Sable Majesty, the King of Dahomey, to barter his surplus subjects, together
                    with such of his neighbors as he could lay hands upon, for what had become to
                    him the necessaries of life: rum, guns, cotton, and small articles for personal
                    adornment of himself and his numerous household. </p>
                <p>Its anchorage was really an open roadstead, exposed to winds and heavy seas, and
                    the Clotilde was obliged to drop her anchor nearly two miles from shore, and
                    depend for communication entirely upon native boats and boatmen. The
                    "barracoons," where were stored the live merchandise of the Dark Potentate, were
                    about five miles inland, to be safe from cruiser's fire or any casual
                    observation. </p>
                <p>Scarcely had the vessel dropped her anchor, when she was boarded by parties eager
                    to "make trade." The barracoons were visited and stock inspected. The pens were
                    full, some of the wares having been held for some time, others newly arrived.
                    Some were true and loving subjects of His Majesty, who had, through no fault of
                    their own, incurred his displeasure, and had in consequence, been swept from
                    their homes and held for sale; others were the visible fruits of raids on his
                    unprepared neighbors. </p>
                <p>Where both parties were eager to trade, there would <pb
                    entity="DSSR_000001484_0002" pid="uva-lib:510507" n="15"/> be but little cheapening or haggling
                    over bargains. The owner wished to dispose of his stock&mdash;which must be
                    fed, even if but lightly&mdash;and to get possession of the equivalent; and
                    the American wished to procure his load with the least possible delay, and leave
                    a place where danger lurked in every passing breeze, not only in the dread coast
                    fever, but in the shape of the armed cruiser. </p>
                <p>One hundred and seventy-five slaves were contracted for, all able-bodied men and
                    women, in the proportion of about two of the former to one of the latter, to be
                    delivered "free on board" (if the language of legitimate traffic can be applied
                    to the transaction,) and the risk of landing the stores paid, from the vessel,
                    to be assumed by the shore parties. Everything to go on shore must be enclosed
                    in water-tight cases and landed through the surf; and nearly half a day was at
                    times required to get a barrel safely on the beach. </p>
                <p>For the number stated, the price paid was ninety casks of rum, eight cases of
                    cotton cloth, and eight thousand six hundred and forty dollars in gold; the
                    latter the share of the Portugese middle man. </p>
                <p>The new cargo was brought off in the long, narrow dugouts of the coast, clad in
                    nature's full dress, and stowed away between decks, the sexes separated, and all
                    ironed at the ankles. A lookout was kept at the mast-head to watch for cruisers,
                    one of which carrying English colors, was known to be on the coast not far
                    distant, and had once paid the Clotilde a visit; but had respected the flag and
                    not searched her. Loading proceeded with all possible haste, and all but one
                    canoe-load were on board, and that had left the shore when, early one March
                    morning, the lookout gave the warning, "Sails, ho!" Springing into the rigging,
                    the supercargo was soon at his side; and saw not one only, but two vessels
                    slowly creeping out from behind a point, not more than six miles distant, and
                    knew them to be cruisers. His information caused a flurry below. Most of the
                    crew wanted to at once abandon ship, and try to reach shore; and were proceeding
                    to launch the boats when he reached the deck. He at once assumed command,
                    ordered the cable cut, and, pistol in hand, drove the crew to the work of making
                    sail; confident as he had the wind in his favor, of outsailing the patrolling
                    vessels. In a very short time the schooner had "steerage way" on her, and in ten
                    minutes more was pulling off the coast at an eleven knot rate, and in less than
                    three hours had passed out of view of the pursuers. Not another sail was sighted
                    during the passage. One hundred and sixty-four slaves had been taken on board.
                    Of these but two died on the passage. </p>
                <p>As soon as fairly off the coast, the cargo was divided into gangs, one of which
                    was allowed to go on deck at a time, for an hour each afternoon, when the water
                    allowance, one and one-half pints each, was issued, and the portion of the
                    vessel occupied by that company washed, the work being done by the members of
                    the gang. Food was issued twice each day, and, judging from the account of the
                    present survivors, more than usual care seems to have been taken to keep them in
                    good condition. </p>
                <p>Of course nothing had been heard of the schooner since her departure, and her
                    arrival was scarcely yet expected, when, one fine Sabbath morning in early
                    April, four months and nine days from her departure, a foam-flecked horse was
                    pulled up at the gate of Captain Meaher's house, three miles north of Mobile,
                    and his rider announced her arrival in the lower bay. Though unexpected at such
                    an early date, her return had been provided for. Of course her cargo could not
                    be publicly landed, but must be hidden until other evidences of the voyage could
                    be disposed of. </p>
                <p>The Captain of a tug was hastily called from his pew in church, and told that the
                    service of his boat was required to land a perishable cargo, waiting for him
                    down the bay. The "Czar," a steamer owned by Captain Meaher, was fired up, and
                    ordered to proceed to a point below the mouth of the Tombigbee, keep steam up,
                    and wait for orders. The regular Montgomery packet, the "Taney," which Captain
                    Meaher commanded in person, was ordered to leave at her regular evening hour,
                    under charge of her mate, but not to have supper served until Captain Meaher
                    came on board. The Clotilde was towed past the city, presumably to a fresh water
                    anchorage above, but, as soon as the tug had left her, was taken in tow by the
                    "Czar," and hauled over into Spanish River, (an arm of the Mobile, emptying into
                    the bay on its eastern side,) her living freight transferred to the Czar, and
                    she was then fired and scuttled, with a guard left to watch the spot, and see
                    that no wreckage floated down the channel. The "Czar" made all possible speed up
                    the Tombigbee, her fuel principally bacon, which, to aid deception, had been
                    taken on as freight. The Africans were landed in a dense canebreak on a
                    plantation of Gen. Dabney Maury, a guard placed over them, and with the crew of
                    the "Clotilde" on board, the "Czar" in the darkness of the early night, sped
                    down to the junction of the rivers, to meet the Taney. On meeting her, the crew
                    of the slaver were transferred to the "Taney," supplied with supper, cards and
                    whiskey, and kept locked in, till the boat arrived at Montgomery, where they
                    were placed on the cars, sent directly to New York, there paid off, and
                    scattered. They could of course be depended on not to tell the story of their
                    last cruise. </p>
                <p>On boarding his own boat, Captain Meaher apologized for the lateness of the
                    supper, took his usual place at the head of the table, said something about a
                    sick cook, and went on with his usual duties as if no unusual event had
                    occurred. The true reason for this proceeding will appear later. </p>
                <p>The Negroes had been landed, but the troubles of their importer were not over.
                    His vessel had not been announced at the Custom-house, and of course the Revenue
                    officers were soon searching for her. The story of the importation soon became
                    public, and the officers of the United States Court joined in the hunt. The
                    location of the Negroes was several times changed, and the gang was broken into
                    small squads, for easier concealment. Day after day the cane-brakes along the
                    river were scrutinized; but, though old camps were found, none could be reached
                    prior to abandonment. While many of the more conservative class of citizens did
                    not favor the importation, none would furnish any information which would tend
                    to imperil the neck of a neighbor. But, deeming himself secure from detection,
                    the supercargo with unparalleled audacity, mingled freely with the crews of the
                    searching craft, and was thus enabled to counteract their plans in some
                    instances. In one, when it was feared that time would not be given for any
                    change if the searching boat got away from Mobile promptly, liquor was smuggled
                    on board, and given to the crew, who all became drunk, detaining the craft till
                    a new one could be shipped, by which time the camp which had been located was
                    empty. </p>
                <p>But so much valid information was obtained regarding the matter and Captain
                    Meaher's share in it, that he was indicted by the Grand Jury at the next term of
                    the United States Court, and placed on trial for piracy; the specific charge
                    being that he had personally imported the cargo. But he was able easily to prove
                    an alibi. He showed by persons serving on board the Taney, and by others, living
                    in Montgomery, that, during the year ending with the time of the alleged landing
                    of the slaves, he had not missed a single weekly trip of his boat to that city;
                    by others, that he was on board the "Taney," the night the landing was said to
                    have been made, and made the trip in command as usual; in short, so well had his
                    plans been laid and carried out that conviction was impossible and he was
                    released. <pb entity="DSSR_000001484_0003" n="16" pid="uva-lib:510508"/>
                </p>
                <p>The supercargo was never arrested, nor his identity publicly known until after
                    the outbreak of hostilities in 1861. </p>
                <p>But the Captain's boast had cost him a small fortune. Frightened by the hunt, and
                    trial, several who had agreed to purchase a number, withdrew from their
                    contract; the trial with its accompanying expenses absorbed money; the schooner
                    and its outfit, had cost him about $35,000; and when he balanced his accounts of
                    the transaction, he found the sum of $100,000 on the wrong side of his
                    profit-and-loss account. He had previously owned over two hundred slaves, and
                    now found himself burdened&mdash;(for they were really a burden) with about
                    a hundred and fifty more. </p>
                <p>When the war broke out, some of them were impressed to work for the Confederate
                    Government, but many were, in a measure, left to shift for themselves. </p>
                <p>After the surrender, a man of the Captain's energy would not remain idle, and he
                    resumed business, employing as freedmen most of those still living near his
                    home. They spoke of him as a kind master. "When the war broke"<ref n="1"
                        target="n1">*</ref> they were informed that they were free, and that if they
                    chose they could work for him for wages&mdash;and many of them did
                    so&mdash;and bought from him small tracts of land, about three miles from
                    Mobile, on which they have erected cottages; thus obtaining houses of their own,
                    perhaps sooner than any others of their race in the vicinity. </p>
                <p>Employed, as many of the men are, in the getting out of timber, and preparing it
                    for market, they spend most of their time away from home, and a Sunday visit to
                    the settlement was necessary, if I would see them. </p>
                <p>On a hot Sabbath afternoon in June, in company with Mr. Augustine Meaher, I drove
                    out from Mobile to the village. On the way we met a man and his wife in a good
                    "road cart" drawn by a good horse, which they owned, en route to church in the
                    city. After some conversation, during which Mr. Meaher stated the object of my
                    visit, we drove on, they stated that we would not find many of the villagers at
                    home, but that, if I would return the next Sabbath, they would notify all whom
                    they could of my wish, and I could see them after church. As we were not far
                    from the village we drove over to it. I found it located on a high, broken
                    ground, half a mile or more from the Mobile River, surrounded by a pine forest
                    in which could still be seen some of the heavy earthworks thrown up for covering
                    the approaches to the city during the war. About thirty small houses are
                    scattered irregularly over an area of forty or fifty acres; many of them quite
                    comfortable structures, compared with the ordinary cabins of the country. On
                    adjoining land, owned by Mr. Meaher, are several others occupied by families of
                    "Country Negroes," working in the vicinity. With these the first generation "the
                    oldest inhabitants"&mdash;of "Little Africa," do not seem to mingle much.
                    Two churches are located in the settlement; one a Methodist, frequented by the
                    outsiders, the other a Baptist "Mission Chapel" of a city church, the resort of
                    the "Africans." </p>
                <p>In appearance there is not much to distinguish these from other colored persons
                    in the vicinity. One thing can be said in their favor. I saw no mulatto children
                    among them, and their morals are said to be better than those of their race,
                    debauched by centuries of slavery though how much of this may be due to feelings
                    at first entertained against them, as "barbarians," is problematical. They are
                    good workers, and their honesty is vouched for by Mr. Meaher and others who
                    employ or trade with them. </p>
                <p>They support a day school taught by a young colored woman from the city, and
                    during the conversation with some of the original ones relating to their
                    locations in Africa, a girl of eleven who acted as interpreter when their
                    English failed, showed not only a knowledge of African geography, but of that of
                    the United States as well; she used good language in the translation, and her
                    name written in my note book, was in clear, legible, well-formed letters. </p>
                <p>Most of the colony were from Dahomey, or as they pronounce the name,
                    "Dah-ho-mah." Conversing with each other, they use their native language, harsh
                    and guttural in sound, but still with more labials than that of the American
                    Indian. It is difficult to tell from their pronunciation of the names, from what
                    portion of the surrounding country those not of Dahomey come. One "Zuma" states
                    that she was from Loandi, captured first by "L'Ascotah" (probably name of
                    raiding chief) and sold twice before shipment. Others call themselves "Tekki"
                    and say they came from the mountains north of Dahomey, captured in a raid by
                    chiefs of that country. Another, "Maum P&oacute;lee" who says she was
                    nineteen at the time she was brought over, and differs in appearance from all
                    the others, says she was "A'tarco" (query "Tavrick"?) and came "long way from
                    Dahomey," probably from vicinity of Lake Tchaad. </p>
                <p>In former years most of them looked up to one woman, said to have been the wife
                    of a chief, as a kind of queen or head-woman; and now, one old Dahoman, named
                    Peter Goolth, is regarded as head-man, together with "Cudjoe"&mdash;both
                    shrewd, though somewhat comical individuals, who must have been men in middle
                    life when brought over. Though stolen and sold by his king, Peter still has a
                    warm spot in his heart for his native land. In reply to a question as to which
                    place he preferred, he at once replied "Dah-ho-mah;" repeating his answer three
                    or four times, and having it echoed by one of the women, who added: "In
                    Dah-ho-mah lan' all free, no buyee any, no payee any tax; go wuk any lan' you
                    want, nobody else wuk;" adding; when reminded of slave-raids. "Oh no catchee
                    all;" seeming to entertain the feeling, "It was by bad luck." Informed of the
                    Dahomey village at the Exposition, Peter expressed surprise, exclaiming; "Who
                    catchee?" He flatly refused to credit the story of French victories over the
                    forces of the king. "No! no! no man whip Dah-ho-mah! Got 'em too much men, got
                    'em too much fight-women. No man whip Dah-ho-mah!" </p>
                <p>Peter wears a belt of tattooing about his waist, elaborately put on; some of the
                    others have bits of tattooing on face and arm. "Zuma" wears a huge crescent on
                    her face across the nose, from cheek to cheek, made by the knife of her father
                    in early girlhood. One man's cheeks are scarred by horizontal parallel lines
                    about two inches in length; a woman has a bracelet on each wrist, done by
                    herself before captured. Others of the original band are more or less marked,
                    but none to any great extent. </p>
                <p>While not indulging in much of that extravagance in colors in dress which so
                    often affect the colored sisterhood in general or the young men of the race,
                    most of those whom I saw at church were fully as well dressed as are the
                    majority of laboring people white or black, in their locality; and most of them
                    had in their appearance and surrounding, an air of substantial physical
                    well-being none too common among the laboring class in that section of the
                    country. </p>
                <p>As I drove up to the gate of the inclosure surrounding their church on the
                    Sabbath afternoon appointed for the meeting with them, the sonorous voice of the
                    preacher, in the midst of his sermon, fell upon the ear. He was not weak-lunged
                    nor troubled with any bronchial <pb entity="DSSR_000001484_0004" n="17"
                        pid="uva-lib:510509"/> affliction. For nearly an hour we waited, while he in
                    thunder tones, dwelt upon the heinousness of disrespect to the Holy Spirit, or
                    as he expressed it, "foolin' wid de Holy Ghos'. Now he pleaded with the hearers,
                    anon he held up before them the terrors of broken law, and unkept promises of
                    better life. There was less of boisterous response, than usually is heard under
                    similar exhortations in congregations of the race, and the chanting of the
                    "Lord's Prayer" by the congregation at the close of the service, was really fine
                    and touching in its soft melody, though somewhat marred by one woman, who
                    insisted on striking one note at the end of the line an octave higher than any
                    one else. In conversation with the preacher, held after the service, he stated
                    that there were between thirty and forty of the original ones left who were
                    members of the church, and that the Sabbath School numbered about sixty
                    children. A heavy rain, lasting until nearly sunset, prevented a personal
                    inspection of much of the village, though, by detaining the people in the
                    church, it gave opportunity for conversations with individuals. They told us, as
                    I had heard from other sources, the story of the ocean passage, with its
                    fifty-five days of wonder, doubt and fear; of the enforced hidings in the cane
                    brakes; the first assignment to labor in the woods and fields, etc; all
                    corroborated by information received by white sources. They spoke of their
                    importer as a kind master, but others hinted that even the overseer was not free
                    in punishing for any dereliction of duty, after he had seen one demonstration of
                    their hatred of the lash. </p>
                <p>Nothing could be learned regarding the practice or nonpractice of any "fetich" or
                    "voudou" rites. If done at all, they are done with the utmost secrecy. When
                    first imported they are said to have buried the dead with weird and heathenish
                    ceremonies, but those I was informed had ceased. Any romance connected with them
                    is fast fading away, and with the passing of the original members of the colony
                    from the scenes of action, it will have ceased to exist, and their descendants
                    will be merged into the ordinary colored inhabitants of the section where they
                    reside. </p>
                <p>Captain Meaher died in 1891. </p>


                <closer>
                    <signed>HENRY ROMEYN.<lb/> Captain 5th Infantry, U S A </signed>
                    <dateline> Fort McPherson, Ga. </dateline>
                </closer>
            </div1>
        </body>
        <back id="d5">
            <div1 id="d6" type="note">
                <note id="n1" n="1">
                    <seg type="note-symbol">*</seg>
                    <p>An expression commonly used in some parts of the South, meaning "when the war
                        closed."</p>
                </note>

                <note id="note1">
                    <p>For most of the facts above stated I am indebted to Dr. S. V. Gaines, Dr.
                        Charles Le Baron, and other citizens of Mobile, but especially to Mr.
                        Augustine Meaher son of Captain Meaher, whose kindness and attention enabled
                        me to obtain much information not otherwise available, and to visit the
                        people in their homes. </p>
                </note>

            </div1>

        </back>
    </text>
</TEI.2>
