<?xml version="1.0"?>

<?dlps id="ShiArti"?>
<?dlps page-images="color" figure-images="yes"?>
<?dlps transcription="other"?>

<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/tei-p4/tei2.dtd" [
<!ENTITY % POSTKB "INCLUDE">
<!ENTITY % TEI.extensions.ent SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.ent">
<!ENTITY % TEI.extensions.dtd SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.dtd">
<!ENTITY % ISOpub SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/charent/iso-pub.ent"> %ISOpub;




<!ENTITY DSSR_000002648_0001 SYSTEM "000002648_0001" NDATA uvaHighRes>
<!ENTITY DSSR_000002648_0002 SYSTEM "000002648_0002" NDATA uvaHighRes>
<!ENTITY DSSR_000002648_0003 SYSTEM "000002648_0003" NDATA uvaHighRes>
<!ENTITY DSSR_000002648_0004 SYSTEM "000002648_0004" NDATA uvaHighRes>
<!ENTITY DSSR_000002648_0005 SYSTEM "000002648_0005" NDATA uvaHighRes>
]>

<TEI.2 id="ShiArti">
<teiHeader type="migrated" creator="Etext">
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title type="main">Artists' Adventures: The Rush to Death</title>
<title type="sort">artists adventures the rush to death</title>
<author>Shirlaw, Walter</author>
<respStmt>
<resp>Creation of machine-readable version</resp>
<name>Judy Boss</name>
</respStmt>
<respStmt>
<resp>Conversion to TEI-conformant markup</resp>
<name>University of Virginia Library Electronic Text Center</name>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt>
<extent>ca. <num type="kilobytes">13</num> kilobytes</extent>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>University of Virginia Library</publisher>
<pubPlace>Charlottesville, Virginia</pubPlace>
<idno type="ETC">ShiArti</idno>
<date value="1994">1994</date>
<availability status="public">
<p n="copyright">Copyright &#xa9; 1994 by the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia</p>
<p n="access">Publicly accessible</p>
</availability>
<idno type="uva-pid">uva-lib:477376</idno>
</publicationStmt>
<seriesStmt>
<title>University of Virginia Library, Text collection</title>
<idno type="uva-set">UVA-LIB-Text</idno>
</seriesStmt>
<notesStmt>
<note>
<p>Illustrations have been included from the print version.</p>
</note>
</notesStmt>
<sourceDesc>
<biblFull>
<titleStmt>
<title type="main">Artists' Adventures: The Rush to Death</title>
<title type="sort">artists adventures the rush to death</title>
<author>Walter Shirlaw</author>
<respStmt>
<resp>Illustrator</resp>
<name>Walter Shirlaw</name>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>The Century Illustrated Monthly Magazine</publisher>
<pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
<date value="1893-11">November 1893</date>
</publicationStmt>
<seriesStmt>
<p>Volume XLVII</p>
</seriesStmt>
</biblFull>
</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc>
<encodingDesc>
<projectDesc>
<p>Prepared for the University of Virginia Library Electronic
Text Center</p>
</projectDesc>
<editorialDecl>
<p>All quotation marks retained as data</p>
<p>All unambiguous end-of-line hyphens have been removed, and the
trailing part of a word has been joined to the preceding line.</p>
<p id="ETC">Keywords in the header are a local Electronic Text
Center scheme to aid in establishing analytical groupings</p>
</editorialDecl>
<refsDecl>
<p>ID elements are given for each page element and are composed
of the text's
unique cryptogram and the given page number, as in SpeFQue1 for
page one of Spenser's Faerie Queene.</p>
</refsDecl>
</encodingDesc>
<profileDesc>
<creation>
<date value="1893-11">November 1893</date>
</creation>
<langUsage>
<language id="eng" usage="main">English</language>
</langUsage>
<textClass>
<keywords>
<term>non-fiction</term>
</keywords>
</textClass>
</profileDesc>
<revisionDesc>
<change>
<date value="1994-10">October 1994</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>corrector</resp>
<name>Bryson Clevenger Jr.</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Created header.  Paginated according to printed text.
Cleaned ambiguous end of line hyphens. Spellchecked against
orginal print. Retagged italics. Scanned images from printed text</item>
</change>
<change>
<date value="2005-07">July 2005</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>Corrector</resp>
<name>John Ivor Carlson</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Converted to XML and/or checked tags.</item>
</change>
<change>
<date value="2007-09">September 2007</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>Migration</resp>
<name>Ethan Gruber, University of Virginia Library</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Converted XML markup from TEI Lite to uva-dl-tei (TEI P4 with local customizations).</item>
</change>
<change>
<date value="2008-01">January 2008</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>Migration</resp>
<name>Greg Murray, University of Virginia Library</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Programmatically updated TEI header markup (but not header content) for minimal compliance with current QA requirements.</item>
</change>
<change>
<date value="2009-03">March 2009</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>Migration</resp>
<name>Scholarly Resources, University of Virginia Library</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Added and/or replaced the digital images accompanying the electronic text. Scanning of exterior and interior (ie. pages) of item was done only for items found in the University of Virginia Special Collections Library.</item>
</change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text id="d1">
<body id="d2">

<div1 type="essay" id="d3">
 <pb entity="DSSR_000002648_0001" n="41"/>
<head>ARTISTS' ADVENTURES: THE RUSH TO DEATH. <lb/>
WITH PICTURES BY THE AUTHOR.</head>

<p>
IN the summer of 1890, while making for the United States
government an enumeration of the Cheyenne Indian Reservation on
Tongue River, Montana, and noting its condition, I was a witness
to the following remarkable incident:</p><p>
On the evening of September 7, a youth named Hugh Boyle was
shot and killed by two Cheyenne bucks called Head Chief and Young
Mule.  Head Chief was so named from his position as leader of a
group of bucks who dressed themselves in varied fantastic and
picturesque costumes of feathers and paint, their main occupation
being to dance a begging dance known as the "Omaha Dance" before
the agency.  Young Mule, a youth of eighteen, was one of the
band, and a close companion of Head Chief, who was really the
murderer, Young Mule being only an accessory.</p>
<p> There was no motive apparent for the act, save a savage
desire to kill.  The lad was unknown to the Indians, having
arrived but recently on a visit to relatives, who were old
settlers.  On the evening of his assassination he was on the way
to aid his uncle in herding cattle.  It was a dark and dismal
night; the road was long
and isolated, and he rode on horseback.  The horse, still
saddled,
was found the following day peacefully grazing.  This was the
first
intimation of a mystery.  After a fruitless three-day quest in
the
wooded hills and ravines,
 
 <pb entity="DSSR_000002648_0002" n="42"/>  
 
 a more careful search for some
clue of the missing boy was made near home in the lowlands, when
we
came upon his hat lying in the bed of a run filled only with damp
sod, and, on turning it over, saw a bullet-hole dotted with
blood.
Here, clearly, was a murder.</p><p>
The chiefs were now called upon, and in a few hours American
Horse, a prominent chief, reported that the body had been found
in
a run between two hills, four miles from the agency.  Learning
this, the agent, accompanied by a force of troops, made the
ascent
of the hill, a toilsome one, to the spot indicated as the place
of
burial.</p><p>
A careful examination was made to determine whether the
killing was the act of a white man or a redskin.  We saw faintly
visible in the fresh earth the marks of a moccasin or bare foot.
The Indian chiefs, seated close in a semicircle, were looking on
with great alertness.  On hearing the decision, they acknowledged
at once that it was the deed of two bucks, whose names they said
they would divulge at the proper time, which meant when they were
compelled to.  The body of the boy was then unearthed, placed on
an
army stretcher, and conveyed to the ambulance waiting below.  As
the procession passed down the narrow path in single file, the
silent tread of the Indians closing in the rear, it was desolate
and mournful in the extreme.</p><p>
The Indians condemned the murder as a cowardly act, and
deeply deplored the sad mishap as tending to break the existing
peace, and
all pledged their faith to aid in bringing the guilty to justice.

The Indian police were called together, with additional trusty
members of the tribe, and were empowered to arrest the murderers.

In twenty-four hours they returned, reporting that the assassins
could not be found.  On Saturday, the 13th, when the rations were
issued, the agent called for a powwow of the chiefs.  The meeting
was most characteristic of Indian duplicity.  They admitted that
they knew who the murderers were, and thought they should be
punished; but they told nothing definite.  During the discussion
the father of Head Chief pleaded most pathetically for the life
of
his son, saying he had tried to bring him up to do right to his
American Father, but that he was young and rash.  This eloquent
appeal was delivered through an interpreter with great dignity.
We
were all much moved, but the situation was unchanged, when
American
Horse, a noble-looking Indian, bearing a strong resemblance to
George Washington, offered forty ponies as a ransom for the life
of
the boy.  The agent said that that was not justice in the eyes of
white men, and expressed his determination to arrest the
murderers
at all hazards; whereupon the chiefs proclaimed that the two
murderers would not be taken alive, but would challenge the
troops,
and would appear in half an hour "to kill and be killed."  The
agent rose to his feet, exclaiming, "We are ready; bring on your
men."</p><p>
In an instant the young bucks who had fringed the outer
space
of the agency mounted their ponies, and from camp to camp
conveyed
the word of challenge.  Then in haste they sought the rounded
edges
of the hills bordering the western bank of the Lame Deer, seeking
reserved seats in the natural amphitheater.

 

 <pb entity="DSSR_000002648_0003"/>

 <pb entity="DSSR_000002648_0004"/>

 <pb entity="DSSR_000002648_0005" n="45"/>

Following them went the squaws old and young, with their papooses
and their household effects.</p><p>
From these picturesque groups came mournful sounds, mingled
with shouts of defiance, as the exodus moved past the agency and
sought points of shelter.  Everything seemed to have been
understood and prepared.  The agent gave orders to all, including
the Indian police, to arm themselves and prepare for the attack.
The military, who were camped a mile below the Lame Deer, were
informed, and sent troops.  A force of cavalry was also quickly on
hand.  The aim of the troops, and of the agent, was not to kill the
two culprits, but to inclose them on all sides and to secure their
arrest.  This just and humane desire, as the sequel shows, failed.
Suddenly there appeared on a rocky point the two braves, mounted,
and arrayed in their war-paint and feathers, daringly facing the
unequal fight.  They moved with great rapidity from point to
point, shouting their battle-cry and firing, while showers of bullets
plowed the ground about them.  For one full hour this natural
fortress was held by them, when, taken in the rear by a troop of
cavalry, they were compelled to seek shelter on the plains or
wooded hills beyond.  Head Chief, still mounted, acted the hero,
knowing that in the legends of the witnessing tribe his name
would be celebrated as one who died a true brave.  Unseen, he crossed
the plain, taking flight for the opposite hills, where without
warning he met a detachment of troops.  The challenge was "to kill and be
killed."  So it was.  Head Chief bit the dust ten feet from the
point of encounter.  Four bullets had done their work, and the
Indian was laid low.</p><p>
Young Mule, the younger Indian, unmounted, his pony having
been shot, was seen bounding like a deer over the uneven ground
and tangled sage-brush.  He sought refuge in a dry run.  Here for an
hour, his ammunition still holding out, he kept at bay all who
dared his capture.  One sad incident preceding his death was the
appeal of his mother to save him from impending doom.  It was
fruitless, none daring to attempt his arrest.  Evidently he meant
to die as his comrade had died.</p><p>
His mother, now knowing that her boy was lost, came out on
the open plain, her legs slashed and cut from the knee downward, the
blood streaming on the ground.  While the bullets cut through the
brush she chanted and wailed his death-dirge.  He fell by the
bullet of one of the Indian police, which penetrated his heart.
The Cheyenne is brave, and the young bucks died like
Spartans.</p><p>
The agent, the doctor, a lieutenant, an Indian chief, and I
viewed the dead.  As we approached the body of Head Chief, I saw
the gleam of a knife.  With sudden frenzy his sister sprang
toward us, shielding the body from our gaze.  The old chief tried to
pacify her, but she burst into tears. </p><p>
The tragedy over, the multitude, eight hundred strong, came
down the hills pell-mell, with colors and dust flying, the young
bucks leading the van, sweeping the plain like a whirlwind; the
squaws coming on with shrill shouts, chanting their dirges, which
mingled with the howling of the dogs,&mdash;a scene never to be
forgotten.</p><p>
That night the burial took place, where or how was never
known; but far into the night could be heard the funeral
rites.</p><p>
The following morning little mounds of stones were seen
dotting the hills and the plain.  Head Chief's trail had been
followed, and wherever blood had dropped from his wounds a heap
of
stones had been laid.  The spot where he fell was marked with a
high mound of stones, and a large feather from his head-dress
stood erect on the summit.  This was a great mark of respect, because
he died facing the enemy.  Young Mule died in a hole behind the
sagebrush; as this was considered the act of a coward, his grave
was left unmarked and his suffering was unnoticed.</p>
<trailer><hi rend="italic">Walter Shirlaw.</hi></trailer>

</div1>
</body>
</text>
</TEI.2>

