<?xml version="1.0"?>

<?dlps id="ShiPart"?>
<?dlps page-images="color" figure-images="no"?>
<?dlps transcription="other"?>

<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/tei-p4/tei2.dtd" [
<!ENTITY % POSTKB "INCLUDE">
<!ENTITY % TEI.extensions.ent SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.ent">
<!ENTITY % TEI.extensions.dtd SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.dtd">
<!ENTITY % ISOpub SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/charent/iso-pub.ent"> %ISOpub;
<!ENTITY DSSR_000002674_0001 SYSTEM "000002674_0001" NDATA uvaHighRes>
<!ENTITY DSSR_000002674_0002 SYSTEM "000002674_0002" NDATA uvaHighRes>
<!ENTITY DSSR_000002674_0003 SYSTEM "000002674_0003" NDATA uvaHighRes>
<!ENTITY DSSR_000002674_0004 SYSTEM "000002674_0004" NDATA uvaHighRes>
<!ENTITY DSSR_000002674_0005 SYSTEM "000002674_0005" NDATA uvaHighRes>
]>
<TEI.2 id="ShiPart">
    <teiHeader type="migrated" creator="Etext">
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title type="main">Life and Sayings of Mrs. Partington and others of the family</title>
                <title type="sort">life and sayings of mrs partington and others of the family</title>
                <author>Shillaber, Benjamin Penhallow</author>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Creation of machine-readable version:</resp>
                    <name>Stephen Railton</name>
                    <resp>Creation of digital images:</resp>
                    <name>Stephen Railton</name>
                    <resp>Conversion to TEI.2-conformant markup:</resp>
                    <name>University of Virginia Library Electronic Text Center.</name>
                </respStmt>
            </titleStmt>
            <extent>ca. <num type="kilobytes">11</num> kilobytes</extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>University of Virginia Library</publisher>
                <pubPlace>Charlottesville, Virginia</pubPlace>
                <idno type="ETC">ShiPart</idno>
                <date value="1997">1997</date>
                <availability status="public">
                    <p n="copyright">Copyright &#xa9; 1997 by the Rector and Visitors of the
                        University of Virginia</p>
                    <p n="access">Publicly accessible</p>
                </availability>
                <idno type="uva-pid">uva-lib:477377</idno>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title>University of Virginia Library, Text collection</title>
                <idno type="uva-set">UVA-LIB-Text</idno>
            </seriesStmt>
            <notesStmt>
                <note>
                    <p>Illustrations in Shillaber's work have been included from the print version.
                        The portrait of Aunt Polly is taken from Mark Twain's The Adventures of Tom
                        Sawyer, UVA library call number PS1306.A1 1876.</p>
                </note>
                <note>
                    <p>The electronic text of Shillaber's work is preceded an editorial note written
                        by Professor Stephen Railton of the University of Virginia.</p>
                </note>
            </notesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull>
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title type="main">Life and Sayings of Mrs. Partington and others of the
                            family</title>
                        <title type="sort">life and sayings of mrs partington and others of the
                            family</title>
                        <author>Benjamin Penhallow Shillaber</author>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <extent>pp. 91-93, 111-12</extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>J.C. Derby</publisher>
                        <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                        <date value="1854">1854</date>
                        <idno type="callNo">Print copy consulted: UVA Library call number PS2817 .L5
                            1854</idno>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <notesStmt>
                        <note>
                            <p>"How Ike Dropped the Cat" and "Moral Training" are excerpts taken
                                from Life and Sayings of Mrs. Partington and others of the
                            family</p>
                        </note>
                    </notesStmt>
                </biblFull>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>Prepared for the University of Virginia Library Electronic Text Center.</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <p>All quotation marks retained as data.</p>
                <p>All unambiguous end-of-line hyphens have been removed, and the trailing part of a
                    word has been joined to the preceding line.</p>
                <p>The images exist as archived TIFF images, one or more JPEG versions for general
                    use, and thumbnail GIFs.</p>
                <p>Keywords in the header are a local Electronic Text Center scheme to aid in
                    establishing analytical groupings.</p>
            </editorialDecl>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <creation>
                <date value="1854">1854</date>
            </creation>
            <langUsage>
                <language id="eng" usage="main">English</language>
            </langUsage>
            <textClass>
                <keywords>
                    <term>prose; fiction</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords>
                    <term type="format">24-bit color; 400 dpi</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change>
                <date value="1997-06">June 1997</date>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>corrector</resp>
                    <name>Carol Osborne</name>
                </respStmt>
                <item>Added TEI header and tags</item>
            </change>
            <change>
                <date value="2005-07">July 2005</date>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Corrector</resp>
                    <name>John Ivor Carlson</name>
                </respStmt>
                <item>Converted to XML and/or checked tags.</item>
            </change>
            <change>
                <date value="2007-09">September 2007</date>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Migration</resp>
                    <name>Ethan Gruber, University of Virginia Library</name>
                </respStmt>
                <item>Converted XML markup from TEI Lite to uva-dl-tei (TEI P4 with local
                    customizations).</item>
            </change>
            <change>
                <date value="2008-01">January 2008</date>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Migration</resp>
                    <name>Greg Murray, University of Virginia Library</name>
                </respStmt>
                <item>Programmatically updated TEI header markup (but not header content) for
                    minimal compliance with current QA requirements.</item>
            </change>
<change>
<date value="2009-03">March 2009</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>Migration</resp>
<name>Scholarly Resources, University of Virginia Library</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Added and/or replaced the digital images accompanying the electronic text. Scanning of exterior and interior (ie. pages) of item was done only for items found in the University of Virginia Special Collections Library.</item>
</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>

    <text id="d1">
        <front id="d2">
            <div1 type="note" id="d3">
                <head>SHILLABER'S IKE</head>
                <lb/>
                <p><hi rend="italic">Like MT, Benjamin Penhallow Shillaber began his career as a
                        newspaper compositor. In 1847, a squib he set into the</hi> Boston Post <hi
                        rend="italic">about a scatter-brained woman named Mrs. Partington instantly
                        caught the public's fancy. In the early 1850s he edited the humor
                    magazine</hi> The Carpet-Bag <hi rend="italic">, the first national periodical
                        to which Samuel Clemens (Mark Twain not having been born yet) sent a
                        contribution. The two sketches below, featuring Mrs. Partington's nephew
                        Isaac, or Ike, were among the pieces Shillaber collected for</hi> The Life
                    and Sayings of Mrs. Partington and Others of the Family <hi rend="italic">(New
                        York: J.C. Derby, 1854). The book sold thousands of copies, and was a
                        favorite of MT's. He probably intended the picture of Mrs. P on the last
                        page of</hi> Tom Sawyer <hi rend="italic"> as both a tribute to Shillaber
                        and an acknowledgment of the kinship between the two aunts and their
                        mischevious nephews.</hi></p>
                
            </div1>
        </front>

        <body id="d4">

            <div1 type="story" id="d5">
                <pb entity="DSSR_000002674_0001" n="91"/>
                <head>HOW IKE DROPPED THE CAT.</head>

               <p>NOW, Isaac," said Mrs. Partington, as she came into the room with a
                    basket snugly covered over, "take our Tabby, and drop her somewhere, and see
                    that she don't come back again, for I am sick and tired of driving her out of
                    the butter. She is the thievinest creatur! But don't hurt her, Isaac; only take
                    care that she don't come back."</p>

                <p>Ike smiled as he received his charge, and the old lady felt happy in getting rid
                    of her trouble without resorting to violence. She would rather have endured the
                    evil of the cat, great as that evil was, than that the poor quadruped should be
                    inhumanly dealt with. She saw Ike depart, in the dusk of the evening, and
                    watched him until he became lost to view in the shadow of a tree. It was a full
                    half hour before he returned with his empty basket, and an unusual glee marked
                    his appearance, &mdash; it sparkled in his eye, it glowed in his cheek, it
                    sported in his hair, &mdash; and Ike looked really handsome, as he stood
                    before the dame, and proclaimed the success of his mission.</p>

                <p>"Did she drop easy, Isaac?" asked the old lady, <pb entity="DSSR_000002674_0002" n="92"/> looking upon him
                    kindly, "and won't she comeback?"</p>

                <p>"She dropt just as easy!" said Ike, letting his basket fall on the floor, and
                    shying his cap upon the table, somewhat endangering a glass lamp with a wooden
                    bottom that stood thereon; "she dropt just as easy! and she won't come back
                    &mdash; you may bet high on that."</p>

                <p>"But you didn't beat and mangle her, Isaac, did you? If you did I should be
                    afraid she would come back and haunt us &mdash; I have heard of such
                    things"; and she looked anxiously in his face; but, detecting there no trace of
                    guilt, she patted him on the head, and parted his hair, and told him to sit down
                    and eat his supper, which the young gentleman did with considerable unction.</p>

                <p>"Isaac! Isaac!" screamed Mrs. Partington, at the foot of the little stairway that
                    led to the attic where the boy slept, the next morning after the above
                    occurrence. "Isaac!" &mdash; and he came down stairs slowly, rubbing his
                    eyes as he came. She had disturbed his morning nap.</p>

                <p>"Isaac," said she, "what is that hanging yonder to a limb of our apple-tree?" One
                    scattering tree, as she said, constituted her whole orchard, unless she counted
                    the poplar by the corner.</p>

                <p>"I can't see so fur off," said Ike, still rubbing his eyes.</p>

                <p>"Well, I should think it was a cat; and it looks to me like our Tabby. O, Isaac!
                    if you have done this!" and a tone akin to horror trembled in her voice.</p>

                <p>"I'll go and see if it's her," said Ike, as if not hearing the last part of her
                    remark; and he dashed out of <pb entity="DSSR_000002674_0003" n="93"/> the door, but soon came back, with
                    wonder depicted on every feature of his expressive countenance. "O, it's her!
                    sure enough, it's her!" cried he, "but I <hi rend="italic">did</hi> drop her!"</p>

                <p>"Well, how could she come there then?" and the good old lady looked puzzled.</p>

                <p>"I'll tell you how I guess it was," said Ike, looking demurely up. "I guess that
                    she committed suicide, because we was going to drop her; they are dreadful
                    knowing critters, you know."</p>

                <p>"True enough," replied the old lady, while something like a tear glistened in her
                    eye &mdash; her pity was excited; "true enough, Isaac, and I dare say she
                    thought hard of us for doing it; but she had n't ought to if she'd have
                    considered a minute."</p>

                <p>Ike said no more, but went out and cut down the supposed suicide, with a serious
                    manner, and buried her beneath her gallows, deep down among the roots of the old
                    tree, and she never came back.</p>

                <p>The old lady told the story to the minister, and Ike vouched for it, but the good
                    man shook his head incredulously at the idea of the suicide, and looked at the
                    boy. He very evidently understood how the cat was <hi rend="italic"
                    >dropped</hi>.</p>
            </div1>

            <div1 type="story" id="d6">
                <pb entity="DSSR_000002674_0004" n="111"/>
                <head>MORAL TRAINING.</head>

                <p> MORAL training," said Mrs. Partington, "is the best, arter all." She
                    had heard some one in the omnibus speaking of moral training, and her
                    benevolence gave it into the charge of memory until she got home, and memory
                    revolved it, and pondered it, and reviewed it, and fancy construed it to mean
                    something about the military training that was to come off the next day.</p>

                <p>"I hope it will be a moral training, I'm shore," said she; "for I see tho Gov'nor
                    is to be there in his new suit, and I hope they'll make their revolutions well
                    before him. I do admire the millintery, where the sogers in their fancy unicorns
                    look jest like a patchwork quilt. They was n't moral trainings in old times,
                    when men put 'enemies into their heads to steal away their hats,' as Mr. Smooth,
                    the schoolmaster, used to say. Your Uncle Paul had a good deal of millintery
                    sperrit sometimes, Isaac."</p>

                <p>Ike had remained very quiet while she was speaking.</p>

                <p>"What upon airth are you doing there, Isaac?" cried she.</p>
                <pb entity="DSSR_000002674_0005" n="112"/>
                <p>The young gentleman readily told her he was painting a horse, at the same time
                    displaying an animal, nominally of that description, done beautifully in blue,
                    which he appeared to look on with much satisfaction.</p>

                <p>"But what are you painting it with? As true as I'm alive you've got your Uncle
                    Paul's tompion that he used to wear in his cap so long ago, and you're using up
                    all my bluing!"</p>

                <p>That pompon, saved for so many years, to be used for such a purpose! Ah, Ike,
                    Ike! we fear the old lady will have sad times with thee yet. Why didst thou,
                    yester even, secrete the large ball of yarn for thine own purposes, which
                    to-morrow she will seek for in vain? Say, why?</p>

            </div1>

        </body>
    </text>
</TEI.2>
