<?xml version="1.0"?>

<?dlps id="SteMary"?>
<?dlps page-images="none" figure-images="yes"?>
<?dlps transcription="other"?>

<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/tei-p4/tei2.dtd" [
<!ENTITY % POSTKB "INCLUDE">
<!ENTITY % TEI.extensions.ent SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.ent">
<!ENTITY % TEI.extensions.dtd SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.dtd">
<!ENTITY % ISOnum SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/charent/iso-num.ent"> %ISOnum;
<!ENTITY % ISOpub SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/charent/iso-pub.ent"> %ISOpub;


<!ENTITY DSSR_000002659_0001 SYSTEM "000002659_0001" NDATA uvaHighRes>
<!ENTITY DSSR_000002659_0002 SYSTEM "000002659_0002" NDATA uvaHighRes>
<!ENTITY DSSR_000002659_0003 SYSTEM "000002659_0003" NDATA uvaHighRes>
<!ENTITY DSSR_000002659_0004 SYSTEM "000002659_0004" NDATA uvaHighRes>
]>

<TEI.2 id="SteMary">
<teiHeader type="migrated" creator="Etext">
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title type="main">Mary Austin</title>
<title type="sort">mary austin</title>
<author>Austin review: Steffens, Lincoln, 1866-1936</author>
<respStmt>
<resp>Creation of machine-readable version:</resp>
<name>Judy Boss</name>
<resp>Creation of digital images:</resp>
<name>Deirdre Johnson, Electronic Text Center, University of Virginia.</name>
<resp>Conversion to TEI.2-conformant markup:</resp>
<name>University of Virginia Library Electronic Text Center.</name>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt>
<extent>ca. <num type="kilobytes">11</num> kilobytes</extent>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>University of Virginia Library</publisher>
<pubPlace>Charlottesville, Virginia</pubPlace>
<idno type="ETC">SteMary</idno>
<date value="1996">1996</date>
<availability status="public">
<p n="copyright">Copyright &#xa9; 1996 by the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia</p>
<p n="access">Publicly accessible</p>
</availability>
<idno type="uva-pid">uva-lib:477409</idno>
</publicationStmt>
<seriesStmt>
<title>University of Virginia Library, Text collection</title>
<idno type="uva-set">UVA-LIB-Text</idno>
</seriesStmt>
<notesStmt>
<note>
<p>Illustrations have been included from the print version.</p>
</note>
</notesStmt>
<sourceDesc>
<biblFull>
<titleStmt>
<title type="main">Mary Austin</title>
<title level="j">American Magazine</title>
<title type="sort">mary austin</title>
<author>Lincoln Steffens</author>
</titleStmt>
<editionStmt>
<p>1st Edition.</p>
</editionStmt>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>Crowell Publishing Company</publisher>
<pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
<date value="1911">1911</date>
</publicationStmt>
<seriesStmt>
<p>American Magazine. Vol. LXXII, 1911. pp. 178-181.</p>
</seriesStmt>
<notesStmt>
<note>
<p>The piece entitled "Mary Austin" has been excerpted from a longer article, called "Interesting People."</p>
</note>
</notesStmt>
</biblFull>
</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc>
<encodingDesc>
<projectDesc>
<p>Prepared for the University of Virginia Library Electronic Text
Center.</p>
</projectDesc>
<editorialDecl>
<p>All quotation marks retained as data.</p>
<p>Spell-check and verification made
against printed text using WordPerfect spell checker.</p>
<p>All unambiguous end-of-line hyphens have been removed, and the
trailing part of a word has been joined to the preceding line.</p>
<p>The images exist as archived TIFF images, one or more JPEG versions
for general use, and thumbnail GIFs.</p>
<p id="ETC">Keywords in the header are a local Electronic Text Center scheme
to aid in establishing analytical groupings.</p>
</editorialDecl>
<refsDecl>
<p>ID elements are given for each page element and are composed of the text's
unique cryptogram and the given page number, as in AusEmma1 for page one of
Jane Austen's Emma.</p>
</refsDecl>
</encodingDesc>
<profileDesc>
<creation>
<date value="1911">1911</date>
</creation>
<langUsage>
<language id="eng" usage="main">English</language>
</langUsage>
<textClass>
<keywords>
<term>non-fiction; prose</term>
<term>Native American</term>
<term>Women Writers</term>
</keywords>
<keywords>
<term type="artist">Bangs</term>
<term type="visual work">Photograph</term>
</keywords>
<keywords>
<term>24-bit color; 300 dpi</term>
</keywords>
</textClass>
</profileDesc>
<revisionDesc>
<change>
<date value="1996-05">May 1996</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>corrector</resp>
<name>Deirdre Johnson</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Added header and basic TEI markup.</item>
</change>
<change>
<date value="2005-07">July 2005</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>Corrector</resp>
<name>John Ivor Carlson</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Converted to XML and/or checked tags.</item>
</change>
<change>
<date value="2007-09">September 2007</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>Migration</resp>
<name>Ethan Gruber, University of Virginia Library</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Converted XML markup from TEI Lite to uva-dl-tei (TEI P4 with local customizations).</item>
</change>
<change>
<date value="2008-01">January 2008</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>Migration</resp>
<name>Greg Murray, University of Virginia Library</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Programmatically updated TEI header markup (but not header content) for minimal compliance with current QA requirements.</item>
</change>
<change>
<date value="2009-03">March 2009</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>Migration</resp>
<name>Scholarly Resources, University of Virginia Library</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Added and/or replaced the digital images accompanying the electronic text. Scanning of exterior and interior (ie. pages) of item was done only for items found in the University of Virginia Special Collections Library.</item>
</change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>
<text id="d1">
<body id="d2">

<div1 type="essay" id="d3">
    
    <pb entity="DSSR_000002659_0001" n="178"/>
<head> <hi rend="center"> MARY AUSTIN</hi></head>
<p>
OUT in the great Southwest they say that the desert &ldquo;gets&rdquo; those
who live there long enough, and they illustrate themselves the
truth of that saying. They say, but they stay; they cannot come
away.
</p><p>&ldquo;No reminders will fend men from its trails,&rdquo; says Mary Austin
in her &ldquo;Lost Borders.&rdquo;  And she thinks the reason is that &ldquo;there is
something incomprehensible to the man-mind in the concurrence of
death and beauty. Shall the tender opal mist betray you? the airy
depth of mountain blueness; the blazonry of painted, mud-scarred
buttes; the far peaks molten with the alpen glow, cooled by the
rising of the velvet, violet twilight tide, and the leagues and
leagues of stars?  As easy for a man to believe that a beautiful
woman can be cruel.&rdquo;
</p><p>That's the desert. Mary Austin got it. It didn't get her,
and she explains that, too.
</p><p>&ldquo;Mind you,&rdquo; she says, &ldquo;it is men who go mostly into the
desert, who love it past all reasonableness, slack their ambitions,
cast off old usages, neglect their families because of the pulse of
a life laid bare to its thews and sinews. Their women hate the
life like the land.&rdquo;
</p><p>This they deny out there. I've heard them say that the desert
did get Mary Austin; that what she calls the &ldquo;mark of the land,&rdquo; is
cut in her own soul; and that after London, Paris and New York, she
will have to come back. And something she said recently about
these &ldquo;lonely, desert, city places,&rdquo; points that way. But this may
mean no more than that, as she saw the whole world and the fulness
thereof in the Mohave, so now she sees the desert and all the
emptiness thereof in the town. New York &ldquo;gets&rdquo; one, too, in time,
especially women.
</p><p>No matter now how this turns out, however, there is no denial
out there that this woman knows and shows the desert. On the
contrary, when the tourist steps, eye-sore, parched and
disappointed, from his train, the contented inhabitants offer him
her books. These tell their tale, and it's the story of a people
who feel and who love the romance in the few, commonplace facts of
a very charming, but very monotonous life. It's poetry, her prose
is; it's the poetry of life, of life lived to-day; conscious,
beautiful poetry. That's what gets them out there, and that's what
Mary Austin got.
</p><p>And it is one of the marvels of the desert that she did get
it; a marvel with a common-place explanation. She was one of those
many little middle Western girls who wanted to write, so she wrote.
She was born in Carlinville, Ill., a Methodist center for hogs and
corn, and she wrote there. &ldquo;Rubbish&rdquo; they called it, and they
sometimes called her a liar. But the reason they called her that
was because, being brought up (like you and me) not to see, not to
hear and especially not to say such things, she saw and she heard
and she told marvelous &ldquo;stories&rdquo; about such things as happen on the
prairie of hogs and corn. In other words, she hit upon the secret
of literary success. Her hungry mind seized upon the life about
her and she saw and she wrote the romance that is in all life. She
is making a novel now of that stuff.</p>
    
    <pb entity="DSSR_000002659_0002" n="179"/>
<p><hi rend="center">MARY AUSTIN</hi><lb/>
A writer of unusual gifts and unusual experience. Mrs. Austin
lived among the<lb/>
Indians in the Nevada desert. Out of this life she wrote &ldquo;The Land
of Little Rain&rdquo;<lb/>
and other books, as well as &ldquo;The Arrow Maker,&rdquo; a play produced last
season at the<lb/>
New Theatre in New York.
 </p>

    <pb entity="DSSR_000002659_0003" n="180"/>
<p>Well, that's how she got the desert. Yearning for the great
world, she was taken to California at nineteen by her family, which
settled at Tejon Pass, on the edge of the Mohave desert. There she
married, and her husband took her deeper in, to Lone Pine. There
was work to do, and they did it. Mrs. Austin worked &ldquo;like an
Indian woman,&rdquo; she says: house-work, gardening, and she taught
school. Also she studied and she wrote. There was nothing to
write about; that is to say, there was nothing to write about that
was like anything that had ever been written. So she wrote what
had never been written. She wrote the desert.
</p><p>&ldquo;I wrote for the great world outside,&rdquo; she says, &ldquo;and I kept
in touch with it. There were no papers, no news, no books, no
theatre, no music, but&mdash;by a sub-sense of some sort, I moved as the
world moved.&rdquo;
</p><p>Once, as a teacher, she drafted a new plan for teaching which
was accepted in California, and, by and by, it developed that this
same plan had been thought of and adopted &ldquo;outside.&rdquo;  She has other
marvelous stories to prove her sub-sense. But there's another
explanation.
</p><p>Mary Austin, having nothing else to study, studied the desert,
its form, its weather, its lights, its plants. &ldquo;I saw that the
shadow of sage brush was a dark tawny color,&rdquo; she says, &ldquo;the rabbit
bush was blue. I painted them to make sure.&rdquo;  She rode and tramped
about everywhere and she &ldquo;saw the coyote look up to see where
buzzards were going, for a sign of food.&rdquo;  And then there were men
and 
    <pb entity="DSSR_000002659_0004" n="181"/> 
    women: miners, herders, storekeepers, gamblers,
Indians, wives, daughters and people. &ldquo;I asked them everything
that I had the courage to know,&rdquo; she says, &ldquo;and,&rdquo; after a pause,
she added &ldquo;I am without fear.&rdquo;  She put the land into &ldquo;The Land of
Little Rain,&rdquo; the land, and the plants, and the shadows. She put
the animals and the animal-like men into &ldquo;The Flock.&rdquo;  The Indians
are in &ldquo;The Basket Women.&rdquo;  And the rest of us are in &ldquo;Lost
Borders.&rdquo;  And, taken all together&mdash;these and her play and her
novels&mdash;they contain knowledge and religion, nature and human
nature; they contain all the plain facts of the desert, but so
understood&mdash;with such sympathy and such comprehension&mdash;that they
are life and the poetry of life anywhere.
</p><signed>                                   LINCOLN STEFFENS.</signed>


</div1>
</body>
</text>
</TEI.2>

