<?xml version="1.0"?>

<?dlps id="WasNegr"?>
<?dlps page-images="color" figure-images="no"?>
<?dlps transcription="other"?>

<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/tei-p4/tei2.dtd" [
<!ENTITY % POSTKB "INCLUDE">
<!ENTITY % TEI.extensions.ent SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.ent">
<!ENTITY % TEI.extensions.dtd SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.dtd">





<!ENTITY DSSR_000002609_0001 SYSTEM "000002609_0001" NDATA uvaHighRes>
<!ENTITY DSSR_000002609_0002 SYSTEM "000002609_0002" NDATA uvaHighRes>
]>
<TEI.2 id="WasNegr"> 
<teiHeader type="migrated" creator="Etext">
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title type="main">Negro Self-Help</title>
<title type="sort">negro self help</title>
<author>Washington, Booker T.</author>
<respStmt>
<resp>Creation of machine-readable version:</resp> 
<name>Judy Boss</name> 
<resp>Creation of digital images:</resp> 
<name>Craig Simmons</name> 
<resp>Conversion to TEI.2-conformant markup:</resp> 
<name>University of Virginia Library Electronic Text Center.</name>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt> 
<extent>ca. <num type="kilobytes">12</num> kilobytes</extent> 
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>University of Virginia Library</publisher>
<pubPlace>Charlottesville, Virginia</pubPlace> 
<idno type="ETC">WasNegr</idno> 
<date value="1996">1996</date>
<availability status="public">
<p n="copyright">Copyright &#xa9; 1996 by the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia</p>
<p n="access">Publicly accessible</p>
</availability>
<idno type="uva-pid">uva-lib:477492</idno>
</publicationStmt>
<seriesStmt>
<title>University of Virginia Library, Text collection</title>
<idno type="uva-set">UVA-LIB-Text</idno>
</seriesStmt> 
<sourceDesc>
<biblFull>
<titleStmt>
<title type="main">Negro Self-Help</title>
<title level="j">The Independent</title>
<title type="sort">negro self help</title>
<author>Booker T. Washington</author>
</titleStmt> 
<editionStmt>
<p>1st Edition</p>
</editionStmt> 
<extent>pp 1207-8</extent> 
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>S. W. Benedict</publisher> 
<pubPlace>New York</pubPlace> 
<date value="1905-11-23">November 23, 1905</date>
</publicationStmt> 
<notesStmt>
<note>
<p>The Independent, Vol. 59, No. 2973 Thursday November 23, 1905.</p>
</note> 
<note>
<p>Copy consulted: UVa Library call number AP2 .I53</p>
</note>
</notesStmt>
</biblFull>
</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc> 
<encodingDesc>
<projectDesc>
<p>Prepared for the University of Virginia Library Electronic TextCenter.</p>
</projectDesc> 
<editorialDecl>
<p>All quotation marks retained as data.</p> 
<p>Spell-check and verification madeagainst printed text using WordPerfect spell checker.</p> 
<p>All unambiguous end-of-line hyphens have been removed, and the trailing part of a word has been joined to the preceding line.</p> 
<p>The images exist as archived TIFF images, one or more JPEG versionsfor general use, and thumbnail GIFs.</p> 
<p>Keywords in the header are a local Electronic Text Center scheme to aid in establishing analytical groupings.</p>
</editorialDecl> 
<refsDecl>
<p>ID elements are given for each page element and are composed of the text'sunique cryptogram and the given page number, as in AusEmma1 for page one of Jane Austen's Emma.</p>
</refsDecl> 
</encodingDesc> 
<profileDesc>
<creation>
<date value="1905">1905</date>
</creation> 
<langUsage>
<language id="eng" usage="main">English</language>
</langUsage> 
<textClass>
<keywords>
<term>CORD</term> 
<term>democracy</term>
</keywords> 
<keywords>
<term>non-fiction; prose</term> 
<term>African-American</term>
</keywords> 
<keywords>
<term>24-bit color; 400 dpi</term>
</keywords>
</textClass>
</profileDesc> 
<revisionDesc>
<change>
<date value="1996-09">September 1996</date> 
<respStmt>
<resp>corrector</resp> 
<name>Craig Simmons; Electronic Text Center at The University of Virginia</name>
</respStmt> 
<item>Added TEI header and tags</item>
</change> 
<change>
<date value="2005-07">July 2005</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>Corrector</resp>
<name>Margaret Konkol</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Converted SGML to XML and fixed tagging.</item>
</change>
<change>
<date value="2007-09">September 2007</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>Migration</resp>
<name>Ethan Gruber, University of Virginia Library</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Converted XML markup from TEI Lite to uva-dl-tei (TEI P4 with local customizations).</item>
</change>
<change>
<date value="2008-01">January 2008</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>Migration</resp>
<name>Greg Murray, University of Virginia Library</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Programmatically updated TEI header markup (but not header content) for minimal compliance with current QA requirements.</item>
</change>
<change>
<date value="2009-03">March 2009</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>Migration</resp>
<name>Scholarly Resources, University of Virginia Library</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Added and/or replaced the digital images accompanying the electronic text. Scanning of exterior and interior (ie. pages) of item was done only for items found in the University of Virginia Special Collections Library.</item>
</change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader> 
<text id="d1"> 
 
<body id="d3"> 
 
 
<div1 type="essay" id="d4"> 
     <pb entity="DSSR_000002609_0001" n="1207"/>
     <head type="main"> 
Negro Self-Help</head> 
     <head type="sub">BY BOOKER T. WASHINGTON, LL.D. </head>

 
<p> 
FROM time to time in the past a great deal of matter has been 
furnished to the public, with the praiseworthy purpose of portraying 
the individual struggles and sacrifices of colored youths to secure an 
education.  These efforts of struggling young men and women, with 
no inspiration in family tradition and fortune, and with little or no 
money with which to secure the knowledge they crave, is one of the 
most encouraging as well as pathetic features I have come across in 
my educational work during the past twenty years.  As a hopeful 
indication of race character, and I may safely so describe it, it must 
be of peculiar interest to the average American interested in the 
Negro people.</p><p> 
     On the other hand, much matter has also been furnished the 
public concerning the aid given the Negro race by philanthropic 
white people; attention is also frequently directed to the volume of 
money expended for the education of the Negro by State and 
municipal governments, the proceeds of land grant funds and of 
common taxation.</p><p> 
     I do not think that the public has been sufficiently informed of 
what the Negro himself has been doing during the past forty years, 
and is doing now, toward his own education thru the religious 
organizations controlled by him.</p><p> 
     Before dwelling upon this principal point, however, I wish to 
direct attention here to several minor ways of more or less 
importance in which the Negro is constantly displaying the quality 
of self-help--the most important and significant force in the uplift of 
any person or race, the absence of which must always be regarded 
as a fatal defect of character.</p><p> 
     First, then, it is well to say that there are very few orphan 
asylums anywhere for Negro children.  Possibly in nine or ten cases 
Negro families care for the orphans of their race in the 
neighborhoods where they reside.  A child is not left many hours 
without parents before it strays into some family, or, more often, is 
sought out by some friend, and, without legal formality, soon 
becomes a real part of the family.  Because of this custom one finds 
very little suffering among Negro children.  In the Southern States 
the masses know little about hospitals.  The sick and unfortunate are 
cared for by secret and fraternal societies, by the churches or by 
individuals.  A second form of self-help, which is increasing year by 
year, is the voluntary taxation of Negro communities for the 
purpose of extending the public school term, often from one to three 
months; that is, these months are added to the regular public school 
term.</p><p> 
     I could name other forms of self-help that are equally 
significant and praise-worthy.</p><p> 
     But to return to the main point.  Of the more than eight 
millions of colored people in the United States, it is estimated that 
two-thirds of the adults are members of some church.  The great 
body of them are either members of the Baptist Church, or of some 
branch of the Methodist Church.  The Methodists are divided into 
four groups or branches, namely: the African Methodist Episcopal, 
the A. M. E. Zion, the Colored Methodist, and those belonging to 
the main body of the Northern Methodist Church.  Besides, in all 
the Southern States, and in some States outside of the South, there 
are Presbyterian, Congregational and Episcopal churches, and a few 
other denominations--including Catholics--not under the Methodist 
or Baptist groups, all contributing something toward the expenses of 
the schools and colleges.</p><p> 
     The plan for securing money from the colored people thru 
their churches varies according to the location and conditions 
surrounding the people, as well as the customs and laws of the 
church.  For example, in the case of the Baptists, there is at least 
one institution, usually called college or university, in each 
Southern State, supported in part or in whole by the pennies and 
dollars of the 
 
     <pb entity="DSSR_000002609_0002" n="1208"/> 

 
masses.  In Alabama, for illustration, there 
is what is known as the Alabama Baptist Colored University, at 
Selma.  Last year the colored people in Alabama contributed to the 
work of this institution $9,441.93, exclusive of student board and 
tuition.  The property is owned by colored people; their money 
created it, with the exception of a few gifts from outside sources. 
There is at least one such school in each of the Southern States. 
The detailed circumstances surrounding them may vary, but the 
general plan is the same.</p><p> 
     In the case of the African Methodist Episcopal Church, there 
are institutions that owe their existence almost wholly to the small 
gifts of the churches and individuals of the denomination.  Last year 
$51,601.86 was raised by this denomination for the purposes of 
education.  The oldest and largest of these institutions is the 
Wilberforce University, at Wilberforce, O.  Altho this institution is 
now somewhat generously assisted by the State of Ohio, it was for 
years supported almost wholly by the colored people.</p><p> 
     Let me use another illustration as showing what the African 
Methodist Episcopal Church is doing in the South.  There is a 
school in Atlanta, Ga., called Morris-Brown College, that was 
organized only a few years ago.  It now owns a very valuable 
property and has a large student body.  The college was built and is 
supported, to a large extent, by money raised by the church 
membership.  For 1904 the institution received from all sources for 
running expenses, $15,985.58, of which the churches in that 
connection in the State of Georgia contributed $6,200, the third 
Sunday in September being set apart for the taking of offerings for 
the educational work; and $850.50 was raised thru the industrial 
department.  The remainder was contributed thru other channels of 
the church, and mostly all of it by Negro people.</p><p> 
     The African Methodist Episcopal Zion Church has ten 
institutions of learning, of which Livingston College, at Salisbury, 
N. D., is the most important.  The Corresponding Secretary of 
Education of the Zion Church reports that the money collected last 
year amounted to $20,706.54, which went to all the schools of the 
church to supplement their other revenues for running purposes.</p><p> 
     Thru the Freedmen's Aid and Southern Education Society of 
the Methodist Episcopal Church, the colored membership 
contributed for education for the current year, $19,251.73.  For the 
ten years, 1896-1905, inclusive, $79,228.13 was contributed.</p><p> 
     The Negro Baptists support quite a number of educational 
institutions, and to carry on the work the churches raised during the 
past year $85,888.18.</p><p> 
     To sum up, we find that the A. M. E. Church contributed 
$51,601.86 for educational purposes last year; the A. M. E. Zion 
Church, $20,706.54; the Colored Methodist Episcopal Church, 
$45,000; the Methodist Episcopal, $15,926.40; the Baptists, 
$85,888.18; making the total, $218,622.98, for only two branches of 
the Christian Church.  If the contributions of the Negro 
Congregationalists, Presbyterians and Episcopalians, etc., be 
approximated, we should have probably an annual contribution for 
educational purposes by the Negro Christians of $250,000.</p><p> 
     Within the past ten years, it is safe to say, according to these 
figures, that the Negro in America has contributed at least 
$2,000,000 thru his churches toward his own education.  This, I 
think, all fair-minded people will agree, is a pretty good record for a 
race of people which was in slavery forty years ago.  And these 
figures, of course, do not include the amounts which colored people 
are contributing constantly to local and independent institutions. 
The Tuskegee Institute, for example, receives contributions from 
colored people annually, and the same is true of other institutions 
which have no direct church connection.</p> 
<closer> 
<dateline>TUSKEGEE, ALABAMA.</dateline> 
</closer> 
 
</div1> 
</body> 
</text> 
</TEI.2> 
