<?xml version="1.0"?>

<?dlps id="WasProg"?>
<?dlps page-images="none" figure-images="yes"?>
<?dlps transcription="other"?>

<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/tei-p4/tei2.dtd" [
<!ENTITY % POSTKB "INCLUDE">
<!ENTITY % TEI.extensions.ent SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.ent">
<!ENTITY % TEI.extensions.dtd SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.dtd">


<!ENTITY DSSR_000002589_0001 SYSTEM "000002589_0001" NDATA uvaHighRes>
<!ENTITY DSSR_000002589_0002 SYSTEM "000002589_0002" NDATA uvaHighRes>
<!ENTITY DSSR_000002589_0003 SYSTEM "000002589_0003" NDATA uvaHighRes>
<!ENTITY DSSR_000002589_0004 SYSTEM "000002589_0004" NDATA uvaHighRes>
<!ENTITY DSSR_000002589_0005 SYSTEM "000002589_0005" NDATA uvaHighRes>
]>
<TEI.2 id="WasProg"> 
<teiHeader type="migrated" creator="Etext">
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title type="main">Negro Progress in Virginia</title>
<title type="sort">negro progress in virginia</title>
<author>Washington, Booker T.</author>
<respStmt>
<resp>Creation of machine-readable version:</resp> 
<name>Judy Boss</name> 
<resp>Creation of digital images:</resp> 
<name>Tom Palombi, Electronic Text Center</name> 
<resp>Conversion to TEI.2-conformant markup:</resp> 
<name>University of Virginia Library Electronic Text Center.</name>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt> 
<extent>ca. <num type="kilobytes">17</num> kilobytes</extent> 
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>University of Virginia Library</publisher>
<pubPlace>Charlottesville, Virginia</pubPlace> 
<idno type="ETC">WasProg</idno> 
<date value="1997-06">June 1997</date>
<availability status="public">
<p n="copyright">Copyright &#xa9; 1997 by the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia</p>
<p n="access">Publicly accessible</p>
</availability>
<idno type="uva-pid">uva-lib:477493</idno>
</publicationStmt>
<seriesStmt>
<title>University of Virginia Library, Text collection</title>
<idno type="uva-set">UVA-LIB-Text</idno>
</seriesStmt> 
<notesStmt>
<note>
<p>Images of ornamentation have been included from the print version.</p>
</note> 
</notesStmt> 
<sourceDesc>
<biblFull>
<titleStmt>
<title type="main">Negro Progress in Virginia</title>
<title level="j">The Southern Workman, volume 43</title>
<title type="sort">negro progress in virginia</title>
<author>Booker T. Washington</author>
</titleStmt> 
<extent>pp. 39-43</extent> 
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>Press of the Hampton Normal and Agricultural Institute</publisher> 
<pubPlace>Hampton, Virginia</pubPlace> 
<date value="1914-01">January 1914</date> 
<idno type="callNo">Print copy consulted: University of Virginia Library, call no. 
LC2701 .S7, volume 43</idno>
</publicationStmt> 
</biblFull>
</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc> 
<encodingDesc>
<projectDesc>
<p>Prepared for the University of Virginia Library Electronic Text Center.</p>
</projectDesc> 
<editorialDecl>
<p>All quotation marks retained as data.</p> 
<p>All unambiguous end-of-line hyphens have been removed, and the trailing part of a word has been joined to the preceding line.</p> 
<p>The images exist as archived TIFF images, one or more JPEG 
versions for general use, and thumbnail GIFs.</p> 
<p>Keywords in the header are a local Electronic Text Center scheme to aid in establishing analytical groupings.</p>
</editorialDecl> 
</encodingDesc> 
<profileDesc>
<creation>
<date value="1914-01">January 1914</date>
</creation> 
<langUsage>
<language id="eng" usage="main">English</language>
</langUsage> 
<textClass>
<keywords>
<term>CORD</term> 
<term>democracy</term>
</keywords> 
<keywords>
<term>LCSH</term> 
<term>African-American</term>
</keywords> 
<keywords>
<term>prose</term>
<term>non-fiction</term>
</keywords> 
<keywords> 
<term type="format">24-bit color; 400 dpi</term>
</keywords>
</textClass>
</profileDesc> 
<revisionDesc>
<change>
<date value="1997-06">June 1997</date> 
<respStmt>
<resp>corrector</resp> 
<name>Tom Palombi, Electronic Text Center</name>
</respStmt> 
<item>Added TEI header and tags</item>
</change> 
<change>
<date value="2005-07">July 2005</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>Corrector</resp>
<name>Margaret Konkol</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Converted SGML to XML and fixed tagging.</item>
</change>
<change>
<date value="2007-09">September 2007</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>Migration</resp>
<name>Ethan Gruber, University of Virginia Library</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Converted XML markup from TEI Lite to uva-dl-tei (TEI P4 with local customizations).</item>
</change>
<change>
<date value="2008-01">January 2008</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>Migration</resp>
<name>Greg Murray, University of Virginia Library</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Programmatically updated TEI header markup (but not header content) for minimal compliance with current QA requirements.</item>
</change>
<change>
<date value="2009-03">March 2009</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>Migration</resp>
<name>Scholarly Resources, University of Virginia Library</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Added and/or replaced the digital images accompanying the electronic text. Scanning of exterior and interior (ie. pages) of item was done only for items found in the University of Virginia Special Collections Library.</item>
</change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader> 
 
<text id="d1"> 
<body id="d2"> 
 
<div1 type="speech" id="d3"> <pb entity= "DSSR_000002589_0001" n="39"/>
<head> 
NEGRO PROGRESS IN VIRGINIA<ref target="n1" n="1">[*]</ref><lb/> 
BY BOOKER T. WASHINGTON<lb/> 
Principal of Tuskegee Institute, Alabama 
</head> 
 
<p>THE members of the colored race who live outside of Virginia are 
beginning to grow somewhat jealous of the progress which our race is 
making in this commonwealth.  The Negro race in Virginia is going 
forward, in my opinion, in all the fundamental and substantial things of 
life, faster than the Negro himself realizes and faster than his white 
neighbor realizes.  I say this notwithstanding there are many existing 
weaknesses and much still to be accomplished.  This progress which 
Virginia Negroes are now experiencing is owing to two causes. 
 
</p><p>First, they have been fortunate for a number of years in having 
governors with foresight, vision, liberality, and courage; and in having 
superintendents of education and other state officials who have 
considered the interests, prosperity, and progress of all the people, 
regardless of race and color.  Though I have done so at a distance, I have 
watched with the greatest interest and satisfaction the interest which 
Governor Mann has shown in the education and uplift of all the people in 
this state.  Governor Mann is in the highest degree a model executive.  It 
is because of the leadership and guidance of such state officials that the 
Negro in Virginia has gone forward as fast as he has.  I have always 
noticed that the character of the colored race in any community or state is 
patterned very largely after the character of the white people in that 
community or state. 
 
</p><p>The second reason why the Negroes of Virginia have made, and are 
making, such great strides, grows out of the fact that they are blessed 
with the leadership and guidance of such level-headed, conservative, safe 
unselfish, and able colored men as Major R. R. Moton, the leader in the 
Negro Organization Society, and dozens of others I could mention. 
 
</p><p>The Negro Organization Society has for its object the unifying and 
focusing of all the organizations among our people in Virginia on certain 
fundamentals of life, such as education, health, and cleanliness.  It is not 
the purpose of this Society to seek to interfere with the special work and 
purpose of any of the individual organizations represented, but to 
co-operate with them 
 
<pb entity= "DSSR_000002589_0002" n="40"/> 
 
so as to promote education in its broadest sense, without which there can 
be no permanent prosperity.  The work which it is doing under the 
general direction of Major Moton, Prof. J. M. Gandy, of Petersburg, the 
Rev. A. A. Graham, of Phoebus, and others equally interested, is worthy 
of all praise and encouragement. 
 
</p><p>The work of this Society is fundamental.  It touches the life and the 
interests of every white citizen in Virginia.  I have watched its growth 
with a great deal of interest and I believe that it is one of the most potent 
factors for our uplift.  Here is a great example of co-operation.  It is 
sometimes said that black people cannot get together and work for the 
general improvement of a community, but we have here, in a great state, 
an example of Negro organizations, of every sort, with diverse interests, 
being able to get together and co-operate for better schools, better farms, 
better homes, better morals, and better health. 
 
</p><p>I find that for educational improvement in Virginia during the past 
year this Society assisted in raising money for the building of schools to 
the value of $10,000, that in one county it aided in raising $900 for 
school improvement and extension of school terms, also that a large 
number of schools were inspired to make adequate provision for 
ventilation, as well as to have individual drinking cups, sanitary 
outhouses, and improved surroundings. 
 
</p><p>I am especially interested in the efforts which are being made for 
better morals among our people.  Special emphasis is being placed upon 
the idea that parents should devote more time and thought to the rearing 
of their children, and that they should inculcate in their offspring correct 
habits of morality. 
 
</p><p>One of the greatest things that the Negro Organization Society 
is doing is that of improving the health of the masses of the black 
people throughout Virginia.  At the last meeting of the National Negro 
Business League, I was particularly interested in the report that 
Professor Gandy gave concerning the work of this Society.  Among other 
things, he told about the "Clean-up Day" that the Negroes of Virginia 
had last April, when 100,000 Negroes were influenced to observe the 
day.  I am especially pleased to know of the hearty response and 
sympathetic co-operation that were shown by the white people, and by 
the white papers in reporting this state-wide "Clean-up Day."  I was 
particularly pleased to note the editorials in the 
<hi rend="italic">Times-Dispatch</hi> and other leading white papers of the state, 
commending the effort and calling upon the white citizens to use their 
influence with the colored people in their employ to get them to 
observe the day.  I was equally gratified to observe the great 
interest that the colored people themselves manifested and the large 
amount of work they did in cleaning up Virginia. 
 
<pb entity= "DSSR_000002589_0003" n="41"/> 
 
</p><p>The Bible tells us that cleanliness is next to godliness.  When 
the colored people in a great state like Virginia all get together and 
co-operate for a general housecleaning&#x2014;whitewashing their houses, 
fences, and outbuildings, cleaning out their wells and springs, and 
seeing that their schoolhouses and homes are properly ventilated&#x2014;this 
people is making progress, not only along health lines, but also along 
educational and religious lines.  Through the Organization Society the 
Negroes of Virginia are contributing, not only towards their own 
improvement, but also towards the improvement of the state as a whole. 
 
</p><p>Virginia is setting a great example for the remainder of the 
South in the matter of showing how the white and colored people may 
co-operate for general improvement.  I find that not only have the 
efforts of the Negro Organization Society received the hearty support 
of the white people of the state, but that other special lines of 
endeavor have likewise received their most cordial support.  This is 
particularly true in the matter of education.  Virginia was the first 
state to have a state supervisor of rural colored schools, and by so 
doing set an example for the remainder of the South.  The work of Mr. 
Jackson Davis in improving the Negro schools of Virginia is an 
indication of how the best white people of the South are ready to give 
their time and talent for the betterment of conditions among Negroes. 
 
</p><p>It has been my pleasure, under the auspices of Hampton 
Institute, to make several trips recently, with Major Moton and 
others, through the tidewater counties of Virginia, and in each one of 
those counties I was most gratified at the evidences of progress on 
the part of our race in getting land, building better houses, 
establishing schools and churches, and in contributing their part 
toward law and order and a higher and better civilization.  In 
Gloucester County, for example, we found that there was not a single 
individual of either race in the county jail.  That is a record which 
can be mentioned by few counties, North or South, or indeed anywhere 
in the United States. 
 
</p><p>In Virginia there are about 675,000 black people, and I find 
that they are making considerable progress along religious lines. 
They are building up-to-date churches which cost from &#x0024;10,000 to 
&#x0024;40,000.  In connection with the material progress of Negro churches, 
there is also improvement intellectually and morally.  You have here 
some of the most capable and intellectual ministers among colored 
people.  There are in Virginia about 2000 colored church organizations 
with a membership of over 300,000.  Another evidence of the progress 
that is being made is the growth in Sunday-school work.  There are in 
the state over 2000 Sunday schools with 13,000 teachers and officers 
and 115,000 pupils.  The value of the church property owned by colored 
people in Virginia is over &#x0024;4,000,000. 
 
<pb entity= "DSSR_000002589_0004" n="42"/> 
 
</p><p>Perhaps in no other section of the country is there a body of 
Negroes who, on the whole, are more progressive than the Negroes of 
Virginia.  Here the first Negro bank was established, and now there are 
more banks operated by Negroes in Virginia than in any other state.  I 
understand that there are altogether twelve such banks.  Richmond has 
the distinction of having the first Negro bank in the country that is 
run by a woman. 
 
</p><p>Along other lines of business Virginia Negroes have made great 
progress in the past few years.  There are today more Negroes in the 
state than ever before who are operating grocery stores, undertaking 
establishments, real estate, and other business enterprises.  In 
practically every city in Virginia where there is any large number of 
Negroes, there are business blocks owned by them. 
 
</p><p>The most notable progress of the race in Virginia has been along 
agricultural lines.  Thirty-four per cent of all persons engaged in farming 
in the state are Negroes.  Almost one-half of all the Negroes in the state 
are engaged in farming.  There are 48,000 who are operating farms; and 
they are operating 26 per cent of all the farms in the state.  Although 
Virginia gained only 10,000 in its Negro population, or a little more than 
one per cent from 1900 to 1910, in the same period the number of 
Negroes owning farms increased 20 per cent.  Something like 2,250,000 
acres of land are under the control of Negroes; that is, owned or rented 
by them.  The Negro farmers in Virginia control over &#x0024;55,000,000 worth 
of farm property.  This is 123 per cent more than they controlled ten 
years ago. 
 
</p><p>These Negro farmers, along with Negro farmers in other parts of 
the South, are using more and more machinery in their farming 
operations.  Ten years ago they owned &#x0024;1,000,000 worth of farm 
machinery.  Now they own &#x0024;2,000,000 worth.  There are 32,000 Negroes 
in Virginia who own land.  No other state has so many.  Mississippi is 
next with 25,000 farm owners among her Negro population.  Virginia 
Negroes own over 1,600,000 acres of land, which is over 300,000 acres 
more than they owned ten years ago.  The remarkable thing about these 
Negro farmers is that they own over half the land they cultivate. 
Except in Kentucky, this is true in no other Southern state.  I find 
that, according to the census, in the ten years from 1900 to 1910, the 
value of land and buildings owned by the Negroes of Virginia increased 
from &#x0024;10,000,000 to &#x0024;28,000,000, or 180 per cent. 
 
</p><p>In the matter of education Virginia Negroes are making progress 
also, but, as in most of our Southern states, much remains to be 
accomplished.  It is true that a large percentage of the colored population 
of Virginia cannot read or write.  We must not, however, be deceived by 
the mere fact that a person can 
 
<pb entity= "DSSR_000002589_0005" n="43"/> 
 
read or write.  Unless he has received that broader training which 
enables him to know the object of education, the uses of education, 
unless he receives that broader training which will make him realize 
that book education is useless without character, without industry, 
without the saving habit, without the willingness to contribute his 
part toward law and order and the highest and best in the community, 
his mere book education will in many cases mean little or nothing.  It 
is the object of the Negro Organization Society to help the colored 
people of Virginia to digest their education, to utilize it in the 
common, ordinary affairs of life for the benefit of white people and 
black people. 
 
</p><p>In the foregoing remarks I have merely hinted at 
some of the instances of progress in Virginia.  I have done so to show 
what can be done, but one must not get the idea that all the work is 
done or that the Negro race is on its feet.  In Virginia, as in other 
Southern states, we are just beginning to teach the Negro how to make 
progress and the two races how to co-operate with each other.  Under 
the leadership of such men as Major Moton and such institutions as 
Hampton and others, we shall soon leave behind all doubt and 
uncertainty as to the future relations of the two races in the South. 
</p> 
 
 
<p><q> 
     THE question with the Negroes is not one 
     of special proficiency, of success in one 
     direction&#x2014;the pursuit of knowledge&#x2014;but 
     of success all around.  It is one of morals, 
     industry, self-restraint; of power to 
     organize society, to draw social lines between the 
     decent and indecent, to form public sentiment 
     that shall support pure morals, and to 
     show common sense in the relations of life. 
     <bibl><hi rend="italic">&#x2014;From "Education for Life"</hi></bibl></q> 
</p> 
 
<note id="n1" n="1"><seg type="note-symbol">[*]</seg><p> Address delivered before the Negro Organization Society, 
Richmond City Auditorium, November 7, 1913</p></note> 
 
</div1> 
 
</body> 
</text> 
</TEI.2> 
